<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[A Research Collaborative to Build Employability Skills for STEM Technology Fields]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>799949.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>868466</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Changes in the technician workplace are increasing the demand for employees who have skills in adaptability, collaboration, communication, workplace diversity, lifelong learning, and understanding the business mission.  This project plans to address this need by developing and testing a professional development model that fosters students’ employability skills.  The focus will be on students who are enrolled in a new Advanced Manufacturing Technology program/career pathway that will prepare them for careers as advanced manufacturing technicians. The research team will adapt the researcher-practitioner-partnership to support the development of these students’ employability skills. The project is estimated to directly serve at least fifty students pursuing associate degrees in the new program, six program faculty, and 25 additional faculty in both postsecondary and secondary technician programs.  The project's research activities will investigate: (1) the effectiveness of this approach to developing employability skills; (2) the feasibility of rapid development and testing of new curricula; and, (3) the effectiveness of short-term employability skills development experiences compared to multiple development experiences over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researcher-practitioner-partnership method was developed to improve the flow and implementation of research findings into practice at the K-12 level.  This method will be adapted for use in post-secondary technician education.   Using a set of research methods and assessments, this effort will study simultaneously the teaching and learning of employability skills while engaging technician educators as co-designers, developers, and knowledge builders.  In alignment with the researcher-practitioner-partnership method, the process to validate assessments will identify and define employability skills constructs and identify instructional strategies to ensure alignment of assessments to practice.  The research team will use grounded theory and the “plan-do-study-act” approach modified for use in the researcher-practitioner-partnership context to adapt, test, and refine employability skills tools, resources, and methods. This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000881</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louise</FirstName>
<LastName>Yarnall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louise Yarnall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[louise.yarnall@sri.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000197941</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyra</FirstName>
<LastName>Caspary</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyra N Caspary</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kyra.caspary@sri.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000789444</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/29/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maniphone</FirstName>
<LastName>Dickerson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maniphone Dickerson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[maniphone.dickerson@evc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/16/2024</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Griffiths</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca Griffiths</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rebecca.griffiths@sri.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828495</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Duran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexandra Duran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alexandra.duran@sjeccd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/10/2024</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angel</FirstName>
<LastName>Fuentes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angel G Fuentes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[angel.fuentes@evc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000950308</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SRI International]]></Name>
<CityName>MENLO PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7032478529</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[333 RAVENSWOOD AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SRG2J1WS9X63</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SRI INTERNATIONAL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>SRG2J1WS9X63</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SRI International]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>741200</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~799949</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~68517</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many community college technician programs teach professional skills such as communication, teamwork, work ethic, and openness to lifelong learning by briefly discussing them in one course or offering students a couple of meetings with a career coach before they graduate. However, employers consistently report that too many recent college graduates arrive in the workplace underperforming such professional skills. Such professional performance gaps have persistent negative effects on the employability of graduates of community college technician programs, limiting their success in getting jobs, keeping them, and advancing in their careers.</p> <p><br />Project GOALS (Greater Opportunities to Advance Lifelong Success), an NSF Advanced Technological Education targeted research project, brought together researchers and community college educators from 2020 through 2024 to co-develop, test, package, and distribute resources for developing technicians' professional skills. Through this work, the team discovered the barriers that hinder both instructors and students from connecting around professional skills development. To address these barriers, the Project GOALS team developed an instructional framework grounded in research that integrates focused low-stakes activities into classes as students work toward their technical certificates. Based on our research, we believe Project GOALS provides ways for students to improve their professional self-awareness and for technical instructors to build their confidence and strategies for developing the career readiness of students.</p> <p><br /><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong> Based on design and testing that involved 8 core instructors, 9 courses, and more than 170 students, Project GOALS produced a set of instructional resources that educators may download through a website. These resources include two handbooks, two rubrics, and a set of reflection tools delivered via mobile application.</p> <p>The Project GOALS curriculum begins by having instructors define professional skills, provide testimonies about the importance of these skills in workplace success, and frame professional skills not as fixed personality traits, but as skills and mindsets that can improve through reflective practice. The Project GOALS curriculum then engages students in periodic reflections about their professional skills following team-based technical labs. These reflections contribute to professional skills stories that students collect in a portfolio during their courses. At the end of their certificate program, students can use these stories to compose resumes and prepare more effectively for job interviews.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>In a research brief, the team describes how the Project GOALS collaboration revealed the supports that technical instructors need to develop the professional awareness and reflection habits of students. Project GOALS began with instructors asking researchers to design professional skills assessments and rubrics. After the researchers developed a rubric and three reflection tools (self-reflection, peer reflection, and instructor reflection), they tested them for validity and reliability and studied the patterns and contrasts in the ratings of students and instructors.</p> <p><br />We found that students and instructors consistently differed in their ratings of student professional skills, with students rating themselves and their peers a point higher on a scale than their instructors did. While the differences were not statistically significant, the disagreement pattern was consistent across all courses and all participants. Such findings align with past research that has found the personal biases and concerns of students about social desirability distort their self-assessments. By studying these differences, the Project GOALS team also discovered the challenges that prevent many instructors from sharing their honest assessments of the professional skills of their students. We found that instructors could easily rate individual students using reflection tools because, in fact, they were implicitly assessing the professional skills of their students all the time, but they had avoided sharing those assessments directly with students based on their own concerns about social desirability and institutional dynamics.</p> <p><br />To navigate such barriers, Project GOALS explored how low-stakes reflection tools could help students develop professional self-awareness and help instructors provide transparent and constructive feedback. For students, Project GOALS developed self-rating activities linked to specific team roles, rubrics, and practices for telling stories about their professional skills. For instructors, Project GOALS developed tools to document their ratings of the professional skills of their students and then share the results in a low-risk, supportive way.<br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 08/01/2024<br> Modified by: Louise&nbsp;Yarnall</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453034443_Project_GOALS_Curriculum_Principles_and_Strategies--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453034443_Project_GOALS_Curriculum_Principles_and_Strategies--rgov-800width.png" title="Project GOALS Learning Principles and Instructional Strategies"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453034443_Project_GOALS_Curriculum_Principles_and_Strategies--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Project GOALS Learning Principles and Instructional Strategies"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This table summarizes the instructional strategies used in the Project GOALS curriculum and aligns them with the three sets of learning principles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">SRI Education</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Louise&nbsp;Yarnall <div class="imageTitle">Project GOALS Learning Principles and Instructional Strategies</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722452756779_Project_GOALS_Learning_Principles--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722452756779_Project_GOALS_Learning_Principles--rgov-800width.png" title="Project GOALS Learning Principles"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722452756779_Project_GOALS_Learning_Principles--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Project GOALS Learning Principles"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">These three sets of principles guide instruction to develop students' professional skills.</div> <div class="imageCredit">SRi Education</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Louise&nbsp;Yarnall <div class="imageTitle">Project GOALS Learning Principles</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453146593_Model_of_Instructor_Driven_Instruction--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453146593_Model_of_Instructor_Driven_Instruction--rgov-800width.png" title="Model of Instructor-Driven Professional Skills Teaching"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453146593_Model_of_Instructor_Driven_Instruction--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Model of Instructor-Driven Professional Skills Teaching"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This graphic models one way to implement the Project GOALS curriculum that results in lower student engagement.</div> <div class="imageCredit">SRi Education</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Louise&nbsp;Yarnall <div class="imageTitle">Model of Instructor-Driven Professional Skills Teaching</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453320445_Model_of_Interactive_Instruction--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453320445_Model_of_Interactive_Instruction--rgov-800width.png" title="Interactive Instruction for Project GOALS"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722453320445_Model_of_Interactive_Instruction--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Interactive Instruction for Project GOALS"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This graphic shows the additional interactions that instructors can foster with students when using the Project GOALS curriculum. The strategies in red appeared to improve student engagement and professional skills development.</div> <div class="imageCredit">SRI Education</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Louise&nbsp;Yarnall <div class="imageTitle">Interactive Instruction for Project GOALS</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722452937804_Project_GOALS_Curriculum_Co_development_Cycle--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722452937804_Project_GOALS_Curriculum_Co_development_Cycle--rgov-800width.png" title="Project GOALS Co-Development Cycle"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2000881/2000881_10662085_1722452937804_Project_GOALS_Curriculum_Co_development_Cycle--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Project GOALS Co-Development Cycle"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">To create the Project GOALS curriculum, researchers and community college educators collaborated in four rounds of the co-development cycle.</div> <div class="imageCredit">SRi Education</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Louise&nbsp;Yarnall <div class="imageTitle">Project GOALS Co-Development Cycle</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Many community college technician programs teach professional skills such as communication, teamwork, work ethic, and openness to lifelong learning by briefly discussing them in one course or offering students a couple of meetings with a career coach before they graduate. However, employers consistently report that too many recent college graduates arrive in the workplace underperforming such professional skills. Such professional performance gaps have persistent negative effects on the employability of graduates of community college technician programs, limiting their success in getting jobs, keeping them, and advancing in their careers.    Project GOALS (Greater Opportunities to Advance Lifelong Success), an NSF Advanced Technological Education targeted research project, brought together researchers and community college educators from 2020 through 2024 to co-develop, test, package, and distribute resources for developing technicians' professional skills. Through this work, the team discovered the barriers that hinder both instructors and students from connecting around professional skills development. To address these barriers, the Project GOALS team developed an instructional framework grounded in research that integrates focused low-stakes activities into classes as students work toward their technical certificates. Based on our research, we believe Project GOALS provides ways for students to improve their professional self-awareness and for technical instructors to build their confidence and strategies for developing the career readiness of students.    Broader Impacts: Based on design and testing that involved 8 core instructors, 9 courses, and more than 170 students, Project GOALS produced a set of instructional resources that educators may download through a website. These resources include two handbooks, two rubrics, and a set of reflection tools delivered via mobile application.   The Project GOALS curriculum begins by having instructors define professional skills, provide testimonies about the importance of these skills in workplace success, and frame professional skills not as fixed personality traits, but as skills and mindsets that can improve through reflective practice. The Project GOALS curriculum then engages students in periodic reflections about their professional skills following team-based technical labs. These reflections contribute to professional skills stories that students collect in a portfolio during their courses. At the end of their certificate program, students can use these stories to compose resumes and prepare more effectively for job interviews.   Intellectual Merit: In a research brief, the team describes how the Project GOALS collaboration revealed the supports that technical instructors need to develop the professional awareness and reflection habits of students. Project GOALS began with instructors asking researchers to design professional skills assessments and rubrics. After the researchers developed a rubric and three reflection tools (self-reflection, peer reflection, and instructor reflection), they tested them for validity and reliability and studied the patterns and contrasts in the ratings of students and instructors.    We found that students and instructors consistently differed in their ratings of student professional skills, with students rating themselves and their peers a point higher on a scale than their instructors did. While the differences were not statistically significant, the disagreement pattern was consistent across all courses and all participants. Such findings align with past research that has found the personal biases and concerns of students about social desirability distort their self-assessments. By studying these differences, the Project GOALS team also discovered the challenges that prevent many instructors from sharing their honest assessments of the professional skills of their students. We found that instructors could easily rate individual students using reflection tools because, in fact, they were implicitly assessing the professional skills of their students all the time, but they had avoided sharing those assessments directly with students based on their own concerns about social desirability and institutional dynamics.    To navigate such barriers, Project GOALS explored how low-stakes reflection tools could help students develop professional self-awareness and help instructors provide transparent and constructive feedback. For students, Project GOALS developed self-rating activities linked to specific team roles, rubrics, and practices for telling stories about their professional skills. For instructors, Project GOALS developed tools to document their ratings of the professional skills of their students and then share the results in a low-risk, supportive way.                    Last Modified: 08/01/2024       Submitted by: LouiseYarnall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
