<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: A North Pacific ice core record of summer climate and wildfire history during the last 1500 years]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>142031.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>142031</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marc Stieglitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mstiegli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924354</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project intends to use the Mount Denali ice core archive to develop the most comprehensive suite of North Pacific fire and summer climate proxy records since about 2500 years before present. Wildfire is a key component of summer climate in the North Pacific where wildfires are projected to increase with continued summer warming. Studies that combine paleorecords of summer climate and wildfire are therefore critically needed, especially in the North Pacific region where fire recurrence rate and decadal-to-centennial scale climate fluctuations occur over longer time periods than are covered by direct observations. The goal of the proposed research is to improve our understanding of relationships between summertime climate and wildfire activity, focusing especially on the Medieval Climate Anomaly (MCA), when regional temperatures were perhaps as warm as the 20th century. Recent advances now permit the measurement of new fire-related (pyrogenic) compounds in ice cores, enabling the development of a robust fire record capable of rigorous comparison with regional paleoclimate reconstructions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The records of summer atmospheric circulation developed through this project will be regionally unique and fill a critical gap in the suite of North Pacific paleoclimate records. The ice core fire records will have synchronously dated temperature, precipitation and circulation time series. Our unique compilation of these ice core records, as well as other regional paleoproxy records will be the first effort at combining these datasets into a regional compilation of paleofire records in the North Pacific region. This compilation will facilitate the examination of fire activity during Medieval Climate Anomaly (MCA) conditions that are of comparable magnitude to present climate changes over socially relevant timescales (decades). We will analyze the archive Denali ice core for black carbon, which is derived from both biomass and fossil fuel combustion, and organic aromatic acids (e.g. vanillic acid) and monosaccharide anhydride (e.g. levoglucosan) which are produced solely from biomass burning. The Denali ice core chronology is already developed, and the archive ice is in hand, ensuring that our research plan can be accomplished. Fire record synthesis and calibration will incorporate instrumental fire databases, gridded burn area data, and HYSPLIT back-trajectory analyses over the instrumental era in order to test the sensitivity of fireclimate relationships over time. With this record we will address the following research questions: (1) How have North Pacific summer atmospheric circulation patterns varied over the last 1500 years? (2) How did North Pacific fire regime characteristics naturally respond to the warm summer conditions of the Medieval Climate Anomaly (MCA)? (3) Are there consistent relationships between North Pacific fire regime and climate?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A focal point of our broader impacts is support for two young investigators who have specialized expertise in North Pacific ice cores and paleofire modeling, respectively. This project will also support one PhD student and several undergraduate students. We will continue our longstanding collaboration with Denali National Park to present and permanently display our major climate- and fire-related findings at the park visitor center in Talkeetna, Alaska. We are partnering with the Natural Sciences Education and Outreach Center at Colorado State University to develop STEM kits focused on the Denali ice core record for distribution to under-served K-12 students in Alaska and Maine. Prototypes of these kits have already been developed and tested with students, and we propose to significantly expand this program and increase its impact. Other activities include the participation of first-year women researchers in this project as part of the Dartmouth Women In Science Project (WISP) initiative, and through participation in the NSF-supported School of Ice, where faculty from historically black colleges and minority-serving institutions learn about ice cores and climate change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002424</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erich</FirstName>
<LastName>Osterberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erich Osterberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[erich.c.osterberg@dartmouth.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000516929</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dartmouth College]]></Name>
<CityName>HANOVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>037552170</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6036463007</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7 LEBANON ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EB8ASJBCFER9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF DARTMOUTH COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>T4MWFG59C6R3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dartmouth College]]></Name>
<CityName>Hanover</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>037553716</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[19 Fayerweather Hill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>528000</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~142031</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Alaska is warming twice as fast as the rest of the United States, and Alaskan wildfires have increased in frequency and burned area over recent decades as summers have warmed. Since 1990, ten Alaskan wildfire seasons exceeded two million total acres burned, whereas only five wildfire seasons reached that extreme level from 1950-1990. In addition to posing significant health, infrastructure, and economic risks to local communities, Alaskan wildfires impact natural ecosystems and can affect global climate through fire emissions of CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;and black carbon (soot). It is critical to understand how wildfire activity is likely to change in the future with continued climate change, but the instrumental wildfire record in Alaska is relatively short (extending back to ~1950), making it challenging to understand relationships between temperature, precipitation, and wildfire activity. Prior periods of natural climate change, including the so-called Medieval Climate Anomaly from ~1000-1300 CE, and the Little Ice Age from ~1400-1850, provide opportunities to examine past wildfire activity during times with relatively warm and cool summers, respectively. Ice cores recovered from Alaskan mountain glaciers preserve chemicals emitted by wildfire smoke plumes in their annual layers of snowfall and can therefore provide a record of wildfire activity extending centuries into the past.</p> <p>In this project, we used an archive of the Denali Ice Core &ndash; collected in 2013 from Begguya, also known as Mount Hunter, in Denali National Park, Alaska &ndash; to develop a record of Alaskan wildfire activity extending over the past 1000 years. We used cutting-edge laboratory analysis methods to measure soot, as well as natural acids and sugar molecules that are only produced by wildfires, throughout the length of the ice core, collecting several samples from each annual layer of ice extending over the past millennium. This represents the first comprehensive record of wildfire in the Alaskan region extending from 1000 CE to present. We also conducted detailed analyses of how temperature, rainfall, atmospheric pressure, winds, and slope aspect affected Alaskan wildfire ignition, spread, and burned area over recent decades to better interpret the ice core record.&nbsp;</p> <p>We find that Alaskan wildfire activity was significantly higher than modern levels between 1032&ndash;1362 C.E., during the Medieval Climate Anomaly. Comparisons with regional tree ring records and snowfall records from the Denali ice core indicate that this was a period of relatively warm and dry summers, which is consistent with the climate conditions that promote high Alaskan wildfire seasons over recent decades. In contrast, cooler and wetter summers from ca. 1402-1542, during the start of the Little Ice Age, were associated with significantly lower wildfire activity in the Denali ice core. Warming summer temperatures over the past several decades have been accompanied by an increase in Alaskan wildfire activity, but modern wildfire seasons are not as extreme as those recorded during the Medieval Climate Anomaly according to the Denali ice core record. We believe than a doubling of precipitation in Alaska since 1850 &ndash; also recorded by the Denali ice core &ndash; is likely suppressing wildfire activity despite the rising temperatures. However, we developed statistical relationships between temperature, precipitation, and Alaskan wildfire over the past 70 years, and applied these relationships to future predictions of Alaskan temperature and precipitation from state-of-the-art global climate models. We find that Alaskan wildfire activity is likely to continue to increase with warming temperatures from climate change over the 21<sup>st</sup>&nbsp;century, even with future increases in rainfall. By the end of the 21<sup>st</sup>&nbsp;century, Alaskan wildfire activity is projected to rival the highest levels of the past 1000 years &ndash; with burned area 160% higher than the 1950-2020 average &ndash; under an intermediate future emissions scenario.&nbsp;</p> <p>This projected supported two early-career researchers, four graduate students, and 15 undergraduate student researchers, including four senior honor&rsquo;s theses. Multiple presentations were made by researchers and students at national and international conferences, and one publication is in peer review with several others in preparation. We are partnering with education specialists at Colorado State University to develop STEM kits focused on the Denali ice core wildfire record for distribution to underserved K-12 students in Alaska and Maine. Prototypes of these kits have already been developed and tested with students.&nbsp;&nbsp;Datasets created during this project are publicly available at the National Climate Data Center (<a href="https://doi.org/10.25921/6cpm-kr44">https://doi.org/10.25921/6cpm-kr44</a>).</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 02/12/2024<br> Modified by: Erich&nbsp;Osterberg</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002424/2002424_10702065_1707715611177_Figure_1--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002424/2002424_10702065_1707715611177_Figure_1--rgov-800width.png" title="Alaskan Wildfire Record from Denali Ice Core, 1000 CE-Present"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002424/2002424_10702065_1707715611177_Figure_1--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Alaskan Wildfire Record from Denali Ice Core, 1000 CE-Present"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Alaskan wildfire record based on fire plume chemicals measured in the Denali ice core. Record displayed as 5-year averages (thin red), and a running 50-year average (black curve). Projections of future wildfire (thick red) based on CMIP5 RPC 4.5 and modern wildfire/climate relationships.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Modified from Youth, 2023</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Erich&nbsp;Osterberg <div class="imageTitle">Alaskan Wildfire Record from Denali Ice Core, 1000 CE-Present</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Alaska is warming twice as fast as the rest of the United States, and Alaskan wildfires have increased in frequency and burned area over recent decades as summers have warmed. Since 1990, ten Alaskan wildfire seasons exceeded two million total acres burned, whereas only five wildfire seasons reached that extreme level from 1950-1990. In addition to posing significant health, infrastructure, and economic risks to local communities, Alaskan wildfires impact natural ecosystems and can affect global climate through fire emissions of CO2and black carbon (soot). It is critical to understand how wildfire activity is likely to change in the future with continued climate change, but the instrumental wildfire record in Alaska is relatively short (extending back to ~1950), making it challenging to understand relationships between temperature, precipitation, and wildfire activity. Prior periods of natural climate change, including the so-called Medieval Climate Anomaly from ~1000-1300 CE, and the Little Ice Age from ~1400-1850, provide opportunities to examine past wildfire activity during times with relatively warm and cool summers, respectively. Ice cores recovered from Alaskan mountain glaciers preserve chemicals emitted by wildfire smoke plumes in their annual layers of snowfall and can therefore provide a record of wildfire activity extending centuries into the past.   In this project, we used an archive of the Denali Ice Core  collected in 2013 from Begguya, also known as Mount Hunter, in Denali National Park, Alaska  to develop a record of Alaskan wildfire activity extending over the past 1000 years. We used cutting-edge laboratory analysis methods to measure soot, as well as natural acids and sugar molecules that are only produced by wildfires, throughout the length of the ice core, collecting several samples from each annual layer of ice extending over the past millennium. This represents the first comprehensive record of wildfire in the Alaskan region extending from 1000 CE to present. We also conducted detailed analyses of how temperature, rainfall, atmospheric pressure, winds, and slope aspect affected Alaskan wildfire ignition, spread, and burned area over recent decades to better interpret the ice core record.   We find that Alaskan wildfire activity was significantly higher than modern levels between 10321362 C.E., during the Medieval Climate Anomaly. Comparisons with regional tree ring records and snowfall records from the Denali ice core indicate that this was a period of relatively warm and dry summers, which is consistent with the climate conditions that promote high Alaskan wildfire seasons over recent decades. In contrast, cooler and wetter summers from ca. 1402-1542, during the start of the Little Ice Age, were associated with significantly lower wildfire activity in the Denali ice core. Warming summer temperatures over the past several decades have been accompanied by an increase in Alaskan wildfire activity, but modern wildfire seasons are not as extreme as those recorded during the Medieval Climate Anomaly according to the Denali ice core record. We believe than a doubling of precipitation in Alaska since 1850  also recorded by the Denali ice core  is likely suppressing wildfire activity despite the rising temperatures. However, we developed statistical relationships between temperature, precipitation, and Alaskan wildfire over the past 70 years, and applied these relationships to future predictions of Alaskan temperature and precipitation from state-of-the-art global climate models. We find that Alaskan wildfire activity is likely to continue to increase with warming temperatures from climate change over the 21stcentury, even with future increases in rainfall. By the end of the 21stcentury, Alaskan wildfire activity is projected to rival the highest levels of the past 1000 years  with burned area 160% higher than the 1950-2020 average  under an intermediate future emissions scenario.   This projected supported two early-career researchers, four graduate students, and 15 undergraduate student researchers, including four senior honors theses. Multiple presentations were made by researchers and students at national and international conferences, and one publication is in peer review with several others in preparation. We are partnering with education specialists at Colorado State University to develop STEM kits focused on the Denali ice core wildfire record for distribution to underserved K-12 students in Alaska and Maine. Prototypes of these kits have already been developed and tested with students.Datasets created during this project are publicly available at the National Climate Data Center (https://doi.org/10.25921/6cpm-kr44).     Last Modified: 02/12/2024       Submitted by: ErichOsterberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
