<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Engineering Band Gap Energy Through Structural Motifs in Nitride Semiconductors]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>443064.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>443064</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yaroslav Koshka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ykoshka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924986</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical Summary&lt;br/&gt;Semiconductor materials form the basis for practically all electronics, from solar cells and solid state lighting, to complex integrated circuits such as microprocessors. Nevertheless, despite a century of investigation, researchers are still making fundamental discoveries in this field – discoveries which lead to improved device performance, reduced manufacturing cost, or streamlined integration with other technologies. The project activity is based on the unexpected discovery by the research team that the fundamental properties of semiconductor materials stem directly from atomic-scale structural motifs, and not deviations from periodicity as is generally accepted. By shifting that viewpoint, it is possible to achieve a much larger range of parameter values than previously realized. The result is a completely new approach to selecting materials for specific applications. The project also incorporates development of outreach activities for both middle school children and teachers, involving the community directly in the project by investigating how artificial intelligence/machine learning techniques are applied to image recognition and data analysis, thereby helping to ensure a diverse and  motivated pool of young students for careers in science/technology/engineering/math (STEM) fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;As part of a previous study on how cation disorder changes the band gap energy of the earth abundant element, sustainably-sourced ternary heterovalent semiconductor ZnSnN2, the research team has discovered the unexpected role played by structural motifs in determining this most fundamental of all semiconductor parameters. Carefully designed experiments indicate that it is not only possible to close the band gap of this material through systematic variation of the type and concentration of motifs that make up the lattice, but it is also possible to access "negative" band gap energies, corresponding to inverted bands. Further, preliminary evidence indicates that the same effect is possible in other compound semiconductors, including the commercially important InGaN family of materials, again through the action of structural motifs. The project investigates the full range of achievable band gap energies of both of these nitrogen-based material systems using plasma-assisted molecular beam epitaxy based crystal growth in conjunction with a complementary suite of optical absorption, Hall effect and electron and x-ray diffraction techniques, with a view towards understanding the ramifications for charge carrier transport, optical properties, and ultimately material selection choices for devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003581</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Durbin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M Durbin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[durbin@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000578728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Makin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert A Makin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[robert.makin@wmich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000802356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Michigan University]]></Name>
<CityName>KALAMAZOO</CityName>
<ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2693878298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1903 W MICHIGAN AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J7WULLYGFRH1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN MICHIGAN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Michigan University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>490085347</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>177500</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094Z</Code>
<Text>Materials Data</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8615</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Devices and Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~443064</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We successfully demonstrated how structural motifs, a fundamental unit of atomic lattices that can be used to describe nearest neighbor environments, are directly related to the charge carrier mobility in semiconductor materials. The mobility is an essential parameter of semiconductors critical to the design and performance of electronic devices, including solar cells, LEDs and laser diodes, and transistors. We showed how process parameters such as the power applied to a radio-frequency plasma source can be used to tune which structural motifs are present in the crystal and in what amounts, providing a new pathway to achieving the desired mobility and other material properties, obviating the need for traditional alloying and impurity doping approaches. We also demonstrated how the occurence of different varieties of structural motifs present in a given semiconductor crystal can dictate the charge carrier concentration, another critical parameter for electronic devices. The result is a new approach to materials-level property engineering, and a broader range of potential materials for different applications.</p> <p>A primary focus of the project was to investigate the potential utility of applying machine learning techniques to crystal growth. In particular, having two decades' worth of data from a specific machine used in thin film crystal synthesis in our possession, we wanted to train artificial neural networks to evaluate their ability to predict outcomes. This can be important when moving to new material systems, upgrading or replacing equipment, or seeking to improve baseline quality. Excellent agreement was found between predicted results based on the trained models and the vast body of literature available on nitride semiconductor thin film crystal growth. We also explored the potential for quantum machine learning algorithms compared to classical machine learning algorithms. We demonstrated that quantum machine learning algorithms routinely outperform other algorithms in terms of accuracy when the material-level figure of merit is the surface morphology of the sample. This suggests that machine learning techniques can be useful in predicting crystal synthesis process parameters needed to achieve desired outcomes, and that quantum-based algorithms, even when deployed on simulated quantum computers, can yield improved performance in some cases.</p> <p>Finally, we developed and delivered training to three different academic years' worth of 9<sup>th</sup> graders, focusing on basics of Python programming and essentials of machine learning. Approximately 150 students learned these skills in conjunction with real-time data acquisition and control applications using the inexpensive Raspberry Pi 400 system, picking up debugging skills along the way, and gaining insights into practical aspects of training and utilizing artificial neural networks.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/15/2024<br> Modified by: Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Durbin</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2003581/2003581_10664172_1729036966182_DraftImage__landscape__2--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2003581/2003581_10664172_1729036966182_DraftImage__landscape__2--rgov-800width.png" title="Graphical Abstract of Completed Project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2003581/2003581_10664172_1729036966182_DraftImage__landscape__2--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Graphical Abstract of Completed Project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Series of images illustrating the project; Three different atomic lattices with different structural motifs; photo of a molecular beam epitaxy system; example machine learning output; carrier mobility plot in the context of disorder; setup used to teaching Python and machine learning to 9th graders.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Scott and Steve Durbin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Durbin <div class="imageTitle">Graphical Abstract of Completed Project</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  We successfully demonstrated how structural motifs, a fundamental unit of atomic lattices that can be used to describe nearest neighbor environments, are directly related to the charge carrier mobility in semiconductor materials. The mobility is an essential parameter of semiconductors critical to the design and performance of electronic devices, including solar cells, LEDs and laser diodes, and transistors. We showed how process parameters such as the power applied to a radio-frequency plasma source can be used to tune which structural motifs are present in the crystal and in what amounts, providing a new pathway to achieving the desired mobility and other material properties, obviating the need for traditional alloying and impurity doping approaches. We also demonstrated how the occurence of different varieties of structural motifs present in a given semiconductor crystal can dictate the charge carrier concentration, another critical parameter for electronic devices. The result is a new approach to materials-level property engineering, and a broader range of potential materials for different applications.   A primary focus of the project was to investigate the potential utility of applying machine learning techniques to crystal growth. In particular, having two decades' worth of data from a specific machine used in thin film crystal synthesis in our possession, we wanted to train artificial neural networks to evaluate their ability to predict outcomes. This can be important when moving to new material systems, upgrading or replacing equipment, or seeking to improve baseline quality. Excellent agreement was found between predicted results based on the trained models and the vast body of literature available on nitride semiconductor thin film crystal growth. We also explored the potential for quantum machine learning algorithms compared to classical machine learning algorithms. We demonstrated that quantum machine learning algorithms routinely outperform other algorithms in terms of accuracy when the material-level figure of merit is the surface morphology of the sample. This suggests that machine learning techniques can be useful in predicting crystal synthesis process parameters needed to achieve desired outcomes, and that quantum-based algorithms, even when deployed on simulated quantum computers, can yield improved performance in some cases.   Finally, we developed and delivered training to three different academic years' worth of 9th graders, focusing on basics of Python programming and essentials of machine learning. Approximately 150 students learned these skills in conjunction with real-time data acquisition and control applications using the inexpensive Raspberry Pi 400 system, picking up debugging skills along the way, and gaining insights into practical aspects of training and utilizing artificial neural networks.     Last Modified: 10/15/2024       Submitted by: StevenMDurbin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
