<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Novel Superconducting Physics Through Microwave Imaging]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>649563.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>649563</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Superconductivity is a game-changing technology that has enabled widespread use of magnetic resonance imaging for medical diagnosis, and is the leading technology platform in the emerging quantum information revolution.  The research project addresses some of the grand challenges of superconductivity for societal needs: The search for a room temperature superconductor that will enable high-impact technologies that will generate tremendous wealth for the nation.  Such materials will revolutionize the distribution of electricity as well as information technology, bringing unparalleled benefit to society.  The search for these new superconducting materials is enabled by the PI’s invention and development of a new microscope specifically designed to image the properties of superconducting materials.  It is part of a discovery process carried out in collaboration with creative materials growers at the University of Maryland and Rutgers University.  The project will also rigorously train two graduate students to attack complex problems and solve them in a creative and quantitative manner.  The students will go on to contribute to the further development of superconductors into high-impact and widely beneficial technologies.  The PI continues to address under-represented groups through both research inclusion and outreach such as Physics is Phun and the Physics Summer Girls Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt; The research team is investigating cutting-edge superconducting phenomena with a novel microscope of their own invention.  The PI has developed a new microscopic tool that can image superconducting gap nodal directions in real space, and measure zero-energy excitations that exist due to nodal gap structure.  The PI’s microscope images the nonlinear Meissner response of superconductors along with nonlinear response from any other zero-energy excitations that live on the surface of the superconducting material (e.g. Andreev bound states, Majorana zero modes, etc.).  The research project goals are to elucidate the pairing state symmetry of new superconducting materials with exotic properties such as proximity-coupled s-wave / topological insulator systems, and superconductors with putative j = 3/2 spin pairing.  The PI’s microscope is particularly well suited to investigate the predicted Bogoliubov Fermi surface in these materials.  The team is also investigating two systems that are proposed to have a change in pairing state symmetry as a function of either doping or pressure.  The microscope can also sensitively measure the complex surface impedance as a function of temperature to provide cross-checking information on the imaging results.  The team is developing a new high-pressure version of the microscope to measure contact-free the Meissner state screening and macroscopic quantum properties of superconductors under extreme conditions where such measurements have never been accomplished before.  With the assistance of creative materials collaborators at Maryland and Rutgers, the team is using this new microscope as a powerful tool for discovery and investigation of the basic properties of exotic superconductors in the temperature-doping-pressure phase diagram.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Anlage</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M Anlage</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anlage@physics.umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000197922</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BUILDING]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1363 John S. Toll Physics Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>171000</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~229959</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~419604</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We have explored and discovered new superconducting physics through careful microwave electrodynamics measurements of correlated-electron materials.&nbsp; These are materials that have unique and unusual properties due to quantum mechanical phenomena that dominate their physical properties.&nbsp; Such quantum materials bring new types of physics and applications, and may be a key ingredient for new technologies such as topological quantum computing, or other technologies that have not yet been discovered.&nbsp; Our interest is in p-wave superconductors that involve Cooper pairs of electrons that orbit each other with one unit of quantized angular momentum.&nbsp; These superconductors are uncommon in nature and have extreme quantum properties.&nbsp; The p-wave Cooper pairs are expected to be in a spin-triplet quantum state, which means that they should survive to very large magnetic fields as compared to almost all other superconducting materials, and this is observed to be the case in the material of our greatest interest, UTe<sub>2</sub>.&nbsp; If p-wave superconductors could be made with transition temperatures between 10 and 100 K, they would enable a new class of extreme high-field magnets, substantially beyond anything available today, which could hasten the development of fusion energy, among other benefits to society.&nbsp; Hence, we are motivated to understand the microscopic physics of these materials in detail, with the hopes of replicating their behavior in other materials systems with higher transition temperatures.&nbsp; Our focus has been on the response of single crystals of the heavy-Fermion superconductor UTe<sub>2</sub> to microwave radiation.&nbsp; By studying how the material responds to electromagnetic waves we can learn about its superconducting order parameter, Cooper-paring state of the electrons, and identify new topological properties that are brought about by its unusual superconducting state.&nbsp; The project has indeed provided such insights and has trained a graduate student to tackle complex problems and to make scientific discoveries at the frontiers of knowledge.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/04/2024<br> Modified by: Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Anlage</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2004386/2004386_10687862_1733081948769_Images_for_NSF_Outcomes_UTe2_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2004386/2004386_10687862_1733081948769_Images_for_NSF_Outcomes_UTe2_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pairing State of UTe2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2004386/2004386_10687862_1733081948769_Images_for_NSF_Outcomes_UTe2_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pairing State of UTe2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Possible electron pairing states and superconducting order parameters for the heavy-Fermion superconductor UTe2.  Our electrodynamics measurements can help distinguish which of these states are present.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Arthur Carlton-Jones and Steven M. Anlage, University of Maryland</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Anlage <div class="imageTitle">Pairing State of UTe2</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2004386/2004386_10687862_1733082135183_Images_for_NSF_Outcomes_UTe2_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2004386/2004386_10687862_1733082135183_Images_for_NSF_Outcomes_UTe2_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Microwave Electrodynamics Experiment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2004386/2004386_10687862_1733082135183_Images_for_NSF_Outcomes_UTe2_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Microwave Electrodynamics Experiment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Experimental setup for measurements of the heavy-Fermion superconductor UTe2.  The single crystal sample is placed inside the microwave resonator.  Some representative experimental surface impedance data is shown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Arthur Carlton-Jones and Steven M. Anlage, University of Maryland</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Anlage <div class="imageTitle">Microwave Electrodynamics Experiment</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  We have explored and discovered new superconducting physics through careful microwave electrodynamics measurements of correlated-electron materials. These are materials that have unique and unusual properties due to quantum mechanical phenomena that dominate their physical properties. Such quantum materials bring new types of physics and applications, and may be a key ingredient for new technologies such as topological quantum computing, or other technologies that have not yet been discovered. Our interest is in p-wave superconductors that involve Cooper pairs of electrons that orbit each other with one unit of quantized angular momentum. These superconductors are uncommon in nature and have extreme quantum properties. The p-wave Cooper pairs are expected to be in a spin-triplet quantum state, which means that they should survive to very large magnetic fields as compared to almost all other superconducting materials, and this is observed to be the case in the material of our greatest interest, UTe2. If p-wave superconductors could be made with transition temperatures between 10 and 100 K, they would enable a new class of extreme high-field magnets, substantially beyond anything available today, which could hasten the development of fusion energy, among other benefits to society. Hence, we are motivated to understand the microscopic physics of these materials in detail, with the hopes of replicating their behavior in other materials systems with higher transition temperatures. Our focus has been on the response of single crystals of the heavy-Fermion superconductor UTe2 to microwave radiation. By studying how the material responds to electromagnetic waves we can learn about its superconducting order parameter, Cooper-paring state of the electrons, and identify new topological properties that are brought about by its unusual superconducting state. The project has indeed provided such insights and has trained a graduate student to tackle complex problems and to make scientific discoveries at the frontiers of knowledge.     Last Modified: 12/04/2024       Submitted by: StevenMAnlage]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
