<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SciGirls in the National Parks: Building Positive STEM Identities in Underserved Girls in Citizen Science Programs Using Gender Equitable and Culturally Responsive Practices]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2999495.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2999495</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin A. Clark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kevclark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As part of its overall strategy to enhance learning in informal environments, the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program funds innovative resources for use in a variety of settings.  This Innovations in Development project addresses the need to broaden girls’ participation in STEM studies and career pathways. While women make up 47% of the U.S. workforce, they hold only 28.3% of STEM jobs and only 1 in 10 employed engineers and scientists are minority women. Girls of low socioeconomic status start losing interest and confidence in STEM during middle school, and this decline often continues as girls get older. Multiple sociocultural barriers contribute to girl’s loss of confidence including gender and ethnic stereotypes; lack of culturally responsive programming; limited exposure to women role models; and few or no hands-on STEM experiences. This project builds upon the success of SciGirls, the PBS television show and national outreach program, which provides professional development on research-based gender equitable and culturally responsive teaching strategies designed to engage girls in STEM. It is a collaboration between Twin Cities Public Television, the Cornell Lab of Ornithology, and the National Park Service. The project’s goal is to create media-rich citizen science experiences for girls, particularly girls of color and/or from rural areas, which broaden their STEM participation, build positive STEM identities and increase girls’ understanding of scientific concepts, while leveraging citizen  science engagement at  national parks.  Project deliverables include  1) creating five new PBS SciGirls episodes that feature real girls working with women mentors in 16 National Parks, 2) producing five new role model videos of women National Park Service STEM professionals, nationally disseminated on multiple PBS platforms, 3) providing professional development for educators and role models.  This project will increase access to STEM education for girls of color and/or from rural areas, inspiring and preparing them for future STEM workforce participation. It will build the capacity of educators and National Park Service women role models to create educational and professional programs that are welcoming to girls of varying racial, ethnic, socioeconomic, and geographic backgrounds. SciGirls’ massive reach to diverse audiences via PBS broadcast and multiple PBS digital platforms will amplify public scientific literacy, particularly for 21st- century audiences that connect, learn and live online.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The research study conducted by the Cornell Lab of Ornithology will address these questions: 1) To what extent does the use of culturally responsive and gender equitable multimedia in citizen science programming affect girls’ learning outcomes, and contribute to the development of positive STEM identity? 2) how will their experiencing citizen science in the parks influence girls’ connection to nature? At the beginning of the project all participating girls (n=160) will complete a survey on their interest in science, efficacy for doing science, and knowledge of citizen science and project-specific subject matter. Researchers will use the suite of DEVISE instruments most of which have been validated for youth to measure these constructs. To measure connection to nature, researchers will use the Connection to Nature Index, a scale developed for children. Interviews with the girls will be used to obtain qualitative data to supplement the survey data. Pre-post data will be analyzed to determine the influence of the culturally responsive media and experiences on girls’ STEM identities. Researchers will share findings with the project evaluator to triangulate data between educators’ implementation of the strategies and girls’ learning outcome providing a more holistic picture of the overall program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004085</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Bonney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard E Bonney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[reb5@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000201013</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rita</FirstName>
<LastName>Karl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rita K Karl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rkarl@tpt.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000661303</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/20/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Peterson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen A Peterson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kpeterson@ngcproject.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000690986</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
<LastName>Pederson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristin Pederson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kpederson@tpt.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000765211</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Twin Cities Public Television]]></Name>
<CityName>SAINT PAUL</CityName>
<ZipCode>551011492</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6512291347</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[172 4TH ST E]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PWSSQNG9W2C7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TWIN CITIES PUBLIC TELEVISION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PWSSQNG9W2C7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Twin Cities Public Television]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Paul</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>551011492</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[172 E 4th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>725900</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~2405415</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~594080</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align: center;"><strong><em>SciGirls in the National Parks: Building Positive STEM Identities in Underserved Girls in Citizen Science Programs Using Gender Equitable and Culturally Responsive Practices<br /> <br /> </em></strong></p> <p class="paragraph">Since the 1980s, the practice of citizen science has inspired learners of all ages to notice, explore and contribute to the science that surrounds them in their daily lives. Meaningful citizen science initiatives have allowed participants to augment their own science learning while helping to advance real-world research and discovery.</p> <p>Despite these benefits, significant barriers to citizen science exist. Data indicates low participation among youth of color and/or lower socioeconomic status. Programming is often only available in afterschool or informal learning spaces that are not always easily accessible due to financial, transportation or time limitations. Finally, not all citizen science leaders are prepared to identify implicit and explicit bias, incorporate participants&rsquo; lived experiences or engage diverse perspectives, all of which are critical to equitable program design and implementation. &nbsp;</p> <p class="paragraph">To address these challenges, Twin Cities PBS partnered with the Cornell Lab of Ornithology, the National Girls Collaborative and the National Park Service (NPS) to create <em>SciGirls in the National Parks.</em> This initiative was the seventh season of the NSF-supported <em>SciGirls</em> program, which includes an Emmy Award-winning PBS series and a national informal education initiative that inspires and motivates girls (ages 8-12), families and educators around gender-equitable STEM studies and career paths.&nbsp;</p> <p class="paragraph">The project goal was to create media-rich citizen science experiences for girls, particularly girls of color and/or from rural areas, which broaden STEM participation, build positive STEM identities and increase understanding of scientific concepts. Project components included: &nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Media:</strong> Five new&nbsp;<em>SciGirls</em>&nbsp;episodes, disseminated to public media stations nationwide, featured real girls working with women NPS mentors on park-based citizen science. A role model video, shared across multiple PBS platforms, profiled a dynamic NPS professional. All media was also employed in the project&rsquo;s outreach and knowledge-building studies.</li> <li> <strong>Professional Development:</strong> Thirty-six girl-serving organization (GSO) educators and STEM professional role models from national parks participated in research-based workshops that prepared them for equitable program implementation.</li> <li> <strong>Youth Programming:</strong> Fourteen GSOs were paired with fourteen geographically diverse national parks, engaging 294 girls and their families in 32+ hours of hands-on citizen science learning within park settings.</li> <li> <strong>Knowledge Building:</strong> The project&rsquo;s study addressed the question: <em>To what extent does the use of culturally responsive and gender-equitable multimedia (video and games) in citizen science programming affect girls&rsquo; proximal and distal learning outcomes, and contribute to the development of positive STEM identity?</em></li> <li> <strong>Digital Games:</strong> The updated citizen science-related games, &ldquo;Creature Feature&rdquo; and &ldquo;Rule the Roost,&rdquo; are available on PBSkids.org/scigirls, and are updated monthly for refreshed play sessions.</li> <li> <strong>Website: </strong>To sustainably share almost two decades of NSF-supported STEM educational resources, the TPT team produced tptlearn.org. This new site highlights seven seasons of <em>SciGirls </em>content, including <em>SciGirls in the Parks</em>, and works in tandem with the PBS LearningMedia site (<a href="https://pbslearningmedia.org/">https://pbslearningmedia.org/</a> ) to ensure free access to STEM content.</li> </ul> <p>All project components were informed by the research-based <em>SciGirls Strategies: How to Engage Girls in STEM, </em>which highlights role modeling as a pathway to STEM engagement. The project tangibly employed this strategy, providing youth participants with in-person and media-based STEM role models, including NPS rangers, nature interpreters, science educators and researchers. Media data demonstrated PBS&rsquo;s powerful national reach, with Season Seven joining existing episodes to foster 1,865,000&nbsp;viewer impressions and 9.8 million digital streams during this reporting period. (Notably, the <em>SciGirls </em>initiative writ large also finished strong, fostering 60,970,408&nbsp;viewer impressions and over 100 million digital streams since the series&rsquo; launch).</p> <p class="paragraph">The project&rsquo;s research study spanned two years and explored changes in four aspects of STEM Identity: 1) Interest in Science, 2) Self-efficacy for Learning and Doing Science, 3) Recognition as a Science Person, and 4) Knowledge of Citizen Science. The team saw strong pre/post gains in all aspects in the aggregated data, and discovered that increased use of <em>SciGirls </em>media had a significant, positive association with four of five STEM identity measures.</p> <p class="paragraph">The project&rsquo;s evaluation illuminated multiple positive impacts, including the establishment of sustainable relationships between parks and partner organizations, increased engagement of girls in outdoor learning, and improvement in educators&rsquo; instructional practices. &#8239;Data also indicated potential for lasting effects on educators, including the integration of citizen science and <em>SciGirls Strategies</em> into programming and greater expertise in employing media as a teaching tool.&nbsp;All knowledge-building findings are available on informalscience.org.</p> <p>Through this innovative combination of media, role modeling and outreach, <em>SciGirls in the National Parks</em> helped inspire youth and prepare educators around citizen science. Exposure to STEM professionals also offered girls a glimpse into future workforce opportunities, and knowledge-building findings will inform future project design. Finally, the project introduced diverse learners&mdash;many of whom had never experienced a state or national park&mdash;to the wonder, beauty and STEM learning opportunities such spaces afford.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/22/2024<br> Modified by: Kristin&nbsp;Pederson</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  SciGirls in the National Parks: Building Positive STEM Identities in Underserved Girls in Citizen Science Programs Using Gender Equitable and Culturally Responsive Practices       Since the 1980s, the practice of citizen science has inspired learners of all ages to notice, explore and contribute to the science that surrounds them in their daily lives. Meaningful citizen science initiatives have allowed participants to augment their own science learning while helping to advance real-world research and discovery.   Despite these benefits, significant barriers to citizen science exist. Data indicates low participation among youth of color and/or lower socioeconomic status. Programming is often only available in afterschool or informal learning spaces that are not always easily accessible due to financial, transportation or time limitations. Finally, not all citizen science leaders are prepared to identify implicit and explicit bias, incorporate participants lived experiences or engage diverse perspectives, all of which are critical to equitable program design and implementation.    To address these challenges, Twin Cities PBS partnered with the Cornell Lab of Ornithology, the National Girls Collaborative and the National Park Service (NPS) to create SciGirls in the National Parks. This initiative was the seventh season of the NSF-supported SciGirls program, which includes an Emmy Award-winning PBS series and a national informal education initiative that inspires and motivates girls (ages 8-12), families and educators around gender-equitable STEM studies and career paths.   The project goal was to create media-rich citizen science experiences for girls, particularly girls of color and/or from rural areas, which broaden STEM participation, build positive STEM identities and increase understanding of scientific concepts. Project components included:   Media: Five newSciGirlsepisodes, disseminated to public media stations nationwide, featured real girls working with women NPS mentors on park-based citizen science. A role model video, shared across multiple PBS platforms, profiled a dynamic NPS professional. All media was also employed in the projects outreach and knowledge-building studies.  Professional Development: Thirty-six girl-serving organization (GSO) educators and STEM professional role models from national parks participated in research-based workshops that prepared them for equitable program implementation.  Youth Programming: Fourteen GSOs were paired with fourteen geographically diverse national parks, engaging 294 girls and their families in 32+ hours of hands-on citizen science learning within park settings.  Knowledge Building: The projects study addressed the question: To what extent does the use of culturally responsive and gender-equitable multimedia (video and games) in citizen science programming affect girls proximal and distal learning outcomes, and contribute to the development of positive STEM identity?  Digital Games: The updated citizen science-related games, Creature Feature and Rule the Roost, are available on PBSkids.org/scigirls, and are updated monthly for refreshed play sessions.  Website: To sustainably share almost two decades of NSF-supported STEM educational resources, the TPT team produced tptlearn.org. This new site highlights seven seasons of SciGirls content, including SciGirls in the Parks, and works in tandem with the PBS LearningMedia site (https://pbslearningmedia.org/ ) to ensure free access to STEM content.    All project components were informed by the research-based SciGirls Strategies: How to Engage Girls in STEM, which highlights role modeling as a pathway to STEM engagement. The project tangibly employed this strategy, providing youth participants with in-person and media-based STEM role models, including NPS rangers, nature interpreters, science educators and researchers. Media data demonstrated PBSs powerful national reach, with Season Seven joining existing episodes to foster 1,865,000viewer impressions and 9.8 million digital streams during this reporting period. (Notably, the SciGirls initiative writ large also finished strong, fostering 60,970,408viewer impressions and over 100 million digital streams since the series launch).   The projects research study spanned two years and explored changes in four aspects of STEM Identity: 1) Interest in Science, 2) Self-efficacy for Learning and Doing Science, 3) Recognition as a Science Person, and 4) Knowledge of Citizen Science. The team saw strong pre/post gains in all aspects in the aggregated data, and discovered that increased use of SciGirls media had a significant, positive association with four of five STEM identity measures.   The projects evaluation illuminated multiple positive impacts, including the establishment of sustainable relationships between parks and partner organizations, increased engagement of girls in outdoor learning, and improvement in educators instructional practices. &#8239;Data also indicated potential for lasting effects on educators, including the integration of citizen science and SciGirls Strategies into programming and greater expertise in employing media as a teaching tool.All knowledge-building findings are available on informalscience.org.   Through this innovative combination of media, role modeling and outreach, SciGirls in the National Parks helped inspire youth and prepare educators around citizen science. Exposure to STEM professionals also offered girls a glimpse into future workforce opportunities, and knowledge-building findings will inform future project design. Finally, the project introduced diverse learnersmany of whom had never experienced a state or national parkto the wonder, beauty and STEM learning opportunities such spaces afford.     Last Modified: 10/22/2024       Submitted by: KristinPederson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
