<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Documenting contact and shift in a demonstrative system]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38118.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38118</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rachel M. Theodore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rtheodor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924770</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Urbanization, globalization, and environmental variability are working together to transform the Arctic region's geophysical environment, economies, and societies. Language use, particularly that by Indigenous peoples, is also profoundly affected; urbanization, for instance, brings with it considerable social and cultural change, as well as assimilation to a majority language. Environmental variability and urbanization are altering both the geophysical environment itself and the way people engage with it, as people increasingly live in urban settings and traditional ways of life are deeply altered. Language is following suit; this is particularly clear in the language used to describe the environment which is linked to subsistence activities within the traditional landscape. All languages have words for referring to aspects of the context surrounding the speech event, which may include the spatial context (e.g. here/there, this/that), the temporal context (e.g. now), speech participants (e.g. I, you, we), or other aspects. There is significant linguistic variation in which contextual aspects are encoded. Demonstratives are "pointers," or deictic words that serve to locate or point out a specific referent within the context. English makes a two-way distinction, contrasting "here/there" or "this/that." Other languages distinguish more deictic categories. Three-way distinctions (here/there/over there) are not uncommon, while others have considerably more. Some of the larger systems use demonstratives in ways that invoke aspects of the geophysical context for locating referents. However, in line with the broader geophysical changes in the real world, the linguistic systems are currently undergoing significant change and reduction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will document and analyze ongoing change in one such demonstrative system, documenting use and variation across different groups of speakers, in order to understand its trajectory of change and unpack the factors influencing the system. Contact with the majority, national language plays an important role, as does contact with globally dominant languages. As demonstratives are anchored to the environment, this research further speaks to the relationship between language and environment, especially within the context of rapid environmental change and evolving human-environment interactions as seen across the region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004015</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lenore</FirstName>
<LastName>Grenoble</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lenore A Grenoble</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[grenoble@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000563381</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hilary</FirstName>
<LastName>McMahan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hilary A McMahan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mcmahanh@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810829</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5801 S ELLIS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6054 South Drexel Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>522100</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~38118</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ab4d1c4a-7fff-6560-89d1-6bfd070f1486"> </span></p>  <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c8fb5d08-7fff-085b-25e3-071b48aa4a95"> </span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Our project has investigated the grammatical system of demonstratives in Kalaallisut, an Inuit language spoken primarily in Greenland, as well as in Denmark. Demonstratives are words like "this"/"that" and "here"/"there", which are used by speakers to refer to things or places in the context of speech. In languages like English, demonstratives indicate a referent with respect to nearness to the speaker, e.g. "here" versus "there". In contrast, Kalaallisut has a much larger demonstrative system that encodes numerous spatial relationships, such as vertical orientation, interior/exterior orientation, orientation to the landscape, and cardinal direction. In this way, the Kalaallisut demonstrative system is cross-linguistically very uncommon, both in terms of its size and the directional distinctions it encodes.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>However, this demonstrative system is currently undergoing rapid change. Many speakers now use a much smaller set of demonstratives in daily life, and many of the traditional meanings and usages are shifting, with the possibility of loss over time. The research focus of this project has been to gain a better understanding of how the system is changing and of what factors are motivating these changes. To this end, data collection consisted of linguistic fieldwork with Kalaallisut speakers in Greenland and Denmark, during which 33 speakers were interviewed using a combination of methods aimed at eliciting usage and knowledge of the demonstratives in different contexts. The speakers interviewed represent a variety of demographics, including age, gender, hometown, and language experience.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Our overall findings depict a linguistic system that is undergoing change and reduction through the influence of broader sociocultural transformations in Greenland. The data from this project illustrate a combination of changes in meaning, usage, and knowledge within the demonstratives, in parallel with processes of urbanization, multilingualism, and globalization. Our research shows that speakers with the most reduced and least conservative demonstrative systems tend to be younger, from the capital city Nuuk or other areas which practice fewer traditional subsistence activities, and/or have had greater exposure to Danish at a young age. Conversely, speakers who have retained a more conservative system tended to be older, from smaller settlements in Greenland, and come from families who engage with traditional subsistence activities, particularly hunting.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>The research described here has implications both within the field of linguistics and more broadly, as it speaks to large-scale social, environmental, and economic phenomena across the Arctic. Beyond contributing to the linguistic knowledge base regarding Kalaallisut language use and the workings of a complex demonstrative system, this project informs our understanding of how language change unfolds in the context of internal and external linguistic factors as well as non-linguistic factors. In particular, this research sheds lights on the extent and possibilities of contact-induced change, showing the effects of multilingualism and intercultural contact on a grammatical system. Furthermore, our work helps elucidate the relationship between language and environment, particularly in the context of environmental transformations like those witnessed today in the Arctic. Broadly, our project contributes to a greater understanding of the impacts of urbanization, globalization, migration, and environmental change on ancestral language use within indigenous communities, which is tied to cultural vitality and well-being in the Arctic.</span></p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <div><span><br /></span></div>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/30/2024<br> Modified by: Hilary&nbsp;A&nbsp;Mcmahan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[            Our project has investigated the grammatical system of demonstratives in Kalaallisut, an Inuit language spoken primarily in Greenland, as well as in Denmark. Demonstratives are words like "this"/"that" and "here"/"there", which are used by speakers to refer to things or places in the context of speech. In languages like English, demonstratives indicate a referent with respect to nearness to the speaker, e.g. "here" versus "there". In contrast, Kalaallisut has a much larger demonstrative system that encodes numerous spatial relationships, such as vertical orientation, interior/exterior orientation, orientation to the landscape, and cardinal direction. In this way, the Kalaallisut demonstrative system is cross-linguistically very uncommon, both in terms of its size and the directional distinctions it encodes.    However, this demonstrative system is currently undergoing rapid change. Many speakers now use a much smaller set of demonstratives in daily life, and many of the traditional meanings and usages are shifting, with the possibility of loss over time. The research focus of this project has been to gain a better understanding of how the system is changing and of what factors are motivating these changes. To this end, data collection consisted of linguistic fieldwork with Kalaallisut speakers in Greenland and Denmark, during which 33 speakers were interviewed using a combination of methods aimed at eliciting usage and knowledge of the demonstratives in different contexts. The speakers interviewed represent a variety of demographics, including age, gender, hometown, and language experience.    Our overall findings depict a linguistic system that is undergoing change and reduction through the influence of broader sociocultural transformations in Greenland. The data from this project illustrate a combination of changes in meaning, usage, and knowledge within the demonstratives, in parallel with processes of urbanization, multilingualism, and globalization. Our research shows that speakers with the most reduced and least conservative demonstrative systems tend to be younger, from the capital city Nuuk or other areas which practice fewer traditional subsistence activities, and/or have had greater exposure to Danish at a young age. Conversely, speakers who have retained a more conservative system tended to be older, from smaller settlements in Greenland, and come from families who engage with traditional subsistence activities, particularly hunting.    The research described here has implications both within the field of linguistics and more broadly, as it speaks to large-scale social, environmental, and economic phenomena across the Arctic. Beyond contributing to the linguistic knowledge base regarding Kalaallisut language use and the workings of a complex demonstrative system, this project informs our understanding of how language change unfolds in the context of internal and external linguistic factors as well as non-linguistic factors. In particular, this research sheds lights on the extent and possibilities of contact-induced change, showing the effects of multilingualism and intercultural contact on a grammatical system. Furthermore, our work helps elucidate the relationship between language and environment, particularly in the context of environmental transformations like those witnessed today in the Arctic. Broadly, our project contributes to a greater understanding of the impacts of urbanization, globalization, migration, and environmental change on ancestral language use within indigenous communities, which is tied to cultural vitality and well-being in the Arctic.                    Last Modified: 12/30/2024       Submitted by: HilaryAMcmahan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
