<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Cultivating Science: Examining the Free-Choice Science Learning Networks of Urban Gardeners]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299901.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299901</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lynn Tran</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ltran@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Free-choice and interest-driven learning activities are a highly significant source of STEM (science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) learning for adults through their lifespans. Gardening is one such activity that is widespread across communities with one in every fifty American adults reporting an interest in gardening/plants and who associate that interest/hobby with science. While the terms interest and hobby are related, the latter refers to something one actively does, not just thinks about doing. Adults who seek out learning and participation opportunities in highly visible community spaces (e.g., gardening clubs, science centers, botanical gardens) are likely to be White and well-educated. Further understanding is needed of when and how community members from other demographic groups access different resources (people, organizations, and places) for information and opportunities, and what influences them to do so. This Pilot and Feasibility Study will explore informal learning networks in Alameda County, California, specifically around gardeners and gardening. Researchers will use surveys, focus groups, and program observations to gather data on how those who pursue self-directed scientific learning about gardening access information. Of interest is how the differential access to and pursuit of information occurs among diverse community members, especially those outside of more established Master Gardener and other organized gardening programs. This research will: 1) contribute to understanding of the resources that interest-driven adult STEM learners access, describing the barriers they perceive and how/if the accessed resources differ by gender, race, or socioeconomics; 2) determine the feasibility of a sampling approach to gather data from individuals in demographic groups who may not have been reached in prior research efforts; and 3) generate insights for informal science education practitioners and researchers about how to better support diverse interest-driven STEM learners. This project is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is hypothesized that there is a large percentage of individuals from non-dominant populations engaged in free-choice STEM learning; past efforts have likely under-counted the participation of individuals from these communities. To achieve the research aims the research team will utilize respondent-driven sampling, engaging gardening hobbyists’ social contacts to recruit participants, and collect data from diverse (gender, race, socioeconomics) urban gardeners who may be differently connected to STEM learning ecosystem resources/organizations than their highly visible peers. This approach will be used to investigate the behaviors, perceptions, and outcomes related to STEM learning such as development of self-efficacy and science identity. Focus groups will provide context for themes that arise in the survey data and clarify hobbyists’ participation preferences and experiences. In situ observations of learning environments comprise the third mechanism for collecting data. All three data sources will support triangulation of results and contribute to the findings. Key outcomes of this project will be to determine if the target population has been reached through the sampling approach, to identify methodological guidelines for sampling with an intent to reach those from populations under-represented in STEM-related free-choice activities, and to clarify which network variables are most useful to study. This research lays the foundation for future work. It is anticipated that the approach developed and tested in this research may be adapted by others in the future and will have the potential to serve as a model for community-based organizations and researchers interested in studying the learning ecosystems of previously hidden populations of participants, including how these individuals perceive and access resources to support their STEM learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005840</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elysa</FirstName>
<LastName>Corin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elysa N Corin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[elysa.corin@freechoicelearning.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Institute for Learning Innovation]]></Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>972174141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4432230694</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5637 N GREELEY AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HYX9HNCUQC35</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INSTITUTE FOR LEARNING INNOVATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Institute for Learning Innovation]]></Name>
<CityName>Beaverton</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>970087105</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9450 SW Gemini Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>725900</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299901</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Introduction:</p>  <p>We developed and tested a snowball sampling method to collect data from 350 diverse adult urban gardeners in the Berkeley/Oakland (California) area to understand how gardeners and plant lovers from different backgrounds use suites of resources, including local places, people, groups for their plant-related activities and learning. The sample varied across multiple dimensions including age, race/ethnicity, gender, income, education, languages spoken, participation frequency, and interests. The online survey took place during the COVID-19 pandemic, which also allowed us to study how participation changed due to the pandemic as well as the benefits experienced.</p>  <p><br />Benefits:&nbsp;</p>  <p>Individuals reported many specific benefits to participating in their plant and gardening hobby. The most impactful included: "Happiness or joy", "Feeling of connection to the natural world", "Stress relief", "The appearance of my surroundings". Additionally, results illustrate the role a science-based hobby such as gardening plays in supporting participants' well-being (intellectual, emotional, social, physical) during an extreme event such as the COVID-19 pandemic and during the following period of great societal uncertainty and stress. Benefits were observed for participants across demographics, by gender, age, race, and socioeconomics, which speaks to the broad appeal of this highly accessible activity. While focusing more on plants in one's home and immediate environment was expected, findings also highlight how gardening brought people together during a period of crisis and loneliness, and how it facilitated profound individual introspection and self-directed change due to the COVID-19 shock.</p>  <p><br />Activities:</p>  <p>Study participants were asked to report on how they participate in their plant and gardening interests, providing feedback on 30 different activities. Seven core activities were found in the top 10 across demographic groups (gender, race/ethnicity, income). These common "top" activities were: grow plants for food, grow plants for decoration or aesthetics/beauty, tend plants at your home (or the home of a family member), weed, start plants from seeds, propagate plants from cuttings, read to learn about plants and gardening. The activity with highest participation was "grow plants for decoration," cited by 72-90% of sampled individuals across the three demographic categories. Next was "grow plants for food," which was listed by 67-88% per subgroup. Fewer than half the sample reported volunteering their time related to plants and gardening, with a large difference apparent by income level: 40% of sampled respondents with low incomes and 17% with high incomes reported volunteering. Other large differences included tending plants at your home or the home of a family member (89% of white respondents, 57% of Black respondents), propagating plants from cuttings (73% of Asian respondents, 46% of Black respondents), and organizing activities for others (26% of Black respondents, 10% of Hispanic respondents).</p>  <p><br />Local Places:</p>  <p>We asked community members to share whether, during the past five years, they visited any of over 250 local places to participate in their plant interest (e.g., buy supplies, attend a course, admire plants). Places included botanic gardens, community gardens, local farms, plant nurseries, stores with garden supplies, famer's markets, seed lending libraries, parks/trails. Around 15 places fell in the top 20 for each demographic subgroup, with some places listed higher by some groups than others. Thirteen places were named by at least half of sampled participants, and 26 were named by at least a third. The most named place, selected by 73% of individuals, was a local grocery store that sells fresh produce, potted plants, and cut flowers. Grocery and hardware stores, as well as parks, figured prominently in places people use to engage in their gardening interests. Garden-specific places (e.g., plant nurseries, seed lending libraries) were common enough but typically not as popular. This work supports the narrative that most hobbyists carry their interest in plants and gardening with them throughout the day and look for incidental, opportunistic, ways to participate when going to the grocery store, walking through their neighborhood, or visiting a park. While some individuals did spend a great deal of time and resources participating in their hobby (particularly individuals with more time and financial means), this was not the most common experience.</p>  <p><br />Our work stresses how adults connect their STEM learning throughout their activities and underscores the inadequacy of studying learning in just one setting if the goal is to understand the scope of a person's knowledge, interests, preferences, and experiences and effectively support their participation. Overall, this project contributes evidence-based understanding about the community resources individuals do and do not access to support their gardening interests and how this might vary by participant characteristics. Places such as local parks, farmer's markets, and grocery stores are very popular, in addition to more specialized places for learning such as gardens. This is critical for the field to attend to, particularly for educators and researchers pursuing applied projects designed to improve the outcomes of diverse free-choice learners participating in lifelong, STEM-learning experiences.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/29/2024<br> Modified by: Elysa&nbsp;N&nbsp;Corin</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Introduction:    We developed and tested a snowball sampling method to collect data from 350 diverse adult urban gardeners in the Berkeley/Oakland (California) area to understand how gardeners and plant lovers from different backgrounds use suites of resources, including local places, people, groups for their plant-related activities and learning. The sample varied across multiple dimensions including age, race/ethnicity, gender, income, education, languages spoken, participation frequency, and interests. The online survey took place during the COVID-19 pandemic, which also allowed us to study how participation changed due to the pandemic as well as the benefits experienced.     Benefits:    Individuals reported many specific benefits to participating in their plant and gardening hobby. The most impactful included: "Happiness or joy", "Feeling of connection to the natural world", "Stress relief", "The appearance of my surroundings". Additionally, results illustrate the role a science-based hobby such as gardening plays in supporting participants' well-being (intellectual, emotional, social, physical) during an extreme event such as the COVID-19 pandemic and during the following period of great societal uncertainty and stress. Benefits were observed for participants across demographics, by gender, age, race, and socioeconomics, which speaks to the broad appeal of this highly accessible activity. While focusing more on plants in one's home and immediate environment was expected, findings also highlight how gardening brought people together during a period of crisis and loneliness, and how it facilitated profound individual introspection and self-directed change due to the COVID-19 shock.     Activities:    Study participants were asked to report on how they participate in their plant and gardening interests, providing feedback on 30 different activities. Seven core activities were found in the top 10 across demographic groups (gender, race/ethnicity, income). These common "top" activities were: grow plants for food, grow plants for decoration or aesthetics/beauty, tend plants at your home (or the home of a family member), weed, start plants from seeds, propagate plants from cuttings, read to learn about plants and gardening. The activity with highest participation was "grow plants for decoration," cited by 72-90% of sampled individuals across the three demographic categories. Next was "grow plants for food," which was listed by 67-88% per subgroup. Fewer than half the sample reported volunteering their time related to plants and gardening, with a large difference apparent by income level: 40% of sampled respondents with low incomes and 17% with high incomes reported volunteering. Other large differences included tending plants at your home or the home of a family member (89% of white respondents, 57% of Black respondents), propagating plants from cuttings (73% of Asian respondents, 46% of Black respondents), and organizing activities for others (26% of Black respondents, 10% of Hispanic respondents).     Local Places:    We asked community members to share whether, during the past five years, they visited any of over 250 local places to participate in their plant interest (e.g., buy supplies, attend a course, admire plants). Places included botanic gardens, community gardens, local farms, plant nurseries, stores with garden supplies, famer's markets, seed lending libraries, parks/trails. Around 15 places fell in the top 20 for each demographic subgroup, with some places listed higher by some groups than others. Thirteen places were named by at least half of sampled participants, and 26 were named by at least a third. The most named place, selected by 73% of individuals, was a local grocery store that sells fresh produce, potted plants, and cut flowers. Grocery and hardware stores, as well as parks, figured prominently in places people use to engage in their gardening interests. Garden-specific places (e.g., plant nurseries, seed lending libraries) were common enough but typically not as popular. This work supports the narrative that most hobbyists carry their interest in plants and gardening with them throughout the day and look for incidental, opportunistic, ways to participate when going to the grocery store, walking through their neighborhood, or visiting a park. While some individuals did spend a great deal of time and resources participating in their hobby (particularly individuals with more time and financial means), this was not the most common experience.     Our work stresses how adults connect their STEM learning throughout their activities and underscores the inadequacy of studying learning in just one setting if the goal is to understand the scope of a person's knowledge, interests, preferences, and experiences and effectively support their participation. Overall, this project contributes evidence-based understanding about the community resources individuals do and do not access to support their gardening interests and how this might vary by participant characteristics. Places such as local parks, farmer's markets, and grocery stores are very popular, in addition to more specialized places for learning such as gardens. This is critical for the field to attend to, particularly for educators and researchers pursuing applied projects designed to improve the outcomes of diverse free-choice learners participating in lifelong, STEM-learning experiences.     Last Modified: 12/29/2024       Submitted by: ElysaNCorin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
