<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Investigating the Impact of Head Start Family Interactions on Childrens STEM Process Skills during Family Events at Two Science Centers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>297336.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>297336</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jowalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Parents and adult caregivers play a significant role in young children’s understanding of—and participation in—science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM). Research suggests that early engagement with STEM can have a profound impact on children’s use of STEM process skills such as exploration, observation, and problem-solving, as well as future academic success. An immediate yet ongoing challenge facing informal STEM learning providers is to understand how limited resources can be used to support effective STEM learning opportunities and experiences for all children and families. Through a collaboration between researchers, Head Start, two science centers (one rural, one urban), and educators, this project aims to foster STEM access and engagement with specific attention to young children and their caregivers. This project is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Pilot and Feasibility study will apply an experimental, mixed-methods design to examine parent/caregiver and child (ages 4-5) interactions before, during, and after informal STEM experiences to identify which factors influence children's transfer of learning STEM process skills across multiple informal contexts. Research results will lay the foundation for a future longitudinal study. The project team will ask: (1) What types of parent/caregiver-child engagement at the science center are most predictive of children’s application of STEM process skills in subsequent problem-solving tasks and school readiness? (2) How do variations in parent/caregiver-child conversational strategies during the science center visit influence children’s memory and learning? and (3) How can informal educators best support Head Start family engagement and children’s emerging STEM knowledge? This study will collect data on 240, 4-5-year-old children, with their caregivers, in two different science centers that serve a largely rural and largely urban population. Data sources will include video/audio of caregiver-child interactions at the science centers and at home, as well as children’s recall, engagement with a problem-solving task, and school readiness scores. Coding and analysis of the tasks during and after the science center visit will detail mechanisms underlying children’s memory, learning, and application of STEM process skills that transfer to the problem-solving task. The project will be implemented by a research-practice partnership, leveraging the expertise of project partners and communities to ensure the use of culturally responsive research practices. This research has the potential to strategically impact how science centers and Head Start grantees work together on Family Engagement programming to achieve equitable STEM learning opportunities, broadening participation for low-income young children and their families.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005594</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwade</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer A Schwade</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jschwade@sciencenter.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000302185</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/02/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Kortenaar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michelle Kortenaar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mkortenaar@sciencenter.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000709329</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erin</FirstName>
<LastName>Jant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erin Jant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[erin.jant@wku.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000786279</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stacey</FirstName>
<LastName>Prinzing</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stacey Prinzing</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sprinzing@mdsci.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000791187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/18/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Via</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen L Via</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kvia@mdsci.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000881553</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sciencenter]]></Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148503507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072720600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 1ST ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VCSCDKJKQFA5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SCIENCENTER DISCOVERY MUSEUM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sciencenter]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148503507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>725900</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~297336</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An overarching goal of this research to practice project was to build knowledge that can be used across Museum-Head Start partnerships nationwide. We evaluated whether family conversations during and after specially designed museum-based experiences improve Head Start children&rsquo;s early STEM learning experiences, bolster family science conversations, and facilitate school readiness. The project teams collective primary goals were to enhance connections between the Sciencenter and Head Start in Tompkins County; as well as the Maryland Science Center and Baltimore City Head Start that support family engagement in STEM and builds STEM process skills such as observing, predicting, and experimenting.</p>  <p>We held monthly free family engagement events at each science center serving 794 children and 601 adults. For each event, the format was the same: the science centers were open for exploration and families were invited to participate in 3 &ndash; 5 facilitated activities. These activities were developed by the Sciencenter education team and complemented the STEM curriculum being used in Head Start classrooms. In order to encourage families to visit all activity stations families were given collectable activity cards, with extension ideas to continue the learning at home. The themes for the family events were construction and engineering, magnets, food science, planet earth, aquatic animals and habitats, Rube Goldberg.</p>  <p>We found that the more family night events that families attended the better children performed in STEM areas of school readiness during the school year. We also found that children transferred science process skills of prediction and hypothesis testing to a sink or float task performed at the school in the weeks following the family engagement event. Our data also suggests that the more times that parents and children engaged in reciprocal conversations about science at the family engagement event the higher children&rsquo;s scores were in the STEM related school readiness areas. Finally, we found that offering family night events at the science centers after hours and specifically for only our Head Start families, encouraged families to visit the science centers who had never visited previously. This increased access and equity for our community members in a way that extended to children&rsquo;s STEM-related learning and science process skill development.&nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/27/2024<br> Modified by: Michelle&nbsp;Kortenaar</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  An overarching goal of this research to practice project was to build knowledge that can be used across Museum-Head Start partnerships nationwide. We evaluated whether family conversations during and after specially designed museum-based experiences improve Head Start childrens early STEM learning experiences, bolster family science conversations, and facilitate school readiness. The project teams collective primary goals were to enhance connections between the Sciencenter and Head Start in Tompkins County; as well as the Maryland Science Center and Baltimore City Head Start that support family engagement in STEM and builds STEM process skills such as observing, predicting, and experimenting.    We held monthly free family engagement events at each science center serving 794 children and 601 adults. For each event, the format was the same: the science centers were open for exploration and families were invited to participate in 3  5 facilitated activities. These activities were developed by the Sciencenter education team and complemented the STEM curriculum being used in Head Start classrooms. In order to encourage families to visit all activity stations families were given collectable activity cards, with extension ideas to continue the learning at home. The themes for the family events were construction and engineering, magnets, food science, planet earth, aquatic animals and habitats, Rube Goldberg.    We found that the more family night events that families attended the better children performed in STEM areas of school readiness during the school year. We also found that children transferred science process skills of prediction and hypothesis testing to a sink or float task performed at the school in the weeks following the family engagement event. Our data also suggests that the more times that parents and children engaged in reciprocal conversations about science at the family engagement event the higher childrens scores were in the STEM related school readiness areas. Finally, we found that offering family night events at the science centers after hours and specifically for only our Head Start families, encouraged families to visit the science centers who had never visited previously. This increased access and equity for our community members in a way that extended to childrens STEM-related learning and science process skill development.         Last Modified: 11/27/2024       Submitted by: MichelleKortenaar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
