<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Promoting Engagement in Informal STEM Learning as a Path to Employment for Adolescents with Autism Spectrum Disorder]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>945539.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>945539</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julie Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjohnson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many people with autism are unemployed and isolated because they do not have access to educational opportunities that support them in finding jobs that match their potential. This research seeks to empower adolescents with autism to seek out careers that are well-matched with their strengths and interests. Many people with autism are interested in computing, a marketable skill. This project builds from this interest by developing strategies to effectively engage teenagers with autism. Although people with autism share a diagnosis, each person is unique and has the capacity to become a visionary and transformer in society in their own way. Teenagers with autism will be invited to participate in a game design workshop hosted by an award-winning, not-for-profit Tech Kids Unlimited. Teenagers often enjoy learning how to design games and can learn many useful skills through design. During each workshop, teenagers will rate different teaching strategies using a picture-based survey developed in collaboration with people with autism. It is expected that teenagers with autism who have difficulty focusing to be most engaged by strategies that include multiple types of information (for example, pictures, text, and speech). The team also expects those who are more focused to be most engaged by strategies with fewer sources of information. By developing clear guidelines to help educators match their teaching styles to how different students learn, the project will help them engage youth more effectively. Through an iterative process, the team will revise the game design workshop to make it more engaging for people with different types of autism. New groups of teenagers with autism will participate in improved game design workshops that include an internship in a technology company. An important outcome is to understand which strategies are engaging for young people with autism that help them develop the belief in their skills needed to seek out fulfilling careers. This award is funded by the Advanced Informal STEM Learning program which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Research in Service to Practice project has the following aims: 1) Identify evidence-based strategies to engage youth with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) in informal STEM learning opportunities that are well matched to their attentional profiles, 2) Determine if engaging youth with ASD in informal STEM learning opportunities increases their STEM self-efficacy, and 3) Determine if engagement with STEM internship activities is associated with increased interest in STEM careers and career decision-making self-efficacy. Principles of Universal Design (UD) and Mayer’s principles of effective multimedia instruction are frameworks employed to identify instructional strategies that are emotionally engaging for youth with diverse attentional profiles. The degree to which attentional differences contribute to different patterns of emotional engagement with informal STEM learning will be investigated. Guided by assessments of youth’s engagement with different learning opportunities, “diversity blueprints” or specific instructional strategies that help youth with diverse attentional profiles engage will be developed. After identifying strategies to engage neurodivergent (neurologically diverse) youth in informal STEM learning opportunities, the extent to which these strategies generalize to STEM internship sites will be explored. The team will study potential specificity of the types of contexts that promote different types of self-efficacy, with engagement with extracurricular STEM learning opportunities expected to preferentially target STEM self-efficacy while engagement with internships targets career decision-making self-efficacy. Although UD is often endorsed to promote STEM learning among students with disabilities, the proposed research would be the first iterative adaptation of instructional strategies designed to engage neurodivergent teens in informal STEM learning guided by a systematic analysis of how they engage with and feel about instructional strategies. Project deliverables include workshops for local after-school program providers, publications, a project website, and a multimodal guide of the process of developing “diversity blueprints” and how to apply them for informal STEM educators and researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005772</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristen</FirstName>
<LastName>Gillespie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristen Gillespie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Kristen.gillespie@csi.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000627333</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY College of Staten Island]]></Name>
<CityName>STATEN ISLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>103146609</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189822254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2800 VICTORY BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L63BKBLD2LH4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY College of Staten Island]]></Name>
<CityName>Staten Island</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>103146600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2800 Victory Blvd 4s-103]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>725900</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0422</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~623066</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~322473</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-8b713289-7fff-f017-fe52-d73ba159b633"> </span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>What were the goals of our project?&nbsp;</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>We engaged diverse Autistic youth in Game Design workshops to develop strategies educators can use to guide Autistic youth to succeed in jobs well-matched to their skills and interests.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>We had three primary hypotheses:</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span>Hypothesis 1: Autistic students with more focused attention will be more engaged when instruction is in one modality while Autistic students with less focused attention will be more engaged when instruction is in multiple modalities;</p>  <p dir="ltr">Hypothesis 2: After participating in a Game Design workshop, Autistic students will report greater video game design self-efficacy than before;</p>  <p dir="ltr">Hypothesis 3: After participating in a workshop, Autistic students will report increased self-determination and career decision making self-efficacy.</p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>What did we do?</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>We collaborated with two award-winning educational organizations that led development and delivery of Game Design workshops for Autistic youth: Tech Kids Unlimited </span><span>and Soft Chaos. We delivered 2 workshops in Summer 2021 (34 students), 1 workshop in 2022 (22 students), and 2 workshops in 2023 (36 students).&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Our process, inspired by a core tenet of the Neurodiversity Movement, "</span><span>Nothing about us without us</span><span>", was increasingly led by Autistic students, Autistic educators, and Autistic researchers. We formed a participatory research group in March, 2021 and developed increasingly transparent processes to empower the group to shape curriculum, training, hypotheses, assessments, and dissemination. Figure 1 depicts the increasing number of decisions Autistic people shaped over the course of the project.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Figure 1</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><em>Increasing Autistic Leadership&nbsp;</em></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span><span><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdYwhmHHx6DSCY5Suubcy0y_cGQuhUt8o5gBVkKxQfWobvLvRMenykVbUxYbdci4N9W4uqK8PKE4FP_IN_-bU0denns2cV6s6Ul9QAer5UZF10PWgkQaBkMAAdsP5Y_7f8wV8TDig?key=93xy7fimNUf6nXaAeM2xQ1_H" alt=" width="556" height="401" /></span></span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Increasing Neurodiversity-Affirmative Practices</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Although Autistic people provided guidance on more decisions in 2022 than 2021, we experienced issues ensuring their guidance was followed. Therefore, we commited to neurodiversity-affirmative values (Figure 2), </span><span>and used </span><span>&nbsp;these values to improve hiring, training and student empowerment in 2023.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Figure 2</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><em>Neurodiversity-Affirmative Values: Adopted Fall 2022&nbsp;</em></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span><span><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcJzZZwVZiamnF-YRxc0D25UUshM2Y6XETfUNPaDk3GR4LoXtLll1uaUGVbA6-YhOXmACZCxAwi7btyr60NnJ7rnELO3lMfxyeUKSPzh1_tdPp7PwufcZKKf9Ui9GpOXt18RPUVbw?key=93xy7fimNUf6nXaAeM2xQ1_H" alt=" width="449" height="250" /></span></span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>How did we address hypotheses?</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Students completed surveys and interviews before and after each workshop in 2021 and 2022. In 2023, students were randomly assigned to one of two workshops. They completed assessments before both workshops, after workshop 1, after workshop 2, and 5 months after both workshops. During workshops, students rated how engaging they found selected activities (Figure 3).&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Figure 3</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><em>Student Engagement Probes&nbsp;</em></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span><span><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdIb646sRyxyMHGnBHktCkZBoWNijN4uXyC302Xwc9yfP6mEB-xN4muJX8-uFvkTR6WRa0PL4Z5btwLVZ8ZVV2R4u0Q2Z90wT463F90bYN94cMPOTnYERy_4h3Ec2hwdVzv_T2qJg?key=93xy7fimNUf6nXaAeM2xQ1_H" alt=" width="274" height="285" /></span></span></p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Empowering Autistic Students&nbsp;</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Before the 2021 and 2022 workshops, researchers made <em>diversity profiles t</em>o help educators adapt instructional approaches to student needs. In 2023, students developed their own <em>diversity profiles</em> to introduce themselves to peers and staff. In 2022 and increasingly in 2023, we used students&rsquo; interests to shape curriculum.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Figure 4</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><em>Helping Students Develop Diversity Profiles</em></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span><span><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdT0n45mpoMnO_uSpIGv-Ks_4hijqILuG9VxFqAfcxl2LZBvyEZA2aAvo1C_lU4HJ_Kh0BSkzoYPhWAJ1K257aPoyR1F4mqy42Y7u24sCL78hv0Hb-ZxzPloPuwtXYiavVtk0P6?key=93xy7fimNUf6nXaAeM2xQ1_H" alt=" width="624" height="173" /></span></span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Starting midway through the 2022 workshop and from the beginning of 2023 workshops, students used engagement ratings to advocate for workshop improvements (Figure 4).&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Figure 4</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><em>Student-led Interpretation of Engagement Ratings Shapes Year 3 Workshops&nbsp;</em></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span><span><img src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcBmwJN6GlFCkooCFJP6jc3ccTgyZc91uessfgrGA-a0JOC7XilVm7wj7e6yYgNGNcp2kRf0gxfqGraZP8tReDrhVzFIxziOAYBRWRRLMVmRyygvBBkUj_wXh7Cy3IknUNPUwn-zA?key=93xy7fimNUf6nXaAeM2xQ1_H" alt=" width="624" height="185" /></span></span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>What did we find?&nbsp;</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>We assessed if measures were valid (or measured what we intended). We found that students who scored higher on a computational thinking survey made more complex games, providing evidence for the validity of the survey.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Contrary to hypothesis one, attention did not predict engagement. Instead, student interests did. Students rated industry speakers particularly engaging. However, in 2022, engagement with industry speakers was inconsistent as visits were less structured. After Soft Chaos structured speaker visits in 2023, industry speakers were again highly rated, particularly when students got to playtest their games with experts.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Across years, improvements in video game design self-efficacy were apparent. Improvements in career decision making self-efficacy were only observed in 2023, when the curriculum focused most on employment. In 2021 and 2023, self-determination improved. Yet we did not find evidence that workshops caused improvements.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>To see if changes between 2022 and 2023 made our workshops more neurodiversity-affirmative, we asked researchers to code video recordings from the 2022 and 2023 workshops without knowing what they were coding or why. Coding revealed that 2023 staff used neurodiversity-affirming practices more than 2022 staff. When asked whether they used student diversity profiles, 2023 staff were more likely to say they did. In 2023, students reported more interest in activities after self-advocacy check-ins.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>What does this mean?&nbsp;</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Findings show that: 1) </span><span>participatory approaches can promote neurodiversity-affirmative instruction and student engagement, 2) </span><span>Game Design workshops can help Autistic students feel confident they can make games and choices about their lives but 3) improvements may not be attributable to workshops.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p><span>Findings highlight the following strategies to support Autistic youth: 1) building curriculum around students' interests, 2) providing hands-on learning opportunities, access to neurodivergent role models and industry experts, and structured engagement opportunities, 3) providing ample training emphasizing neurodiversity-affirmative values, and 4) giving educators time to practice, critique, and shape curriculum so they can model the skills they hope to teach. Our work highlights the value of iterative, participatory, and flexible approaches that include validity assessments and opportunities to build toward controlled designs. Curriculum and training materials are available open-access via our </span><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/gamedesignemploymentresources/home?authuser=0"><span>webpage</span></a><span>.</span></p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/30/2024<br> Modified by: Kristen&nbsp;Gillespie</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       What were the goals of our project?    We engaged diverse Autistic youth in Game Design workshops to develop strategies educators can use to guide Autistic youth to succeed in jobs well-matched to their skills and interests.    We had three primary hypotheses:    Hypothesis 1: Autistic students with more focused attention will be more engaged when instruction is in one modality while Autistic students with less focused attention will be more engaged when instruction is in multiple modalities;    Hypothesis 2: After participating in a Game Design workshop, Autistic students will report greater video game design self-efficacy than before;    Hypothesis 3: After participating in a workshop, Autistic students will report increased self-determination and career decision making self-efficacy.    What did we do?    We collaborated with two award-winning educational organizations that led development and delivery of Game Design workshops for Autistic youth: Tech Kids Unlimited and Soft Chaos. We delivered 2 workshops in Summer 2021 (34 students), 1 workshop in 2022 (22 students), and 2 workshops in 2023 (36 students).    Our process, inspired by a core tenet of the Neurodiversity Movement, "Nothing about us without us", was increasingly led by Autistic students, Autistic educators, and Autistic researchers. We formed a participatory research group in March, 2021 and developed increasingly transparent processes to empower the group to shape curriculum, training, hypotheses, assessments, and dissemination. Figure 1 depicts the increasing number of decisions Autistic people shaped over the course of the project.    Figure 1    Increasing Autistic Leadership        Increasing Neurodiversity-Affirmative Practices    Although Autistic people provided guidance on more decisions in 2022 than 2021, we experienced issues ensuring their guidance was followed. Therefore, we commited to neurodiversity-affirmative values (Figure 2), and used these values to improve hiring, training and student empowerment in 2023.    Figure 2    Neurodiversity-Affirmative Values: Adopted Fall 2022        How did we address hypotheses?    Students completed surveys and interviews before and after each workshop in 2021 and 2022. In 2023, students were randomly assigned to one of two workshops. They completed assessments before both workshops, after workshop 1, after workshop 2, and 5 months after both workshops. During workshops, students rated how engaging they found selected activities (Figure 3).    Figure 3    Student Engagement Probes            Empowering Autistic Students    Before the 2021 and 2022 workshops, researchers made diversity profiles to help educators adapt instructional approaches to student needs. In 2023, students developed their own diversity profiles to introduce themselves to peers and staff. In 2022 and increasingly in 2023, we used students interests to shape curriculum.    Figure 4    Helping Students Develop Diversity Profiles        Starting midway through the 2022 workshop and from the beginning of 2023 workshops, students used engagement ratings to advocate for workshop improvements (Figure 4).    Figure 4    Student-led Interpretation of Engagement Ratings Shapes Year 3 Workshops        What did we find?    We assessed if measures were valid (or measured what we intended). We found that students who scored higher on a computational thinking survey made more complex games, providing evidence for the validity of the survey.    Contrary to hypothesis one, attention did not predict engagement. Instead, student interests did. Students rated industry speakers particularly engaging. However, in 2022, engagement with industry speakers was inconsistent as visits were less structured. After Soft Chaos structured speaker visits in 2023, industry speakers were again highly rated, particularly when students got to playtest their games with experts.    Across years, improvements in video game design self-efficacy were apparent. Improvements in career decision making self-efficacy were only observed in 2023, when the curriculum focused most on employment. In 2021 and 2023, self-determination improved. Yet we did not find evidence that workshops caused improvements.    To see if changes between 2022 and 2023 made our workshops more neurodiversity-affirmative, we asked researchers to code video recordings from the 2022 and 2023 workshops without knowing what they were coding or why. Coding revealed that 2023 staff used neurodiversity-affirming practices more than 2022 staff. When asked whether they used student diversity profiles, 2023 staff were more likely to say they did. In 2023, students reported more interest in activities after self-advocacy check-ins.    What does this mean?    Findings show that: 1) participatory approaches can promote neurodiversity-affirmative instruction and student engagement, 2) Game Design workshops can help Autistic students feel confident they can make games and choices about their lives but 3) improvements may not be attributable to workshops.    Findings highlight the following strategies to support Autistic youth: 1) building curriculum around students' interests, 2) providing hands-on learning opportunities, access to neurodivergent role models and industry experts, and structured engagement opportunities, 3) providing ample training emphasizing neurodiversity-affirmative values, and 4) giving educators time to practice, critique, and shape curriculum so they can model the skills they hope to teach. Our work highlights the value of iterative, participatory, and flexible approaches that include validity assessments and opportunities to build toward controlled designs. Curriculum and training materials are available open-access via our webpage.             Last Modified: 12/30/2024       Submitted by: KristenGillespie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
