<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Quantum acoustics for optomechanical transduction and entanglement of solid-state spin qubits]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>66000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>66000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Future quantum computers will need to utilize different physical types of qubits that need to communicate and convert between each other with high fidelity and high efficiency. While photons are ideal for quantum communication, different qubit systems couple to photons of vastly different frequency ranges. The strain field generated by the mechanical wave in a solid-state material is a promising approach to enable coupling with a broad range of qubits with theoretically high efficiency. With a traveling velocity of five orders of magnitude lower than photons, acoustic waves are ideal for quantum interconnect between multiple qubits. The quantum acoustic technology developed in this project and the integration with NV-defect center qubits is an essential first step toward a chip-scale hybrid, multiple qubit systems. The proposed research both addresses the imminent issue of frequency inhomogeneity that has been plaguing solid-state optical qubits and explores the frontier of strong coupling of mechanical modes with spin qubits. The project will make significant advances from previous studies of discrete systems to realizing a monolithic quantum system that includes waveguides, optical and acoustic cavities, and acoustic transducers to directly interface with qubits, all integrated on a novel material platform. The approach offers a path to the realization of the integrated quantum computing system based on hybrid solid-state qubits interconnected with photons and phonons. The research leverages the tremendous technological development in the acoustic MEMS technology and advances it to the quantum regime, with the potential outcome that can impact both quantum information science and microwave photonics for classical communication. Education and outreach activities aim to increase the participation of students from underrepresented groups and improve the diversity of the STEM workforce and include course development in advanced quantum computing and K-12 science outreach programs with publicly accessible online courses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to develop a novel integrated quantum acoustic device platform for optomechanical transduction and quantum state manipulation of solid-state spin qubits based on defect centers in diamond. The integrated devices will be built on the high-performance heterogeneous material platform of gallium phosphide (GaP) on the crystalline diamond. The platform uniquely utilizes the layer of piezoelectric GaP for the dual functions of optical waveguiding and acoustic wave generation and guiding, thereby to achieve tremendously enhanced acousto-optic interaction. The effort will include three main thrusts. The first thrust will realize integrated acousto-optic frequency shifter (AOFS) to address the optical frequency inhomogeneity problem of qubits based on defect centers. AOFS can achieve single-sideband, carrier-suppressed frequency shift of photons from qubits freely over a range of ±3GHz and with an efficiency better than 80%. The second thrust will investigate the coupling of itinerant acoustic waves to ensembles and single defect centers. The acoustic coupling strength will be enhanced to reach the strong coupling regime and realize time-dependent control over the states of the qubits. The final thrust will realize the strong coupling of acoustic modes confined in a high-Q cavity with single defect centers embedded therein. Quantum state manipulation and quantum entanglement of the qubits by utilizing the acoustic mode will be achieved. Ensembles of NV-centers coupled to the cavity acoustic mode in the strong-coupling regime and novel physics effects in this regime will be explored.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006076</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lin</FirstName>
<LastName>Tian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lin Tian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ltian@ucmerced.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000506634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California - Merced]]></Name>
<CityName>MERCED</CityName>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2092012039</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5200 N LAKE RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FFM7VPAG8P92</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, MERCED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California - Merced]]></Name>
<CityName>Merced</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5200 North Lake Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151700</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~66000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This is a collaborative project between the groups of Li and Fu at Univ. Washington (experiment) and Tian&rsquo;s group at UCM (theory). This is a seed project on developing a novel integrated quantum acoustic device platform for optomechanical transduction and quantum state manipulation of solid-state spin qubits based on defect centers in diamond.&nbsp; On the theory part, we have accomplished the main objective of this project: studying the inhomogeneity problem of the spin defects coupled to the acoustic cavity and developing a theory on the effect of the inhomogeneity on the collective effect of the spins. We are preparing 2 manuscripts on this result. We are also preparing for in-depth research on this problem for Tavis-Cummings quantum emitter. &nbsp;</p> <p>Besides the above main objectives, this project also enables us to study several related topics. (1) We developed a method to construct an anisotropic quantum Rabi/Dicke model to observe superradiant phase transition and designed a scheme to use the constructed Rabi model to generate multi-photon bundles (2 papers published). (2) We studied quantum state preparation in Jaynes-Cummings lattice, which is composed of a network of coupled qubit-cavity system and can demonstrate quantum phase transition (1 paper published). (3) We conducted phonon spectrum calculation for another type of surface mechanical mode - the surface wave of a liquid Helium film confined to a disk (1 paper published). (4) We studied the generation of switchable bipartite and genuine tripartite entanglement between microwave and optical photons via an optoelectromechanical interface and the generation of ultrastrong optomechanical-like coupling with a two-mode (2 papers published). (5) We are studying the generation of novel entanglement in phononic quantum network. We showed that continuous variable cluster states can be generated in a phonionic quantum network composed of mechanical resonators, waveguides and optical cavities. We are preparing 1 manuscript on this subject.</p> <p>&nbsp;The educational outcomes include the following. (1) The PI developed the course PHYS 274 and PHYS 174 &ldquo;Advanced quantum computing&rdquo;, which can disseminate progress in quantum technology and train students on quantum computing. The course was taught in Spring 2021 and Spring 2023, and will be offered again Spring 2025. &nbsp;(2) The PI served as faculty advisor for 3 REU students (2 in summer 2023, 1 in summer 2024) on the topic &ldquo;IBM Cloud Simulation of&nbsp; the 1-D Transverse Field Ising Model&rdquo;.</p> <p>&nbsp;Below is a list of the manuscripts we are preparing and the publications:</p> <p class="MCBodySP">L. Tian et al, &ldquo;Bound on Parameter Spreads in Tavis-Cummings Quantum Emitter&rdquo;, in preparation.</p> <p class="MCBodySP">K. Yip, S. Asshab, and L. Tian, &ldquo;Quantum Simulation of an Harmonic Oscillator with Qubits&rdquo;, in preparation.</p> <p class="MCBodySP">A. Govindarajan et al, &ldquo;Generating Continuous-Variable Cluster States in Phononic Quantum Network&rdquo;, in preparation.</p> <p class="MCBodySP">J.-F. Huang and L. Tian, &ldquo;Modulation-based superradiant phase transition in the strong-coupling regime&rdquo;, Phys. Rev. A 107, 063713 (2023).</p> <p class="MCBodySP">C. Liu, J.-F. Huang, and L. Tian, &ldquo;Deterministic generation of multi-photon bundles in a quantum Rabi model&rdquo;, SCPMA 66, 220311 (2023).</p> <p>K. Cai, P. Parajuli, G.-L. Long, C.-W. Wong, and L. Tian, &ldquo;Robust Preparation of Many-body Ground States in Jaynes-Cummings Lattices&rdquo;, Npj Quantum Information 7, 96 (2021).</p> <p class="MCBodySP">Y. L. Sfendla, C. G. Baker, G. I. Harris, L. Tian, R. A. Harrison, W. P. Bowen, &ldquo;Extreme quantum nonlinearity in superfluid thin-film surface waves&rdquo;, Npj Quantum Information 7, 62 (2021)</p> <p class="MCBodySP">C. Jiang, S. Tserkis, K. Collins, S. Onoe, Y. Li, and L. Tian, &ldquo;Switchable bipartite and genuine tripartite entanglement via an optoelectromechanical interface&rdquo;, Phys. Rev. A 101, 042320 (2020); DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevA.101.042320</p> <p class="MCBodySP">J.-Q. Liao, J.-F. Huang, L. Tian, L.-M. Kuang, C.-P. Sun, &ldquo;Generalized ultrastrong optomechanicallike coupling&rdquo;, Phys. Rev. A 101, 063802 (2020).</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/31/2024<br> Modified by: Lin&nbsp;Tian</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This is a collaborative project between the groups of Li and Fu at Univ. Washington (experiment) and Tians group at UCM (theory). This is a seed project on developing a novel integrated quantum acoustic device platform for optomechanical transduction and quantum state manipulation of solid-state spin qubits based on defect centers in diamond. On the theory part, we have accomplished the main objective of this project: studying the inhomogeneity problem of the spin defects coupled to the acoustic cavity and developing a theory on the effect of the inhomogeneity on the collective effect of the spins. We are preparing 2 manuscripts on this result. We are also preparing for in-depth research on this problem for Tavis-Cummings quantum emitter.    Besides the above main objectives, this project also enables us to study several related topics. (1) We developed a method to construct an anisotropic quantum Rabi/Dicke model to observe superradiant phase transition and designed a scheme to use the constructed Rabi model to generate multi-photon bundles (2 papers published). (2) We studied quantum state preparation in Jaynes-Cummings lattice, which is composed of a network of coupled qubit-cavity system and can demonstrate quantum phase transition (1 paper published). (3) We conducted phonon spectrum calculation for another type of surface mechanical mode - the surface wave of a liquid Helium film confined to a disk (1 paper published). (4) We studied the generation of switchable bipartite and genuine tripartite entanglement between microwave and optical photons via an optoelectromechanical interface and the generation of ultrastrong optomechanical-like coupling with a two-mode (2 papers published). (5) We are studying the generation of novel entanglement in phononic quantum network. We showed that continuous variable cluster states can be generated in a phonionic quantum network composed of mechanical resonators, waveguides and optical cavities. We are preparing 1 manuscript on this subject.   The educational outcomes include the following. (1) The PI developed the course PHYS 274 and PHYS 174 Advanced quantum computing, which can disseminate progress in quantum technology and train students on quantum computing. The course was taught in Spring 2021 and Spring 2023, and will be offered again Spring 2025. (2) The PI served as faculty advisor for 3 REU students (2 in summer 2023, 1 in summer 2024) on the topic IBM Cloud Simulation of the 1-D Transverse Field Ising Model.   Below is a list of the manuscripts we are preparing and the publications:   L. Tian et al, Bound on Parameter Spreads in Tavis-Cummings Quantum Emitter, in preparation.   K. Yip, S. Asshab, and L. Tian, Quantum Simulation of an Harmonic Oscillator with Qubits, in preparation.   A. Govindarajan et al, Generating Continuous-Variable Cluster States in Phononic Quantum Network, in preparation.   J.-F. Huang and L. Tian, Modulation-based superradiant phase transition in the strong-coupling regime, Phys. Rev. A 107, 063713 (2023).   C. Liu, J.-F. Huang, and L. Tian, Deterministic generation of multi-photon bundles in a quantum Rabi model, SCPMA 66, 220311 (2023).   K. Cai, P. Parajuli, G.-L. Long, C.-W. Wong, and L. Tian, Robust Preparation of Many-body Ground States in Jaynes-Cummings Lattices, Npj Quantum Information 7, 96 (2021).   Y. L. Sfendla, C. G. Baker, G. I. Harris, L. Tian, R. A. Harrison, W. P. Bowen, Extreme quantum nonlinearity in superfluid thin-film surface waves, Npj Quantum Information 7, 62 (2021)   C. Jiang, S. Tserkis, K. Collins, S. Onoe, Y. Li, and L. Tian, Switchable bipartite and genuine tripartite entanglement via an optoelectromechanical interface, Phys. Rev. A 101, 042320 (2020); DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevA.101.042320   J.-Q. Liao, J.-F. Huang, L. Tian, L.-M. Kuang, C.-P. Sun, Generalized ultrastrong optomechanicallike coupling, Phys. Rev. A 101, 063802 (2020).     Last Modified: 07/31/2024       Submitted by: LinTian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
