<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CIF: Small: Deep Stochastic Geometry: A New Paradigm for Wireless Network Analysis and Design]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Fowler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jafowler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928910</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The use of wireless networks is rapidly extending towards applications with strict reliability and/or latency constraints. For example, in 5G cellular systems, standards not only specify average data rates but also the minimum rates that 95% of the users should be able to achieve. Meanwhile, for vehicular safety messaging or in manufacturing, extremely high reliability under strict latency constraints is required. In contrast to these developments, the theoretical tools available for wireless network analysis and design mostly focus on network-wide averages, which makes them unsuitable for these new applications. As a result, there is an urgent need to develop a theory for networks with strict performance constraints and guarantees. This project focuses on the development of such a theory, which will allow a sharp performance analysis and enable researchers and engineers in industry to characterize the user experience much more efficiently than by lengthy and expensive simulations. Accordingly, it is expected to have a significant impact on the design of future wireless systems. In addition, it will help train future generations of students in emerging wireless technologies and analytical techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In view of the increasing density, irregularity, and uncertainty in the locations of wireless transceivers, a probabilistic approach to modeling and analysis that includes the network geometry as its key ingredient is warranted.  Stochastic geometry is the natural mathematical tool for modeling and analysis. However, its use has been largely restricted to the derivation of average performance metrics, which do not capture the disparity in the link or user performances nor incorporate reliability or latency constraints. To address these shortcomings, this project develops a new theoretical framework, called deep stochastic geometry, that focuses on spatial distributions rather than merely averages. Deep stochastic geometry enables a direct evaluation of the performance of user or link percentiles and the performance under constraints. As such, it is a theory of guaranteed performance, in contrast to the existing theory of average performance. At the heart of the new theory are so-called meta distributions, which are distributions of conditional distributions (given the network geometry). Meta distributions naturally emerge when the different sources of randomness in a network are separated according to their time scales. The specific research activities include the development of efficient numerical methods and simulation techniques to calculate meta distributions, finding effective approximation techniques, the extension of meta distributions to joint distributions, and, finally, the combination of multiple metrics into a comprehensive approach to characterize and optimize network performance under constraints.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2007498</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Haenggi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin Haenggi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[haenggi.1@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000488396</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[940 GRACE HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FPU6XGFXMBE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FPU6XGFXMBE9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[940 Grace Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>779700</Code>
<Text>Comm &amp; Information Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7935</Code>
<Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~499999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many emerging wireless network applications, including machine-to-machine communications, vehicular safety communication, virtual reality, telesurgery, etc., require strict performance guarantees in the form of throughput, delay, and/or reliability. However, the theoretical tools used for the performance analysis have not kept pace with these developments. They traditionally focus on the derivation of average metrics, which is insufficient to characterize network performance under latency or reliability constraints or the experience of user percentiles (the performance levels that a certain fraction of users observe).<br />This project filled this gap by developing a novel theoretical framework, called deep stochastic geometry, that is tailored to the demands of future wireless networks. It made significant progress towards a theory of guaranteed performance while the prior state-of-the-art was mostly a theory of average performance. The main objects studied are meta distributions (MDs), which are distributions of conditional probabilities and emerge naturally through a decomposition of spatial and temporal randomness. In particular, MDs characterize the performance of user or link percentiles, which is directly relevant to specifications in next-generation cellular networks, such as the user-experienced data rates in 5G and 6G.<br /><br />In terms of intellectual merit, a key outcome are efficient methods to solve the Hausdorff moment problem that naturally arises in MD theory since in most cases, only moments of the conditional distributions can be calculated. Despite its long mathematical tradition, many practically important aspect of Hausdorff moment transforms have not been studied, including effective approximations when only a finite number of moments are available and the sensitivity of the reconstruction to inaccuracies in the calculation of the moments. This project has solved both of these problems by introducing computationally optimal methods and deriving the tightest bounds on the distributions. In particular, a novel method based on Fourier-Chebyshev series was introduced. To measure the accuracy of MD reconstructions, a new distance metric between MDs was introduced; it corresponds to the Wasserstein-1 distance of the distance between distributions of random variables that are mapped homeomorphically by X/(1+X). Another important part was the development of methods to produce moment sequences that are uniformly distributed in the moment space (i.e., the space of finite completely monotonic sequences). <br /><br />In terms of the broader impact, the findings enable researchers and engineers to analyze and design future wireless systems that meet strict application requirements. The theoretical framework developed elimininates or complements lengthy simulations - or replaces them altogether - and has great potential to lead to new approaches for network architectures and protocols.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/03/2024<br> Modified by: Martin&nbsp;Haenggi</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2007498/2007498_10679953_1725372300644_fig1b--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2007498/2007498_10679953_1725372300644_fig1b--rgov-800width.png" title="The meta distribution and its relationship to standard distributions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2007498/2007498_10679953_1725372300644_fig1b--rgov-66x44.png" alt="The meta distribution and its relationship to standard distributions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The left box shows the relationships between the mean, cumulative distribution function (ccdf), and meta distribution (MD) of a random variable Z = f(X, Y ). The right box shows that if U is the conditional ccdf given Y , then the ccdf of Z is the mean of U, while the MD of Z is the ccdf of U.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Martin Haenggi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Martin&nbsp;Haenggi <div class="imageTitle">The meta distribution and its relationship to standard distributions</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Many emerging wireless network applications, including machine-to-machine communications, vehicular safety communication, virtual reality, telesurgery, etc., require strict performance guarantees in the form of throughput, delay, and/or reliability. However, the theoretical tools used for the performance analysis have not kept pace with these developments. They traditionally focus on the derivation of average metrics, which is insufficient to characterize network performance under latency or reliability constraints or the experience of user percentiles (the performance levels that a certain fraction of users observe). This project filled this gap by developing a novel theoretical framework, called deep stochastic geometry, that is tailored to the demands of future wireless networks. It made significant progress towards a theory of guaranteed performance while the prior state-of-the-art was mostly a theory of average performance. The main objects studied are meta distributions (MDs), which are distributions of conditional probabilities and emerge naturally through a decomposition of spatial and temporal randomness. In particular, MDs characterize the performance of user or link percentiles, which is directly relevant to specifications in next-generation cellular networks, such as the user-experienced data rates in 5G and 6G.  In terms of intellectual merit, a key outcome are efficient methods to solve the Hausdorff moment problem that naturally arises in MD theory since in most cases, only moments of the conditional distributions can be calculated. Despite its long mathematical tradition, many practically important aspect of Hausdorff moment transforms have not been studied, including effective approximations when only a finite number of moments are available and the sensitivity of the reconstruction to inaccuracies in the calculation of the moments. This project has solved both of these problems by introducing computationally optimal methods and deriving the tightest bounds on the distributions. In particular, a novel method based on Fourier-Chebyshev series was introduced. To measure the accuracy of MD reconstructions, a new distance metric between MDs was introduced; it corresponds to the Wasserstein-1 distance of the distance between distributions of random variables that are mapped homeomorphically by X/(1+X). Another important part was the development of methods to produce moment sequences that are uniformly distributed in the moment space (i.e., the space of finite completely monotonic sequences).   In terms of the broader impact, the findings enable researchers and engineers to analyze and design future wireless systems that meet strict application requirements. The theoretical framework developed elimininates or complements lengthy simulations - or replaces them altogether - and has great potential to lead to new approaches for network architectures and protocols.     Last Modified: 09/03/2024       Submitted by: MartinHaenggi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
