<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[WoU-MMA: Can Black Hole Images Constrain Modified Gravity Theories?]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>555828.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>555828</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The recent imaging of the black hole at the center of the galaxy M87 by the Event Horizon Telescope holds the promise of revealing wonders about the astrophysics of material accreting onto a supermassive black hole. The information contained in these images has promise to also allow for tests of general relativity in the region of strong gravitational fields outside the event horizon of a supermassive black hole. A research group at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign will study whether these images can indeed be used to constrain deviations from Einstein's theory.  This research will be integrated with activities aimed at increasing the interest of middle-school students and the general public in physics and science in general. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research plan is aimed at studying whether the images obtained from the observation of the black holes at the center of the galaxy M87 and at the center of the Milky Way can be used to constrain deviations from Einstein's theory of general relativity. First, the investigators will study how the shape of the so-called shadow in these images changes in modified gravity, developing a fit for the boundary and calculating the Lyapunov exponents of unstable geodesics near the light-ring, which produce certain features in the image. Then, they will develop simple, phenomenological models of accretion flow in modified gravity, which will allow them to generate simple synthetic images and study the effect of deviations from general relativity. This study will be followed by an analysis of the Blandford-Znajek process in modified gravity to test how sensitive the jet power and magnetic field structure are to departures from general relativity. The project will conclude with a thorough treatment of general relativistic magnetohydrodynamics and accretion in modified gravity, and the generation of synthetic polarized images from realistic accretion models to determine whether deviations from general relativity can be disentangled from other astrophysical processes.  This project advances the goals of the NSF Windows on the Universe Big Idea.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2007936</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Gammie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles F Gammie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gammie@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000097603</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicolas</FirstName>
<LastName>Yunes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicolas Yunes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nyunes@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000569735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S WRIGHT ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>V2PHZ2CSCH63</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 South Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>107Y00</Code>
<Text>WoU-Windows on the Universe: T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>121500</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125300</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>069Z</Code>
<Text>Windows on the Universe (WoU)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~555828</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award focused on studying whether we can learn about the true nature of gravity at play when a supermassive black hole accretes matter into its interior, forcing this matter to produce light that can be observed with sophisticated telescopes on Earth. Black holes, one of the most interesting predictions of Einstein's theory, are incredibly dense stars whose gravity is so intense that not even light can escape from their interiors. These objects can be as massive as several times the mass of our Sun, or they can be millions of times more massive than the Sun, as is the case for the supermassive black hole at the center of our galaxy (so-called "Sagittarius A*", or Sag A* for short) and that at the center of the nearby M87 galaxy. Through the combination of lengthy observations carried out with several telescopes spread around over vast distances on Earth (many of which are NSF-funded), the silhouette of Sag A* and that of the M87 black hole were decoded in 2019 by the Event Horizon Telescope collaboration. One cannot observe a black hole itself, since no light can escape its interior, but the matter that surrounds it forms a disk that emits electromagnetic radiation (light at very low frequencies), as this matter accretes into the black hole. By observing this electromagnetic radiation, one can decode the shape of the accretion disk, its "silhouette," in the immediate vicinity of the black hole's event horizon. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />The type of black holes that exist in Nature, the details of the gravity such black holes produce, the trajectories matter takes as it accretes into the black hole, and the electromagnetic radiation this matter emits all depends, at least in part, on the details of Nature's gravitational theory. Einstein's theory of general relativity provides our most successful description of gravity, having passed a plethora of tests in a variety of environments over the last century. However, certain theoretical and observational anomalies related to Einstein's theory still persist today, such as general relativity's intrinsic incompatibility with quantum mechanics or the fact that we observe much more matter than antimatter in the universe. Such anomalies have prompted for the search of extensions to Einstein's theory that may be able to resolve them, but any such extensions must continue to pass all current and future observational tests we may carry out. The Event Horizon Telescope's observations of the light emitted by the accretion disks in the vicinity of Sag A* and the M87 black hole can be used as a test of Einstein's theory and a probe of its extensions. Through this NSF grant, we studied whether such new tests are possible when focusing on well-motivated extensions of Einstein's theory that come from the low-energy limit of certain string theories. We found that although the shape of the accretion disk silhouette is indeed predicted to be modified in these theories, relative to predictions in Einstein's theory, the deviations from General Relativity are too small to lead to interesting constraints and can easily be confused with other astrophysical effects (like the effect of the spin of the supermassive black hole on the accretion disk). &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/16/2024<br> Modified by: Charles&nbsp;F&nbsp;Gammie</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This award focused on studying whether we can learn about the true nature of gravity at play when a supermassive black hole accretes matter into its interior, forcing this matter to produce light that can be observed with sophisticated telescopes on Earth. Black holes, one of the most interesting predictions of Einstein's theory, are incredibly dense stars whose gravity is so intense that not even light can escape from their interiors. These objects can be as massive as several times the mass of our Sun, or they can be millions of times more massive than the Sun, as is the case for the supermassive black hole at the center of our galaxy (so-called "Sagittarius A*", or Sag A* for short) and that at the center of the nearby M87 galaxy. Through the combination of lengthy observations carried out with several telescopes spread around over vast distances on Earth (many of which are NSF-funded), the silhouette of Sag A* and that of the M87 black hole were decoded in 2019 by the Event Horizon Telescope collaboration. One cannot observe a black hole itself, since no light can escape its interior, but the matter that surrounds it forms a disk that emits electromagnetic radiation (light at very low frequencies), as this matter accretes into the black hole. By observing this electromagnetic radiation, one can decode the shape of the accretion disk, its "silhouette," in the immediate vicinity of the black hole's event horizon.     The type of black holes that exist in Nature, the details of the gravity such black holes produce, the trajectories matter takes as it accretes into the black hole, and the electromagnetic radiation this matter emits all depends, at least in part, on the details of Nature's gravitational theory. Einstein's theory of general relativity provides our most successful description of gravity, having passed a plethora of tests in a variety of environments over the last century. However, certain theoretical and observational anomalies related to Einstein's theory still persist today, such as general relativity's intrinsic incompatibility with quantum mechanics or the fact that we observe much more matter than antimatter in the universe. Such anomalies have prompted for the search of extensions to Einstein's theory that may be able to resolve them, but any such extensions must continue to pass all current and future observational tests we may carry out. The Event Horizon Telescope's observations of the light emitted by the accretion disks in the vicinity of Sag A* and the M87 black hole can be used as a test of Einstein's theory and a probe of its extensions. Through this NSF grant, we studied whether such new tests are possible when focusing on well-motivated extensions of Einstein's theory that come from the low-energy limit of certain string theories. We found that although the shape of the accretion disk silhouette is indeed predicted to be modified in these theories, relative to predictions in Einstein's theory, the deviations from General Relativity are too small to lead to interesting constraints and can easily be confused with other astrophysical effects (like the effect of the spin of the supermassive black hole on the accretion disk).       Last Modified: 11/16/2024       Submitted by: CharlesFGammie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
