<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Stronger weak lensing cosmology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>426498.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>426498</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Juan Madrid</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmadrid@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927297</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cosmologists have determined that 95% of the mass and energy in the Universe is "dark," meaning that it neither absorbs nor emits its own light. But the gravity of "dark matter" does bend light, so it is possible to map the dark matter by careful study of the distortions of sky images. Led by the Dark Energy Survey (DES), three large-scale experiments are now measuring distortions using the images of over 100 million galaxies to measure the dark-matter structure of the nearby universe, to see if its growth over time matches the predictions of current theories of gravity, dark matter, and dark energy. To help complete the DES analysis, these researchers will develop new methods for measuring both the distortion of the galaxies and their distances from Earth. The grant also will fund participation of first-generation/low-income undergraduates and the sharing of dark-universe results with the Philadelphia community by travelling exhibits and presentations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many of the current methods for testing cosmology with imaging surveys like DES and the Rubin Observatory’s Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) are based on ad hoc assumptions and statistics that require complex testing for accuracy and may lose valuable information. This research will replace many of these with methods based on principled statistical representations of the data, rendering the results more understandable, precise, and closer to optimal in extracting information. The PI will also transfer techniques developed for DES calibration to LSST, which will benefit a broad swath of astronomy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2009210</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Bernstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary M Bernstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[garyb@physics.upenn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000246595</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3451 WALNUT ST STE 440A]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GM1XX56LEP58</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GM1XX56LEP58</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046396</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[209 S 33rd St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>121700</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~426498</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research funded by this grant measures how gravity has caused matter in the Universe to become more clumpy or clustered over the past 13 billion years, which can be compared with the prediction of the standard model of a Universe dominated by dark matter and a cosmological constant.&nbsp; This is done by analysing 80,000 images covering 1/8 of the full sky taken by the Dark Energy Survey (DES), then measuring the positions of &gt;100 million galaxies found in those images and extracting the clustering statistics of the galaxies.&nbsp; Furthermore the shapes of the galaxies are subtly altered by the weak gravitational lensing (WL) deflections of light by dark and visible matter as the photons travel from their source to Earth.&nbsp; DES results to date (final results are not quite done) suggest but do not conclusively prove that the real universe is slightly less lumpy that LCDM would predict.&nbsp; The imminent full analysis of DES will improve accuracy somewhat, and next year the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) will begin a more sensitive survey over more of the sky, which should yield sharper tests.<br /><br />This grant led, in particular, to improved methods of measuring the positions of stars and galaxies in the DES images, implementation of a new method to measure the tiny WL distortions of the galaxy shapes, and improvements in the estimations of the redshifts of the galaxies seen in the images based on their colors and clustering.&nbsp; The funded researchers were also able to co-lead the DES collaboration to making the first accurate tests of LCDM using "non-Gaussian" statistics of the WL distortions, and make significant strides toward using the entire WL patterns instead of just some summary statistics.&nbsp; All of these advances will yield further improvements for LSST.<br /><br />The broader impact of the grant was primarily to (at least partially) fund the training of one postdoctoral research and two PhD students.&nbsp; The grant also enabled several undergraduate students to engage in astronomical research.&nbsp; These researchers also brought the excitement and challenges of cosmological research to the community in presentations to schools, retirement homes, and the general public.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/11/2024<br> Modified by: Gary&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bernstein</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The research funded by this grant measures how gravity has caused matter in the Universe to become more clumpy or clustered over the past 13 billion years, which can be compared with the prediction of the standard model of a Universe dominated by dark matter and a cosmological constant. This is done by analysing 80,000 images covering 1/8 of the full sky taken by the Dark Energy Survey (DES), then measuring the positions of 100 million galaxies found in those images and extracting the clustering statistics of the galaxies. Furthermore the shapes of the galaxies are subtly altered by the weak gravitational lensing (WL) deflections of light by dark and visible matter as the photons travel from their source to Earth. DES results to date (final results are not quite done) suggest but do not conclusively prove that the real universe is slightly less lumpy that LCDM would predict. The imminent full analysis of DES will improve accuracy somewhat, and next year the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) will begin a more sensitive survey over more of the sky, which should yield sharper tests.  This grant led, in particular, to improved methods of measuring the positions of stars and galaxies in the DES images, implementation of a new method to measure the tiny WL distortions of the galaxy shapes, and improvements in the estimations of the redshifts of the galaxies seen in the images based on their colors and clustering. The funded researchers were also able to co-lead the DES collaboration to making the first accurate tests of LCDM using "non-Gaussian" statistics of the WL distortions, and make significant strides toward using the entire WL patterns instead of just some summary statistics. All of these advances will yield further improvements for LSST.  The broader impact of the grant was primarily to (at least partially) fund the training of one postdoctoral research and two PhD students. The grant also enabled several undergraduate students to engage in astronomical research. These researchers also brought the excitement and challenges of cosmological research to the community in presentations to schools, retirement homes, and the general public.     Last Modified: 12/11/2024       Submitted by: GaryMBernstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
