<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joel Abraham</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkabraha@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924694</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions Between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes. The fellowship supports research and training of the Fellow that will contribute to the area of Rules of Life in innovative ways. Results from this work will advance a growing body of evidence that underscores the importance of parental care not only for offspring nutrition and survival but also how social experiences early in life contribute to development of offspring stress response and health throughout life and improve understanding of the proposed Rule of Life, developing a modeling framework will serve as a road map for future studies. Educational outreach will be accomplished through public presentations and blog posts while a statistical modeling workshop will be offered to university students recruited from groups underrepresented in STEM disciplines.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Quantity and quality of parental care have lifelong impacts on development of offspring stress phenotypes. For example, in mammals, birds, fish, and insects, variation in parental care corresponds with substantial and persistent differences in offspring stress physiology and behaviors. Yet, much remains unknown about the underlying mechanisms that link experiences early in life with phenotypes later in life - an especially puzzling question given the long latency between the initial exposure and the phenotypic outcome. Such questions motivate investigating the Rule of Life: experiences of parental care early in life have profound and lasting impacts on an offspring’s stress phenotype. This research uses North American barn swallows to test the hypothesis that inadequate parental care leads to a dysregulated stress hormone response in offspring later in life, and that this relationship is mediated by DNA methylation. Observational data and a cross-fostering, brood manipulation experiment will be used to determine the extent to which parental care corresponds to development of offspring stress phenotype via a DNA methylation mechanism. In addition to testing this hypothesis, the Fellow will learn advanced statistical approaches to derive unbiased estimates of association and improve causal inference, with an emphasis on modeling high-dimensional genomics data. The Fellow will receive training in innovative areas of research, including genomics and statistical analyses of big data, in preparation for a productive research and mentoring career. Finally, the Fellow will lead a series of analytical workshops geared towards improving participation and programming skills among underrepresented groups at the University of Colorado and Colorado State University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010607</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
<LastName>Laubach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zachary M Laubach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000730462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Laubach, Zachary]]></Name>
<CityName>Aurora</CityName>
<ZipCode>800101231</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090334</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>727500</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="vert-spacing"><span>The scientific objectives of this project were to investigate a Rule of Life: experiences and environmental exposure during early ontogeny affect later life phenotypes,&nbsp;<em>i.e.</em>, an individual&rsquo;s condition, physiology, or health through a process called developmental plasticity. Developmental plasticity is when<span>&nbsp;the same genotype produces distinct phenotypes in response to being reared in different environments</span>. In addition to asking,&nbsp;<em>how&nbsp;</em>do early life experiences affect future phenotypes, my collaborators and I also asked&nbsp;<em>why</em>these experiences are important. To answer this question, we grounded our hypotheses in theory from life history evolution and considered whether costs associated with adverse experiences affected traits that are linked to health and/or fitness.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p class="vert-spacing"><span>In wild barn swallows, I tested two complementary hypotheses regarding prioritization of resources to optimize life history traits. The overarching goal of this work is to assess how organisms invest limited resources towards essential functions like growth and physiological development. The differential allocation hypothesis posits that&nbsp;an inverse association between two traits indicates a trade-off involving prioritization of resources, whereas the differential acquisition hypothesis suggests that a positive association between traits is a consequence of differences in individual access to resources. My findings indicate that differences in resource access limit structural growth and physiological development. However, adequate parental care can mitigate these costs. These findings support the differential acquisition hypothesis.&nbsp;In this same study system, I have an ongoing effort investigating if the relationship between&nbsp;growth/offspring stress related glucose physiology is mediated by patterns of DNA methylation using a dataset generated with support from this grant.&nbsp;DNA methylation has been championed as a key mechanism that facilitates developmental plasticity since it is a molecular marker that is both responsive to environmental factors and a determinant of gene expression.&nbsp;My goal is to identify differentially methylated CpG sites that are associated with both early-life environment and nestling life-history traits to identify potential molecular mechanisms of developmental plasticity.</span></p>  <p class="vert-spacing"><span>I also led a project in humans on social determinants of health and aging. This work was part of my longer term goal to use&nbsp;a comparative approach to understand the role of social factors in the natural history of aging. In a recent study, my collaborators and I showed that&nbsp;<em>in utero</em>&nbsp;exposure to maternal experiences of racism and discrimination resulted in slower epigenetic aging in humans prior to puberty.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p>  <p class="vert-spacing"><span>Beyond the above empirical work, I am leading a large cross-species quantitative review on evidence of developmental plasticity across diverse taxa. While this effort is ongoing, it was initiated and carried out while funded by this NSF award.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p class="vert-spacing"><span>Finally, this grant was instrumental in fostering cross-talk between evolutionary biologists, such as myself, epidemiologists, and biostatisticians. These collaborations resulted in two narrative reviews on systematic approaches to improving causal inference when testing hypotheses with observational data. In an era when large observational data sets are more and more common, these types of interdisciplinary collaborations in which theory and modern quantitative methods are exchanged between fields of study, hold great promise for innovative science. Moreover, interdisciplinary science has the potential for broadening knowledge about the principles that underpin basic biology, including animal and human health.</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p>  <p class="vert-spacing"><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This project has generated several intellectual contributions by testing predictions grounded in life history theory and using methods from behavioral ecology. My use of prospectively collected, repeated data on individual animals over their lifetime enhanced causal interpretation and understanding of socioecological determinants of life history traits and health. Further, I was able to identify early development as a sensitive period during which both the type and timing of social experiences influence developmental processes and future phenotypes in both birds as well as humans. Such consistency in associations across species supports generalizability of developmental plasticity as a way in which organism respond to early-life environments and provides insights on the long-term ramifications on physiology and health.</span></p>  <p><span>Finally, this grant supported multiple broader impact initiatives.&nbsp;I have been actively involved in several efforts that aim to improve Diversity, Equity, Inclusivity, and Accessibility in biology. I led an outreach program on spotted hyena biology to several classrooms of elementary students within the Denver Public School system (in the U.S.). As part of this program, students were shown pictures of diverse people doing field biology and then asked to draw a picture of what a scientist looks like to them. This is part a developing project that aims to showcase diversity in science and importantly to encourage students to see themselves as scientists, if that aligns with their interests. NSF support also facilitated several teaching and mentorship opportunities. I co-instructed a graduate course that aimed to improve DEIA issues within the Evolutionary Biology Department at the University of Colorado, Boulder. I also, co-advised&nbsp;a Kenyan veterinarian who is pursuing a master&rsquo;s degree at the University of Nairobi and two&nbsp;gender-diverse PhD students in the U.S.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/01/2024<br> Modified by: Zachary&nbsp;M&nbsp;Laubach</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The scientific objectives of this project were to investigate a Rule of Life: experiences and environmental exposure during early ontogeny affect later life phenotypes,i.e., an individuals condition, physiology, or health through a process called developmental plasticity. Developmental plasticity is whenthe same genotype produces distinct phenotypes in response to being reared in different environments. In addition to asking,howdo early life experiences affect future phenotypes, my collaborators and I also askedwhythese experiences are important. To answer this question, we grounded our hypotheses in theory from life history evolution and considered whether costs associated with adverse experiences affected traits that are linked to health and/or fitness.    In wild barn swallows, I tested two complementary hypotheses regarding prioritization of resources to optimize life history traits. The overarching goal of this work is to assess how organisms invest limited resources towards essential functions like growth and physiological development. The differential allocation hypothesis posits thatan inverse association between two traits indicates a trade-off involving prioritization of resources, whereas the differential acquisition hypothesis suggests that a positive association between traits is a consequence of differences in individual access to resources. My findings indicate that differences in resource access limit structural growth and physiological development. However, adequate parental care can mitigate these costs. These findings support the differential acquisition hypothesis.In this same study system, I have an ongoing effort investigating if the relationship betweengrowth/offspring stress related glucose physiology is mediated by patterns of DNA methylation using a dataset generated with support from this grant.DNA methylation has been championed as a key mechanism that facilitates developmental plasticity since it is a molecular marker that is both responsive to environmental factors and a determinant of gene expression.My goal is to identify differentially methylated CpG sites that are associated with both early-life environment and nestling life-history traits to identify potential molecular mechanisms of developmental plasticity.    I also led a project in humans on social determinants of health and aging. This work was part of my longer term goal to usea comparative approach to understand the role of social factors in the natural history of aging. In a recent study, my collaborators and I showed thatin uteroexposure to maternal experiences of racism and discrimination resulted in slower epigenetic aging in humans prior to puberty.    Beyond the above empirical work, I am leading a large cross-species quantitative review on evidence of developmental plasticity across diverse taxa. While this effort is ongoing, it was initiated and carried out while funded by this NSF award.    Finally, this grant was instrumental in fostering cross-talk between evolutionary biologists, such as myself, epidemiologists, and biostatisticians. These collaborations resulted in two narrative reviews on systematic approaches to improving causal inference when testing hypotheses with observational data. In an era when large observational data sets are more and more common, these types of interdisciplinary collaborations in which theory and modern quantitative methods are exchanged between fields of study, hold great promise for innovative science. Moreover, interdisciplinary science has the potential for broadening knowledge about the principles that underpin basic biology, including animal and human health.    This project has generated several intellectual contributions by testing predictions grounded in life history theory and using methods from behavioral ecology. My use of prospectively collected, repeated data on individual animals over their lifetime enhanced causal interpretation and understanding of socioecological determinants of life history traits and health. Further, I was able to identify early development as a sensitive period during which both the type and timing of social experiences influence developmental processes and future phenotypes in both birds as well as humans. Such consistency in associations across species supports generalizability of developmental plasticity as a way in which organism respond to early-life environments and provides insights on the long-term ramifications on physiology and health.    Finally, this grant supported multiple broader impact initiatives.I have been actively involved in several efforts that aim to improve Diversity, Equity, Inclusivity, and Accessibility in biology. I led an outreach program on spotted hyena biology to several classrooms of elementary students within the Denver Public School system (in the U.S.). As part of this program, students were shown pictures of diverse people doing field biology and then asked to draw a picture of what a scientist looks like to them. This is part a developing project that aims to showcase diversity in science and importantly to encourage students to see themselves as scientists, if that aligns with their interests. NSF support also facilitated several teaching and mentorship opportunities. I co-instructed a graduate course that aimed to improve DEIA issues within the Evolutionary Biology Department at the University of Colorado, Boulder. I also, co-adviseda Kenyan veterinarian who is pursuing a masters degree at the University of Nairobi and twogender-diverse PhD students in the U.S.         Last Modified: 12/01/2024       Submitted by: ZacharyMLaubach]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
