<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Targeted Infusion Project: Infusion of Computer Technology into General and Organic Chemistry.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399948.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399948</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leroy Jones II</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924684</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP), through Targeted Infusion Projects, supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. This project at the University of Arkansas Pine Bluff (UAPB) will infuse the General and Organic Chemistry curriculum with web-based teaching tools and simulation software. It is expected that learning outcomes will be improved leading to an overall increase in retention.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to increase the number of students completing Organic Chemistry I and moving to Organic Chemistry II, resulting in an overall increase in retention of students in STEM disciplines. This project is also designed to incorporate Peer Led Team Learning (PLTL) practices into General and Organic Chemistry classes at UAPB. The intervention strategies will improve students’ performance in organic chemistry leading to overall increase in retention of students in the sciences. It will also strengthen STEM curricula through infusion of new pedagogical approaches that will promote a greater depth of knowledge in Organic Chemistry. This project will quantify and analyze the effects of technology infusion in learning difficult concepts in Organic Chemistry. The study will also identify the effectiveness of educational TPACK Framework in framing the study for technology infusion in the classroom and laboratory settings. This project will help UAPB to produce a greater number of qualified minority graduates who will pursue careers in the STEM areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011901</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Walker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard B Walker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[walker_r@uapb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000458734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Onyilagha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph Onyilagha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[onyilaghaj@uapb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000532569</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Grant</FirstName>
<LastName>Wangila</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Grant W Wangila</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wangilag@uapb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000618028</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abul</FirstName>
<LastName>Kazi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abul Kazi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kazia@uapb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000726867</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff]]></Name>
<CityName>PINE BLUFF</CityName>
<ZipCode>716012780</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8705758750</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 UNIVERSITY DR STOP 4984]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS4HPMAP57Q5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>CBQ1T88L7TC6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff]]></Name>
<CityName>Pine Bluff</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>716012790</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 N. University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>159400</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~399948</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The initiative to increase the number of students completing Organic Chemistry I and advancing to Organic Chemistry II, thereby boosting overall retention in STEM disciplines, has shown promising results. The primary research question investigated whether the infusion of Web-based teaching tools (Study.Com) in General and Organic Chemistry courses, along with the integration of visualization (Chem4D) and computational (Chem3D) software in Organic Chemistry courses, would improve learning and retention of Organic Chemistry concepts.</p> <p><strong>Hypothesis:</strong> The infusion of Web-based teaching tools (Study.Com) in General and Organic Chemistry courses, as well as the use of visualization (Chem4D) and computational (Chem3D) software in Organic Chemistry courses, will enhance learning in Organic Chemistry.</p> <p><strong>Findings:</strong></p> <ol> <li><strong>Increased Course Completion:</strong> The data indicates a significant increase in the number of students completing Organic Chemistry I and progressing to Organic Chemistry II. This suggests that the additional resources helped in better understanding and engagement with the material, thereby reducing dropout rates.</li> <li><strong>Enhanced Learning Outcomes:</strong> Students exposed to Study.Com, Chem4D, and Chem3D tools demonstrated improved performance in assessments and practical applications of Organic Chemistry concepts. This was evidenced by higher average scores in both General and Organic Chemistry courses compared to previous cohorts without these interventions.</li> <li><strong>Improved Retention Rates:</strong> There was a notable increase in retention rates within the STEM disciplines among students who utilized the Web-based tools and software. These students were more likely to continue their studies in STEM fields, showing a stronger grasp of foundational chemistry concepts critical for advanced coursework.</li> <li><strong>Positive Student Feedback:</strong> Qualitative feedback from students highlighted the value of interactive and visual learning tools in enhancing their understanding of complex concepts. Many students reported that these resources made learning more engaging and less intimidating.</li> <li><strong>Faculty Observations:</strong> Instructors observed a marked improvement in classroom participation and enthusiasm for the subject matter. The tools facilitated a more dynamic and interactive learning environment, which contributed to better overall academic performance.</li> </ol> <p><strong>Conclusion:</strong> The hypothesis that the infusion of Web-based teaching tools (Study.Com) in General and Organic Chemistry courses, alongside visualization (Chem4D) and computational (Chem3D) software in Organic Chemistry courses, would enhance learning has been supported by the findings. This approach has led to higher completion rates of Organic Chemistry I, improved learning outcomes, and increased retention of students in STEM disciplines. The successful implementation of these educational technologies suggests a valuable strategy for improving student success in challenging STEM courses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/30/2024<br> Modified by: Grant&nbsp;W&nbsp;Wangila</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The initiative to increase the number of students completing Organic Chemistry I and advancing to Organic Chemistry II, thereby boosting overall retention in STEM disciplines, has shown promising results. The primary research question investigated whether the infusion of Web-based teaching tools (Study.Com) in General and Organic Chemistry courses, along with the integration of visualization (Chem4D) and computational (Chem3D) software in Organic Chemistry courses, would improve learning and retention of Organic Chemistry concepts.   Hypothesis: The infusion of Web-based teaching tools (Study.Com) in General and Organic Chemistry courses, as well as the use of visualization (Chem4D) and computational (Chem3D) software in Organic Chemistry courses, will enhance learning in Organic Chemistry.   Findings:  Increased Course Completion: The data indicates a significant increase in the number of students completing Organic Chemistry I and progressing to Organic Chemistry II. This suggests that the additional resources helped in better understanding and engagement with the material, thereby reducing dropout rates. Enhanced Learning Outcomes: Students exposed to Study.Com, Chem4D, and Chem3D tools demonstrated improved performance in assessments and practical applications of Organic Chemistry concepts. This was evidenced by higher average scores in both General and Organic Chemistry courses compared to previous cohorts without these interventions. Improved Retention Rates: There was a notable increase in retention rates within the STEM disciplines among students who utilized the Web-based tools and software. These students were more likely to continue their studies in STEM fields, showing a stronger grasp of foundational chemistry concepts critical for advanced coursework. Positive Student Feedback: Qualitative feedback from students highlighted the value of interactive and visual learning tools in enhancing their understanding of complex concepts. Many students reported that these resources made learning more engaging and less intimidating. Faculty Observations: Instructors observed a marked improvement in classroom participation and enthusiasm for the subject matter. The tools facilitated a more dynamic and interactive learning environment, which contributed to better overall academic performance.    Conclusion: The hypothesis that the infusion of Web-based teaching tools (Study.Com) in General and Organic Chemistry courses, alongside visualization (Chem4D) and computational (Chem3D) software in Organic Chemistry courses, would enhance learning has been supported by the findings. This approach has led to higher completion rates of Organic Chemistry I, improved learning outcomes, and increased retention of students in STEM disciplines. The successful implementation of these educational technologies suggests a valuable strategy for improving student success in challenging STEM courses.        Last Modified: 07/30/2024       Submitted by: GrantWWangila]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
