<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Targeting Infusion Project: LU- FIELDS: Lincoln University -  Food Intersectional Education Linked to Diversify Sustainability]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>438000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alfred Hall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alfhall@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924895</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. This project at Lincoln University LU-FIELDS will broaden participation in STEM through the implementation of an interdisciplinary sustainability minor rooted in food studies at the nation’s first HBCU. The local community as well as the broader sustainability community will be engaged through outreach activities, social media engagement, and a certificate course in food sustainability offered at Lincoln as a required course for sustainability minors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of LU-FIELDS (Lincoln University – Food Intersectional Education Linked to Diversify Sustainability) is to increase and broaden STEM engagement through the design and implementation of a state-of-the-art sustainability curriculum around interdisciplinary food studies and social media engagement with built-in assessment. The interdisciplinary approach to curriculum development will ensure an inclusive methodology that engages students across disciplines while fostering science thinking. Outcomes of the project will include a new sustainability minor at Lincoln University, a certificate course in Food Sustainability open to both Lincoln students and the greater community, student research projects in sustainable garden practices, food justice, intersectionality assessment, and app development, as well as community engagement around sustainable food production, food security and food justice. Students and faculty will present their research at local and national conferences and publish outcomes in peer reviewed journals. The project app will be used to engage students by utilizing the capabilities of gamification mixed with the accessibility of mobile technology and social media connection. The app will also be used to collect assessment data on student learning outcomes and sustainability engagement. Contributions to the fields of sustainability and intersectionality research will include new frameworks of methodologies and assessment pertaining to minority populations and community engagement in sustainability studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011736</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Hull</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna K Hull</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ahull@lincoln.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000061204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melina</FirstName>
<LastName>McConatha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melina McConatha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmcconatha@lincoln.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000809886</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Uzoma</FirstName>
<LastName>Chikwem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Uzoma Chikwem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[uchikwem@lincoln.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000735282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lincoln University]]></Name>
<CityName>LINCOLN UNIVERSITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>193529141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4843657695</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1570 BALTIMORE PIKE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T59JHM69NCZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LINCOLN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lincoln University]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln University</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>193520999</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1570 Baltimore Pike]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>159400</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~38000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main purpose of the award was to support faculty and undergraduate student research in interdisciplinary food sustainability to develop a student-centered sustainability minor at Lincoln University, the nation&rsquo;s first Historically black University located in southeastern Pennsylvania. In the project&rsquo;s four-year span, twenty-two (22) undergraduate students from diverse disciplines including, biology, computer science, environmental science, finance, general science, human services, and visual arts conducted faculty mentored food sustainability research. The students presented their findings at local and national conferences including the HBCU Climate Change Conference in both 2022 and 2023. A collaboration with the Environmental Protection Agency, Region 3, offered full-year internships to six students who were able to conduct semi-independent research on water and soil contamination under EPA mentorship. &nbsp;Together with students, faculty developed website materials to promote sustainability efforts, assessment methods for sustainable workspaces with equitable access to open spaces, and three new courses in sustainability that are incorporated into a new sustainability minor. Connections with local food sustainability partners were strengthened through collaborations to enhance sustainability, equity, and inclusion in food sovereignty and open land access. The principal investigators participated in faculty development in permaculture, ecological healing, and climate wayfinding to grow teaching resources at Lincoln University and increase student engagement around issues related to sustainability in both the social and natural sciences. The award was recognized by PA legislatures and resulted in visits from representative Chrissy Houlahan as well as a recommendation for additional infrastructure funding by senator Bob Casey to support sustainability efforts at the University. In total, the project resulted in 20 poster presentations, three peer-reviewed publications, four invited conference presentations, and three videos. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/21/2024<br> Modified by: Anna&nbsp;K&nbsp;Hull</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377250617_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.30.38_PM--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377250617_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.30.38_PM--rgov-800width.png" title="Earth Day 2022"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377250617_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.30.38_PM--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Earth Day 2022"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Earth Day Celebration at the LU-FIELDS garden in 2022.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lincoln University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;K&nbsp;Hull <div class="imageTitle">Earth Day 2022</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377497865_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.20.29_PM--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377497865_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.20.29_PM--rgov-800width.png" title="Student Presenters at the 8th HBCU Climate Change Conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377497865_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.20.29_PM--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Student Presenters at the 8th HBCU Climate Change Conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students in front of their poster at the 8th HBCU Climate Conference in New Orleans, LA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anna K Hull</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;K&nbsp;Hull <div class="imageTitle">Student Presenters at the 8th HBCU Climate Change Conference</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377869686_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.19.24_PM--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377869686_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.19.24_PM--rgov-800width.png" title="Award Winner, 8th HBCU Climate Change Conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377869686_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.19.24_PM--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Award Winner, 8th HBCU Climate Change Conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Three LU-FIELDS students win awards at the 8th HBCU Climate Change Conference, April 2022.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anna K Hull</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;K&nbsp;Hull <div class="imageTitle">Award Winner, 8th HBCU Climate Change Conference</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729373879361_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_5.26.32_PM--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729373879361_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_5.26.32_PM--rgov-800width.png" title="Chrissy Houlahan visits Lincoln University on September 3, 2020"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729373879361_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_5.26.32_PM--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Chrissy Houlahan visits Lincoln University on September 3, 2020"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Representative Houlahan joined the LU-FIELDS harvest celebration in the first few months of the LU-FIELDS project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lincoln University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;K&nbsp;Hull <div class="imageTitle">Chrissy Houlahan visits Lincoln University on September 3, 2020</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729375715732_FC032B3A_27A6_4B03_9152_FD0FE1FFCD21--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729375715732_FC032B3A_27A6_4B03_9152_FD0FE1FFCD21--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Human Services Establishes Herb Garden, April 2023"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729375715732_FC032B3A_27A6_4B03_9152_FD0FE1FFCD21--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Human Services Establishes Herb Garden, April 2023"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A Human Services class designs and establishes an herb garden on Lincoln's campus.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Melina McConatha</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;K&nbsp;Hull <div class="imageTitle">Human Services Establishes Herb Garden, April 2023</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377678321_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.15.35_PM--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377678321_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.15.35_PM--rgov-800width.png" title="9th HBCU Climate Change Conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2011736/2011736_10676477_1729377678321_Screen_Shot_2024_10_19_at_6.15.35_PM--rgov-66x44.png" alt="9th HBCU Climate Change Conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Student in front of their poster at the 9th HBCU Climate Change Conference, New Orleans, LA in October 2023.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anna K Hull</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;K&nbsp;Hull <div class="imageTitle">9th HBCU Climate Change Conference</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The main purpose of the award was to support faculty and undergraduate student research in interdisciplinary food sustainability to develop a student-centered sustainability minor at Lincoln University, the nations first Historically black University located in southeastern Pennsylvania. In the projects four-year span, twenty-two (22) undergraduate students from diverse disciplines including, biology, computer science, environmental science, finance, general science, human services, and visual arts conducted faculty mentored food sustainability research. The students presented their findings at local and national conferences including the HBCU Climate Change Conference in both 2022 and 2023. A collaboration with the Environmental Protection Agency, Region 3, offered full-year internships to six students who were able to conduct semi-independent research on water and soil contamination under EPA mentorship. Together with students, faculty developed website materials to promote sustainability efforts, assessment methods for sustainable workspaces with equitable access to open spaces, and three new courses in sustainability that are incorporated into a new sustainability minor. Connections with local food sustainability partners were strengthened through collaborations to enhance sustainability, equity, and inclusion in food sovereignty and open land access. The principal investigators participated in faculty development in permaculture, ecological healing, and climate wayfinding to grow teaching resources at Lincoln University and increase student engagement around issues related to sustainability in both the social and natural sciences. The award was recognized by PA legislatures and resulted in visits from representative Chrissy Houlahan as well as a recommendation for additional infrastructure funding by senator Bob Casey to support sustainability efforts at the University. In total, the project resulted in 20 poster presentations, three peer-reviewed publications, four invited conference presentations, and three videos.         Last Modified: 10/21/2024       Submitted by: AnnaKHull]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
