<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[APS CUWiP: Supporting the Success of All Undergraduate Women in Physics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449866.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>449866</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award to the American Physical Society supports the continued growth and improvement of the Conferences for Undergraduate Women in Physics (CUWiP), held annually since 2006. The goals of the CUWiP effort are to increase retention and improve career outcomes of undergraduate women in physics by (i) communicating the breadth of education and career paths open to physics majors; (ii) disseminating information and advice on applying for summer research, graduate school and professional employment; and (iii) providing opportunities to share experiences, advice and ideas with women at different stages of their education or career paths. The CUWiP goals will be achieved by providing (i) inspiring talks by female physicists, (ii) workshops and panel discussions on summer research, graduate school, physics careers, professional development, and issues facing minority women in physics, (iii) student presentations or poster sessions, and (iv) opportunities for networking and informal mentoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CUWiP aims to broaden the participation of women in physics by providing information, resources, networks and motivation to pursue advanced degrees and/or careers in physics. The broad geographic distribution of the conferences maximizes access to the conferences and facilitates recruitment of students from underrepresented minority groups and from local community colleges. Local conference organization provides opportunities for students and postdocs to engage directly in broadening participation in science. The proposed activities will enable the organizers to probe how these conferences facilitate networking and improve participants’ attitudes concerning self-efficacy and identity as physicists. The results of the proposed annual assessments will be used to improve the effectiveness of the conferences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported jointly by two divisions of NSF's Mathematical and Physical Sciences Directorate: the Division of Physics and the Division of Materials Research&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012033</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
<LastName>Plisch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Monica J Plisch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[plisch@aps.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000314699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mu-Chun</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mu-Chun Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[muchunc@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000217293</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Szczerbinska</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara Szczerbinska</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[barbara.szczerbinska@tamucc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000493834</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/29/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shubha</FirstName>
<LastName>Tewari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shubha Tewari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stewari@wnec.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000081356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Renee Michelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Goertzen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Renee Michelle Goertzen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[goertzen@aps.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000565869</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/02/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evangeline</FirstName>
<LastName>Downie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evangeline J Downie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[edownie@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000597650</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/29/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brianna</FirstName>
<LastName>Mount</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brianna Mount</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Brianna.Mount@bhsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000605567</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Nash</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelly L Nash</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kelly.nash@utsa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000614557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/30/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Crystal</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Crystal Bailey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bailey@aps.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000690594</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erika</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erika Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brown@aps.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000736693</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/22/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Physical Society]]></Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>207403841</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3012093657</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ONE PHYSICS ELL IPSE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CE5JV8E9K4S3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN PHYSICAL SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GQQEEZHBUFC6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Physical Society]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207403841</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Physics Ellipse]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125300</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>722200</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>762100</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>913400</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~449866</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-83142821-7fff-c339-e956-832b8e4f3da6"> </span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>The APS </span><span>Conferences for Undergraduate Women in Physics (CUWiP) were held annually between 2021 and 2024, bringing together over 2,000 women and gender minorities each year, nearly equaling the number of physics bachelor&rsquo;s degrees awarded in some years (e.g. 2023 and 2024). While the 2021 and 2022 conferences were fully virtual out of concern for the safety of participants during the COVID pandemic, the 2023 and 2024 conferences were held in person at 14 sites distributed around the United States. The Conferences were organized by local organizing committees, which were supported by a national leadership structure convened by APS.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Activities at the CUWiPs included presentations and panel discussions featuring speakers from various sectors such as academia, industry, and public policy. Workshops focused on career development, including applying to internships and graduate schools; the conferences also included networking opportunities for students to meet with graduate school and company recruiters. Participants engaged in oral and poster presentations to showcase their research, and informal discussions allowed them to connect with mentors and peers. Additionally, there were tours of national laboratories and other facilities, enhancing the participants' understanding of various career paths in physics. In 2024, the CUWiPs were situated within a broader Gender Inclusive Community (GIC), a program which also incorporates a graduate-focused conference and virtual platform for year-round mentoring between graduate and undergraduate participants.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Pre- and post-conference survey data each year indicated that the conferences produced positive shifts in several key factors associated with a participant&rsquo;s likelihood of persisting in physics, such as an increased belief in their ability to do and understand physics. Participants also left the conferences with greater knowledge of job opportunities, career paths, and strategies for achieving these career paths. Longitudinal data from surveys conducted on participants from previous conferences demonstrated a &ldquo;halo effect," namely that while participants reported participation as being extremely valuable during and immediately after the event, attendees tended to revert to beliefs held prior to CUWiP with the passage of time, indicating a need for more continued engagement with community members to sustain the conferences' positive impacts. This formed part of the rationale for moving the CUWiPs into the GIC, so that participants could also participate in grad conferences, receive near-peer mentorship from graduate participants, and remain a part of a community beyond attending a CUWiP and/or receiving their undergraduate physics degree.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition to supporting the Conferences, a toolkit of effective practices for organizing and hosting the Conferences was developed in collaboration with each cohort of local organizing committee members, national leadership, APS staff, and external evaluators. Local organizers met annually at a Convocation, led by APS staff and the national leadership group to receive guidance on budgeting and fundraising; conference logistics; and how to utilize evidence-based practices to design an agenda which will maximize participants&rsquo; senses of belonging, self-efficacy, confidence and interest in physics. Evaluation data was shared each year from the previous year&rsquo;s conference so local organizers were able to learn from previous outcomes and results.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition to the above, improvements were continually made to centralized operations supporting the conferences, such as the implementation of a centralized application process for student participants, which helped reduce the workload of the local committees and minimize travel expenses; an application process which helped ensure an adequate number of well prepared sites with balanced geographic coverage; and several APS-hosted digital resources helped organizers learn about and implement best practices.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong><span>This project supports the continued growth and improvement of the CUWiP model. The external evaluation team has expertise in faculty professional development, women in physics, and social networking analysis, and their work will be guided by a CUWiP Theory of Change, which is grounded in well-established theoretical frameworks. They will contribute evaluation and research results on the proposed activities to build knowledge of evidence-based practices and assess the impact of conferences on improving participants&rsquo; knowledge of careers, identity as physicists, and persistence in the field. Professional development for conference organizers will be guided by a curriculum map and follow effective practices for supporting faculty learning.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong><span> The CUWiPs aim to broaden the participation of women in physics by providing information, resources, networks and motivation to pursue advanced degrees and/or careers in physics. The broad geographic distribution of the conferences maximizes access to the conferences and facilitates the recruitment of students from underrepresented minority groups and from local CCs. In addition, local conference organization provides opportunities for students and postdocs to engage directly in broadening participation in science. By offering the opportunity for nearly every woman and gender minority physics major to attend a CUWiP, our vision is to see the fraction of bachelor&rsquo;s degrees in physics granted to female students begin to increase again--reversing the downward trend observed over the past decade.</span></p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/28/2024<br> Modified by: Crystal&nbsp;Bailey</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       The APS Conferences for Undergraduate Women in Physics (CUWiP) were held annually between 2021 and 2024, bringing together over 2,000 women and gender minorities each year, nearly equaling the number of physics bachelors degrees awarded in some years (e.g. 2023 and 2024). While the 2021 and 2022 conferences were fully virtual out of concern for the safety of participants during the COVID pandemic, the 2023 and 2024 conferences were held in person at 14 sites distributed around the United States. The Conferences were organized by local organizing committees, which were supported by a national leadership structure convened by APS.    Activities at the CUWiPs included presentations and panel discussions featuring speakers from various sectors such as academia, industry, and public policy. Workshops focused on career development, including applying to internships and graduate schools; the conferences also included networking opportunities for students to meet with graduate school and company recruiters. Participants engaged in oral and poster presentations to showcase their research, and informal discussions allowed them to connect with mentors and peers. Additionally, there were tours of national laboratories and other facilities, enhancing the participants' understanding of various career paths in physics. In 2024, the CUWiPs were situated within a broader Gender Inclusive Community (GIC), a program which also incorporates a graduate-focused conference and virtual platform for year-round mentoring between graduate and undergraduate participants.    Pre- and post-conference survey data each year indicated that the conferences produced positive shifts in several key factors associated with a participants likelihood of persisting in physics, such as an increased belief in their ability to do and understand physics. Participants also left the conferences with greater knowledge of job opportunities, career paths, and strategies for achieving these career paths. Longitudinal data from surveys conducted on participants from previous conferences demonstrated a halo effect," namely that while participants reported participation as being extremely valuable during and immediately after the event, attendees tended to revert to beliefs held prior to CUWiP with the passage of time, indicating a need for more continued engagement with community members to sustain the conferences' positive impacts. This formed part of the rationale for moving the CUWiPs into the GIC, so that participants could also participate in grad conferences, receive near-peer mentorship from graduate participants, and remain a part of a community beyond attending a CUWiP and/or receiving their undergraduate physics degree.    In addition to supporting the Conferences, a toolkit of effective practices for organizing and hosting the Conferences was developed in collaboration with each cohort of local organizing committee members, national leadership, APS staff, and external evaluators. Local organizers met annually at a Convocation, led by APS staff and the national leadership group to receive guidance on budgeting and fundraising; conference logistics; and how to utilize evidence-based practices to design an agenda which will maximize participants senses of belonging, self-efficacy, confidence and interest in physics. Evaluation data was shared each year from the previous years conference so local organizers were able to learn from previous outcomes and results.    In addition to the above, improvements were continually made to centralized operations supporting the conferences, such as the implementation of a centralized application process for student participants, which helped reduce the workload of the local committees and minimize travel expenses; an application process which helped ensure an adequate number of well prepared sites with balanced geographic coverage; and several APS-hosted digital resources helped organizers learn about and implement best practices.    Intellectual Merit: This project supports the continued growth and improvement of the CUWiP model. The external evaluation team has expertise in faculty professional development, women in physics, and social networking analysis, and their work will be guided by a CUWiP Theory of Change, which is grounded in well-established theoretical frameworks. They will contribute evaluation and research results on the proposed activities to build knowledge of evidence-based practices and assess the impact of conferences on improving participants knowledge of careers, identity as physicists, and persistence in the field. Professional development for conference organizers will be guided by a curriculum map and follow effective practices for supporting faculty learning.    Broader Impacts: The CUWiPs aim to broaden the participation of women in physics by providing information, resources, networks and motivation to pursue advanced degrees and/or careers in physics. The broad geographic distribution of the conferences maximizes access to the conferences and facilitates the recruitment of students from underrepresented minority groups and from local CCs. In addition, local conference organization provides opportunities for students and postdocs to engage directly in broadening participation in science. By offering the opportunity for nearly every woman and gender minority physics major to attend a CUWiP, our vision is to see the fraction of bachelors degrees in physics granted to female students begin to increase again--reversing the downward trend observed over the past decade.         Last Modified: 11/28/2024       Submitted by: CrystalBailey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
