<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[New Frontiers in Nuclear Astrophysics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>525000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>525000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmihaila@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Humanity has long been fascinated by the majesty of the night sky.  Now, with powerful scientific tools, we can better observe stars, galaxies, and the universe itself.  We can also better understand the mechanisms behind this majesty.  Nuclear physics processes are especially important.  Stars are powered by fusion reactions, supernova explosions produce and disperse chemical elements, and the remnants of these explosions accelerate high-energy cosmic rays.  A better understanding of these nuclear processes would help us understand the origin, nature, and fate of the universe.  A way forward is possible using neutrinos, tiny particles with zero charge, almost no mass, and only weak interactions.  Neutrinos are abundantly produced in many astrophysical objects.  Detecting neutrinos is very difficult, but doing so can reveal physical conditions deep within these sources, beyond the reach of observations with light.  The PI will lead a broad program of theoretical work in neutrino astrophysics designed to lead to breakthroughs in understanding astrophysical objects and neutrino properties.  Junior scientists will be trained on cutting-edge research as well as career skills.  The PI and junior scientists will work to share results with the public and to broaden participation by under-represented groups, including the Deaf and Hard of Hearing.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project features three main thrusts: solar neutrinos, supernova neutrinos, and high-energy neutrinos.  The central tenet of this work is that a broad-based, tightly integrated, theory-led approach to neutrino astronomy can decisively advance nuclear astrophysics.  For solar neutrinos, long-term outcomes could include significantly reduced detector backgrounds and thus improvements in the precision of signals from existing detectors, along with a high-statistics solar-neutrino measurement in the DUNE detector.  For supernova neutrinos, these could include better observing a Milky Way supernova and the discovery of the Diffuse Supernova Neutrino Background (DSNB).  For high-energy neutrinos, these could include new detection techniques that facilitate the discovery of astrophysical neutrino sources.  All three thrusts will benefit from the addition of gadolinium to Super-Kamiokande in 2020, as originally proposed by Beacom and Vagins in 2003 to help separate signals from backgrounds.  Throughout, the PI will use the progress in neutrino astronomy to advance multi-messenger astrophysics and beyond-standard model physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project advances the objectives of "Windows on the Universe: the Era of Multi-Messenger Astrophysics", one of the 10 Big Ideas for Future NSF Investments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012955</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Beacom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Beacom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[beacom.7@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000431236</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 KENNY RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101117</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[191 W. Woodruff Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>107y00</Code>
<Text>WoU-Windows on the Universe: T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>121500</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128500</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>723500</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>069Z</Code>
<Text>Windows on the Universe (WoU)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~525000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nuclear astrophysics is essential to our understanding of the visible universe.&nbsp; Nuclear fusion powers stars, supernovae produce chemical elements, and as-yet unknown sources accelerate cosmic rays.&nbsp; It has long been known that nuclear processes in astrophysical sources copiously produce neutrinos, which are almost non-interacting elementary particles.&nbsp; Detecting these neutrinos, while extremely challenging, opens new frontiers in nuclear astrophysics.&nbsp; In addition, neutrinos are an essential tool for multi-messenger astrophysics and a sensitive probe of physics beyond the standard model.&nbsp; Realizing this potential requires theoretical work to generate new insights about possible sources, new techniques to enable their detection, and new syntheses of multi-messenger data.<br /><br />For the intellectual-merit aspects of this grant, PI Beacom led novel research projects focused on theoretical neutrino astrophysics and physics, making strong connections to experiment and observation.&nbsp; One highlight of the published work is a comparison of the neutrino signals predicted by modern supernova models to each other and to the Supernova 1987A data, showing that improved models are needed.&nbsp;&nbsp;A second is a detailed study of how backgrounds caused by atmospheric neutrinos impede our ability to detect the signal of neutrinos from all past supernovae, opening new directions to reduce these backgrounds.&nbsp;&nbsp;A third is a multi-messenger study --- using cosmic rays, gamma rays, and neutrinos --- of the Milky Way's PeVatron sources (those where the particle energies are about fifteen orders of magnitude higher than for visible light).&nbsp;&nbsp;Other important thrusts include probing the Sun as a high-energy source, new tests of dark matter, and multi-messenger studies associated with supernovae and other transients.&nbsp;&nbsp;The results of the supported research were documented through 30 publications in peer-reviewed journals.<br /><br />For the broader-impacts aspects of this grant, PI Beacom led a broad program of activities.&nbsp; One highlight is his ongoing work with the SciAccess initiative, which "... brings together a diverse community of researchers, professionals, students, educators, employers, and disability rights advocates, whose shared knowledge and ideas are critical to increasing skills, knowledge, and opportunities in STEM fields for individuals with disabilities." &nbsp;A second is his sustained work to improve mentoring for students and postdocs, not only at Ohio State but more broadly, which has been recognized with multiple awards.&nbsp;&nbsp;A third is his continued leadership of the "Science Sundays" program at Ohio State, which provides free public lectures on a variety of topics in cutting-edge science.&nbsp;&nbsp;Other activities include building connections between academia and industry, outreach to a variety of groups, and consistently working to broaden participation in science of people from under-represented groups, especially people with disabilities.<br /><br />This work was done in conjunction with students, postdocs, and other collaborators.&nbsp; Junior scientists were trained in technical, career, and outreach skills.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 06/05/2024<br> Modified by: John&nbsp;Beacom</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Nuclear astrophysics is essential to our understanding of the visible universe. Nuclear fusion powers stars, supernovae produce chemical elements, and as-yet unknown sources accelerate cosmic rays. It has long been known that nuclear processes in astrophysical sources copiously produce neutrinos, which are almost non-interacting elementary particles. Detecting these neutrinos, while extremely challenging, opens new frontiers in nuclear astrophysics. In addition, neutrinos are an essential tool for multi-messenger astrophysics and a sensitive probe of physics beyond the standard model. Realizing this potential requires theoretical work to generate new insights about possible sources, new techniques to enable their detection, and new syntheses of multi-messenger data.  For the intellectual-merit aspects of this grant, PI Beacom led novel research projects focused on theoretical neutrino astrophysics and physics, making strong connections to experiment and observation. One highlight of the published work is a comparison of the neutrino signals predicted by modern supernova models to each other and to the Supernova 1987A data, showing that improved models are needed.A second is a detailed study of how backgrounds caused by atmospheric neutrinos impede our ability to detect the signal of neutrinos from all past supernovae, opening new directions to reduce these backgrounds.A third is a multi-messenger study --- using cosmic rays, gamma rays, and neutrinos --- of the Milky Way's PeVatron sources (those where the particle energies are about fifteen orders of magnitude higher than for visible light).Other important thrusts include probing the Sun as a high-energy source, new tests of dark matter, and multi-messenger studies associated with supernovae and other transients.The results of the supported research were documented through 30 publications in peer-reviewed journals.  For the broader-impacts aspects of this grant, PI Beacom led a broad program of activities. One highlight is his ongoing work with the SciAccess initiative, which "... brings together a diverse community of researchers, professionals, students, educators, employers, and disability rights advocates, whose shared knowledge and ideas are critical to increasing skills, knowledge, and opportunities in STEM fields for individuals with disabilities." A second is his sustained work to improve mentoring for students and postdocs, not only at Ohio State but more broadly, which has been recognized with multiple awards.A third is his continued leadership of the "Science Sundays" program at Ohio State, which provides free public lectures on a variety of topics in cutting-edge science.Other activities include building connections between academia and industry, outreach to a variety of groups, and consistently working to broaden participation in science of people from under-represented groups, especially people with disabilities.  This work was done in conjunction with students, postdocs, and other collaborators. Junior scientists were trained in technical, career, and outreach skills.        Last Modified: 06/05/2024       Submitted by: JohnBeacom]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
