<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Expanding and Evaluating an Ecological, Networked Course-based Undergraduate Research Experience]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>66486.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>66486</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Olivia S. Long</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>olong@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927897</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest by evaluating evidence-based practices for engaging students in authentic ecological research across the undergraduate curriculum. Research opportunities enable students to engage in the scientific process, as well as help them to develop workforce readiness and to evaluate potential careers. By embedding research within instruction, Course-based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs) provide research opportunities to large numbers of students. This project will evaluate a set of community-based CURE modules intended to help students build scientific skills throughout their undergraduate experience. The modules provide students with repeated opportunities to conduct authentic research on the behavioral ecology of squirrels.  These animals are intrinsically interesting to many people and can be studied across a wide range of environments.  These CURES are supported by a national network (Squirrel-Net) that provides tools and training for instructors who seek to increase CURE adoption.  The Network also provides opportunities for students and faculty to communicate and collaborate across courses and institutions. This project seeks to enhance understanding of evidence-based approaches to STEM instruction and to improve the education of a diverse scientific workforce through broad implementation of the CURE modules.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to assess the impacts of scaffolding CURE modules within curricula and supporting students and instructors through a network. The project goals are twofold: (1) disseminate and support a set of broadly transferable teaching modules and toolkits to allow instructors to easily embed field-based, behavioral ecology CUREs within courses; and (2) assess how networked CURE modules impact student gains in content knowledge, skills, and self-identification as a scientist across multiple and varied institutions. Participating instructors will be trained in the use of open-access teaching modules and supported through digital resources (e.g., instructional materials; an online database of student-collected data) and field equipment loans. By scaffolding modules among multiple courses at diverse institutions, this project will examine how specific features of CURE module implementation affect student outcomes across a variety of contexts and student demographics. Student outcomes will be evaluated with assessments derived from validated survey instruments focused on scientific skills, sense of belonging to a community, and self-identity as a scientist. Structural equation modeling will be used to evaluate the impacts of CURE participation on student content knowledge, analytical skills, and engagement following a theory of change framework. This project will guide the implementation and improvement of evidence-based practices in STEM teaching and learning by empirically testing whether repeated CUREs and belonging to a nationwide research network improves student outcomes. This project is supported by the NSF Improving Undergraduate STEM Education Program: Education and Human Resources, which supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students.  Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013281</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Johanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Varner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Johanna Varner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jvarner@coloradomesa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792689</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado Mesa University]]></Name>
<CityName>GRAND JUNCTION</CityName>
<ZipCode>815013122</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9702481424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1100 NORTH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E5RRMPPLNMD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO MESA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HAL9A8N46NB3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado Mesa University]]></Name>
<CityName>Grand Junction</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>815013122</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1100 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~66486</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-df7f587b-7fff-ad5e-5e4f-c2c7b681dad2" style="line-height: 1.3800000000000001; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 6pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Squirrel-Net (</span><a style="text-decoration: none;" href="http://squirrel-net.org"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #1155cc; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; text-decoration-skip-ink: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">http://squirrel-net.org</span></a><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">) is a course-based undergraduate research experience (CURE) network that provides students across the country with opportunities to study the behavioral ecology of squirrels. Our broad goals were to increase undergraduate research opportunities, to support instructors in implementing field-based CUREs, and to measure how networking and scaffolding our CURE modules affect student learning outcomes, motivation, and science identity.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.3800000000000001; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 6pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Through this award, we developed and disseminated a set of five, open-access, broadly transferable teaching modules and toolkits that allow instructors to easily build field-based ecology CUREs into their college courses.</span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: italic; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">By making our CURE modules freely available, we have improved the reach of high-impact, student-centered teaching approaches in biology. Collectively, we have provided materials to nearly 500 instructors at a variety of institutions, and at least 10,000 students have participated in at least one CURE module during this award. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">We also developed a number of resources to support network instructors, including 4 published CURE modules, monthly email newsletters, and 15 how-to videos available on Squirrel-Net&rsquo;s YouTube channel (</span><a style="text-decoration: none;" href="https://www.youtube.com/c/squirrelneted"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #1155cc; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; text-decoration-skip-ink: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">https://www.youtube.com/c/squirrelneted</span></a><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">). Finally, this award has resulted in 12 peer-reviewed publications, as well as 22 contributed abstracts, 3 organized symposia/panel discussions, and 6 workshops at national or international conferences.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.3800000000000001; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: bold; font-style: italic; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Intellectual Merit: </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">This project demonstrated that a scaffolded, nationwide CURE network increases access, inclusion, and scalability for undergraduate research experiences across institutions. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Through paired pre- and post-CURE surveys, we assessed how participation in a Squirrel-Net CURE affected student gains in content knowledge, skills, and science identity. We found that after participating in Squirrel-Net CUREs, students were more likely to self-identify as scientists compared to their self-described identity before. We also observed significant gains in &lsquo;Readiness for more research&rsquo; among students who belong to historically marginalized groups. Additionally, after completing a Squirrel-Net module, significantly more students reported interest in doctoral programs, becoming certified as a teacher, or working in a science lab. Thus, our results suggest participation in Squirrel-Net CUREs encourages retention of students and the pursuit of occupations in STEM. We expect several additional publications to come from these assessment data. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Finally, this work has allowed us to test how specific features of CUREs (such as scaffolding content within the curriculum and networking among schools) are linked to student outcomes, thereby addressing critical information gaps in the CURE literature and advancing knowledge of STEM instructional practices.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.3800000000000001; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: bold; font-style: italic; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Broader Impacts: </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Our activities have resulted in significant impacts on teaching and educational experiences by supporting instructors. Through this grant, over 100 instructors, including several graduate students, were trained in using active learning strategies to increase inclusion in their courses through our </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">6</span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> conference workshops. In addition, </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">9</span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> instructors have been supported to attend workshops and conferences through travel grants. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Our workshop and conference presentations included dissemination of &lsquo;best practices&rsquo; for helping students develop strong science identities through CUREs, as well as strategies for increasing inclusion in classes more generally. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">We have also provided equipment loans to 3 instructors (renewed for several years each), </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">broadening access to high-impact teaching practices at less affluent schools.</span></p> <p><br /><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">As a result, our activities have provided authentic research experiences to a large and diverse population of undergraduate STEM majors and non-majors across a range of institutional types and locations (see Fig. 1). </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Collectively, a minimum of 10,000</span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> students have p</span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">articipated in the Squirrel-Net CURE modules. Although many of these students may not choose to pursue careers in STEM, they will be entering society with a better understanding of how scientific research is conducted. In particular, integrating research into a classroom experience (i.e., through a CURE) increases the number of students exposed to and participating in authentic research experiences, and in turn broadens impacts on society outside of academia, compared to more selective, traditional, mentored research experiences. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">In addition, because our CUREs are being used in non-majors courses, community colleges, and non-profit research organizations, this project has provided widespread opportunities for improving science literacy and workforce readiness beyond STEM majors. Finally, our project has brought together undergraduate students and researchers in a research community, with the development of discussion forums, blogs, and interactions via our social media. </span></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/30/2024<br> Modified by: Johanna&nbsp;Varner</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724128917_Student_GUD_Tray--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724128917_Student_GUD_Tray--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Giving Up Density (GUD) Module"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724128917_Student_GUD_Tray--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Giving Up Density (GUD) Module"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Student places an experimental foraging tray to measure giving up density (GUD) on the Colorado Mesa University campus. GUD is an integrative measure of risk and reward in animal behavior studies.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Johanna Varner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johanna&nbsp;Varner <div class="imageTitle">Giving Up Density (GUD) Module</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724884427_Student_Field_Observation--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724884427_Student_Field_Observation--rgov-800width.JPG" title="Students Observing Squirrel Behavior in the Field"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724884427_Student_Field_Observation--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="Students Observing Squirrel Behavior in the Field"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students observe squirrel behavior at a field site near Grand Junction, CO as part of one of the Squirrel-Net Course-based Undergraduate Research Experience (CURE) modules.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Johanna Varner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johanna&nbsp;Varner <div class="imageTitle">Students Observing Squirrel Behavior in the Field</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724761856_Student_Observations_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724761856_Student_Observations_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students Observing Campus Squirrels"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724761856_Student_Observations_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students Observing Campus Squirrels"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students observe squirrel behavior on a college campus as part of one of the Squirrel-Net Course-based Undergraduate Research Experience (CURE) modules.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Johanna Varner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johanna&nbsp;Varner <div class="imageTitle">Students Observing Campus Squirrels</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727723948554_Telemetry--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727723948554_Telemetry--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Telemetry Module"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727723948554_Telemetry--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Telemetry Module"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Student uses telemetry equipment to track collared California ground squirrels at California State University, Monterey Bay</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jenny Duggan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johanna&nbsp;Varner <div class="imageTitle">Telemetry Module</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724170984_Participating_Institutions--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724170984_Participating_Institutions--rgov-800width.png" title="Map of Participating Institutions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724170984_Participating_Institutions--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Map of Participating Institutions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of participating institutions classified by time period during which access to Squirrel-Net materials was first requested.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Squirrel-Net</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johanna&nbsp;Varner <div class="imageTitle">Map of Participating Institutions</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724638257_ASM_Workshop--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724638257_ASM_Workshop--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ASM Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2013281/2013281_10690533_1727724638257_ASM_Workshop--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ASM Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Instructors participate in a workshop on evidence-based teaching practices, led by Squirrel-Net PIs and Senior Personnel, at the 2024 American Society of Mammalogists conference in Boulder, CO.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Patrice Connors</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johanna&nbsp;Varner <div class="imageTitle">ASM Workshop</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Squirrel-Net (http://squirrel-net.org) is a course-based undergraduate research experience (CURE) network that provides students across the country with opportunities to study the behavioral ecology of squirrels. Our broad goals were to increase undergraduate research opportunities, to support instructors in implementing field-based CUREs, and to measure how networking and scaffolding our CURE modules affect student learning outcomes, motivation, and science identity.   Through this award, we developed and disseminated a set of five, open-access, broadly transferable teaching modules and toolkits that allow instructors to easily build field-based ecology CUREs into their college courses. By making our CURE modules freely available, we have improved the reach of high-impact, student-centered teaching approaches in biology. Collectively, we have provided materials to nearly 500 instructors at a variety of institutions, and at least 10,000 students have participated in at least one CURE module during this award. We also developed a number of resources to support network instructors, including 4 published CURE modules, monthly email newsletters, and 15 how-to videos available on Squirrel-Nets YouTube channel (https://www.youtube.com/c/squirrelneted). Finally, this award has resulted in 12 peer-reviewed publications, as well as 22 contributed abstracts, 3 organized symposia/panel discussions, and 6 workshops at national or international conferences.   Intellectual Merit: This project demonstrated that a scaffolded, nationwide CURE network increases access, inclusion, and scalability for undergraduate research experiences across institutions. Through paired pre- and post-CURE surveys, we assessed how participation in a Squirrel-Net CURE affected student gains in content knowledge, skills, and science identity. We found that after participating in Squirrel-Net CUREs, students were more likely to self-identify as scientists compared to their self-described identity before. We also observed significant gains in Readiness for more research among students who belong to historically marginalized groups. Additionally, after completing a Squirrel-Net module, significantly more students reported interest in doctoral programs, becoming certified as a teacher, or working in a science lab. Thus, our results suggest participation in Squirrel-Net CUREs encourages retention of students and the pursuit of occupations in STEM. We expect several additional publications to come from these assessment data. Finally, this work has allowed us to test how specific features of CUREs (such as scaffolding content within the curriculum and networking among schools) are linked to student outcomes, thereby addressing critical information gaps in the CURE literature and advancing knowledge of STEM instructional practices.      Broader Impacts: Our activities have resulted in significant impacts on teaching and educational experiences by supporting instructors. Through this grant, over 100 instructors, including several graduate students, were trained in using active learning strategies to increase inclusion in their courses through our 6 conference workshops. In addition, 9 instructors have been supported to attend workshops and conferences through travel grants. Our workshop and conference presentations included dissemination of best practices for helping students develop strong science identities through CUREs, as well as strategies for increasing inclusion in classes more generally. We have also provided equipment loans to 3 instructors (renewed for several years each), broadening access to high-impact teaching practices at less affluent schools.    As a result, our activities have provided authentic research experiences to a large and diverse population of undergraduate STEM majors and non-majors across a range of institutional types and locations (see Fig. 1). Collectively, a minimum of 10,000 students have participated in the Squirrel-Net CURE modules. Although many of these students may not choose to pursue careers in STEM, they will be entering society with a better understanding of how scientific research is conducted. In particular, integrating research into a classroom experience (i.e., through a CURE) increases the number of students exposed to and participating in authentic research experiences, and in turn broadens impacts on society outside of academia, compared to more selective, traditional, mentored research experiences. In addition, because our CUREs are being used in non-majors courses, community colleges, and non-profit research organizations, this project has provided widespread opportunities for improving science literacy and workforce readiness beyond STEM majors. Finally, our project has brought together undergraduate students and researchers in a research community, with the development of discussion forums, blogs, and interactions via our social media.      Last Modified: 09/30/2024       Submitted by: JohannaVarner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
