<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[AGEP Research Universities Alliance Model: Advancing Minority Math, Physical Science, Environmental Science, and Engineering PhD Candidates and Postdoctoral Scholars to Faculty]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98337.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98337</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keri Ann Sather-Wagstaff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ksatherw@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922534</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative research project brings together nine very high research (R1) universities with the goal of developing, implementing, self-studying, externally evaluating, and disseminating an AGEP Alliance Model about faculty career pathways that increases the number of historically underrepresented minority (URM) Mathematical, Physical Science, Environmental Science, and Engineering (MPESE) faculty.  The partnership involves the University of California Berkeley (Berkeley), the University of California Los Angeles (UCLA), Stanford University (Stanford), the California Institute of Technology (Caltech), the University of Washington, the University of Texas at Austin, the University of Michigan, Harvard University and the Georgia Institute of Technology.  The Alliance team is expanding and improving activities that have previously been piloted by a Berkeley, UCLA, Stanford and Caltech partnership; and the nine-institution team will study, operationalize, adapt and implement the activities across all collaborating universities.  The project employs multiple participant-focused interventions to facilitate the advancement of URM doctoral candidates, postdoctoral scholars and early-career faculty in MPESE disciplines: A doctoral candidate and postdoctoral scholar research exchange across partnering institutions; an on-line portal to facilitate placement and hiring management of postdoctoral scholars; a faculty advancement initiative for postdoctoral scholars transitioning into early-career faculty positions; and a suite of academic community-building activities to enhance faculty career pathways, such as targeted professional development, cohort building and network development.  The primary outcomes of this AGEP Alliance Model project are increased rates of doctoral candidates transitioning into postdoctoral scholar positions and postdoctoral scholars transitioning into early-career faculty employment, as well as the scaling of the research exchange and postdoctoral on-line portal beyond the nine partnering institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the nation addresses a STEM achievement gap between URM and non-URM undergraduate and graduate students, our universities and colleges struggle to recruit, retain and promote URM STEM faculty who serve as role models and academic leaders for URM students to learn from, work with and emulate. Recent NSF reports indicate that URM STEM associate and full professors occupy only 8% of these senior faculty positions at all 4-year colleges and universities, and only about 6% of these positions at the nation's most research-intensive institutions. This AGEP Alliance Model has the potential to improve the success of URM doctoral candidates and postdoctoral scholars transitioning into early-career MPESE faculty positions.  Advancing the careers of URM faculty ultimately leads to improved academic mentorship for URM undergraduate and graduate students, and postdoctoral scholars, in STEM disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015214</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Baker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew H Baker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbaker@math.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000235916</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/19/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terri</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terri T Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[terri.lee@gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000257501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/13/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terri</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terri T Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[terri.lee@gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000257501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/13/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Felicia</FirstName>
<LastName>Benton-Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Felicia J Benton-Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[felicia.johnson@coe.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000074184</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/13/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303186395</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[926 DALNEY ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151500</Code>
<Text>AGEP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~32839</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~38039</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~27388</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~71</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Research University Alliance (RUA) is a partnership involving nine research universities: University of California Berkeley, University of California Los Angeles, Stanford University, California Institute of Technology, University of Washington, University of Texas at Austin, University of Michigan, Harvard University and Georgia Institute of Technology. The goals of RUA were the development, implementation, and dissemination of an Alliance for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP) model for faculty career pathways that increases the number of historically underrepresented minority (URM) Mathematical, Physical Science, Environmental Science, and Engineering (MPESE) faculty. RUA employed multiple participant-focused interventions, with self-study and external evaluation, to facilitate the advancement of URM doctoral candidates and postdoctoral fellows in MPESE disciplines: a doctoral candidate and postdoc research exchange across partnering institutions; an online portal to facilitate placement and hiring of postdocs; a faculty advancement initiative for postdocs transitioning into early-career faculty positions; and a suite of academic community-building activities to enhance faculty career pathways, such as targeted professional development, cohort building and network development. The primary objectives of this AGEP Alliance Model project were increased rates of doctoral candidates transitioning into postdoc positions and postdocs transitioning into early-career faculty employment, as well as the scaling of the research exchange and postdoctoral online portal. The objectives of the scholarly research were to identify barriers to success among URM graduate students and postdocs; use evidence-based research to explore institutional strategies to overcome barriers; and apply research to practice to advance equitable outcomes in STEM higher education.<br /> <br /> The following publications, presentations and preprints have been disseminated as a result of this award:<br /> <br /> Fleming, G. C., Hunt, G., Watson, D., Mastronardi, M., You, S., Contreras, L., Borrego, M., Smith, M. J. T. (2023). A new hybrid model for faculty hiring workshops. Journal of STEM Education: Innovations and Research, 24(1).&nbsp;<a href="https://jstem.org/jstem/index.php/JSTEM/article/view/2601" target="_blank">https://jstem.org/jstem/index.php/JSTEM/article/view/2601</a><br /> <br /> Heirwegh, M., Rees, D.C., &amp; Malcom-Piqueux, L. (2024). Postdoctoral scholar recruitment and hiring practices in STEM: A pilot study. bioRxiv.&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.02.12.580018" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.02.12.580018</a><br /> <br /> Mendoza-Denton, R., Patt, C., &amp; Carter-Sowell, A. R. (2023). Editorial: Diversifying the STEM fields: From individual to structural approaches. Frontiers in Psychology, 13.&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.1113227" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.1113227</a><br /> <br /> Mendoza-Denton, R., &amp; Wu, J. (2024). Ambiguity and stigma: An opportunity for intervention. In S. Hinshaw (Chair), Overcoming stigma: Diverse populations, diverse methods, diverse outcomes. Invited symposium, American Psychological Society, San Francisco, CA.<br /> <br /> Patt, C. (2023). Presentation on the Research Exchange. University Partnerships for Faculty Diversity Meeting, Washington, DC.<br /> <br /> Patt, C., Eppig, A., &amp; Richards, M. A. (2022). Postdocs as key to faculty diversity: A structured and collaborative approach for research universities. Frontiers in Psychology, 12.&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.759263" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.759263</a><br /> <br /> Patt, C., Rees, D., &amp; Cresiski, R. (2021). Intentionality, inclusivity, and intersectionality: Advancing equity in STEM through social justice framework [Conference presentation]. NSF INCLUDES Conference, Virtual.<br /> <br /> Patt, C. (2022). Postdoctoral stepping stone [Conference presentation]. Native FEWS Alliance Annual Meeting, Berkeley, CA.<br /> <br /> Patt, C. (2021). [Video presentation]. Group on Research, Education, and Training (GREAT) Virtual Conference.<br /> <br /> Smith, M. J. T. (2023). Influence of faculty hiring workshops on DEI [Panel presentation]. Beyond Broadening Participation: Research to Progress to Impact Workshop, National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, Washington, DC, United States.<br /> <br /> Smith, M. J. T., Hunt, G., Watson, D., &amp; Contreras, L. (2022, November). Next generation model for educating faculty search committees [Oral presentation]. 2022 AGEP National Research Conference, Corpus Christi, TX.<br /> <br /> Smith, M. J. T., Hackert, M., &amp; Achilike, P. (2022, November). Building a culture that promotes diversity hiring [Poster presentation]. 2022 AGEP National Research Conference, Corpus Christi, TX.<br /> <br /> Wu, J., Patt, C., &amp; Mendoza-Denton, R. (2023). Advancing equitable outcomes in STEM doctoral education: The effect of departmental advising and guidance. Paper presented at the 2023 American Educational Research Association Annual Meeting, Chicago, IL.&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.3102/2008839" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.3102/2008839</a>.<br /> <br /> Wu, J., Patt, C., &amp; Mendoza-Denton, R. (2023). A path analysis of program clarity and graduate student outcomes: The effect of race. Paper presented at the Association for the Study of Higher Education&rsquo;s 2023 General Conference, Minneapolis, MN.<br /> <br /> Wu, J., Patt, C., &amp; Mendoza-Denton, R. (2024). Reducing discrimination and increasing belonging in graduate education through structure. Paper presented at the 2024 American Educational Research Association Annual Meeting, Philadelphia, PA.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/29/2024<br> Modified by: Terri&nbsp;T&nbsp;Lee</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Research University Alliance (RUA) is a partnership involving nine research universities: University of California Berkeley, University of California Los Angeles, Stanford University, California Institute of Technology, University of Washington, University of Texas at Austin, University of Michigan, Harvard University and Georgia Institute of Technology. The goals of RUA were the development, implementation, and dissemination of an Alliance for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP) model for faculty career pathways that increases the number of historically underrepresented minority (URM) Mathematical, Physical Science, Environmental Science, and Engineering (MPESE) faculty. RUA employed multiple participant-focused interventions, with self-study and external evaluation, to facilitate the advancement of URM doctoral candidates and postdoctoral fellows in MPESE disciplines: a doctoral candidate and postdoc research exchange across partnering institutions; an online portal to facilitate placement and hiring of postdocs; a faculty advancement initiative for postdocs transitioning into early-career faculty positions; and a suite of academic community-building activities to enhance faculty career pathways, such as targeted professional development, cohort building and network development. The primary objectives of this AGEP Alliance Model project were increased rates of doctoral candidates transitioning into postdoc positions and postdocs transitioning into early-career faculty employment, as well as the scaling of the research exchange and postdoctoral online portal. The objectives of the scholarly research were to identify barriers to success among URM graduate students and postdocs; use evidence-based research to explore institutional strategies to overcome barriers; and apply research to practice to advance equitable outcomes in STEM higher education.    The following publications, presentations and preprints have been disseminated as a result of this award:    Fleming, G. C., Hunt, G., Watson, D., Mastronardi, M., You, S., Contreras, L., Borrego, M., Smith, M. J. T. (2023). A new hybrid model for faculty hiring workshops. Journal of STEM Education: Innovations and Research, 24(1).https://jstem.org/jstem/index.php/JSTEM/article/view/2601    Heirwegh, M., Rees, D.C., & Malcom-Piqueux, L. (2024). Postdoctoral scholar recruitment and hiring practices in STEM: A pilot study. bioRxiv.https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.02.12.580018    Mendoza-Denton, R., Patt, C., & Carter-Sowell, A. R. (2023). Editorial: Diversifying the STEM fields: From individual to structural approaches. Frontiers in Psychology, 13.https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.1113227    Mendoza-Denton, R., & Wu, J. (2024). Ambiguity and stigma: An opportunity for intervention. In S. Hinshaw (Chair), Overcoming stigma: Diverse populations, diverse methods, diverse outcomes. Invited symposium, American Psychological Society, San Francisco, CA.    Patt, C. (2023). Presentation on the Research Exchange. University Partnerships for Faculty Diversity Meeting, Washington, DC.    Patt, C., Eppig, A., & Richards, M. A. (2022). Postdocs as key to faculty diversity: A structured and collaborative approach for research universities. Frontiers in Psychology, 12.https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.759263    Patt, C., Rees, D., & Cresiski, R. (2021). Intentionality, inclusivity, and intersectionality: Advancing equity in STEM through social justice framework [Conference presentation]. NSF INCLUDES Conference, Virtual.    Patt, C. (2022). Postdoctoral stepping stone [Conference presentation]. Native FEWS Alliance Annual Meeting, Berkeley, CA.    Patt, C. (2021). [Video presentation]. Group on Research, Education, and Training (GREAT) Virtual Conference.    Smith, M. J. T. (2023). Influence of faculty hiring workshops on DEI [Panel presentation]. Beyond Broadening Participation: Research to Progress to Impact Workshop, National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, Washington, DC, United States.    Smith, M. J. T., Hunt, G., Watson, D., & Contreras, L. (2022, November). Next generation model for educating faculty search committees [Oral presentation]. 2022 AGEP National Research Conference, Corpus Christi, TX.    Smith, M. J. T., Hackert, M., & Achilike, P. (2022, November). Building a culture that promotes diversity hiring [Poster presentation]. 2022 AGEP National Research Conference, Corpus Christi, TX.    Wu, J., Patt, C., & Mendoza-Denton, R. (2023). Advancing equitable outcomes in STEM doctoral education: The effect of departmental advising and guidance. Paper presented at the 2023 American Educational Research Association Annual Meeting, Chicago, IL.https://doi.org/10.3102/2008839.    Wu, J., Patt, C., & Mendoza-Denton, R. (2023). A path analysis of program clarity and graduate student outcomes: The effect of race. Paper presented at the Association for the Study of Higher Educations 2023 General Conference, Minneapolis, MN.    Wu, J., Patt, C., & Mendoza-Denton, R. (2024). Reducing discrimination and increasing belonging in graduate education through structure. Paper presented at the 2024 American Educational Research Association Annual Meeting, Philadelphia, PA.           Last Modified: 07/29/2024       Submitted by: TerriTLee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
