<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: High-order Phonon Scattering and Highly Nonequilibrium Carrier Transport in Two-dimensional Electronic and Optoelectronic Materials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>208183.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>208183</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sumanta Acharya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sacharya@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Semiconductor research and development over the past several decades have enabled widespread use of electronic devices in society. However, the semiconductor industry is facing significant challenges, such as the difficulty in dissipating the large amount of heat generated in silicon electronic chips. The challenges have motivated the investigation of emerging two-dimensional (2D) electronic materials because of their superior electronic and thermal properties. One representative 2D material is graphene that is made of a single layer of carbon atoms. However, compared to the abundant knowledge of silicon electronics, there is only limited understanding of heat dissipation in 2D electronic materials. Therefore, the goal of this project is to establish an in-depth understanding of the distinctly different heat generation and dissipation processes in 2D materials and devices. The obtained knowledge will be used to develop open-source simulation tools, enhance online courses and classroom instruction, and develop hands-on outreach activities to improve the recruitment and training of a diverse population of next-generation workforce in thermal engineering.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to understand the unique fundamental mechanisms underlying heat generation and conduction processes in emerging 2D electronic and optoelectronic materials, including graphene and transition metal dichalcogenides (TMD). Specifically, three outstanding questions that are relevant to the performance and thermal reliability of 2D electronic and optoelectronic materials will be addressed: (1) the importance of four-phonon scattering processes in graphene and other 2D materials; (2) the length scales for different phonon polarizations and electronic excitations to establish local thermal equilibrium in 2D semiconductors; and (3) the phonon mode conversion and transmission processes across the dimensionally mismatched interfaces between a 2D layer and its 3D support. The questions will be addressed via first principles and atomistic theoretical calculations that resolve the modal scattering and coupling behaviors of phonons and electrons, in conjunction with thermal transport and inelastic light scattering measurements of graphene and TMD. Improved understanding of the three specific questions helps to build the foundation for modeling and controlling heat dissipation processes in 2D materials and devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015946</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiulin</FirstName>
<LastName>Ruan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiulin Ruan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ruan@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000079093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE # 1100]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072088</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[585 Purdue Mall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>140600</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~208183</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research was to establish a fundamental understanding of open questions that are relevant to the performance and thermal reliability of emerging two-dimensional (2D) electronic and optoelectronic materials. The questions included the assessment of four-phonon scattering processes in graphene and other 2D materials, and the length scales for different phonon polarizations and electronic excitations to establish local thermal equilibrium in 2D semiconductors. These questions have been addressed via first principles and atomistic theoretical calculations in conjunction with thermal transport and inelastic light scattering measurements of graphene and Molybdenum disulfide.</p> <p>We have first investigated four-phonon contribution to the Raman linewidth of monolayer graphene. The Raman peak position and linewidth provide insight into phonon anharmonicity and electron-phonon interactions in materials. For monolayer graphene, prior first-principles calculations had yielded decreasing linewidth with increasing temperature, which was opposite to measurement results. In this project, we have explicitly considered four-phonon anharmonicity, phonon renormalization, and electron-phonon coupling, and find all to be important to successfully explain both the G peak frequency shift and linewidths in our suspended graphene sample over a wide temperature range. Four-phonon scattering contributes a prominent linewidth that increases with temperature. This work resolved the outstanding discrepancy between prior theory and experiments.</p> <p>We have then expanded our calculation to all phonon modes and predicted the thermal conductivity of monolayer graphene. We have considered both four-phonon scattering and phonon renormalization, and found that the intrinsic room temperature thermal conductivity of graphene is 1300 W/m-K, which is surprisingly lower than those of diamond and graphite. This indicates that four-phonon scattering overall contributes 57% to the total thermal resistance and becomes the leading phonon scattering mechanism over three-phonon scattering. This very non-mainstream result has generated considerable interest in the community and inspired experimentalists to pursue validations of the theory.</p> <p>Considering four-phonon scattering prediction is very complicated, we have deployed an open-source code FourPhonon on GitHub. Since its release in 2021, it has already been widely adopted by hundreds of researchers worldwide to advance their own research. Further, since four-phonon scattering is computationally expensive, we have developed a machine learning approach that predicts phonon scattering rates and thermal conductivity with experimental and first principles accuracy. The success was enabled by mitigating computational challenges associated with the high skewness of phonon scattering rates and their complex contributions to the total thermal resistance. The approach offered up to two orders of magnitude acceleration compared to first principles calculations and would enable large-scale thermal transport informatics.</p> <p>To explore nonequilibrium resulted from electron-phonon, we have developed a semiconductor-specific multitemperature model by including relevant physical processes including electron-hole pair generation, diffusion, and recombination, and show that a conventional phonon branch-level model does not yield observable non-equilibrium in laser-irradiated molybdenum disulfide. In contrast, appreciable non-equilibrium is predicted between zone-center optical phonons and the other modes. The momentum-based non-equilibrium ratio is found to increase with decreasing laser spot size and interaction with a substrate. Our prediction results have been confirmed by experimental measurements of Prof. Li Shi, our collaborator on this collaborative proposal. This finding is relevant to the understanding of the energy relaxation process in two-dimensional optoelectronic devices and Raman measurements of thermal transport.</p> <p>Overall, our work has advanced the thermal transport theory of 2D materials from the conventional three-phonon scattering to four-phonon scattering. In addition, the predicted nonequilibrium processes are expected to provide essential information for both 2D device operations and thermal transport measurements of 2D materials. This project will impact the development of 2D electronics and optoelectronics and has generated state-of-the-art open-source code that has been widely used by the research community. Moreover, the PI has incorporated the knowledge gained in this project in his graduate level course &ldquo;ME 697: Computational Methods for Nanoscale Energy Transport&rdquo;, including the surprising thermal conductivity in graphene due to four-phonon scattering, machine learning-accelerated prediction of phonon scattering and thermal conductivity, and thermal nonequilibrium phenomena. His course notes and videos have been deployed on nanoHUB and attracted numerous users. Both graduate and undergraduate students have been trained in this research.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 05/20/2024<br> Modified by: Xiulin&nbsp;Ruan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186557670_image_4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186557670_image_4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Energy carrier coupling and nonequilibrium in laser-irradiated MoS2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186557670_image_4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Energy carrier coupling and nonequilibrium in laser-irradiated MoS2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Schematic showing the electron (hole)-phonon scattering and phonon-phonon scattering process after laser irradiation. (b) The nonequilibrium occurs between zone-center optical phonons and other phonons, rather than between optical branches and other branches.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zherui Han and Xiulin Ruan (Purdue University)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiulin&nbsp;Ruan <div class="imageTitle">Energy carrier coupling and nonequilibrium in laser-irradiated MoS2</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186304274_image_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186304274_image_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Raman linewidth of graphene"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186304274_image_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Raman linewidth of graphene"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Three-phonon and four-phonon contributions to Raman linewidth in graphene, with and without phonon renormalization. (b) It shows that only after including both four-phonon scattering and phonon renormalization, the experimental Raman linewidth can be successfully explained.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zherui Han and Xiulin Ruan (Purdue University)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiulin&nbsp;Ruan <div class="imageTitle">Raman linewidth of graphene</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186141412_image_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186141412_image_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Four-phonon scattering and thermal conductivity in graphene"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186141412_image_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Four-phonon scattering and thermal conductivity in graphene"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Our prediction shows that after including four-phonon scattering, the thermal conductivity of graphene is considerably lower than those of diamond and graphite. This is in contrast to mainstream perception.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zherui Han and Xiulin Ruan (Purdue University)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiulin&nbsp;Ruan <div class="imageTitle">Four-phonon scattering and thermal conductivity in graphene</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716185879497_image_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716185879497_image_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FourPhonon open-source code"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716185879497_image_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FourPhonon open-source code"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The FourPhonon open-source code has been deployed on GitGub and attracted use by hundreds of researchers worldwide. The associated tutorial paper has been named a Highly Cited Paper and Hor Paper by Clarivate Web of Science.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zherui Han and Xiulin Ruan (Purdue University)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiulin&nbsp;Ruan <div class="imageTitle">FourPhonon open-source code</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186685696_image_5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186685696_image_5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Machine learning-accelerated prediction"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2015946/2015946_10684333_1716186685696_image_5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Machine learning-accelerated prediction"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) The accumulated thermal conductivity with respect to phonon frequency calculated by analytical and surrogate models, respectively. (b) The surrogate model is shown to accelerate the calculation by up to two orders of magnitude.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ziqi Guo and Xiulin Ruan (Purdue University)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiulin&nbsp;Ruan <div class="imageTitle">Machine learning-accelerated prediction</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The goal of this research was to establish a fundamental understanding of open questions that are relevant to the performance and thermal reliability of emerging two-dimensional (2D) electronic and optoelectronic materials. The questions included the assessment of four-phonon scattering processes in graphene and other 2D materials, and the length scales for different phonon polarizations and electronic excitations to establish local thermal equilibrium in 2D semiconductors. These questions have been addressed via first principles and atomistic theoretical calculations in conjunction with thermal transport and inelastic light scattering measurements of graphene and Molybdenum disulfide.   We have first investigated four-phonon contribution to the Raman linewidth of monolayer graphene. The Raman peak position and linewidth provide insight into phonon anharmonicity and electron-phonon interactions in materials. For monolayer graphene, prior first-principles calculations had yielded decreasing linewidth with increasing temperature, which was opposite to measurement results. In this project, we have explicitly considered four-phonon anharmonicity, phonon renormalization, and electron-phonon coupling, and find all to be important to successfully explain both the G peak frequency shift and linewidths in our suspended graphene sample over a wide temperature range. Four-phonon scattering contributes a prominent linewidth that increases with temperature. This work resolved the outstanding discrepancy between prior theory and experiments.   We have then expanded our calculation to all phonon modes and predicted the thermal conductivity of monolayer graphene. We have considered both four-phonon scattering and phonon renormalization, and found that the intrinsic room temperature thermal conductivity of graphene is 1300 W/m-K, which is surprisingly lower than those of diamond and graphite. This indicates that four-phonon scattering overall contributes 57% to the total thermal resistance and becomes the leading phonon scattering mechanism over three-phonon scattering. This very non-mainstream result has generated considerable interest in the community and inspired experimentalists to pursue validations of the theory.   Considering four-phonon scattering prediction is very complicated, we have deployed an open-source code FourPhonon on GitHub. Since its release in 2021, it has already been widely adopted by hundreds of researchers worldwide to advance their own research. Further, since four-phonon scattering is computationally expensive, we have developed a machine learning approach that predicts phonon scattering rates and thermal conductivity with experimental and first principles accuracy. The success was enabled by mitigating computational challenges associated with the high skewness of phonon scattering rates and their complex contributions to the total thermal resistance. The approach offered up to two orders of magnitude acceleration compared to first principles calculations and would enable large-scale thermal transport informatics.   To explore nonequilibrium resulted from electron-phonon, we have developed a semiconductor-specific multitemperature model by including relevant physical processes including electron-hole pair generation, diffusion, and recombination, and show that a conventional phonon branch-level model does not yield observable non-equilibrium in laser-irradiated molybdenum disulfide. In contrast, appreciable non-equilibrium is predicted between zone-center optical phonons and the other modes. The momentum-based non-equilibrium ratio is found to increase with decreasing laser spot size and interaction with a substrate. Our prediction results have been confirmed by experimental measurements of Prof. Li Shi, our collaborator on this collaborative proposal. This finding is relevant to the understanding of the energy relaxation process in two-dimensional optoelectronic devices and Raman measurements of thermal transport.   Overall, our work has advanced the thermal transport theory of 2D materials from the conventional three-phonon scattering to four-phonon scattering. In addition, the predicted nonequilibrium processes are expected to provide essential information for both 2D device operations and thermal transport measurements of 2D materials. This project will impact the development of 2D electronics and optoelectronics and has generated state-of-the-art open-source code that has been widely used by the research community. Moreover, the PI has incorporated the knowledge gained in this project in his graduate level course ME 697: Computational Methods for Nanoscale Energy Transport, including the surprising thermal conductivity in graphene due to four-phonon scattering, machine learning-accelerated prediction of phonon scattering and thermal conductivity, and thermal nonequilibrium phenomena. His course notes and videos have been deployed on nanoHUB and attracted numerous users. Both graduate and undergraduate students have been trained in this research.     Last Modified: 05/20/2024       Submitted by: XiulinRuan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
