<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: A Workshop for Evaluating the Value and Scope of a Biological Repository of Antarctic Specimens]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>57293.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>57293</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Gast</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rgast@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This workshop will bring together Antarctic marine freshwater and terrestrial biologists, students, and experts in specimen curation to assess the value of, need for, and scope of a biological repository of Antarctic specimens, including tissue samples. Currently, some US collected Antarctic specimen collections are housed in various museums, repositories, and labs. These collections are not easily discoverable on the internet, and how well they represent the biodiversity of Antarctica is largely unknown. The workshop coordinators will advertise the conference broadly and recruit underrepresented groups to participate. Participants will assess current repositories and determine how to make Antarctica biological samples more accessible in a unified location (or through better coordination). This effort will benefit the broader community of biologists working with Antarctic organisms by providing opportunities to conduct Antarctic science by investigators and their students that might otherwise not be possible due to the logistical and budget challenges for deployments. Following workshop activities, a final report will be published on the outcomes of the efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Brien</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristin M O'Brien</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kmobrien@alaska.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000149777</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>FAIRBANKS</CityName>
<ZipCode>997750001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 N TANANA LOOP]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FDLEQSJ8FF63</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALASKA FAIRBANKS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>205600001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>511100</Code>
<Text>ANT Organisms &amp; Ecosystems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>540700</Code>
<Text>Polar Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~57293</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>In the 21<sup>st</sup>&nbsp;century, there has been an explosion in the growth of electronic data repositories to facilitate data sharing and transparency. Somewhat less common are biological and/or specimen repositories, which can maximize resources and expand research opportunities. Even more important in today&rsquo;s rapidly changing world, biological repositories enable longitudinal studies of global change and safeguard specimens for future studies as technologies develop and ignite new questions.&nbsp;</p> <p>Currently, Antarctic specimen collections are housed across the US in museums and repositories, yet these collections are not easily discoverable on the internet, and how well they represent the biodiversity of Antarctica is largely unknown. A large number of frozen and preserved specimens are scattered across university laboratories and often lack the ancillary data that would make them useful and accessible to a broader scientific community. As climate change continues to erode the biodiversity of Antarctica, it becomes imperative to assess the current state of Antarctic collections and identify gaps in collections before the opportunity to preserve a record of Antarctic biodiversity is lost.</p> <p>The goal of this project was to convene a workshop, bringing together Antarctic biologists from diverse disciplines, and experts in specimen curation, in order to&nbsp;(1) assess the current state of Antarctic collections, (2) evaluate strategies for maximizing visibility and accessibility of specimens, and (3) determine how a biological repository (or multiple biorepositories) would fill gaps in collections to expand opportunities for Antarctic research and maximize resources.&nbsp;</p> <p>Antarctic biological scientists, museum curators, and collections managers convened at a virtual, three-day NSF-funded workshop (Feb 2-4, 2022) to identify and define the value in, and scope of, an Antarctic biorepository. Workshop sessions examined domestic and international biological repositories; advantages and disadvantages of one versus multiple repositories; financial management; specimen management; and integration of data via data aggregators. Two breakout sessions based on broad taxonomic affiliations were held to facilitate conversations among collections personnel and principal investigators (PIs) about collection status, taxonomic and biogeographic gaps, storage and metadata needs, education and outreach.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Forty to 50 attendees participated in each workshop session. Values of a biorepository were identified as expanding opportunities for education, outreach and engagement of scientists not currently conducting Antarctic research, especially those from underrepresented groups, maximizing the use of limited and priceless resources, and accelerating scientific progress in the Antarctic, a region that is facing unprecedented changes brought about by anthropogenic influences.&nbsp;</p> <p>Prior to the workshop, a survey was deployed to assess the current status of Antarctic biological collections in the U.S. and attitudes towards the potential development of an Antarctic biorepository. Eighty-seven responses representing 56 institutions were received, including 50 from PIs, 31 from curators or collection managers, and 6 who described themselves as &ldquo;other.&rdquo; Although not all surveys were completed, trends in the data likely reflect the current status of collections, as well as attitudes toward an Antarctic biorepository. Results from the survey identified important collection opportunities, needs and gaps, which were reinforced by participants during the workshop: (1) existing museum Antarctic biological collections are widely accessible and queried through online data aggregators, yet are underutilized by many Antarctic investigators who are largely unaware of the nature, extent, and location of these collections; (2) NSF-funded PIs have extensive Antarctic collections, that for some taxa exceed those of U.S. museum and/or biorepository collections; (3) PI collections are not well cataloged, curated, managed, or accessible to others; (4) PIs are eager to deposit specimens in public biorepositories to increase specimen accessibility and enhance opportunities for Antarctic science; (5) PIs acknowledge that robust metadata for their collections are often lacking; (6) PIs are generally unfamiliar with the process of specimen deposition; and (7) PIs lack the time and resources to deposit specimens.&nbsp;</p> <p>Outcomes from the workshop were summarized in recommendations to NSF and a commentary published in the journal&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em>, co-authored by 23 participants in the workshop.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, 1,342 Antarctic fish tissue samples from 35 species and 9 different tissue types were deposited in the public repository,&nbsp;<em>Ocean Genome Legacy</em>.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Increasing the accessibility of Antarctic specimens would provide opportunities to conduct Antarctic science by investigators and their students that might otherwise not be possible due to the logistical challenges and high cost of conducting research in Antarctica. Increasing the visibility of, and expanding, current collections would markedly grow opportunities for engaging students, thereby increasing the diversity and breadth of perspectives and enhancing capacities for solving problems that challenge science and society.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/29/2024<br> Modified by: Kristin&nbsp;M&nbsp;O'brien</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merit   In the 21stcentury, there has been an explosion in the growth of electronic data repositories to facilitate data sharing and transparency. Somewhat less common are biological and/or specimen repositories, which can maximize resources and expand research opportunities. Even more important in todays rapidly changing world, biological repositories enable longitudinal studies of global change and safeguard specimens for future studies as technologies develop and ignite new questions.   Currently, Antarctic specimen collections are housed across the US in museums and repositories, yet these collections are not easily discoverable on the internet, and how well they represent the biodiversity of Antarctica is largely unknown. A large number of frozen and preserved specimens are scattered across university laboratories and often lack the ancillary data that would make them useful and accessible to a broader scientific community. As climate change continues to erode the biodiversity of Antarctica, it becomes imperative to assess the current state of Antarctic collections and identify gaps in collections before the opportunity to preserve a record of Antarctic biodiversity is lost.   The goal of this project was to convene a workshop, bringing together Antarctic biologists from diverse disciplines, and experts in specimen curation, in order to(1) assess the current state of Antarctic collections, (2) evaluate strategies for maximizing visibility and accessibility of specimens, and (3) determine how a biological repository (or multiple biorepositories) would fill gaps in collections to expand opportunities for Antarctic research and maximize resources.   Antarctic biological scientists, museum curators, and collections managers convened at a virtual, three-day NSF-funded workshop (Feb 2-4, 2022) to identify and define the value in, and scope of, an Antarctic biorepository. Workshop sessions examined domestic and international biological repositories; advantages and disadvantages of one versus multiple repositories; financial management; specimen management; and integration of data via data aggregators. Two breakout sessions based on broad taxonomic affiliations were held to facilitate conversations among collections personnel and principal investigators (PIs) about collection status, taxonomic and biogeographic gaps, storage and metadata needs, education and outreach.   Forty to 50 attendees participated in each workshop session. Values of a biorepository were identified as expanding opportunities for education, outreach and engagement of scientists not currently conducting Antarctic research, especially those from underrepresented groups, maximizing the use of limited and priceless resources, and accelerating scientific progress in the Antarctic, a region that is facing unprecedented changes brought about by anthropogenic influences.   Prior to the workshop, a survey was deployed to assess the current status of Antarctic biological collections in the U.S. and attitudes towards the potential development of an Antarctic biorepository. Eighty-seven responses representing 56 institutions were received, including 50 from PIs, 31 from curators or collection managers, and 6 who described themselves as other. Although not all surveys were completed, trends in the data likely reflect the current status of collections, as well as attitudes toward an Antarctic biorepository. Results from the survey identified important collection opportunities, needs and gaps, which were reinforced by participants during the workshop: (1) existing museum Antarctic biological collections are widely accessible and queried through online data aggregators, yet are underutilized by many Antarctic investigators who are largely unaware of the nature, extent, and location of these collections; (2) NSF-funded PIs have extensive Antarctic collections, that for some taxa exceed those of U.S. museum and/or biorepository collections; (3) PI collections are not well cataloged, curated, managed, or accessible to others; (4) PIs are eager to deposit specimens in public biorepositories to increase specimen accessibility and enhance opportunities for Antarctic science; (5) PIs acknowledge that robust metadata for their collections are often lacking; (6) PIs are generally unfamiliar with the process of specimen deposition; and (7) PIs lack the time and resources to deposit specimens.   Outcomes from the workshop were summarized in recommendations to NSF and a commentary published in the journalProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, co-authored by 23 participants in the workshop.   In addition, 1,342 Antarctic fish tissue samples from 35 species and 9 different tissue types were deposited in the public repository,Ocean Genome Legacy.   Broader Impacts   Increasing the accessibility of Antarctic specimens would provide opportunities to conduct Antarctic science by investigators and their students that might otherwise not be possible due to the logistical challenges and high cost of conducting research in Antarctica. Increasing the visibility of, and expanding, current collections would markedly grow opportunities for engaging students, thereby increasing the diversity and breadth of perspectives and enhancing capacities for solving problems that challenge science and society.        Last Modified: 10/29/2024       Submitted by: KristinMO'brien]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
