<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Fundamental Study of Fatigue Life Enhancement in Hierarchical Carbon-Fiber/Epoxy/Nanoparticle Composites]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>397537.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>397537</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Wells</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awells@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Carbon-fiber reinforced composites, with their favorable strength-to-weight and stiffness-to-weight ratios, are replacing their metal counterparts in a variety of high-performance structural applications. However, the principal limitation of such composite materials is their brittle failure and insufficient fatigue life. A new concept for fatigue-resistant carbon-fiber composites features a modified epoxy resin matrix that is infiltrated with nanoparticle additives. These nanoscale particles will be engineered to interfere with or disrupt crack propagation processes and thereby significantly prolong the fatigue life of the composite material. The ability to combat fatigue is critical for safe and reliable operation as well as reduction in the operational and maintenance costs for structural components. This will be of great benefit to the aerospace, defense, energy and automotive industries which extensively use carbon-fiber reinforced plastics. One of the emerging industries where such new fatigue-resistant materials can have high impact is in wind energy. Wind is one of the fastest growing energy technologies on the globe and enhancing the fatigue properties and the operating life of carbon-fiber composite materials used in wind turbine construction is therefore of great practical relevance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to understand the fundamental mechanisms by which the nanoparticle additives enhance the fatigue life of the composite material and to reveal how these mechanisms are affected by the geometry, interface strength, loading fraction and dispersion of nanoparticles. To accomplish this, investigators will employ an integrated modeling, simulation, manufacturing, characterization and experimental fatigue testing approach to understand and optimize the underlying mechanisms that are responsible for fatigue life improvement. To be consistent with industrial practices, researchers will manufacture pre-pregs in which microfiber plies are pre-impregnated with nanoparticle-laden epoxy resins, or in which  nanoparticles are pre-dispersed on the microfibers which are then impregnated with neat resins. The fundamental knowledge gained from the above tasks will be applied to establish processing-structure-property relationships that will be used to manufacture proof-of-concept carbon fiber-reinforced composites with optimized nanoparticle geometry, loading, dispersion and interface strength. These composites will be tested to quantify and benchmark the fatigue-life improvements that can be achieved relative to the traditional composites used by industry. This project will lead to an in-depth understanding of the role of the nanoparticle geometry, surface chemistry, loading fraction and dispersion in fatigue life improvements for the next generation of carbon-fiber reinforced composites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015750</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikhil</FirstName>
<LastName>Koratkar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikhil Koratkar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[koratn@rpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000229996</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yunfeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Shi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yunfeng Shi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shiy2@rpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000513283</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Johnson</FirstName>
<LastName>Samuel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Johnson Samuel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[samuej2@rpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000587288</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>TROY</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803590</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U5WBFKEBLMX3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y00</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>163000</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>085E</Code>
<Text>POLYMER &amp; COMPOSITES PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~397537</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to study the fundamental mechanisms by which nanoparticle additives can toughen thermosetting epoxies and to deploy this toughened epoxy as the matrix to manufacture carbon-fiber reinforced polymer composites with superior fatigue life. In this context, three types of nano-carbon additives were considered: (1) Zero-dimensional (i.e. fullerenes), (2) One-dimensional (i.e. carbon nanotubes) and (3) Two-dimensional (i.e. graphene). Epoxy nanocomposites were designed, fabricated and tested to determine the effect of type and load fraction of nano-carbon additive on the fracture toughness of the nanocomposite epoxy. Based on these results, our conclusion was that two-dimensional graphene additives outperformed both zero-dimensional fullerene and one-dimensional carbon nanotubes, since they were able to achieve substantial increase in fracture toughness at the lowest nano-particle loading fraction. Therefore graphene additives represent the best option among the available suite of nano-carbon materials. Subsequently, we have extended this work to non-carbon based additives such as nano-silica. Our results indicate that nano-silica can be very easily dispersed in the epoxy and hence outperforms graphene, from a performance as well as cost and scalability perspective. We utilized this nanocomposite epoxy formulation with nano-silica additives to manufacture and build carbon-fiber reinforced polymer composites. These composites were tested to quantify their fundamental fracture and fatigue properties: upto 7-fold increase in high cycle fatigue life was achieved with the incorporation of nano-silica additives, which bodes well for practical applications. To develop an in-depth fundamental understanding of the toughening effect induced by the nano-additives, we developed a highly efficient two body reactive potential that can simulate bond breaking/formation in a large polymer system with comparatively small amount of computing resources. Spurious system size and strain rate effects have been eliminated in our simulations to obtain a "brittle" fracture, consistent with experimental observations. Our computational results indicate that nano-additives that provide "semi-strong interfaces" with the epoxy matrix give the best results in terms of developing high-performing polymer nanocomposites that are concurrently stiff, strong as well as tough. These results underscore the importance of carefully balancing the interfacial strength to simultaneously enhance stiffness, strength, toughness, and durability in nanocomposites, providing crucial insights for designing high-performance materials for structural applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project has resulted in the development and manufacturing of fatigue-resistant carbon-fiber composites featuring a modified epoxy resin matrix that is infiltrated with nanoparticle additives. These nanoscale particles have been engineered to interfere or disrupt crack propagation processes and thereby significantly prolong the fatigue life of the composite material. The ability to combat fatigue is critical for safe and reliable operation as well as reduction in the operational and maintenance costs for structural components. This will be of great benefit to the aerospace, defense, energy and automotive industries which extensively use carbon-fiber reinforced plastics. One of the emerging industries where such new fatigue resistant materials can have high impact is in wind energy. Wind is one of the fastest growing energy technologies on the globe and enhancing the fatigue properties and the operating life of carbon-fiber composite materials used in wind turbine construction is therefore of great practical relevance.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 08/09/2024<br> Modified by: Nikhil&nbsp;Koratkar</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The goal of this project was to study the fundamental mechanisms by which nanoparticle additives can toughen thermosetting epoxies and to deploy this toughened epoxy as the matrix to manufacture carbon-fiber reinforced polymer composites with superior fatigue life. In this context, three types of nano-carbon additives were considered: (1) Zero-dimensional (i.e. fullerenes), (2) One-dimensional (i.e. carbon nanotubes) and (3) Two-dimensional (i.e. graphene). Epoxy nanocomposites were designed, fabricated and tested to determine the effect of type and load fraction of nano-carbon additive on the fracture toughness of the nanocomposite epoxy. Based on these results, our conclusion was that two-dimensional graphene additives outperformed both zero-dimensional fullerene and one-dimensional carbon nanotubes, since they were able to achieve substantial increase in fracture toughness at the lowest nano-particle loading fraction. Therefore graphene additives represent the best option among the available suite of nano-carbon materials. Subsequently, we have extended this work to non-carbon based additives such as nano-silica. Our results indicate that nano-silica can be very easily dispersed in the epoxy and hence outperforms graphene, from a performance as well as cost and scalability perspective. We utilized this nanocomposite epoxy formulation with nano-silica additives to manufacture and build carbon-fiber reinforced polymer composites. These composites were tested to quantify their fundamental fracture and fatigue properties: upto 7-fold increase in high cycle fatigue life was achieved with the incorporation of nano-silica additives, which bodes well for practical applications. To develop an in-depth fundamental understanding of the toughening effect induced by the nano-additives, we developed a highly efficient two body reactive potential that can simulate bond breaking/formation in a large polymer system with comparatively small amount of computing resources. Spurious system size and strain rate effects have been eliminated in our simulations to obtain a "brittle" fracture, consistent with experimental observations. Our computational results indicate that nano-additives that provide "semi-strong interfaces" with the epoxy matrix give the best results in terms of developing high-performing polymer nanocomposites that are concurrently stiff, strong as well as tough. These results underscore the importance of carefully balancing the interfacial strength to simultaneously enhance stiffness, strength, toughness, and durability in nanocomposites, providing crucial insights for designing high-performance materials for structural applications.      This project has resulted in the development and manufacturing of fatigue-resistant carbon-fiber composites featuring a modified epoxy resin matrix that is infiltrated with nanoparticle additives. These nanoscale particles have been engineered to interfere or disrupt crack propagation processes and thereby significantly prolong the fatigue life of the composite material. The ability to combat fatigue is critical for safe and reliable operation as well as reduction in the operational and maintenance costs for structural components. This will be of great benefit to the aerospace, defense, energy and automotive industries which extensively use carbon-fiber reinforced plastics. One of the emerging industries where such new fatigue resistant materials can have high impact is in wind energy. Wind is one of the fastest growing energy technologies on the globe and enhancing the fatigue properties and the operating life of carbon-fiber composite materials used in wind turbine construction is therefore of great practical relevance.        Last Modified: 08/09/2024       Submitted by: NikhilKoratkar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
