<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Systemic Signailng Networks in Arabidopsis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>469112.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>469112</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Cyr</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rcyr@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928440</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Stresses such as herbivore or pathogen attack can severely limit plant growth and development, for example, by reducing crop production and impacting food security around the World. Plants possess natural sensory systems that allow them to detect these stresses and then mount defenses against them. Defining how these response systems operate is therefore important in both understanding how plants survive and thrive in the natural world and how to effectively capitalize on these innate responses to improve the resilience of agriculture. Recent research has made key advances in characterizing these signaling systems within the plant, revealing that plants deploy an internal biochemical communication system that broadcasts stress information from its site of perception to the rest of the plant body. This information then triggers the production of defenses such as the accumulation of toxic chemicals, priming even the non-attacked parts of the plant for defense. This communication system operates quickly, spreading information throughout the plant over the course of minutes. Despite such a central role in coordinating each plant’s rapid stress responses, the cellular components that trigger this system and then transmit the stress signal throughout the plant remain poorly defined. This project will focus on characterizing the role of two major cellular messengers, the calcium ion and reactive oxygen species, in propagating these rapid stress signals. The investigation will also explore how amino acids released by the plant may act as initial triggers for this response. This work will train graduate students and postdoctoral fellows to help prepare them for their future careers in research and science. The project will also provide public education on plant stress responses and provide training to students in effective science communication.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent studies have revealed a rapid systemic signaling system in plants mediated through Ca2+- and reactive oxygen species-dependent events. This research program seeks to extend our understanding of these processes to the levels of the channels and tissue architectures that support this signaling network. The Arabidopsis thaliana Glutamate-Like Receptor (GLR) channels and reactive oxygen species-producing NADPH oxidases have been linked to this rapid systemic propagation of Ca2+-based signals. Therefore, this study will focus on defining the role(s) of these proteins in systemic transmission of local wound, pathogen elicitor (flg22) and salt stresses. The specific aims are to: (1) compare the patterns of Ca2+ and ROS signaling that occur during the initiation and propagation of long-distance signals in response to these stimuli and define the spatial and temporal characteristics of the channels and ROS-related enzymes supporting these activities; and (2) explore how glutamate and other amino acid signals are involved in triggering these long-distance signals. These goals will be accomplished using a combination of bioreporter imaging and mutant and molecular analyses. This study will reveal new insight into the molecular machinery underlying rapid plant systemic signaling. The project will help define the spatial and temporal changes in calcium and reactive oxygen species that relay information about stresses throughout the plant. The research will also help define whether information about each stress is likely encoded in specific signaling dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016177</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Simon</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilroy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Simon Gilroy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Sgilroy@wisc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000489493</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 N PARK ST STE 6301]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LCLSJAGTNZQ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin, Department of Botany]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537061313</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Birge Hall, 430 Lincoln Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>111400</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~469112</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Plants are literally rooted to the spot and so must have mechanisms to sense and then react to their ever-changing environment. They must continuously take in information on events as varied as pathogen attack or wounding, to changes in soil nutrient and water availability. Plants then use this information to trigger responses that can range from rapid induction of defense chemicals to long-term shifts in growth and development. These stimuli often arrive in a highly localized manner, yet responses occur throughout the plant body. For example, as an insect chews on a leaf, the undamaged parts of the plant rapidly and preemptively accumulate defense chemicals. This research program has sought to define the cellular signals that the plant uses to transmit these plant-wide signals.&nbsp;</p> <p>Changes in the level of calcium is used as a cellular regulator by many organisms. Further, these calcium signals can be visualized in real time in plants by genetically engineering them to produce a fluorescent Ca2+-responsive protein named GCaMP. As calcium signals are generated, the green fluorescence from that part of the plant increases. As the signal dissipates, the fluorescence drops. Using this approach wounding of one leaf has been shown to trigger rapid transmission of a wave of calcium response that propagates to unwounded leaves at speeds of up to 1 cm/second. Mapping the patterns of this calcium response in this research project has shown that leaves transmit these kinds of signals to other leaves but not to the root system, whereas the damaged root system transmits both to other roots and the aerial parts of the plant. The conduit for the propagation of these signals appears to be the plant vascular system, i.e., the internal tissues that move water through the plant.</p> <p>Analysis of the cellular machinery underlying this wound response system has shown two families of membrane channels are needed to propagate the calcium signal: (1) members of the glutamate receptor-like channel family and, (2) the cyclic nucleotide gated channel family.</p> <p>In addition to wounding, a range of other stimuli were shown to trigger Ca2+ changes including touch, flooding and cold temperatures. Local cold stimulation to a leaf led to rapid, plant-wide Ca2+ changes with a similar time frame as wounding but with distinct spatial patterns. These changes were not reliant upon the glutamate receptor-like channels needed for the wounding response. Blocking these calcium changes blocked cold adaptation in these plants. Taken together these observations suggest the propagating calcium signals are important for the plant-wide cold responses but they are generated by a mechanism distinct from the wound-triggered system.&nbsp;</p> <p>Flooding of the roots of a plant triggered a whole plant response that was similarly linked to Ca2+ signaling. In this case, the changes were dependent on a calcium transporter called CAX2 that is found on internal membranes of the cell. Mutating this transporter such that it was non-functional led to plants that were much more tolerant of waterlogging stress, remaining green and showing no induction of genes usually related to flooding stress even after 4 weeks of the roots constantly being underwater. This effect was likely due to the normal role of CAX2 in dampening calcium changes, with its mutant showing elevated calcium levels and signals that preadapted the plants to waterlogging stress prior to them being flooded.</p> <p>Overall, these findings have helped reveal an extensive, rapid, calcium-based signaling system that integrates the activities of an individual plant to local stresses. The plant-wide transmission of response to these stimuli occurs within seconds but each stimulus triggers a unique pattern of calcium change that may be important for carrying specific information about the triggering stimulus. Identification of specific molecular players in these processes such as the glutamate receptor-like channels, the cyclic nucleotide-gated channels, and transporters like CAX2 now provide molecular landmarks to help further dissect the signaling pathways responsible for these changes. These genes also provide targets for molecular manipulation to help develop stress resilient plants through approaches such as genetic engineering or targeted breeding.</p> <p>This work has supported multiple outreach events each year that the project has been running at venues such as the University of Wisconsin-Madison&rsquo;s Science Expo. A major element of these efforts has been presenting a plant biology &ldquo;exploration station&rsquo; that has given the general public a &lsquo;hands-on&rsquo; plant physiology and cell biology experience.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/12/2024<br> Modified by: Simon&nbsp;Gilroy</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Plants are literally rooted to the spot and so must have mechanisms to sense and then react to their ever-changing environment. They must continuously take in information on events as varied as pathogen attack or wounding, to changes in soil nutrient and water availability. Plants then use this information to trigger responses that can range from rapid induction of defense chemicals to long-term shifts in growth and development. These stimuli often arrive in a highly localized manner, yet responses occur throughout the plant body. For example, as an insect chews on a leaf, the undamaged parts of the plant rapidly and preemptively accumulate defense chemicals. This research program has sought to define the cellular signals that the plant uses to transmit these plant-wide signals.   Changes in the level of calcium is used as a cellular regulator by many organisms. Further, these calcium signals can be visualized in real time in plants by genetically engineering them to produce a fluorescent Ca2+-responsive protein named GCaMP. As calcium signals are generated, the green fluorescence from that part of the plant increases. As the signal dissipates, the fluorescence drops. Using this approach wounding of one leaf has been shown to trigger rapid transmission of a wave of calcium response that propagates to unwounded leaves at speeds of up to 1 cm/second. Mapping the patterns of this calcium response in this research project has shown that leaves transmit these kinds of signals to other leaves but not to the root system, whereas the damaged root system transmits both to other roots and the aerial parts of the plant. The conduit for the propagation of these signals appears to be the plant vascular system, i.e., the internal tissues that move water through the plant.   Analysis of the cellular machinery underlying this wound response system has shown two families of membrane channels are needed to propagate the calcium signal: (1) members of the glutamate receptor-like channel family and, (2) the cyclic nucleotide gated channel family.   In addition to wounding, a range of other stimuli were shown to trigger Ca2+ changes including touch, flooding and cold temperatures. Local cold stimulation to a leaf led to rapid, plant-wide Ca2+ changes with a similar time frame as wounding but with distinct spatial patterns. These changes were not reliant upon the glutamate receptor-like channels needed for the wounding response. Blocking these calcium changes blocked cold adaptation in these plants. Taken together these observations suggest the propagating calcium signals are important for the plant-wide cold responses but they are generated by a mechanism distinct from the wound-triggered system.   Flooding of the roots of a plant triggered a whole plant response that was similarly linked to Ca2+ signaling. In this case, the changes were dependent on a calcium transporter called CAX2 that is found on internal membranes of the cell. Mutating this transporter such that it was non-functional led to plants that were much more tolerant of waterlogging stress, remaining green and showing no induction of genes usually related to flooding stress even after 4 weeks of the roots constantly being underwater. This effect was likely due to the normal role of CAX2 in dampening calcium changes, with its mutant showing elevated calcium levels and signals that preadapted the plants to waterlogging stress prior to them being flooded.   Overall, these findings have helped reveal an extensive, rapid, calcium-based signaling system that integrates the activities of an individual plant to local stresses. The plant-wide transmission of response to these stimuli occurs within seconds but each stimulus triggers a unique pattern of calcium change that may be important for carrying specific information about the triggering stimulus. Identification of specific molecular players in these processes such as the glutamate receptor-like channels, the cyclic nucleotide-gated channels, and transporters like CAX2 now provide molecular landmarks to help further dissect the signaling pathways responsible for these changes. These genes also provide targets for molecular manipulation to help develop stress resilient plants through approaches such as genetic engineering or targeted breeding.   This work has supported multiple outreach events each year that the project has been running at venues such as the University of Wisconsin-Madisons Science Expo. A major element of these efforts has been presenting a plant biology exploration station that has given the general public a hands-on plant physiology and cell biology experience.        Last Modified: 11/12/2024       Submitted by: SimonGilroy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
