<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Insufficient Sleep and Dietary Choices: An Ecologically Valid Examination of the Decision Foundations of Eating Behaviors when Sleep Restricted.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>406628.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>406628</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The dual problems of insufficient sleep and obesity in the U.S. both now effect more than one-third of all adults.  Unhealthy dietary choices, obesity, and poor sleep often occur together, but it is difficult to understand the intricacies of these connections from naturally occurring data.  Such data are typically present with many other confounding factors such that determining whether poor sleep impacts dietary choice or vice versa is a challenge.  This project is aimed at improving our understanding of the impact of insufficient sleep on dietary choice.  To do this, we will experimentally manipulate the level of sleep experienced in one’s home environment in a sample of young adults.  A key benefit of this study is that we will be able to more confidently determine causation from sleep levels to dietary choices and decision making because the experimental environment varies participant sleep levels in a controlled manner.  Also, the fact that participants undergo the sleep treatment in their home environment means their altered sleep levels are done at a level and in an environment that closely mimics real life.  For example, sleep restriction is not total sleep deprivation in our study, but rather we induce chronic partial sleep restriction to the insufficient-sleep levels experienced by a large portion of the U.S. population.  This helps ensure better transferability of our results to the real-world.  The results learned from this project will serve public interest in furthering our understanding of the links between sleep and dietary choice, and they can help inform interventions designed to improve well-being in the key areas of sleep health and dietary choice. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Insufficient sleep and poor dietary habits are serious societal concerns that impact tens of millions of adults (not to mention adolescents) across the globe.  In the U.S. alone, 35% of adults reported short sleep duration of &lt; 7 hrs/night (2014 data), and over 39% of U.S. adults were considered obese (2015-2016 data).  Recent research has shown that poor sleep habits often coexist with unhealthy dietary choices, but it is often difficult in field data to identify causal links or determine the underlying mechanisms between sleep and dietary choices.  The goal of this project is to systematically examine how sleep restriction affects choices of young adults in decision tasks relevant to dietary choice, such as information selection, impulse control, and present-bias.  We will do this using a 3-week validated at-home sleep restriction protocol for sleep level manipulation within which each participant will undergo a full week of well-rested (WR) and a full week of sleep restricted (SR) sleep levels, thus allowing us to compare each participant’s behavior when SR to that same participant’s baseline WR behaviors and food choices.  Additionally, participants will keep daily food records that will allow analysis of objective outcomes from actual dietary choices, and decision making assessments following each sleep treatment week will provide data in key building block task domains in the face of SR. The unique protocol will generate data on SR and dietary choice highly relevant to a large segment of the population.  The tasks selected will produce simple outcome measures that allow testing of key hypotheses and will help identify underlying causal mechanisms responsible for unhealthy dietary choice when sleep restricted.  This project is uniquely interdisciplinary (behavioral economics, cognitive neuroscience/psychology, and sleep psychology), which will serve the interests of advancing knowledge across different fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Dickinson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David L Dickinson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dickinsondl@appstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000433521</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naomi</FirstName>
<LastName>Kakoschke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Naomi Kakoschke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[naomi.kakoschke@monash.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814664</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Drummond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sean Drummond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sean.drummond@monash.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818439</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Appalachian State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOONE</CityName>
<ZipCode>286080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8282627459</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[438 ACADEMY ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F1NAKY5L1425</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>APPALACHIAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Appalachian State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>286072051</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>132100</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~131578</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~142315</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~132735</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aimed to study how commonly experienced levels of insufficient sleep impact decision making related to dietary choices.&nbsp; Public health data indicates that many adults get 5-6 hours of nightly sleep, which falls below the recommended 7-8 hours per night of sleep. Thus, it seems the more general public health concern is chronic levels of insufficient sleep, rather than total sleep deprivation (though this occurs as well).&nbsp; One merit of this project was to experimentally assign treatment participants two treatment conditions that approximated recommended nightly sleep and commonly experienced insufficient sleep levels:&nbsp; a full week each of well-rested (WR: 8-9 hours/night of sleep) and sleep-restricted (SR: 5-6 hours/night of sleep) sleep levels in randomly assigned order.&nbsp; At the end of each treatment week, a set of decision tasks was administered to all participants to better understand how SR impacts decision-making in key cognitive areas that are important for dietary choices.&nbsp; Another merit of the study was that participants experienced these assigned sleep levels in their naturalistic at-home sleep environment, which increases our confidence that findings should transfer to real world participants.&nbsp; Sleep levels were passively but objectively measured using research-grade wrist-worn activity trackers.&nbsp; These activity data only allowed us to have a validated measure of participant&rsquo;s nightly sleep, when activity is at or near zero, but it produced complementary data on the objective daytime physical activity levels of the participants.&nbsp; Finally, to complement diet-related decision data collected at the end of each treatment week, all participants gave daily dietary intake reports using a validated online assessment tool.&nbsp; The merit of this data collection was that it would provide data on multi-day comprehensive dietary choices that were unrestricted (i.e., participant ate/drank however they chose during the study), which may differ from choices made in a momentary laboratory decision task setting often used in research.</p> <p>There is broad impact to the use of this validated at-home sleep protocol for our research questions, because the environment and conditions of participant sleep-assignments are less artificial than that of a sleep-lab study (though those clearly have their own merits).&nbsp; The methodology of this study was also multidisciplinary in how it combined insights from sleep science, psychology, and behavioral economics.&nbsp; As a result, the investigators have disseminated findings in a multi-disciplinary fashion to audiences in sleep science, psychology, and economics. &nbsp;&nbsp;The study award also provided training to several undergraduate students as research assistants (RAs) on the project.&nbsp; We recruited undergraduate students from both economics and psychology majors, and this enhanced the educational experience of the diverse set of RAs by providing exposure to human subjects research, training in ethical conduct of research, and experience with data collection and experimental methodology.&nbsp; Additionally, one of the RAs from this award was also able to engage in faculty-mentored behavioral research with the Principal Investigator, which led to a co-authored peer-reviewed journal publication between the student and Principal Investigator.</p> <p>Outcomes from this project are not yet finalized (i.e., data analysis is ongoing at the time of this report), but two key findings are noteworthy.&nbsp; First, the data did not show a <em>general </em>negative impact of SR compared to WR on dietary choices but rather negative dietary choice effects only in a subset of participants.&nbsp; Specifically, in those who had a higher baseline characteristic related to cognitive or behavioral control, SR increased daily calories reported and increased one&rsquo;s focus on item-taste over healthiness in a consequential snack/beverage task administered at the end of a treatment week.&nbsp; On the other hand, the objective physical activity data collected showed a clear and <strong><em>general</em> negative effect of SR (compared to WR) on daytime physical activity</strong>&mdash;the data showed less physical activity and an increased proportion of time spent in sedentary activities during SR.&nbsp; Thus, one conclusion from this study is that <strong><em>the more general pathway</em></strong> that links SR to increased risk of overweight and obesity is via negative impacts on physical activity as opposed to negative impacts on dietary choices.</p> <p>Another finding, which was contrary to our hypothesis, was that SR did not have a significant effect on decision making in cognitive tasks related to dietary choices (i.e., the type of tasks that would be considered building-block to real world dietary choices).&nbsp; While the data showed that participants process diet-related information in ways that are predictably biased against any information that is counter to one&rsquo;s dietary-ideology, the level of bias appears similar whether the participant is well-rested or sleep-restricted.&nbsp;</p> <p>There are broad implications of these findings in terms how we understand the health-related risks of current societal levels of insufficient sleep.&nbsp; The data from this award did not show the sleep-related impacts on diet-related decision making that were hypothesized, but our findings place an increased focus on the impact of insufficient sleep on physical <em>inactivity </em>and sedentary behaviors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/11/2024<br> Modified by: David&nbsp;L&nbsp;Dickinson</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project aimed to study how commonly experienced levels of insufficient sleep impact decision making related to dietary choices. Public health data indicates that many adults get 5-6 hours of nightly sleep, which falls below the recommended 7-8 hours per night of sleep. Thus, it seems the more general public health concern is chronic levels of insufficient sleep, rather than total sleep deprivation (though this occurs as well). One merit of this project was to experimentally assign treatment participants two treatment conditions that approximated recommended nightly sleep and commonly experienced insufficient sleep levels: a full week each of well-rested (WR: 8-9 hours/night of sleep) and sleep-restricted (SR: 5-6 hours/night of sleep) sleep levels in randomly assigned order. At the end of each treatment week, a set of decision tasks was administered to all participants to better understand how SR impacts decision-making in key cognitive areas that are important for dietary choices. Another merit of the study was that participants experienced these assigned sleep levels in their naturalistic at-home sleep environment, which increases our confidence that findings should transfer to real world participants. Sleep levels were passively but objectively measured using research-grade wrist-worn activity trackers. These activity data only allowed us to have a validated measure of participants nightly sleep, when activity is at or near zero, but it produced complementary data on the objective daytime physical activity levels of the participants. Finally, to complement diet-related decision data collected at the end of each treatment week, all participants gave daily dietary intake reports using a validated online assessment tool. The merit of this data collection was that it would provide data on multi-day comprehensive dietary choices that were unrestricted (i.e., participant ate/drank however they chose during the study), which may differ from choices made in a momentary laboratory decision task setting often used in research.   There is broad impact to the use of this validated at-home sleep protocol for our research questions, because the environment and conditions of participant sleep-assignments are less artificial than that of a sleep-lab study (though those clearly have their own merits). The methodology of this study was also multidisciplinary in how it combined insights from sleep science, psychology, and behavioral economics. As a result, the investigators have disseminated findings in a multi-disciplinary fashion to audiences in sleep science, psychology, and economics. The study award also provided training to several undergraduate students as research assistants (RAs) on the project. We recruited undergraduate students from both economics and psychology majors, and this enhanced the educational experience of the diverse set of RAs by providing exposure to human subjects research, training in ethical conduct of research, and experience with data collection and experimental methodology. Additionally, one of the RAs from this award was also able to engage in faculty-mentored behavioral research with the Principal Investigator, which led to a co-authored peer-reviewed journal publication between the student and Principal Investigator.   Outcomes from this project are not yet finalized (i.e., data analysis is ongoing at the time of this report), but two key findings are noteworthy. First, the data did not show a general negative impact of SR compared to WR on dietary choices but rather negative dietary choice effects only in a subset of participants. Specifically, in those who had a higher baseline characteristic related to cognitive or behavioral control, SR increased daily calories reported and increased ones focus on item-taste over healthiness in a consequential snack/beverage task administered at the end of a treatment week. On the other hand, the objective physical activity data collected showed a clear and general negative effect of SR (compared to WR) on daytime physical activitythe data showed less physical activity and an increased proportion of time spent in sedentary activities during SR. Thus, one conclusion from this study is that the more general pathway that links SR to increased risk of overweight and obesity is via negative impacts on physical activity as opposed to negative impacts on dietary choices.   Another finding, which was contrary to our hypothesis, was that SR did not have a significant effect on decision making in cognitive tasks related to dietary choices (i.e., the type of tasks that would be considered building-block to real world dietary choices). While the data showed that participants process diet-related information in ways that are predictably biased against any information that is counter to ones dietary-ideology, the level of bias appears similar whether the participant is well-rested or sleep-restricted.   There are broad implications of these findings in terms how we understand the health-related risks of current societal levels of insufficient sleep. The data from this award did not show the sleep-related impacts on diet-related decision making that were hypothesized, but our findings place an increased focus on the impact of insufficient sleep on physical inactivity and sedentary behaviors.        Last Modified: 11/11/2024       Submitted by: DavidLDickinson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
