<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Travel Grant for 2020 Cyber-Physical Systems and Internet-of-Things Week (CPS-IoT Week)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vishal Sharma</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vsharma@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will provide funding for students from U.S. institutions of higher learning to attend the 2020 Cyber-Physical Systems and Internet-of-Things Week (CPS-IoT Week 2020). CPS-IoT Week will be held in Sydney, Australia during April 21-24, 2020.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018203</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Omprakash</FirstName>
<LastName>Gnawali</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Omprakash Gnawali</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gnawali@cs.uh.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000601008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>772043067</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4300 MARTIN LUTHER KING BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QKWEF8XLMTT3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4800 Calhoun Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033y00</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project successfully enabled 22 students from US-based institutions of higher education to participate in 2023 Cyber-Physical Systems and Internet-of-Things Week (CPS-IoT Week) and its co-located events.&nbsp; Most of the awardees were PhD students in a field within the scope of the CPS IoT Week conference. Some awardees were pursuing Bachelors degrees but had demonstrated interest in reserch in Cyber Physical Systems or Internet of Things or related areas. At the end of the conference, each student reflected on their participation at the conference and they reported that the conference was helpful for them to network with the senior researchers in the field and to get a sense of the breadth of research in CPS and IoT areas. The award was also helpful in improving the diversity among its participants. The award also brought participants from Minority-Serving Institutions and Sispanic-Serving Institutions. The CPS IoT Week 2023 was organized in San Antonio, TX, USA and included five conferences, 16 workshops, one tutorial, one competition, and one PhD forum. The conference also included keynotes from established researchers in the field from the US. Overall, the conference provided&nbsp;ample opportunities to the awardees to enhance their research experience in CPS, IoT, and related areas.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 03/08/2024<br> Modified by: Omprakash&nbsp;Gnawali</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The project successfully enabled 22 students from US-based institutions of higher education to participate in 2023 Cyber-Physical Systems and Internet-of-Things Week (CPS-IoT Week) and its co-located events. Most of the awardees were PhD students in a field within the scope of the CPS IoT Week conference. Some awardees were pursuing Bachelors degrees but had demonstrated interest in reserch in Cyber Physical Systems or Internet of Things or related areas. At the end of the conference, each student reflected on their participation at the conference and they reported that the conference was helpful for them to network with the senior researchers in the field and to get a sense of the breadth of research in CPS and IoT areas. The award was also helpful in improving the diversity among its participants. The award also brought participants from Minority-Serving Institutions and Sispanic-Serving Institutions. The CPS IoT Week 2023 was organized in San Antonio, TX, USA and included five conferences, 16 workshops, one tutorial, one competition, and one PhD forum. The conference also included keynotes from established researchers in the field from the US. Overall, the conference providedample opportunities to the awardees to enhance their research experience in CPS, IoT, and related areas.     Last Modified: 03/08/2024       Submitted by: OmprakashGnawali]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
