<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[GOALI/Collaborative Research: Improving Incremental Sheet Forming by Ultrasonically Enhanced Material Deformation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>298067.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>298067</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Grant Opportunity for Academic Liaison with Industry (GOALI) award supports research that contributes to the understanding of ultrasonically-enhanced incremental sheet forming with funding from the Advanced Manufacturing Program in the Civil, Mechanical, and Manufacturing Innovation Division and from the Metals and Metallic Nanostructures Program in the Division of Materials Research. Despite the rapid development of ultra-high strength materials, their readiness to use is limited by limitations in the associated manufacturing processes, especially in the field of sheet metal forming. One promising solution is to temporarily soften the material during the forming process, which can be achieved with the assistance of ultrasonic energy. However, the underlying principles of this softening phenomenon remain elusive. Another benefit of applying ultrasonic energy is improved tribological behavior. Among forming technologies, incremental sheet forming is advantageous in rapid prototyping based on its universal tooling and high flexibility, which meet the increasingly competitive market demands of product updates and customization. However, achieving high geometric accuracy and surface finish quality are challenging. In this aspect, both the ultrasonic softening and modified friction can be harnessed as a unique process and property enhancement solution. The fundamental research of ultrasonic effects on material behavior facilitates effective incorporation of ultrasonic energy into incremental sheet forming, which greatly benefits sheet metal applications in industries such as aerospace, automotive and biomedical. Students involved in the project gain multidisciplinary knowledge and research experiences in materials, mechanical engineering and manufacturing. Students, particularly women and underrepresented minorities, have the opportunity to interact with GOALI partner Boeing engineers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to advance the fundamental knowledge of ultrasonic softening mechanisms on material deformation behavior.  The research is to effectively utilize ultrasonic energy to enhance the incremental sheet forming (ISF) process based on both its bulk softening and modified surface tribological behavior. First, an innovative ultrasonically assisted (UA) micro-tensile testbed, equipped with an in situ high speed optical microscope imaging system, is developed. This enables digital image correlation analysis on the transient inter and intragranular strain field within the ultrasonic vibration cycle. Post mortem multiscale microstructure characterizations are then performed. A dislocation density-based crystal plasticity constitutive material model is developed to reveal the physical principles that are beyond experimental observations. Second, the UA-ISF process is comprehensively studied, in which relationships between the reduced forming force, increased forming accuracy, improved surface finish and the ISF and ultrasonic parameters are established. Finally, a coupled acousto-mechanical process model for UA-ISF is developed, which incorporates the ultrasonically affected material constitutive model developed in the first task. With experimental validations, this model would be utilized to optimize UA-ISF in forming parts with complex free-form geometries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019238</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xun</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xun Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[liu.7054@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000767273</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 KENNY RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432213560</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1248 Arthur E. Adams Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y00</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>150400</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>177100</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~298067</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ultrasonic (UA) softening effects on metallic alloys were recognized in early 1950s, where the material flow stress can be remarkably reduced with superimposed UA vibration during plastic deformation. However, the underlying physical principles of this phenomenon remain elusive due to the limitations and inconsistencies of existing experimental designs, lack of in situ deformation analysis and insufficient modeling. Accordingly, efficient utilization of ultrasonic energy to improve relevant manufacturing processes is challenging. Among forming technologies, incremental sheet forming (ISF) is advantageous in rapid prototyping based on its universal tooling and high flexibility. However, achieving high dimensional and geometric accuracy, particularly for high strength materials, limit the widespread applications of ISF. The goals of this GOALI collaborative project are to advance the fundamental knowledge of ultrasonic softening effects on different material systems (led by Ohio State University OSU) and to enhance ISF through effective incorporation of UA into the process (led by University of Michigan UM and Boeing company).</p> <p>At OSU, an innovative ultrasonically assisted micro-tensile testbed equipped with in situ high speed digital image correlation (DIC) analysis is developed. The sample gauge length is one order of magnitude smaller than the ultrasonic wavelength, allowing a relatively uniform vibration distribution and minimizing the frictional heating associated with UA compression. Consistent flow stress reduction is observed in both intermittent and continuous UA tensile tests for the various materials studied throughout the project, with the softening degree ranking from the highest to lowest as: transformation induced plasticity (TRIP) steel, low carbon steel, pure copper, Ti-6Al-4V, pure Titanium, aluminum alloy AA2024 O-temper, AA2219 with refined grains achieved from friction stir processing (AA2219-FSW), which is almost the same as AA2219-T4, and lastly AA2024-T4. The flow stress reduction all follows an approximately linear relationship with the UA amplitude. In low carbon and TRIP steel, UA reduces the work hardening rate and can even lead to work softening when the amplitude exceeds a certain threshold. In situ DIC analysis reveals UA enhances L&uuml;ders band propagation with higher strain rate for low carbon steel and promotes L&uuml;ders-like deformation bands for TRIP steel. For aluminum alloys AA2219 and 2024 with different heat treatments and grain sizes, the Portevin&ndash;Le Chatelier (PLC) band formation and propagation is consistently promoted by UA.</p> <p>Residual softening occurs for low carbon steel, opposite to the residual hardening in TRIP steel, attributed to the different UA effects on deformation microstructure and dominating strengthening mechanisms of the two steels. Electron Backscatter Diffraction (EBSD) characterization reveals an increase in Kernal average misorientation, grain reference orientation deviation and the low-angle grain boundary (LAGB) fraction, suggesting enhanced subgrain formation. In contrast, UA delays martensitic transformation for TRIP steel, in addition to the reduced LAGB and geometrically necessary dislocations. For aluminum alloys, AA2024 O-temper shows residual softening, which is minimal for AA2024 T4 and AA2219-FSW. Uniquely, AA2219-T4 shows intriguing behavior of both residual hardening and higher elongation under UA, highly desirable for forming processes. For Ti-6Al-4V, high UA amplitude induces residual softening, which can be the result of UA suppressed deformation texture.</p> <p>A novel approach to model ultrasonic softening effect is developed by considering the orientation relationship between loading and ultrasonic vibration. The UA effect on dislocation slip is assumed to be the most significant for the slip system orientated in the same direction as UA. The directional softening was implemented in a Visco-Plastic Self-Consistent (VPSC) model and validated with micro-tensile tests of pure copper. Statistical analysis on grain level shows that Von Mises stress on all grains decrease under UA, while the level of stress reduction varies among grains and shows a strong dependence on grain orientation. EBSD analysis reveals that grains originally have high Taylor factors are plastically hard for deformation with multislip. A relative decrease in Taylor factor in those grains is experimentally observed with UA and matches with model prediction.</p> <p>At OSU, the project provided multidisciplinary training to 1 Ph.D. student and 1 Master student, both successfully graduated and now works at the Exponent, and the GE aviation company respectively. 1 undergraduate participated in the project as a research internship. The research results have been integrated to the course curriculum taught by PI Liu, such as explanations of the ultrasonic metal welding principles. The research results have been disseminated through 3 journal publications, 1 PhD thesis and 1 Master thesis, conferences in the fields of manufacturing, materials science and engineering, such as TMS and MST.</p> <p>Throughout the project, OSU collaborated closely with UM and Boeing company. The stress-strain curves obtained in UA micro-tensile tests are shared with UM as material mechanical properties for FEM modeling of UA-ISF. Difference of softening between UA compression and tension are compared and correlate with the ISF forming force reduction. Boeing company has provided technical insights and in-kind support of materials and testing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 06/14/2024<br> Modified by: Xun&nbsp;Liu</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718385858140_Figure_4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718385858140_Figure_4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experimental and modeling results of UA effects on stress"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718385858140_Figure_4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experimental and modeling results of UA effects on stress"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">True stress-strain curves of pure copper (a) experimental (b) VPSC modeling results; (c) Distribution of grain level Von Mises stress; (d) VPSC yield surface and (e) zoomed-in view; (f) Discrete orientation of subset showing grains with higher stress reduction rotates further towards 111 direction</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiarui Kang, Xun Liu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xun&nbsp;Liu <div class="imageTitle">Experimental and modeling results of UA effects on stress</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718392255280_Figure_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718392255280_Figure_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Digital image correlation (DIC) results of AA2024 O temper"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718392255280_Figure_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Digital image correlation (DIC) results of AA2024 O temper"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Digital image correlation (DIC) results of AA2024 O temper (a) strain rate map at 8.5% strain, (b-e) spatial-temporal contour plots of strain rate under different ultrasonic (UA) conditions showing the Portevin Le Chatelier band initiation and propagation is enhanced with UA</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiarui Kang, Xun Liu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xun&nbsp;Liu <div class="imageTitle">Digital image correlation (DIC) results of AA2024 O temper</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718386082455_Figure_6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718386082455_Figure_6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="OSU and UM collaboration on UA force reduction analysis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718386082455_Figure_6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="OSU and UM collaboration on UA force reduction analysis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison of the deformation force reduction measured from ultrasonic compressions (from UM), UA micro-tension (from OSU), and UA incremental sheet forming (UA-ISF, from UM) for aluminum alloys</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiarui Kang, Randy Cheng, Xun Liu, Alan Taub</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xun&nbsp;Liu <div class="imageTitle">OSU and UM collaboration on UA force reduction analysis</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718386011720_Figure_5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718386011720_Figure_5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experimental and modeling results of UA effects on texture"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718386011720_Figure_5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experimental and modeling results of UA effects on texture"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Taylor factor map of 17% strain (a) no UA and (c) UA; (b) and (d) corresponding Taylor factor maps of 111 subset; (e) EBSD measurement and (f) VPSC simulation showing Taylor factor distribution of the orientation subset shift toward lower values under UA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiarui Kang, Steve Niezgoda, Xun Liu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xun&nbsp;Liu <div class="imageTitle">Experimental and modeling results of UA effects on texture</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718384317558_Figure_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718384317558_Figure_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ultrasonic effects on flow stress of various materials"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718384317558_Figure_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ultrasonic effects on flow stress of various materials"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ultrasonic (UA) effects on stress-strain curves of various materials (a) AA2024-O temper (b) AA2024-T4 with intermittent UA (c) TRIP steel with continuous UA (d) Reduced work hardening rate of TRIP steel with continuous UA (e) Flow stress reduction as a function of vibration amplitude</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiarui Kang, Thomas Kang, Xun Liu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xun&nbsp;Liu <div class="imageTitle">Ultrasonic effects on flow stress of various materials</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718385668868_Figure_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718385668868_Figure_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="EBSD characterization on the TRIP steel deformation microstructure"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019238/2019238_10701316_1718385668868_Figure_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="EBSD characterization on the TRIP steel deformation microstructure"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Grain boundary, geometrically necessary dislocation (GND) and reconstructed phase maps of TRIP steel (a) undeformed; (b) 5% strain; (c) 5% strain with UA; (d) 17% strain; (e) 17% strain with UA</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jiarui Kang, Xun Liu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xun&nbsp;Liu <div class="imageTitle">EBSD characterization on the TRIP steel deformation microstructure</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The ultrasonic (UA) softening effects on metallic alloys were recognized in early 1950s, where the material flow stress can be remarkably reduced with superimposed UA vibration during plastic deformation. However, the underlying physical principles of this phenomenon remain elusive due to the limitations and inconsistencies of existing experimental designs, lack of in situ deformation analysis and insufficient modeling. Accordingly, efficient utilization of ultrasonic energy to improve relevant manufacturing processes is challenging. Among forming technologies, incremental sheet forming (ISF) is advantageous in rapid prototyping based on its universal tooling and high flexibility. However, achieving high dimensional and geometric accuracy, particularly for high strength materials, limit the widespread applications of ISF. The goals of this GOALI collaborative project are to advance the fundamental knowledge of ultrasonic softening effects on different material systems (led by Ohio State University OSU) and to enhance ISF through effective incorporation of UA into the process (led by University of Michigan UM and Boeing company).   At OSU, an innovative ultrasonically assisted micro-tensile testbed equipped with in situ high speed digital image correlation (DIC) analysis is developed. The sample gauge length is one order of magnitude smaller than the ultrasonic wavelength, allowing a relatively uniform vibration distribution and minimizing the frictional heating associated with UA compression. Consistent flow stress reduction is observed in both intermittent and continuous UA tensile tests for the various materials studied throughout the project, with the softening degree ranking from the highest to lowest as: transformation induced plasticity (TRIP) steel, low carbon steel, pure copper, Ti-6Al-4V, pure Titanium, aluminum alloy AA2024 O-temper, AA2219 with refined grains achieved from friction stir processing (AA2219-FSW), which is almost the same as AA2219-T4, and lastly AA2024-T4. The flow stress reduction all follows an approximately linear relationship with the UA amplitude. In low carbon and TRIP steel, UA reduces the work hardening rate and can even lead to work softening when the amplitude exceeds a certain threshold. In situ DIC analysis reveals UA enhances Lders band propagation with higher strain rate for low carbon steel and promotes Lders-like deformation bands for TRIP steel. For aluminum alloys AA2219 and 2024 with different heat treatments and grain sizes, the PortevinLe Chatelier (PLC) band formation and propagation is consistently promoted by UA.   Residual softening occurs for low carbon steel, opposite to the residual hardening in TRIP steel, attributed to the different UA effects on deformation microstructure and dominating strengthening mechanisms of the two steels. Electron Backscatter Diffraction (EBSD) characterization reveals an increase in Kernal average misorientation, grain reference orientation deviation and the low-angle grain boundary (LAGB) fraction, suggesting enhanced subgrain formation. In contrast, UA delays martensitic transformation for TRIP steel, in addition to the reduced LAGB and geometrically necessary dislocations. For aluminum alloys, AA2024 O-temper shows residual softening, which is minimal for AA2024 T4 and AA2219-FSW. Uniquely, AA2219-T4 shows intriguing behavior of both residual hardening and higher elongation under UA, highly desirable for forming processes. For Ti-6Al-4V, high UA amplitude induces residual softening, which can be the result of UA suppressed deformation texture.   A novel approach to model ultrasonic softening effect is developed by considering the orientation relationship between loading and ultrasonic vibration. The UA effect on dislocation slip is assumed to be the most significant for the slip system orientated in the same direction as UA. The directional softening was implemented in a Visco-Plastic Self-Consistent (VPSC) model and validated with micro-tensile tests of pure copper. Statistical analysis on grain level shows that Von Mises stress on all grains decrease under UA, while the level of stress reduction varies among grains and shows a strong dependence on grain orientation. EBSD analysis reveals that grains originally have high Taylor factors are plastically hard for deformation with multislip. A relative decrease in Taylor factor in those grains is experimentally observed with UA and matches with model prediction.   At OSU, the project provided multidisciplinary training to 1 Ph.D. student and 1 Master student, both successfully graduated and now works at the Exponent, and the GE aviation company respectively. 1 undergraduate participated in the project as a research internship. The research results have been integrated to the course curriculum taught by PI Liu, such as explanations of the ultrasonic metal welding principles. The research results have been disseminated through 3 journal publications, 1 PhD thesis and 1 Master thesis, conferences in the fields of manufacturing, materials science and engineering, such as TMS and MST.   Throughout the project, OSU collaborated closely with UM and Boeing company. The stress-strain curves obtained in UA micro-tensile tests are shared with UM as material mechanical properties for FEM modeling of UA-ISF. Difference of softening between UA compression and tension are compared and correlate with the ISF forming force reduction. Boeing company has provided technical insights and in-kind support of materials and testing.        Last Modified: 06/14/2024       Submitted by: XunLiu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
