<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Belmont Forum Collaborative Research: Arctic Community Resilience to Boreal Environmental Change: Assessing Risks from Fire and Disease (ACRoBEAR)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>129964.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>147902</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Uhle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>muhle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support to U.S. researchers participating in a project competitively selected by a 55-country initiative on global change research through the Belmont Forum.  The Belmont Forum is a consortium of research funding organizations focused on support for transdisciplinary approaches to global environmental change challenges and opportunities.  It aims to accelerate delivery of the international research most urgently needed to remove critical barriers to sustainability by aligning and mobilizing international resources. Each partner country provides funding for their researchers within a consortium to alleviate the need for funds to cross international borders. This approach facilitates effective leveraging of national resources to support excellent research on topics of global relevance best tackled through a multinational approach, recognizing that global challenges need global solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Working together in this Collaborative Research Action, the partner agencies have provided support to foster global transdisciplinary research teams of natural (including climate), health and social scientists and stakeholders from across the globe to improve understanding of climate, environment and health pathways to protect and promote health. The projects will provide crucial new understanding into the health implications arising from the impacts of climate change and variability on; 1) the quality/quantity of food, 2) chronic exposure to increases/changes in heat and humidity and 3) changes in the distribution and incidence of a range of infectious diseases and emergence of novel pathogens. This award provides support for the U.S. researchers to cooperate in consortia that consist of partners from at least three of the participating countries to increase our knowledge of the complex linkages and pathways between the climate, environment and health to help solve complex challenges that face societies.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to predict and understand health risks from wildfire air pollution and vector-borne disease in the Arctic, and the resilience and adaptability of communities across the region to these risks.  This project focuses on a critical challenge as the Arctic has warmed rapidly over recent decades, at around twice the rate of global mean temperature increases, resulting in rapid changes to this environment.  The Arctic has been affected by unprecedented fire activity, leading to unhealthy air quality in high latitude towns and cities. Vector-borne disease occurrence in these regions is also changing in response to rapid changes in temperature and moisture. The fire activity is also affecting this disease risk by altering the habitat conditions for vectors and their hosts.  The project will focus on integrating satellite and in-situ observations, modelling, health data, and community knowledge and stakeholder dialogue to understand community resilience and response to these changing risks.  This information will help communities address environmental, social, and governance challenges in the most rapidly warming region of the planet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050, 47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019494</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Orttung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert W Orttung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rorttung@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000461824</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Anenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Anenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sanenberg@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000760516</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1918 F ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1918 F St NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>522100</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>731300</Code>
<Text>Intl Global Change Res &amp; Coord</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>U27200</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1679</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7313</Code>
<Text>REGIONAL INST FOR GLOBAL CHANG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021RB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~117564</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~30338</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project made two major sets of advances to our knowledge about wildfire smoke and human health. First, it increased our understanding of how wildfire affects human health by employing satellite data to gain much better measurements of smoke in the atmosphere. These improved measurements made it easier to understand how much smoke the newly active wildfires are creating and how that smoke affects human populations, particularly those living in Alaska and western parts of the United States.</p> <p>Secondly, the project developed new insights into how best to communicate information about wildfire smoke to a variety of audiences, particularly residents who live in the wildland-urban interface where smoke events are increasing. The communications analysis demonstrated the complexity of the wildfire infosphere and the various obstacles complicating the ability of the authorities to transmit information to residents before, during, and after wildfire events. The research findings stressed the need to develop tailored messages and find appropriate pathways for transmitting the information to the different types of audiences among the residents to ensure that the recipients would be able to use the knowledge about the wildfires in an effective manner.</p> <p>Since this NSF-sponsored project was part of a larger Belmont Forum project, the work conducted by the American team contributed to an international study that produced a broader set of outcomes. In particular, the larger project developed projections of changes in wildfire risk across all Arctic nations, under a range of climate change scenarios incorporating global warming levels ranging from +1 to +4<sup>O</sup>C.</p> <p>The funds from the project provided support for three early career researchers. They participated directly in analyzing data (including focus groups in Alaska and air pollution data from satellite observations) and then helped draft manuscripts submitted for publication. Direct involvement in the research and writing processes gave the early career researchers a firsthand professional experience in the development and submission of a manuscript to a peer-reviewed journal. Additionally, they received a chance to work with a mentor in learning how to conduct independent research. The material generated in the project also provided curriculum support for a course on sustainability research methods taught each semester at George Washington University.</p> <p>The work for this project created a basis for applying successfully for additional funds from other sources. These new grants will provide the support needed to continue the work started here and further explore the links between wildfire smoke events and human health.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/03/2024<br> Modified by: Robert&nbsp;W&nbsp;Orttung</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project made two major sets of advances to our knowledge about wildfire smoke and human health. First, it increased our understanding of how wildfire affects human health by employing satellite data to gain much better measurements of smoke in the atmosphere. These improved measurements made it easier to understand how much smoke the newly active wildfires are creating and how that smoke affects human populations, particularly those living in Alaska and western parts of the United States.   Secondly, the project developed new insights into how best to communicate information about wildfire smoke to a variety of audiences, particularly residents who live in the wildland-urban interface where smoke events are increasing. The communications analysis demonstrated the complexity of the wildfire infosphere and the various obstacles complicating the ability of the authorities to transmit information to residents before, during, and after wildfire events. The research findings stressed the need to develop tailored messages and find appropriate pathways for transmitting the information to the different types of audiences among the residents to ensure that the recipients would be able to use the knowledge about the wildfires in an effective manner.   Since this NSF-sponsored project was part of a larger Belmont Forum project, the work conducted by the American team contributed to an international study that produced a broader set of outcomes. In particular, the larger project developed projections of changes in wildfire risk across all Arctic nations, under a range of climate change scenarios incorporating global warming levels ranging from +1 to +4OC.   The funds from the project provided support for three early career researchers. They participated directly in analyzing data (including focus groups in Alaska and air pollution data from satellite observations) and then helped draft manuscripts submitted for publication. Direct involvement in the research and writing processes gave the early career researchers a firsthand professional experience in the development and submission of a manuscript to a peer-reviewed journal. Additionally, they received a chance to work with a mentor in learning how to conduct independent research. The material generated in the project also provided curriculum support for a course on sustainability research methods taught each semester at George Washington University.   The work for this project created a basis for applying successfully for additional funds from other sources. These new grants will provide the support needed to continue the work started here and further explore the links between wildfire smoke events and human health.        Last Modified: 11/03/2024       Submitted by: RobertWOrttung]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
