<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Increasing Undergraduate Student Interpreters' Fluency and Accuracy in Interpreting Biology Vocabulary in American Sign Language]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>297126.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>297126</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gordon Uno</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>geuno@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922574</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest by broadening participation of hearing-impaired students in STEM learning, majors, and careers, specifically in biological sciences.  Many undergraduate students who are deaf or hard of hearing encounter language-related obstacles to learning biological content.  Overcoming these obstacles could support their success in biological sciences courses and majors. Increasing the biological vocabulary of American Sign Language (ASL) interpreters is a key step toward achieving this goal.  In this project, TERC and Lamar University will develop and evaluate a unique set of materials for training ASL interpreters. The cornerstone of these materials is a Signing BioScience Dictionary that includes a set of signed terms commonly found in undergraduate lecture material.  To accompany the dictionary, the project will develop summaries of core biology concepts to provide context for the terms and video examples of accurate and fluent interpretations of biology lecture material.  Finally, strategies will be developed to help instructors incorporate these materials into Lamar University’s four-year undergraduate ASL interpreter training program. This project builds on the outcomes of prior work that produced a prototype Signing BioScience Dictionary and findings about the types of teaching and learning materials that are most useful to support training ASL interpreters to communicate biology content fluently and accurately. This project has the potential to open doors to STEM knowledge, particularly in biology, for deaf and hard of hearing learners across the nation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has six goals: 1) Prepare a beta version of the Signing BioScience Dictionary; 2) Create summaries of core biology content needed for fluent and accurate interpretation of undergraduate biology lecture material; 3) Produce video examples of fluent interpretations of biology lecture material; 4) Evaluate the use and effectiveness of the Signing BioScience Dictionary, summaries, and videos in increasing student interpreters’ ASL vocabulary, knowledge of related content, and ability to accurately and fluently interpret undergraduate biology lecture material; 5) Design a set of instructional practices for use of the Signing BioScience Dictionary, summaries, and videos in interpreter training programs; and 6) Disseminate project deliverables. A mixed-measurement design that combines qualitative and quantitative data will be employed to evaluate how Lamar University undergraduate students in the interpreter training program use the Signing BioScience Dictionary, biology content summaries, and videos.  In addition, the research will explore the effectiveness of the Signing BioScience Dictionary, content summaries, and videos in increasing the undergraduate student interpreters’ ASL biology vocabulary and biology content knowledge, as well as their ability to interpret a typical undergraduate biology lecture accurately and clearly.  Results of these studies will inform the project team about additions and/or changes that could make the materials more effective.  The project has the potential to make biology content more accessible to undergraduates who are deaf or hard of hearing, and thus may be instrumental in supporting their pursuit of biology (or other STEM) majors and careers. The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019843</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judy</FirstName>
<LastName>Vesel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judy Vesel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[judy_vesel@terc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000456154</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Clark</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary D Clark</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[diane.clark@lamar.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000729478</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TERC Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021401339</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178739600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2067 MASSACHUSETTS AVE STE 26]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GSLCJ3M62XX1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TERC, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TERC Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021401339</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2067 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~297126</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Increasing Undergraduate Student Interpreters&rsquo; American Sign Language (ASL) Biology Vocabulary, Content Knowledge, and Interpreting Ability</em> is a Level 1: Engaged Student Learning project. Its goal is to broaden participation of students who are deaf or hard of hearing in courses and majors that incorporate biology content. With this project, TERC and Lamar University researched and developed a unique set of teaching and learning materials to provide student interpreters enrolled in Lamar&rsquo;s four-year undergraduate interpreter training program with the knowledge and skills they require to support students who are deaf or hard of hearing in successful learning of biology content. The project builds on outcomes of an IUSE Exploration and Design project that resulted in a prototype Signing Bioscience Dictionary (SBD) and new knowledge about what interpreters need to know and be able to do to fluently interpret biology content.</p> <p>During this 36-month project, the partners accomplished the following: 1) Prepared a beta version of the SBD that includes a total of 1580 primary terms and a total of 7099 links to terms below definitions. 2) Created summaries of core biology content needed for fluent and accurate interpretation of undergraduate biology lecture material. 3) Produced a video that explains fingerspelling principles by demonstrating the fingerspelling linguistic features of ASL using&nbsp;the phonological processes of assimilation, epenthesis, metathesis, reduction, and elision. It then looks at how the five ASL fingerspelling principles of unimorph, synomorph, dimorph, trimorph, and quadmorph appear in different words. Tutorial Activities provide examples of the fingerspelling of biology terms and offer opportunities for review and practice of the concepts introduced in the video. 4) Evaluated the materials for use and effectiveness. 5) Disseminated products and findings.</p> <p>Evaluation for use and effectiveness involved a two-phase study. During Phase I, students focused on studying and mastering the genetics vocabulary included in the SBD. During Phase II, they focused on learning and becoming able to use syllabification in signed fingerspelling. The Lamar team mentored and guided participants during both phases. A video narrative of a genetics lecture produced in spoken language provided the measure used to determine the effectiveness and accuracy of participants&rsquo; interpreting ability using a pre- and post-design. The presentation was interpreted at the beginning and end of the first phase. This same video was used weekly to monitor fluency of interpretation during the second phase. To analyze the data, results were organized around each of four research questions. Taken together, findings show use of the SBD in combination with summaries of fundamental bioscience content when used in study sessions appears to contribute to Lamar university&rsquo;s student interpreters having an increased ASL bioscience vocabulary and ability to sign bioscience terms. However, use of the definitions and access to information about relevant bioscience content does not appear to contribute to them having an increased knowledge of the content presented in a typical undergraduate biology lecture. Study of videos explaining the principles of fingerspelling and the application of these principles to the fingerspelling of terms included in the SBD show that when used in study sessions, these new and original resources appear to contribute to Lamar&rsquo;s student interpreters having an improved ability to accurately and fluently fingerspell bioscience terms. They also show that this new knowledge appears to translate into them having an increased ability to interpret typical bioscience lecture material accurately and fluently.</p> <p>Dissemination of products and findings involved publication of articles in the Forum from Linguistic Studies and in TERC&rsquo;s publication Hands On! and presentation of posters at the 2022 and 2024 IUSE Summit.</p> <p>Products and findings are available from the Resources section of the project Web site at <a href="https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/">https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/</a>.The beta version of the SBD is also available directly at <a href="https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD.htm">https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD.htm</a>; the summaries at <a href="https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/content-summaries.html">https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/content-summaries.html</a>; and the fingerspelling videos at <a href="https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/fingerspelling-tutorials.html">https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/fingerspelling-tutorials.html</a>. An evaluation report that includes a detailed discussion of the research methodology and findings is available directly from the Evaluation Reports section of the project Web site at <a href="https://sign-sci.s3.amazonaws.com/publications/SBD_Interpreters_Year_2_Evaluation_Report.pdf">https://sign-sci.s3.amazonaws.com/publications/SBD_Interpreters_Year_2_Evaluation_Report.pdf</a> .</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 08/05/2024<br> Modified by: Judy&nbsp;Vesel</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722276624550_SBD_Signing_Page--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722276624550_SBD_Signing_Page--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SBD Signing Page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722276624550_SBD_Signing_Page--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SBD Signing Page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image provides an example of the signing features that are available on an SBD term page.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judy Vesel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judy&nbsp;Vesel <div class="imageTitle">SBD Signing Page</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722276786102_Content_Summaries--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722276786102_Content_Summaries--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SBD Content Summary Page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722276786102_Content_Summaries--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SBD Content Summary Page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image provides information about the biology content summaries that can be used in conjunction with the SBD.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judy Vesel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judy&nbsp;Vesel <div class="imageTitle">SBD Content Summary Page</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722277173429_Fingerspelling_Videos--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722277173429_Fingerspelling_Videos--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fingerspelling Videos"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722277173429_Fingerspelling_Videos--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fingerspelling Videos"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image image provides examples of the videos that are available from the fingerspelling video and tutorial Home page.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judy Vesel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judy&nbsp;Vesel <div class="imageTitle">Fingerspelling Videos</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722277240129_Fingerspelling_Tutorials--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722277240129_Fingerspelling_Tutorials--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fingerspelling Tutorials"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2019843/2019843_10694725_1722277240129_Fingerspelling_Tutorials--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fingerspelling Tutorials"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image image provides examples of the tutorials that are available from the fingerspelling video and tutorial Home page</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judy Vesel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judy&nbsp;Vesel <div class="imageTitle">Fingerspelling Tutorials</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Increasing Undergraduate Student Interpreters American Sign Language (ASL) Biology Vocabulary, Content Knowledge, and Interpreting Ability is a Level 1: Engaged Student Learning project. Its goal is to broaden participation of students who are deaf or hard of hearing in courses and majors that incorporate biology content. With this project, TERC and Lamar University researched and developed a unique set of teaching and learning materials to provide student interpreters enrolled in Lamars four-year undergraduate interpreter training program with the knowledge and skills they require to support students who are deaf or hard of hearing in successful learning of biology content. The project builds on outcomes of an IUSE Exploration and Design project that resulted in a prototype Signing Bioscience Dictionary (SBD) and new knowledge about what interpreters need to know and be able to do to fluently interpret biology content.   During this 36-month project, the partners accomplished the following: 1) Prepared a beta version of the SBD that includes a total of 1580 primary terms and a total of 7099 links to terms below definitions. 2) Created summaries of core biology content needed for fluent and accurate interpretation of undergraduate biology lecture material. 3) Produced a video that explains fingerspelling principles by demonstrating the fingerspelling linguistic features of ASL usingthe phonological processes of assimilation, epenthesis, metathesis, reduction, and elision. It then looks at how the five ASL fingerspelling principles of unimorph, synomorph, dimorph, trimorph, and quadmorph appear in different words. Tutorial Activities provide examples of the fingerspelling of biology terms and offer opportunities for review and practice of the concepts introduced in the video. 4) Evaluated the materials for use and effectiveness. 5) Disseminated products and findings.   Evaluation for use and effectiveness involved a two-phase study. During Phase I, students focused on studying and mastering the genetics vocabulary included in the SBD. During Phase II, they focused on learning and becoming able to use syllabification in signed fingerspelling. The Lamar team mentored and guided participants during both phases. A video narrative of a genetics lecture produced in spoken language provided the measure used to determine the effectiveness and accuracy of participants interpreting ability using a pre- and post-design. The presentation was interpreted at the beginning and end of the first phase. This same video was used weekly to monitor fluency of interpretation during the second phase. To analyze the data, results were organized around each of four research questions. Taken together, findings show use of the SBD in combination with summaries of fundamental bioscience content when used in study sessions appears to contribute to Lamar universitys student interpreters having an increased ASL bioscience vocabulary and ability to sign bioscience terms. However, use of the definitions and access to information about relevant bioscience content does not appear to contribute to them having an increased knowledge of the content presented in a typical undergraduate biology lecture. Study of videos explaining the principles of fingerspelling and the application of these principles to the fingerspelling of terms included in the SBD show that when used in study sessions, these new and original resources appear to contribute to Lamars student interpreters having an improved ability to accurately and fluently fingerspell bioscience terms. They also show that this new knowledge appears to translate into them having an increased ability to interpret typical bioscience lecture material accurately and fluently.   Dissemination of products and findings involved publication of articles in the Forum from Linguistic Studies and in TERCs publication Hands On! and presentation of posters at the 2022 and 2024 IUSE Summit.   Products and findings are available from the Resources section of the project Web site at https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/.The beta version of the SBD is also available directly at https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD.htm; the summaries at https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/content-summaries.html; and the fingerspelling videos at https://signsci.terc.edu/video/SBD/interpreters/fingerspelling-tutorials.html. An evaluation report that includes a detailed discussion of the research methodology and findings is available directly from the Evaluation Reports section of the project Web site at https://sign-sci.s3.amazonaws.com/publications/SBD_Interpreters_Year_2_Evaluation_Report.pdf .                 Last Modified: 08/05/2024       Submitted by: JudyVesel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
