<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Roles of Working Memory in Reinforcement Learning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>772575.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>772575</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>slim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Humans learn how to make rewarding choices in multiple ways, often in parallel. Some learning mechanisms are fast and flexible, but mentally effortful; others are slow and inflexible, but effortless, learning the value of different choices in different situations. This project investigates the possibility that the mechanisms are not independent. Specifically, the investigators test the hypothesis that effortful processes contribute to identifying what the slow and effortless “reinforcement learning” processes learn the value of: what features of the situation are relevant, what aspects of the choices matter. In that sense, the simpler reinforcement learning process, usually thought to be automated and instinctive, may be improved by the exertion of cognitive effort such as attention and short term memory, and impaired by a lack thereof. Better understanding the role of cognitive effort in effortless reinforcement learning processes should strengthen our ability to identify sources of learning impairment and optimize learning in the many everyday life situations where we need to learn, be it new software, parenting, or interacting with others in new environments. Better understanding of the mechanisms that support human learning will provide inspiration for improved algorithms for artificial intelligence. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Learning in humans is the result of a carefully orchestrated set of processes interacting in parallel. Some processes, like working memory, rely on executive function to store information in a flexible format that is effortful to maintain and use. Other processes, like reinforcement learning, store information in a less flexible but more robust and virtually effortless format, encoding the value of choices. In this project, the investigators study how executive functions may additionally support reinforcement learning processes. This project uses novel experimental protocols to examine how weakening executive functions affects learning, and apply novel computational models to disentangle the learning processes.  A goal  is to establish a computational architecture to explain how executive function supports reinforcement learning processes. This project will significantly advance our understanding of the computational mechanisms that underly learning in humans. The project will highlight the importance of considering how different processes that contribute to learning interact, and the fact that even learning processes considered to be mostly automated depend on “intelligent” executive functions. This project has important broader implications to learning in everyday life as well as to the use of artificial intelligence in technological advances.  Future findings could help design more effective pedagogical approaches and lead to more adaptive and individualized teaching, impacting many domains where learning is essential, including education, public health, software design, with significant implications for individuals with learning impairments. Several young scientists will be trained during this project, in particular in highly sought computational modeling skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020844</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Collins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne G Collins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[annecollins@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000677515</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1608 4TH ST STE 201]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>127Y00</Code>
<Text>Sci of Lrng &amp; Augmented Intel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~248738</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~258146</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~265691</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Human learning is the result of a carefully orchestrated set of interacting cognitive processes. Some processes, like working memory, store information in a flexible format that is effortful to maintain and use. Other processes, like reinforcement learning, store information in a less flexible but more robust and virtually effortless format, encoding the value of actions. While working memory depends on executive functions, such as attention, reinforcement learning is typically thought of as a non-executive process that relies on lower level, less cognitive operations. However, it is unknown whether reinforcement learning is indeed independent of executive function. The contributions of executive functions to reinforcement learning have rarely been investigated because they are difficult to isolate.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>The goal of this project was to investigate the multiple roles executive processes play when biological agents such as humans or rodents use reward outcomes to learn what choices to make. The project led to multiple findings, which were disseminated to the public through peer reviewed publications, including original research articles, literature reviews, and opinion pieces; as well as many invited presentations at international conferences and colloquia in multiple countries. For example, we established that reinforcement learning processes cannot operate well without executive functions contributions to representing which state the learner is in, which options it is selecting from, and what its goals are. We also made progress in isolating the distinct processes that contribute to learning, showing that episodic memory (long term recall of very specific events) only minimally contributes to learning; furthermore, we developed a protocol to isolate and further characterize working memory in the context of learning, and ad different protocol to isolate habit-like processes as essential components of learning. &nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>The results of our project significantly improve our understanding of interacting processes in learning and pave the way for progress in cognitive neuroscience. Beyond our field, the results may have a broader impact in multiple domains. For example, understanding how humans learn efficiently could inform the development of more flexible and data-efficient artificial agents in the domains of artificial intelligence and robotics. Better understanding how humans learn could also help improve education and curriculum design, and support public health policies seeking to help citizens establish new habits across many domains. It could also help our understanding of learning differences in individuals in a normal spectrum as well as in individuals who show learning disabilities due to psychiatric or neurological conditions: indeed, identifying which specific processes may cause the differences could inform strategies to support learning.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>This project also provided many opportunities for training and professional development. Across the duration of the project, many trainees were fully or partially supported by the grant, and contributed to the project. In particular, four current of former post-doctoral fellows were involved (one of which is not assistant Professor at a research university); two former or current graduate students contributed to this research (one of which is now a post-doctoral fellow in a different lab); one staff research assistant and three senior thesis undergraduate students were supported (all of whom have now started graduate school); and multiple other undergraduate research assistants received research training, some of whom have gone on to graduate school.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/15/2024<br> Modified by: Anne&nbsp;G&nbsp;Collins</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Human learning is the result of a carefully orchestrated set of interacting cognitive processes. Some processes, like working memory, store information in a flexible format that is effortful to maintain and use. Other processes, like reinforcement learning, store information in a less flexible but more robust and virtually effortless format, encoding the value of actions. While working memory depends on executive functions, such as attention, reinforcement learning is typically thought of as a non-executive process that relies on lower level, less cognitive operations. However, it is unknown whether reinforcement learning is indeed independent of executive function. The contributions of executive functions to reinforcement learning have rarely been investigated because they are difficult to isolate.        The goal of this project was to investigate the multiple roles executive processes play when biological agents such as humans or rodents use reward outcomes to learn what choices to make. The project led to multiple findings, which were disseminated to the public through peer reviewed publications, including original research articles, literature reviews, and opinion pieces; as well as many invited presentations at international conferences and colloquia in multiple countries. For example, we established that reinforcement learning processes cannot operate well without executive functions contributions to representing which state the learner is in, which options it is selecting from, and what its goals are. We also made progress in isolating the distinct processes that contribute to learning, showing that episodic memory (long term recall of very specific events) only minimally contributes to learning; furthermore, we developed a protocol to isolate and further characterize working memory in the context of learning, and ad different protocol to isolate habit-like processes as essential components of learning.         The results of our project significantly improve our understanding of interacting processes in learning and pave the way for progress in cognitive neuroscience. Beyond our field, the results may have a broader impact in multiple domains. For example, understanding how humans learn efficiently could inform the development of more flexible and data-efficient artificial agents in the domains of artificial intelligence and robotics. Better understanding how humans learn could also help improve education and curriculum design, and support public health policies seeking to help citizens establish new habits across many domains. It could also help our understanding of learning differences in individuals in a normal spectrum as well as in individuals who show learning disabilities due to psychiatric or neurological conditions: indeed, identifying which specific processes may cause the differences could inform strategies to support learning.        This project also provided many opportunities for training and professional development. Across the duration of the project, many trainees were fully or partially supported by the grant, and contributed to the project. In particular, four current of former post-doctoral fellows were involved (one of which is not assistant Professor at a research university); two former or current graduate students contributed to this research (one of which is now a post-doctoral fellow in a different lab); one staff research assistant and three senior thesis undergraduate students were supported (all of whom have now started graduate school); and multiple other undergraduate research assistants received research training, some of whom have gone on to graduate school.         Last Modified: 12/15/2024       Submitted by: AnneGCollins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
