<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Scholars Award: From Wet Nursing to Milk Banks: A History of Nursing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>226228.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>226228</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christine Leuenberger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cleuenbe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927563</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Global health experts are concerned with low nursing rates and are seeking targeted interventions with the potential to substantially improve nursing practices, yet there have been few studies of the history of nursing or milk banking. This project investigates how scientists, medical practitioners, parents, and policy makers have produced diverse forms of knowledge about nursing from the 19th century to the present and how these various understandings have been challenged, upheld, and/or changed. It has five main goals: (1) examine the production and transformation of scientific knowledge about nursing; (2) explore the history of nursing techniques and technologies; (3) investigate changing understandings of the human labor involved in nursing; (4) consider racialized understanding of the labor involved in nursing; and, (5) trace the growth and development of milk banks. Overall, the project will contribute to understanding of why nursing is more or less common at different moments and for whom, and it will be useful for those involved in efforts to support maternal and infant health as it relates to nursing, milk banking, and the decisions families make vis-a-vis infant nutrition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project applies historical and qualitative analysis to archival materials and oral histories to examine nursing as intertwined with the histories of wet nursing and milk banking in relation to studies of carework and the commodification of biosubstances. In so doing, it provides a novel perspective on the relationship between racialized understandings of the forms of labor involved in nursing and the development of biobanking practices that depersonalize milk from the women who produce it. The project contributes to ongoing conversations in STS about the ways in which gender, race, and technology are co-constitutive; to historical and sociological studies of reproductive labor, intimate labor, and carework; to gender and women’s studies; and to histories of medicine, public health, labor, and gender.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020648</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victoria</FirstName>
<LastName>Langland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victoria Langland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[langland@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000753631</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 State St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y00</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~226228</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary outcome of this NSF STS Scholar&rsquo;s Award is an in-progress book manuscript,&nbsp;<em>From Wet Nursing to Milk Banks: A History of Nursing in Brazil, 1890-2010</em><em>.</em>&nbsp;</p> <p>The funded research sought to explicate the various ways that people fed their infants across an extended period of history, from the late 19<sup>th</sup> century to the early 21<sup>st</sup>, and how parents, policy makers and medical practitioners created and furthered ideas about infant nutrition and the labors of nursing and human milk extraction. At the book&rsquo;s outset in the 1890s, many elite Brazilian families considered lactation and maternal nursing to be a particularly debilitating form of gendered and racialized labor to which some women were ill disposed, routinely displacing nursing responsibilities onto enslaved or freed women of color as wet nurses. &nbsp;By the book&rsquo;s final chapters at the turn of the 21<sup>st</sup> century, Brazil had become widely known for its successful efforts to increase nursing rates nation-wide, and for the development of a national system of human milk banks, including the pioneering of low-cost technologies that helped facilitate this rise.&nbsp; The change from one set of understandings about lactation to the other, and the intervening shifts in popular and medical ideas and practices around infant feeding practices, motherhood, labor, gender, race, and the body, constituted some of the main foci of this research.</p> <p><em>From Wet Nurses to Milk Banks</em> will be the first full-length historical monograph on maternal nursing, wet nursing and human milk banking in Brazil, the first work to document and study the practice of wet nursing beyond the early twentieth century, and one of the first examples in the care work literature that takes on a sustained analysis of lactational labor. It will contribute to a dynamic and exciting wave of new historical studies on related topics such as histories of pregnancy, childbirth, contraception, abortion, neonatal death, paternity, and infanticide, and will reveal how deeply imbricated these topics are with the history of infant nutrition.&nbsp; On the one hand, the project will explicate aspects unique to Brazil, such as how popular and institutional support for human milk banking, human milk donation, and support for nursing workers developed and how ideas about lactation intersected with, buttressed or challenged configurations of gender, race, class and reproductive labor. On the other hand, it will illuminate transnational developments that impacted many areas beyond Brazil, especially the exchange of information among medical practitioners and policy makers, and the rise of a global market in infant formula. One of the book&rsquo;s broader goals is to showcase the complexities of human experiences with infant feeding across time.</p> <p>The NSF funded archival research at the Brazilian National Archives and National Library in Rio de Janeiro, and oral histories in Rio de Janeiro, supplementing previous research at the Instituto Fernandes Figueira, the Library of the Funda&ccedil;&atilde;o Oswaldo Cruz, the Martag&atilde;o Gesteira Hospital Archives, the U.S. National Library of Medicine, the New York Academy of Medicine and the U.S. Library of Congress.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Additional outcomes include six public presentations, including at two K-12 teacher-training workshops, and the incorporation of the research into a new undergraduate course at the University of Michigan, &ldquo;Maternal and Infant Health in Latin American History.&rdquo; The course exposes undergraduate students to the transformations and continuities in practices of maternal and infant health in the Latin American context.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 05/16/2024<br> Modified by: Victoria&nbsp;Langland</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The primary outcome of this NSF STS Scholars Award is an in-progress book manuscript,From Wet Nursing to Milk Banks: A History of Nursing in Brazil, 1890-2010.   The funded research sought to explicate the various ways that people fed their infants across an extended period of history, from the late 19th century to the early 21st, and how parents, policy makers and medical practitioners created and furthered ideas about infant nutrition and the labors of nursing and human milk extraction. At the books outset in the 1890s, many elite Brazilian families considered lactation and maternal nursing to be a particularly debilitating form of gendered and racialized labor to which some women were ill disposed, routinely displacing nursing responsibilities onto enslaved or freed women of color as wet nurses. By the books final chapters at the turn of the 21st century, Brazil had become widely known for its successful efforts to increase nursing rates nation-wide, and for the development of a national system of human milk banks, including the pioneering of low-cost technologies that helped facilitate this rise. The change from one set of understandings about lactation to the other, and the intervening shifts in popular and medical ideas and practices around infant feeding practices, motherhood, labor, gender, race, and the body, constituted some of the main foci of this research.   From Wet Nurses to Milk Banks will be the first full-length historical monograph on maternal nursing, wet nursing and human milk banking in Brazil, the first work to document and study the practice of wet nursing beyond the early twentieth century, and one of the first examples in the care work literature that takes on a sustained analysis of lactational labor. It will contribute to a dynamic and exciting wave of new historical studies on related topics such as histories of pregnancy, childbirth, contraception, abortion, neonatal death, paternity, and infanticide, and will reveal how deeply imbricated these topics are with the history of infant nutrition. On the one hand, the project will explicate aspects unique to Brazil, such as how popular and institutional support for human milk banking, human milk donation, and support for nursing workers developed and how ideas about lactation intersected with, buttressed or challenged configurations of gender, race, class and reproductive labor. On the other hand, it will illuminate transnational developments that impacted many areas beyond Brazil, especially the exchange of information among medical practitioners and policy makers, and the rise of a global market in infant formula. One of the books broader goals is to showcase the complexities of human experiences with infant feeding across time.   The NSF funded archival research at the Brazilian National Archives and National Library in Rio de Janeiro, and oral histories in Rio de Janeiro, supplementing previous research at the Instituto Fernandes Figueira, the Library of the Fundao Oswaldo Cruz, the Martago Gesteira Hospital Archives, the U.S. National Library of Medicine, the New York Academy of Medicine and the U.S. Library of Congress.    Additional outcomes include six public presentations, including at two K-12 teacher-training workshops, and the incorporation of the research into a new undergraduate course at the University of Michigan, Maternal and Infant Health in Latin American History. The course exposes undergraduate students to the transformations and continuities in practices of maternal and infant health in the Latin American context.           Last Modified: 05/16/2024       Submitted by: VictoriaLangland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
