<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[START International: Core Support from US Global Change Research Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2885998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1191061</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lina Patino</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lpatino@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925047</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support from the US Global Change Research Program for the Secretariat operations of the global change SysTem for Analysis, Research, and Training (START). This organization is an essential component of the US Global Change Research Program strategic plan as it relates to international engagement. Their mission "to increase opportunities for research, education and training that strengthen scientific capacities in developing countries to understand, communicate and motivate action on critical global change challenges" addresses all of the US Global Change Research Program strategic goals. The funding will enable START Secretariat to continue developing and implementing programs that advance research-driven capacity building in Africa and Asia. This approach emphasizes experiential learning by doing, particularly for early-career scientists, in which targeted skill building and networking opportunities are integrated into research on regional impacts and risks stemming from global change. The work focuses on critical challenges at the intersection of global/climate change and sustainable development, including disaster risk reduction, land-use/land-cover change, biodiversity conservation, urban development, human health, water resources management, and agriculture and food security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Padgham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon Padgham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jpadgham@start.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000597256</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Schweizer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah E Schweizer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sschweizer@start.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000737059</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[START International, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>FORT COLLINS</CityName>
<ZipCode>805211714</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024622213</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1236 COLUMBINE CT]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MWKDZBRKS2S9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>START INTERNATIONAL, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[START International, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200052001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1440 G St NW, office 9202]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>157700</Code>
<Text>GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>731300</Code>
<Text>Intl Global Change Res &amp; Coord</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1679</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7313</Code>
<Text>REGIONAL INST FOR GLOBAL CHANG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~321351</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~397000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~472710</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-fb529bfd-7fff-95de-fe0e-027997ddf23b" dir="ltr"><span>During this award period, core support for START International allowed it to carry out activities that further advanced the organization's mission to strengthen scientific capacities and science-society engagement. Each of these projects had a large number of partners, and partnerships ranged in scope from small universities through to UN programs. Capacity strengthening was an important throughline for all of these projects, as described below.</span></p>  <ul>  <li dir="ltr">  <p dir="ltr"><a href="https://start.org/programs/ldc_university_leadership_for_catalyzing_climate_adaptation_finance/"><span>Strengthening capacities on climate finance</span></a><span>: In partnership with UNEP and the Least Developed Country (LDC) University Consortium on Climate Change, START coordinated the work of a 13-country university network across Africa and South Asia dedicated to strengthening the ability of universities to advise their governments in accessing climate finance for adaptation. A key incentive for this work stems from the need to create an internally driven university-based alternative to the external-consultancy led model for generating access to climate finance in LDCs. During this reporting period, START led the creation of university-based think-tanks on climate finance in Uganda, Mozambique, Senegal, and Nepal, and coordinated development of five climate finance short-courses to support LDC university efforts to provide technical advice to their governments on climate finance.&nbsp;</span></p>  </li>  </ul>  <ul>  <li dir="ltr">  <p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.cascade.org.za/"><span>Strengthening partnerships on climate adaptation research</span></a><span>: START embarked on a collaboration with several African universities and the Red Cross/Red Crescent Climate Center on using transdisciplinary approaches to engage local communities in creating actionable research on climate change and health in African cities. This effort, through the CASCADE project, renews START's long-standing, productive relationships with African partners. Within this project period, START led training efforts to foster learning on transdisciplinary research skill development and science leadership in working at research-action interfaces. The training involved early- and mid-career researchers from five African cities. In addition, START is leading a small opportunity grant program to enable cross-learning and network development across the five cities.&nbsp;</span></p>  </li>  </ul>  <ul>  <li dir="ltr">  <p dir="ltr"><a href="https://start.org/programs/educational-partnerships-for-innovation-in-communities-network-epic-n/"><span>Strengthening the role of universities to engage local governments and communities</span></a><span>:&nbsp; START has a long-term partnership with the </span><a href="https://www.epicn.org/"><span>Educational Partnerships for Innovation in Communities</span></a><span> (EPIC) - Network. The EPIC model provides an innovative way to harness both university and municipal resources to address pressing local needs related to climate adaptation and resilient development, through fostering collaboration between local universities, communities and governments. Within this period, START initiated training on the EPIC model in African and Asian cities, and oversaw locally based EPIC projects in 8 African and 11 Asian cities related to climate adaptation, flood risk management, food systems and food security, and waste management.&nbsp;</span></p>  </li>  </ul>  <ul>  <li dir="ltr">  <p dir="ltr"><a href="https://gofcgold.umd.edu/"><span>Strengthening capacities to interpret and use remote sensing tools for land-use, land-cover change research</span></a><span>: Satellite images and remote sensing data provide critical information to better understand complex dynamics between forest cover, land-use change and climate change. In turn, this science helps to inform evidence-based decision making related to sustainably managing natural resources and developing appropriate climate adaptation and mitigation strategies. The Global Observations of Forest Cover and Land-use Dynamics (GOFC-GOLD) program addresses this critical need through a coordinated effort to broaden access to existing data and foster regional and international networks of scientists working on land cover and forest change issues. START has a long-term commitment to strengthening these capabilities through involvement in the GOFC-GOLD program administered by NASA. Within this period, START led coordination of regional scientific meetings and training in Central Asia, South Asia, Southeast Asia, and Latin America.&nbsp;</span></p>  </li>  </ul>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/25/2024<br> Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Schweizer</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  During this award period, core support for START International allowed it to carry out activities that further advanced the organization's mission to strengthen scientific capacities and science-society engagement. Each of these projects had a large number of partners, and partnerships ranged in scope from small universities through to UN programs. Capacity strengthening was an important throughline for all of these projects, as described below.        Strengthening capacities on climate finance: In partnership with UNEP and the Least Developed Country (LDC) University Consortium on Climate Change, START coordinated the work of a 13-country university network across Africa and South Asia dedicated to strengthening the ability of universities to advise their governments in accessing climate finance for adaptation. A key incentive for this work stems from the need to create an internally driven university-based alternative to the external-consultancy led model for generating access to climate finance in LDCs. During this reporting period, START led the creation of university-based think-tanks on climate finance in Uganda, Mozambique, Senegal, and Nepal, and coordinated development of five climate finance short-courses to support LDC university efforts to provide technical advice to their governments on climate finance.            Strengthening partnerships on climate adaptation research: START embarked on a collaboration with several African universities and the Red Cross/Red Crescent Climate Center on using transdisciplinary approaches to engage local communities in creating actionable research on climate change and health in African cities. This effort, through the CASCADE project, renews START's long-standing, productive relationships with African partners. Within this project period, START led training efforts to foster learning on transdisciplinary research skill development and science leadership in working at research-action interfaces. The training involved early- and mid-career researchers from five African cities. In addition, START is leading a small opportunity grant program to enable cross-learning and network development across the five cities.            Strengthening the role of universities to engage local governments and communities: START has a long-term partnership with the Educational Partnerships for Innovation in Communities (EPIC) - Network. The EPIC model provides an innovative way to harness both university and municipal resources to address pressing local needs related to climate adaptation and resilient development, through fostering collaboration between local universities, communities and governments. Within this period, START initiated training on the EPIC model in African and Asian cities, and oversaw locally based EPIC projects in 8 African and 11 Asian cities related to climate adaptation, flood risk management, food systems and food security, and waste management.            Strengthening capacities to interpret and use remote sensing tools for land-use, land-cover change research: Satellite images and remote sensing data provide critical information to better understand complex dynamics between forest cover, land-use change and climate change. In turn, this science helps to inform evidence-based decision making related to sustainably managing natural resources and developing appropriate climate adaptation and mitigation strategies. The Global Observations of Forest Cover and Land-use Dynamics (GOFC-GOLD) program addresses this critical need through a coordinated effort to broaden access to existing data and foster regional and international networks of scientists working on land cover and forest change issues. START has a long-term commitment to strengthening these capabilities through involvement in the GOFC-GOLD program administered by NASA. Within this period, START led coordination of regional scientific meetings and training in Central Asia, South Asia, Southeast Asia, and Latin America.             Last Modified: 11/25/2024       Submitted by: SarahESchweizer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
