<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Direct impacts of executive functions on language comprehension: Evidence from eye movements and electrophysiology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405348.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405348</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dwight Kravitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dkravitz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924502</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Human beings confront pervasive ambiguity in language as they listen and read. For example, two spoken words can sound nearly identical (e.g., “beach” and “peach”); sentences can be grammatically analyzed in multiple ways; and speech is often obscured by environmental sounds, as in a crowded restaurant. Although ambiguity routinely increases the risk of arriving at the wrong interpretation, or even no interpretation of a message, healthy young adults are marvelously adept at understanding language, vastly surpassing the capabilities of automatic systems despite major advances in machine learning. Explaining how humans understand language in the face of ambiguity, and why some populations fail, is a fundamental challenge for cognitive science, and is crucial for assisting people with language impairments that intensify under conditions of ambiguity, including stroke patients and healthy older adults with hearing loss. This research will use advanced neurophysiological and eye-tracking methods to illuminate how people regulate their interpretations of speech and language input by using executive functions (EF): the family of cognitive mechanisms that enable information processing in the brain and the flexible guidance of goal-directed behavior. EF are thought to be critical to helping people select among different interpretations of a sentence when more than one is possible, and for guiding the mind toward perceiving a word when the environment is “noisy.” However, the neural and cognitive mechanisms that allow EF to contribute to language comprehension are poorly understood. This project will elucidate EF’s role in language comprehension. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will test the hypothesis that two particular forms of executive function – attention control and cognitive control – play fundamental and distinct roles in supporting language comprehension in the face of ambiguity. Attention control is hypothesized to regulate the collection of information by directing perceptual processing toward the intended signal, isolating it from noise under suboptimal listening conditions. Cognitive control is hypothesized to assist the revision of misinterpretations by guiding internal representations to align with relevant sources of evidence when multiple cues compete. The investigators will use neural oscillatory activity in scalp-recorded EEG to provide novel markers of cognitive control and attention control during cognitive task performance. Eye-movement patterns will be used to track participants’ interpretations of language input in real time, by recording the millisecond-level dynamics of listeners’ gaze while they listen to sentences and interrogate a scene before them. The combination of EEG and eye tracking will provide a multi-modal characterization of the neural processes and temporal nature of interpretation procedures during language comprehension. In order to illuminate how attention and cognitive control separately affect humans’ ability to deal with ambiguity, the experiments will manipulate the engagement status of these EF subtypes just prior to processing language, by having participants perform tasks, such as the Flanker task, which are known to recruit cognitive-control processes. This experimental approach will establish causal relationships between EF and language processing and will identify the distinctive contributions of cognitive control and attention control to comprehension.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020932</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jared</FirstName>
<LastName>Novick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jared M Novick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jnovick1@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000513085</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BUILDING]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207423370</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>131100</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>169900</Code>
<Text>Cognitive Neuroscience</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>COGNEURO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~405348</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ed30424d-7fff-30c6-db6c-dca9e7134e20"> </span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project Overview</strong><span><br /></span><span>For most people, understanding language feels automatic and effortless. Yet this seemingly unremarkable ability relies on remarkably complex brain systems. The challenges of language processing become apparent when we attempt to understand a foreign language, navigate a conversation at a noisy party, or observe the struggles of individuals with neurological injuries affecting the brain&rsquo;s language networks. The research in this project advances our insight into the neural systems that support language comprehension, with a particular focus on how cognitive control enables us to interpret unclear or conflicting information&mdash;challenges&nbsp; that frequently arise in everyday communication.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Why cognitive control matters in language processing</strong><span><br /></span><span>Ambiguity is everywhere in language. For example, a sentence like &ldquo;The cat was chased by the mouse&rdquo; creates ambiguity about who is the chaser and who is being chased&mdash;Is it the mouse who is in pursuit, as the sentence suggests, or the cat, which seems more plausible? Failure to rapidly resolve this ambiguity during language processing can lead to comprehension errors, which are well-documented in neurological patients and in children learning language.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Our research shows how cognitive control&ndash;part of the brain&rsquo;s system for regulating thoughts and behaviors in order to achieve goals&mdash;plays an essential role in language comprehension by helping to select a single, most likely interpretation when ambiguity in the message causes multiple interpretations to arise. By tracking neural activity using scalp-recorded electroencephalography (EEG), we observed that when participants encountered conflicting interpretations while reading sentences, their brains exhibited a distinct pattern of oscillatory brain activity in the theta band (4-8 Hz); this is a well-established marker of cognitive control in neuroscience. This increase in theta activity provides a signal that cognitive control is actively responding to the conflict. Moreover, we&nbsp; discovered that the pattern of neural theta activity predicts whether participants will ultimately understand the sentence correctly. This finding highlights the fact that cognitive control is not only engaged during moments of ambiguity but that it plays a critical role in steering language users toward the correct meaning when information is unclear.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Notably, the theta activity pattern occurs quickly after conflict arises in the linguistic input&mdash;within just 300 milliseconds&mdash;underscoring the rapid dynamics of cognitive processing that contribute to language comprehension.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Our research precisely identifies when and how cognitive control contributes to language comprehension, pinpointing not only the aspects of language processing that require cognitive control but also those that do not, even when comprehension is difficult. For instance, sentences introducing unexpected or implausible meanings (e.g., &ldquo;The boy will eat the phone&rdquo;) elicit well-known brain activity signatures associated with semantic processing difficulty but do not show increased theta-band activity. Overall, our findings suggest that cognitive control is engaged </span><span>specifically</span><span> in situations where multiple interpretations compete, requiring the brain to decide which one makes the most sense. In contrast, other aspects of language comprehension, such as constructing creative interpretations for implausible sentences, can be challenging but may not necessarily rely on cognitive control.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impact and Future Directions</strong><span><br /></span><span>Why do these discoveries matter? Our findings have both scientific and practical significance. Our research matters because it advances basic scientific knowledge of how the brain works.&nbsp; Our findings about the role of cognitive control in language processing provide crucial insight into how human beings are able to understand language, which is riddled with ambiguity. We show that the same neural systems that are involved in helping us regulate behaviors are also important for regulating our interpretations of sentences. This discovery is fundamentally informative about both the nature of human language and about cognition more generally.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>But our findings also have important significance beyond the basic science. They have implications for clinical populations, such as people with aphasia or hearing loss, who often struggle with language comprehension when faced with conflicting or unclear information. Strengthening cognitive control could improve language processing in these individuals, opening pathways for targeted interventions.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>By identifying how and when cognitive control influences language comprehension, and when it does not, we can improve interventions for people with language-related challenges, such as those with cognitive impairments or communication disorders.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>Finally, these insights can inform the development of smarter language-processing technologies. In spite of profound advances in recent years, natural language processing technology continues to make glaring errors and to have substantial trouble with ambiguity in stimuli that humans can interpret easily. The key to superior technologies may lie in systems that mimic the human system&rsquo;s ability to resolve ambiguity.&nbsp;</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>In summary, understanding cognitive control&rsquo;s role in language comprehension holds great potential to enhance both human communication and the tools designed to support it.</span></p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/18/2024<br> Modified by: Jared&nbsp;M&nbsp;Novick</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       Project Overview For most people, understanding language feels automatic and effortless. Yet this seemingly unremarkable ability relies on remarkably complex brain systems. The challenges of language processing become apparent when we attempt to understand a foreign language, navigate a conversation at a noisy party, or observe the struggles of individuals with neurological injuries affecting the brains language networks. The research in this project advances our insight into the neural systems that support language comprehension, with a particular focus on how cognitive control enables us to interpret unclear or conflicting informationchallenges that frequently arise in everyday communication.    Why cognitive control matters in language processing Ambiguity is everywhere in language. For example, a sentence like The cat was chased by the mouse creates ambiguity about who is the chaser and who is being chasedIs it the mouse who is in pursuit, as the sentence suggests, or the cat, which seems more plausible? Failure to rapidly resolve this ambiguity during language processing can lead to comprehension errors, which are well-documented in neurological patients and in children learning language.    Our research shows how cognitive controlpart of the brains system for regulating thoughts and behaviors in order to achieve goalsplays an essential role in language comprehension by helping to select a single, most likely interpretation when ambiguity in the message causes multiple interpretations to arise. By tracking neural activity using scalp-recorded electroencephalography (EEG), we observed that when participants encountered conflicting interpretations while reading sentences, their brains exhibited a distinct pattern of oscillatory brain activity in the theta band (4-8 Hz); this is a well-established marker of cognitive control in neuroscience. This increase in theta activity provides a signal that cognitive control is actively responding to the conflict. Moreover, we discovered that the pattern of neural theta activity predicts whether participants will ultimately understand the sentence correctly. This finding highlights the fact that cognitive control is not only engaged during moments of ambiguity but that it plays a critical role in steering language users toward the correct meaning when information is unclear.    Notably, the theta activity pattern occurs quickly after conflict arises in the linguistic inputwithin just 300 millisecondsunderscoring the rapid dynamics of cognitive processing that contribute to language comprehension.    Our research precisely identifies when and how cognitive control contributes to language comprehension, pinpointing not only the aspects of language processing that require cognitive control but also those that do not, even when comprehension is difficult. For instance, sentences introducing unexpected or implausible meanings (e.g., The boy will eat the phone) elicit well-known brain activity signatures associated with semantic processing difficulty but do not show increased theta-band activity. Overall, our findings suggest that cognitive control is engaged specifically in situations where multiple interpretations compete, requiring the brain to decide which one makes the most sense. In contrast, other aspects of language comprehension, such as constructing creative interpretations for implausible sentences, can be challenging but may not necessarily rely on cognitive control.    Broader Impact and Future Directions Why do these discoveries matter? Our findings have both scientific and practical significance. Our research matters because it advances basic scientific knowledge of how the brain works. Our findings about the role of cognitive control in language processing provide crucial insight into how human beings are able to understand language, which is riddled with ambiguity. We show that the same neural systems that are involved in helping us regulate behaviors are also important for regulating our interpretations of sentences. This discovery is fundamentally informative about both the nature of human language and about cognition more generally.    But our findings also have important significance beyond the basic science. They have implications for clinical populations, such as people with aphasia or hearing loss, who often struggle with language comprehension when faced with conflicting or unclear information. Strengthening cognitive control could improve language processing in these individuals, opening pathways for targeted interventions.    By identifying how and when cognitive control influences language comprehension, and when it does not, we can improve interventions for people with language-related challenges, such as those with cognitive impairments or communication disorders.    Finally, these insights can inform the development of smarter language-processing technologies. In spite of profound advances in recent years, natural language processing technology continues to make glaring errors and to have substantial trouble with ambiguity in stimuli that humans can interpret easily. The key to superior technologies may lie in systems that mimic the human systems ability to resolve ambiguity.    In summary, understanding cognitive controls role in language comprehension holds great potential to enhance both human communication and the tools designed to support it.             Last Modified: 12/18/2024       Submitted by: JaredMNovick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
