<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: The Antarctic Circumpolar Current: A Conduit or Blender of Antarctic Bottom Waters?]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>263756.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>263756</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Gast</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rgast@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Part 1: Because of the manner in which it is formed at high latitudes in the Antarctic ice, Antarctic Bottom Water (AABW) is the coldest, saltiest and densest water on the planet. The global circulation of is often quantiﬁed via the transport in a two-dimensional, latitude/depth coordinate space.  However, AABW formation, northward ﬂow and distribution between the Atlantic, Indian and Paciﬁc basins are fundamentally three-dimensional processes. AABW is formed in a handful of distinct sites around the Antarctic coast, notably the southern Weddell Sea, the western Ross Sea, along the  Ad´elie  coast, and  in  Prydz  Bay. AABW is one of the key components of the global ocean overturning circulation, and plays a critical role in regulating Earth's climate, on multi-decadal-to-millennial time scales. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2: Mapping of AABW transport to northern basins is not well constrained, with conflicting conclusions drawn in previous studies. At one extreme  the ACC has been suggested to be a “conduit" that simply allows each variety of AABW to transit directly northward. At the other extreme, it has been suggested that the ACC “blends" all shelf AABW sources together before they reach the northern basins. To close the gap in understanding, this collaborative project draws on three complementary analytical tools: process-oriented modeling of AABW export across the ACC, a high-resolution global ocean model, and an observationally-constrained estimate of the global circulation. The proposed identification and mechanistic understanding of AABW pathways. This project will also advance the careers of three postdoctoral researchers and two early-career faculty members, and will continue collaborative links between the PI and a foreign investigator.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023259</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew F Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andrewt@caltech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000597274</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E CALIFORNIA BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U2JMKHNS5TG4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E California Blvd, M C 131-]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>511300</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~263756</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The margins of Antarctica play an important role in the global  circulation of the ocean. Around the coast of Antarctica, the  combination of surface cooling and the formation of sea ice leads to the  formation of a cold and salty water mass, called Antarctic Bottom Water  (<span><span>AABW</span></span>), that is dense enough to sink to the bottom of the ocean and fill most of the global deep ocean. This source of <span><span>AABW</span></span> to the abyss is a major driver of the recirculation of global ocean currents, known as the overturning circulation.  The overturning circulation determines the timescale over which deep  waters and their properties, such as heat, nutrient and carbon content,  are stored away from the surface and exchange with the atmosphere.  Similar to the North Atlantic, processes that set the formation rate of <span><span>AABW</span></span> are changing due our evolving climate system. However, the impact of these changes on the export of <span><span>AABW</span></span> and associated modifications to local and global circulation features remains critically under-explored.&#8232;&#8232;<br /><br />Our  NSF-supported project, "The Antarctic Circumpolar Current: A Conduit or  Blender of Antarctic Bottom Waters?" addressed multiple topics related  to both the changes that may occur around the Antarctic margins and how  they might be monitored. First, we used a realistic global ocean model to track the pathways by which <span><span>AABW</span></span>,  formed along the coast, is exported to the global ocean. This was  accomplished by releasing numerical tracers -- essentially "dye" that is  carried and mixed by the model currents -- in the simulation and  tracking their evolution over many years. Although <span><span>AABW</span></span> is formed in four distinct geographical regions, we found that <span><span>AABW</span></span> is only exported via two major pathways. The knowledge that certain <span><span>AABW</span></span> sources are blended before they cross the Southern Ocean is critical  for identifying changes to waters formed in regions that are difficult  to observe directly due to their remote location and harsh conditions.&#8232;&#8232;<br /><br />There  has been substantial research by the oceanography and climate  communities on how the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (<span><span>AMOC</span></span>) will respond to a warming climate. The <span><span>AMOC</span></span> is responsible for bringing relatively warm waters to high latitudes in the Atlantic basins, and thus a shut-down of the <span><span>AMOC</span></span> would have substantial impact on sea ice conditions, ecosystems, and global climate. Recent work has suggested that a similar reduction in the production of <span><span>AABW</span></span> could result in a weakening of the <span><span>overturning's</span></span> lower cell. The impact of these potential changes on local circulation  features within the Southern Ocean, such as boundary currents over the  Antarctic shelf and slope, as well as the Antarctic Circumpolar Current,  the largest and strongest current in the global ocean, has received substantially less attention.<br /><br /> In  the latter half of this project, we have used a range of numerical  models to address how the Antarctic margins both respond to changes  related to a warming climate and how they might precipitate larger-scale  overturning transitions. These models have spanned more idealized  approaches that isolate key physical processes to more complex and  realistic models that simulate processes for which there does not exist a  deep understanding. For the idealized approach, we intentionally  targeted a simplified representation of West Antarctic coastal ocean  dynamics to highlight mechanistic links between surface forcing,  interior mixing, stratification changes, and overturning pathways on the  West Antarctic continental shelf. We showed that processes occurring  near the coast, such as mixing and convection associated with <span><span>AABW</span></span> formation, can impact shelf stratification and boundary currents around  Antarctica. Finally, we identified a positive feedback to ice-shelf  mass loss that can not be represented in ocean models that apply fixed <span><span>meltwater</span></span> inputs. This emphasizes the need to utilize models that directly  simulate ocean-ice interactions and the evolving melt at the base of  floating ice shelves. Thus, for the final stage of this project we  carried out the first study that estimates how Antarctica will respond  to climate warming with numerical experiments that couple ocean  circulation and ice-shelf melt. The response of the Antarctic margins  were found to occur across multiple timescales. First, there is an  initial increase in ice-shelf melt simply due to oceanic heat uptake.  However, the introduction of this increased melt over the continental  shelf modifies the density structure and can strengthen currents that  may ultimately suppress the transport of warm water towards the coast.  This study also has implications for targeting future observational  efforts that can (i) identify the first signs of abrupt changes to the  Southern Ocean overturning circulation and (i) provide data needed to  validate models and reduce uncertainty in future predictions.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/28/2024<br> Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;F&nbsp;Thompson</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The margins of Antarctica play an important role in the global  circulation of the ocean. Around the coast of Antarctica, the  combination of surface cooling and the formation of sea ice leads to the  formation of a cold and salty water mass, called Antarctic Bottom Water  (AABW), that is dense enough to sink to the bottom of the ocean and fill most of the global deep ocean. This source of AABW to the abyss is a major driver of the recirculation of global ocean currents, known as the overturning circulation.  The overturning circulation determines the timescale over which deep  waters and their properties, such as heat, nutrient and carbon content,  are stored away from the surface and exchange with the atmosphere.  Similar to the North Atlantic, processes that set the formation rate of AABW are changing due our evolving climate system. However, the impact of these changes on the export of AABW and associated modifications to local and global circulation features remains critically under-explored.&#8232;&#8232;  Our  NSF-supported project, "The Antarctic Circumpolar Current: A Conduit or  Blender of Antarctic Bottom Waters?" addressed multiple topics related  to both the changes that may occur around the Antarctic margins and how  they might be monitored. First, we used a realistic global ocean model to track the pathways by which AABW,  formed along the coast, is exported to the global ocean. This was  accomplished by releasing numerical tracers -- essentially "dye" that is  carried and mixed by the model currents -- in the simulation and  tracking their evolution over many years. Although AABW is formed in four distinct geographical regions, we found that AABW is only exported via two major pathways. The knowledge that certain AABW sources are blended before they cross the Southern Ocean is critical  for identifying changes to waters formed in regions that are difficult  to observe directly due to their remote location and harsh conditions.&#8232;&#8232;  There  has been substantial research by the oceanography and climate  communities on how the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) will respond to a warming climate. The AMOC is responsible for bringing relatively warm waters to high latitudes in the Atlantic basins, and thus a shut-down of the AMOC would have substantial impact on sea ice conditions, ecosystems, and global climate. Recent work has suggested that a similar reduction in the production of AABW could result in a weakening of the overturning's lower cell. The impact of these potential changes on local circulation  features within the Southern Ocean, such as boundary currents over the  Antarctic shelf and slope, as well as the Antarctic Circumpolar Current,  the largest and strongest current in the global ocean, has received substantially less attention.   In  the latter half of this project, we have used a range of numerical  models to address how the Antarctic margins both respond to changes  related to a warming climate and how they might precipitate larger-scale  overturning transitions. These models have spanned more idealized  approaches that isolate key physical processes to more complex and  realistic models that simulate processes for which there does not exist a  deep understanding. For the idealized approach, we intentionally  targeted a simplified representation of West Antarctic coastal ocean  dynamics to highlight mechanistic links between surface forcing,  interior mixing, stratification changes, and overturning pathways on the  West Antarctic continental shelf. We showed that processes occurring  near the coast, such as mixing and convection associated with AABW formation, can impact shelf stratification and boundary currents around  Antarctica. Finally, we identified a positive feedback to ice-shelf  mass loss that can not be represented in ocean models that apply fixed meltwater inputs. This emphasizes the need to utilize models that directly  simulate ocean-ice interactions and the evolving melt at the base of  floating ice shelves. Thus, for the final stage of this project we  carried out the first study that estimates how Antarctica will respond  to climate warming with numerical experiments that couple ocean  circulation and ice-shelf melt. The response of the Antarctic margins  were found to occur across multiple timescales. First, there is an  initial increase in ice-shelf melt simply due to oceanic heat uptake.  However, the introduction of this increased melt over the continental  shelf modifies the density structure and can strengthen currents that  may ultimately suppress the transport of warm water towards the coast.  This study also has implications for targeting future observational  efforts that can (i) identify the first signs of abrupt changes to the  Southern Ocean overturning circulation and (i) provide data needed to  validate models and reduce uncertainty in future predictions.     Last Modified: 12/28/2024       Submitted by: AndrewFThompson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
