<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Advancing the Use of Professional Decision-Making Strategies in a Culturally Diverse Research Community]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>396599.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>396599</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jason D. Borenstein</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jborenst@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924207</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Contemporary science is a global enterprise. International research collaborations continue to increase with globalization and as research becomes more complex and specialized. In the United States (U.S.), international researchers, especially from East Asian countries (e.g., China, Taiwan, Korea, Japan), make up a large portion of the research workforce. Researchers from different cultures may take different approaches to problems depending on their cultural upbringing. Decision-making strategies help researchers navigate complex and ambiguous professional and ethical problems they face throughout their careers. Yet, there is little evidence of how cultural upbringing shapes the approaches researchers take when making decisions about ethical problems in research. Educational approaches to fostering responsible conduct of research (RCR) in the U.S. have generally overlooked this issue as well. There is an urgent need to examine cultural differences in decision making and develop RCR training that is more culturally inclusive and effective for researchers from Eastern and Western cultural backgrounds. The goal of the present project is to identify and understand the similarities and differences in decision-making strategies among East Asian and U.S. researchers and use this knowledge to refine and evaluate the effectiveness of a culturally inclusive RCR training curriculum focused on decision-making skills. Data from this project will foster awareness of the perspectives of East Asian researchers. This awareness will contribute to improved communication, problem solving, and conflict resolution skills among researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses three objectives: 1) identify similarities and differences in ethical and professional decision-making strategies among East Asian and U.S. researchers using qualitative think-aloud interviews, 2) refine and deliver a culturally inclusive RCR training curriculum and assess the learning outcomes of decision-making strategies, behavioral indicators of strategy use, and implementation intentions, and 3) evaluate whether participants in the refined RCR training apply decision-making strategies in their daily research activities and test the effect of a monthly learning transfer intervention on strategy use over time. A vignette-based measure of professional decision-making in research will be completed by hundreds of U.S. and East Asian faculty, postdoctoral researchers, and graduate students. In-depth interviews will then be conducted with U.S. and East Asian researchers with both low and high scores on the professional-decision making measure to ensure a comprehensive range of perspectives about strategies for approaching decision-making. Data from interviews will then be used to refine, deliver, and evaluate a RCR training program that will be delivered to multiple cohorts of students. Longitudinal data will be collected from RCR training program participants to determine the effects of the refined RCR training and a learning transfer intervention on learning outcomes and behavior. Overall, greater awareness of cultural influences on the workplace perspectives and behaviors of researchers lays the groundwork for open dialogue among the research community and strengthening research, teaching, and community roles that researchers play in society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal was funded through the ER2 program by the SBE Directorate and Office of International Science and Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024345</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tristan</FirstName>
<LastName>McIntosh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tristan McIntosh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[t.mcintosh@wustl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796578</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alison</FirstName>
<LastName>Antes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alison L Antes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aantes@wustl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000797846</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 BROOKINGS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L6NFUM28LQM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[CAMPUS BOX 1054]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>129Y00</Code>
<Text>ER2-Ethical &amp; Responsible Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~396599</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ethical decision-making skills help create an ethical research workplace, which is essential for encouraging responsible scientific behavior and shared ethical norms among the scientific community. These skills help offset the potential harmful influence of self-serving biases, stress, and emotions which are likely to be activated when faced with an ethical or professional dilemma. Responsible Conduct of Research (RCR) education aims to enhance knowledge, skills, and attitudes related to ethical practices in scientific research. However, the effectiveness of RCR education and the best approaches to achieving its goals have been the subject of debate within the scientific community. Research shows that RCR education has improved in recent years, yet there is still variability in its effectiveness.</p>  <p>One possible reason for this variability is the lack of culturally inclusive content and approaches to RCR education, especially considering that the research workforce is becoming increasingly multicultural. That is, people from different cultural backgrounds might interpret, make assumptions about, and respond to ethical and professional challenges in different ways. RCR content that addresses this variety in approaches to navigating such challenges can be beneficial and impactful for researchers from diverse backgrounds.</p>  <p>There is also limited data about the long-term effectiveness of RCR education initiatives and factors that support the transfer of learning from formal training to real-world settings. Designing learning transfer interventions that prompt reflection on the use of professional decision-making skills may help reinforce intentions to implement those skills.</p>  <p>The goals of this project were to 1) learn more about the ethical decision-making processes used by researchers from diverse cultural backgrounds in their scientific workplace, 2) use that knowledge to revise content of an RCR course for doctoral students that emphasizes development of professional decision-making skills and test the effectiveness of this improved content on professional decision-making skills, and 3) examine the impact of a 5-month learning transfer exercise on professional decision-making skills after the formal RCR course concluded.</p>  <p>We first interviewed 66 researchers who were graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, or faculty at a large research-intensive university about their decision-making processes when faced with ethical and professional challenges. Half of these researchers were originally from East Asia and were working in the United States (US), while the other half were originally from the US. We presented them with three hypothetical scenarios and asked them to tell us how they would handle the situation, as well as how they felt about different ways the situation could be handled. We found both similarities and differences in approaches between the two groups. Two major differences pertained to managing emotions and seeking help. Participants from East Asia tended to not want to be perceived as emotional and prioritized acting objectively, rationally, and quickly. US participants were keener to express emotions. Participants from East Asia were more likely to problem solve by talking to those directly involved with a situation, whereas participants from the US were more likely to seek advice from a colleague external to the situation.</p>  <p>We used what we learned from the interviews to make changes to an RCR course for doctoral-level graduate students. These changes focused on proactively addressing assumptions people tend to have about the professional decision-making strategies taught in the course (i.e., seeking help, managing emotions, anticipating consequences, recognizing context, and testing assumptions). We found that the revised RCR course content was more effective at improving professional decision-making skills compared to the original unrevised content.</p>  <p>There was no significant benefit of the monthly learning transfer intervention on professional decision-making skills in the long-term (i.e., 6 months after the conclusion of the RCR course). Interviews with a small subset of those who participated in the learning transfer exercise provided some modest support for the value of periodic reflection on skills after formal training. Notably, among individuals who had less developed professional decision-making skills before the course, we found statistically significant increases in their skills after the course, and these gains were maintained at 6 months. Those who already had high levels of professional decision-making skills before the course did demonstrate gains immediately after the course, but those gains were not sustained in the long-term; instead, their skills returned to their initial levels.</p>  <p>Leaders of RCR initiatives at universities can use what was learned from this project to make improvements to current approaches to RCR training. These leaders may also want to invest in identifying strategies that increase the perceived need to adopt and apply professional decision-making skills after training. It is possible that trainees may not be sufficiently motivated to adopt new strategies and skills, especially graduate students early on in their scientific careers. Perhaps trainees at this stage have not yet experienced major professional challenges, or they may not have sufficiently developed the skills to identify problems that require application of decision-making skills.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/20/2024<br> Modified by: Tristan&nbsp;Mcintosh</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Ethical decision-making skills help create an ethical research workplace, which is essential for encouraging responsible scientific behavior and shared ethical norms among the scientific community. These skills help offset the potential harmful influence of self-serving biases, stress, and emotions which are likely to be activated when faced with an ethical or professional dilemma. Responsible Conduct of Research (RCR) education aims to enhance knowledge, skills, and attitudes related to ethical practices in scientific research. However, the effectiveness of RCR education and the best approaches to achieving its goals have been the subject of debate within the scientific community. Research shows that RCR education has improved in recent years, yet there is still variability in its effectiveness.    One possible reason for this variability is the lack of culturally inclusive content and approaches to RCR education, especially considering that the research workforce is becoming increasingly multicultural. That is, people from different cultural backgrounds might interpret, make assumptions about, and respond to ethical and professional challenges in different ways. RCR content that addresses this variety in approaches to navigating such challenges can be beneficial and impactful for researchers from diverse backgrounds.    There is also limited data about the long-term effectiveness of RCR education initiatives and factors that support the transfer of learning from formal training to real-world settings. Designing learning transfer interventions that prompt reflection on the use of professional decision-making skills may help reinforce intentions to implement those skills.    The goals of this project were to 1) learn more about the ethical decision-making processes used by researchers from diverse cultural backgrounds in their scientific workplace, 2) use that knowledge to revise content of an RCR course for doctoral students that emphasizes development of professional decision-making skills and test the effectiveness of this improved content on professional decision-making skills, and 3) examine the impact of a 5-month learning transfer exercise on professional decision-making skills after the formal RCR course concluded.    We first interviewed 66 researchers who were graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, or faculty at a large research-intensive university about their decision-making processes when faced with ethical and professional challenges. Half of these researchers were originally from East Asia and were working in the United States (US), while the other half were originally from the US. We presented them with three hypothetical scenarios and asked them to tell us how they would handle the situation, as well as how they felt about different ways the situation could be handled. We found both similarities and differences in approaches between the two groups. Two major differences pertained to managing emotions and seeking help. Participants from East Asia tended to not want to be perceived as emotional and prioritized acting objectively, rationally, and quickly. US participants were keener to express emotions. Participants from East Asia were more likely to problem solve by talking to those directly involved with a situation, whereas participants from the US were more likely to seek advice from a colleague external to the situation.    We used what we learned from the interviews to make changes to an RCR course for doctoral-level graduate students. These changes focused on proactively addressing assumptions people tend to have about the professional decision-making strategies taught in the course (i.e., seeking help, managing emotions, anticipating consequences, recognizing context, and testing assumptions). We found that the revised RCR course content was more effective at improving professional decision-making skills compared to the original unrevised content.    There was no significant benefit of the monthly learning transfer intervention on professional decision-making skills in the long-term (i.e., 6 months after the conclusion of the RCR course). Interviews with a small subset of those who participated in the learning transfer exercise provided some modest support for the value of periodic reflection on skills after formal training. Notably, among individuals who had less developed professional decision-making skills before the course, we found statistically significant increases in their skills after the course, and these gains were maintained at 6 months. Those who already had high levels of professional decision-making skills before the course did demonstrate gains immediately after the course, but those gains were not sustained in the long-term; instead, their skills returned to their initial levels.    Leaders of RCR initiatives at universities can use what was learned from this project to make improvements to current approaches to RCR training. These leaders may also want to invest in identifying strategies that increase the perceived need to adopt and apply professional decision-making skills after training. It is possible that trainees may not be sufficiently motivated to adopt new strategies and skills, especially graduate students early on in their scientific careers. Perhaps trainees at this stage have not yet experienced major professional challenges, or they may not have sufficiently developed the skills to identify problems that require application of decision-making skills.     Last Modified: 12/20/2024       Submitted by: TristanMcintosh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
