<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SG: A revised classification of the flowering plant family Cleomaceae as a tool to understand drivers of diversification]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199072.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199072</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carolyn J. Ferguson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cferguso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922689</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project creates a reorganized classification of the flowering plant family Cleomaceae based on new genomic data and a new assessment of physical characteristics of the plants. The classification and associated hypotheses of relationships among lineages will provide a critical and foundational framework for studies of physiology, development, and genome structure in the family. It will also contribute to the evaluation of fossil seeds that are thought to belong to this plant group, enabling improved estimates of the ages of lineages in the family. The advancement of knowledge inherent to this project particularly contributes to society by providing a standardized classification for organizing our understanding of these plants. This is foundational knowledge for horticultural use, identification manuals, conservation studies, and many other applications by scientists and the general public. It will also provide training for one graduate student researcher at Washington State University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses DNA sequence data and morphology to create revised hypotheses of the major lineages in the family and will complete the ongoing revision of the classification of these lineages. One specific goal of this project is to create a robust phylogenetic hypothesis of the relationships among major lineages of Cleomaceae. The goal of the project is to use near-complete species-level sampling and new genomic data to place all or nearly all species in currently recognized or newly identified lineages. Researchers will sequence about 290 species, or ~90% of the taxonomic diversity of the family. The second major goal of the project is to use the phylogeny to revise the classification of Cleomaceae. Once lineages are resolved, it will be necessary to identify structural characteristics that can be used to define these lineages and assign valid names to the groups. New micromorphological characters from seeds and pollen will be investigated, and these as well as additional macromorphological characters will be evaluated for potential to define lineages. The goal is to create a classification of Cleomaceae that is predictive, practical, and robust. This revised classification will provide an invaluable framework for comparative studies of physiology, floral development, and genome structure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025224</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Roalson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric H Roalson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[roalson@mail.wsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000368192</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington State University]]></Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>991640001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[240 FRENCH ADMINISTRATION BLDG]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XRJSGX384TD6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>991644236</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>737400</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199072</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cleomaceae, the spider&#8208;flower family, includes 29 genera (groups of closely related species) and ~270 species, and includes annual and perennial herbaceous plants, woody shrubs, and small trees. The family is found in tropical, desert, and warm temperate regions of all continents, excluding Antarctica. Cleomaceae is closely related to the mustard family, a group that has become essential in studies of plant evolution, genetics, physiology, and plant&#8208;microbe interactions because it contains the model organism <em>Arabidopsis thaliana</em> and important crop species. As the plant family that is closest to the mustards, Cleomaceae offers important opportunities to extend knowledge learned from model organisms to other groups. The spider-flower family contains species with a variety of photosynthetic pathways (ways of capturing sunlight for energy), making it an important model of photosynthetic pathway evolution. The observed polyploidy (duplication of genetic material in organisms) and hypothesized hybridization among species in Cleomaceae suggest that it is a good group in which to study the impacts of hybridization on species boundaries and diversification. Cleomaceae species also vary widely in the structure of their flowers and so provide the opportunity to study how these changes arise through time and might be important for the diversification process.</p> <p>This project focused on 5 major components: (1) understanding patterns of diversification, (2) understanding seed variation, (3) understanding fine-scale patterns of relationship in some clades, (4) revising the classification of species, and (5) contributing th our understanding of genome structure.</p> <p>(1) We sequenced more than 300 DNA regions for ~90% of the species in the family to understand this diversification process. This provided a much more robust overall hypothesis of diversification of the family, and it provides the structure and context for the rest of the studies in the project.</p> <p>(2) We created high resolution images of the seeds of most species to be able to better characterize the natural variation in seed characteristics and what they tell us about how species are related and adapt to different environments. We compared these seed images to seed fossils to understand better how seeds have changed through time, and to create hypotheses of how the family has become distributed around the world over the past ~55 million years. All of the known fossils from the Cleomaceae are seed fossils and connecting these fossils to the lineages of the family helps us understand the diversification process.</p> <p>(3) Some of the groups within the family were sequenced in more detail (sequences of many individuals per species) to understand how species can be differentiated. These studies of fine-scale relationships in some parts of the family clarify how species can be differentiated where there is uncertainty about species boundaries, and, particularly, how hybridization between species might influence species distinctness. This has been a particular issue in some of the groups found in the Andes Mountains of South America. Our results suggest that despite the occasional occurrence of hybridization, there are clear genetic differences among most of the species, and they can be differentiated based on both their genetic characteristics as well as their physical (morphological) characteristics.</p> <p>(4) One of the important outcomes of this project is the revision of how the species in the family are classified woldwide, something that has not been addressed in almost 90 years. Revising the classification will provide for a consistent framework for future studies of members of the family, and it will provide the structure for tools we are developing to identify species. This will be important for studies across biology to use a shared framework for information about species in the family. This revised classification has also helped clarify how some of the historical names have been used, and to clarify what the correct name is of various species where there was uncertainty.</p> <p>(5) This project has also countributed to our knowledge of how whole genomes change through time and how genome structure influences plant function through contributions to a broader collaborative project where we sequenced the entire genome of one of the Cleomaceae species, <em>Cleomella arborea</em>. This genome will help us understand how genomes change through time and contribute to the distinctive characteristics of lineages in the family and the broader group known as the Brassicales. We are comparing the genome to the three other sequenced genomes in the family as part of this research.</p> <p>In all, this project has redefined our understanding of this group of plants, contributed resources that will allow for a better understanding of how species are related to each other, created identification resources for anyone interested in trying to identify species world-wide, standardized the classification of species for the entire family, and contributed to a variety of research studies on different characteristics of the family.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/14/2024<br> Modified by: Eric&nbsp;H&nbsp;Roalson</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Cleomaceae, the spider&#8208;flower family, includes 29 genera (groups of closely related species) and ~270 species, and includes annual and perennial herbaceous plants, woody shrubs, and small trees. The family is found in tropical, desert, and warm temperate regions of all continents, excluding Antarctica. Cleomaceae is closely related to the mustard family, a group that has become essential in studies of plant evolution, genetics, physiology, and plant&#8208;microbe interactions because it contains the model organism Arabidopsis thaliana and important crop species. As the plant family that is closest to the mustards, Cleomaceae offers important opportunities to extend knowledge learned from model organisms to other groups. The spider-flower family contains species with a variety of photosynthetic pathways (ways of capturing sunlight for energy), making it an important model of photosynthetic pathway evolution. The observed polyploidy (duplication of genetic material in organisms) and hypothesized hybridization among species in Cleomaceae suggest that it is a good group in which to study the impacts of hybridization on species boundaries and diversification. Cleomaceae species also vary widely in the structure of their flowers and so provide the opportunity to study how these changes arise through time and might be important for the diversification process.   This project focused on 5 major components: (1) understanding patterns of diversification, (2) understanding seed variation, (3) understanding fine-scale patterns of relationship in some clades, (4) revising the classification of species, and (5) contributing th our understanding of genome structure.   (1) We sequenced more than 300 DNA regions for ~90% of the species in the family to understand this diversification process. This provided a much more robust overall hypothesis of diversification of the family, and it provides the structure and context for the rest of the studies in the project.   (2) We created high resolution images of the seeds of most species to be able to better characterize the natural variation in seed characteristics and what they tell us about how species are related and adapt to different environments. We compared these seed images to seed fossils to understand better how seeds have changed through time, and to create hypotheses of how the family has become distributed around the world over the past ~55 million years. All of the known fossils from the Cleomaceae are seed fossils and connecting these fossils to the lineages of the family helps us understand the diversification process.   (3) Some of the groups within the family were sequenced in more detail (sequences of many individuals per species) to understand how species can be differentiated. These studies of fine-scale relationships in some parts of the family clarify how species can be differentiated where there is uncertainty about species boundaries, and, particularly, how hybridization between species might influence species distinctness. This has been a particular issue in some of the groups found in the Andes Mountains of South America. Our results suggest that despite the occasional occurrence of hybridization, there are clear genetic differences among most of the species, and they can be differentiated based on both their genetic characteristics as well as their physical (morphological) characteristics.   (4) One of the important outcomes of this project is the revision of how the species in the family are classified woldwide, something that has not been addressed in almost 90 years. Revising the classification will provide for a consistent framework for future studies of members of the family, and it will provide the structure for tools we are developing to identify species. This will be important for studies across biology to use a shared framework for information about species in the family. This revised classification has also helped clarify how some of the historical names have been used, and to clarify what the correct name is of various species where there was uncertainty.   (5) This project has also countributed to our knowledge of how whole genomes change through time and how genome structure influences plant function through contributions to a broader collaborative project where we sequenced the entire genome of one of the Cleomaceae species, Cleomella arborea. This genome will help us understand how genomes change through time and contribute to the distinctive characteristics of lineages in the family and the broader group known as the Brassicales. We are comparing the genome to the three other sequenced genomes in the family as part of this research.   In all, this project has redefined our understanding of this group of plants, contributed resources that will allow for a better understanding of how species are related to each other, created identification resources for anyone interested in trying to identify species world-wide, standardized the classification of species for the entire family, and contributed to a variety of research studies on different characteristics of the family.     Last Modified: 10/14/2024       Submitted by: EricHRoalson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
