<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[LTER: Ecological Response and Resilience to “Press-Pulse” Disturbances and a Recent Decadal Reversal in Sea Ice Trends Along the West Antarctic Peninsula]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2374386.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2374386</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Ambrose</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wambrose@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928048</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Part 1: Non-technical description &lt;br/&gt;The goal of all LTER sites is to conduct policy-relevant ecosystem research for questions that require tens of years of data and cover large geographical areas. The Palmer Antarctica Long Term Ecological Research (PAL-LTER) site has been in operation since 1990 and has been studying how the marine ecosystem west of the Antarctica Peninsula (WAP) is responding to a climate that is changing as rapidly as any place on the Earth. The study is evaluating how warming conditions and decreased ice cover leading to extended periods of open water are affecting many aspects of ecosystem function. The team is using combined cutting-edge approaches including yearly ship-based research cruises, small-boat weekly sampling, autonomous vehicles, animal biologging, oceanographic floats and seafloor moorings, manipulative lab-based process studies and modeling to evaluate both seasonal and annual ecosystem responses. These combined approaches are allowing for the study the ecosystem changes at scales needed to assess both short-term and long-term drivers. The study region also includes submarine canyons that are special regions of enhanced biological activity within the WAP. This research program is paired with a comprehensive education and outreach program promoting the global significance of Antarctic science and research. In addition to training for graduate and undergraduate students, they are using newly-developed Polar Literacy Principles as a foundation in a virtual schoolyard program that shares polar instructional materials and provides learning opportunities for K-12 educators. The PAL-LTER team is also leveraging the development of Out of School Time materials for afterschool and summer camp programs, sharing Palmer LTER-specific teaching materials with University, Museum, and 4-H Special Interest Club partners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2: Technical description&lt;br/&gt;Polar ecosystems are among the most rapidly changing on Earth. The Palmer LTER (PAL-LTER) program builds on three decades of coordinated research along the western side of the Antarctic Peninsula (WAP) to gain new mechanistic and predictive understanding of ecosystem changes in response to disturbances spanning long-term decadal (‘press’) drivers and changes due to higher-frequency (‘pulse’) drivers, such as large storms and extreme seasonal anomaly in sea ice cover. The influence of major natural climate modes that modulate variations in sea ice, weather, and oceanographic conditions to drive changes in ecosystem structure and function (e.g., El Niño Southern Oscillation and Southern Annular Mode) are being studied at multiple time scales –from diel, seasonal, interannual, to decadal intervals, and space scales–from hemispheric to global scale investigated by remote sensing, the regional scales. Specifically, the team is evaluating how variability of physical properties (such as vertical and  alongshore connectivity processes) interact to modulate biogeochemical cycling and community ecology in the WAP region.  The study is providing an evaluation of ecosystem resilience and ecological responses to long-term “press-pulse” drivers and a decadal-level reversal in sea ice coverage. This program is providing fundamental understanding of population and biogeochemical responses for a marine ecosystem experiencing profound change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026045</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
<LastName>McDonnell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janice McDonnell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mcdonnel@marine.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000198025</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oscar</FirstName>
<LastName>Schofield</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oscar Schofield</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[oscar@marine.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000453617</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3 RUTGERS PLZ]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>529200</Code>
<Text>ANT Integrated System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1195</Code>
<Text>LONG TERM ECOLOGICAL RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>0100CYXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~1187128</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~1187258</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em><span style="color: black;">Intellectual Merit</span></em></strong><span style="color: black;">: High-latitude coastal marine ecosystems are vulnerable to climate change because of the interactions of sea/continental ice, ocean physics, biogeochemistry, and food-web structure. The West Antarctic Peninsula is one of the most rapidly changing locations in the ocean and is exhibiting accelerating change. This project is a Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) site and is focused on understanding how a shifting climate will alter the marine ecosystems. This work combines data collected by scientists working in Antarctica, robots and satellites with mathematical modeling approaches. In the Southern Ocean, ice influences marine food webs by modulating solar inputs to the ocean, inhibiting wind mixing, altering the freshwater balance and ocean stability, and providing a physical substrate for organisms. Additionally there is a clear increases in storms and ocean heat. These physical changes ripple through the food web, shifting the magnitude of primary production and its community composition, altering the abundance of krill and other prey essential for marine mammals and seabirds. Accelerating change in the recent years is predicted to transition the system away from a short polar food web, which not only drives significant deposition of atmospheric carbon into the deep sea but also supports a diverse array of migratory organisms taking advantage of the highly productive summer months. A warmer future is predicted to lead to a lower productivity system. Understanding the pace of change and whether the state transition is reversible remains a critical open question. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong><em><span style="color: black;">Broader Impacts</span></em></strong><span style="color: black;">: This program </span><span style="color: black;"><span>supports the science training of undergraduate students, graduate students, and early-career scientists including postdoctoral researchers. </span>The education and outreach efforts focus on increasing the publics&rsquo; knowledge and excitement for science conducted along the western Antarctic peninsula through partnerships with a wide variety of informal science centers, universities, science museums, aquariums, nonprofit organizations, corporations, broadcast media, community and government leaders. We strive to A) promote understanding of the polar ocean environment though our Polar Literacy Initiative, B) support the next generation of young scientists through rich and innovative field and classroom experiences for K-12 students and C) provide opportunities to pursue lifelong learning through public outreach initiatives, events, and meetings. We infuse the science into effective practices of teaching and learning through our focus on data literacy that highlight the value of long-term ecological research and scientific data collection. Our educational programing builds students&rsquo; data skills. We have been leveraging other National Science Foundation programs to develop Polar Camps &amp; Afterschool Programs (CAP). Our project is developing an educational research-based program designed to develop innovative ways of engaging young learners in exploring scientific data while increasing their understanding of the polar regions. Developed during the 2020 pandemic, the Polar CAP materials were designed to be adaptable for various facilitators and youth groups. The Polar Adventure online modules provide a guided tour through the Polar Regions for youth.&nbsp;Our Facilitator guides offers opportunities and information on how to engage young people in social interaction and collaboration as they learn about the Polar Regions and climate change. We encourage learning through conversation where youth can tap their prior knowledge and share their ideas and insights.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/12/2024<br> Modified by: Oscar&nbsp;Schofield</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802420190_Deploying_Mooring--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802420190_Deploying_Mooring--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Deploying an ocean mooring"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802420190_Deploying_Mooring--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Deploying an ocean mooring"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Deploying an ocean mooring from the research vessel Gould near Palmer Station Antarctica</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steve Ackelson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oscar&nbsp;Schofield <div class="imageTitle">Deploying an ocean mooring</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802304586_6_Penguin_Fishing--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802304586_6_Penguin_Fishing--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Penguin swimming"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802304586_6_Penguin_Fishing--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Penguin swimming"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Penguin foraging in the ocean waters of the West Antarctic Peninsula.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Andrew Corso</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oscar&nbsp;Schofield <div class="imageTitle">Penguin swimming</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802553627_20200103_193843--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802553627_20200103_193843--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Melting Marr Glacier"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802553627_20200103_193843--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Melting Marr Glacier"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The melting glacier behind Palmer Station Antarctica.  The meltwater streams are clearly visible and reflects long term trended changes in the West Antarctic eninsula.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Andrew Corso</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oscar&nbsp;Schofield <div class="imageTitle">Melting Marr Glacier</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802175608__8106435--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802175608__8106435--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Research vessel Gould"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2026045/2026045_10732254_1720802175608__8106435--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Research vessel Gould"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Research Vessel Gould in the sea ice.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steve Ackelson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oscar&nbsp;Schofield <div class="imageTitle">Research vessel Gould</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merit: High-latitude coastal marine ecosystems are vulnerable to climate change because of the interactions of sea/continental ice, ocean physics, biogeochemistry, and food-web structure. The West Antarctic Peninsula is one of the most rapidly changing locations in the ocean and is exhibiting accelerating change. This project is a Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) site and is focused on understanding how a shifting climate will alter the marine ecosystems. This work combines data collected by scientists working in Antarctica, robots and satellites with mathematical modeling approaches. In the Southern Ocean, ice influences marine food webs by modulating solar inputs to the ocean, inhibiting wind mixing, altering the freshwater balance and ocean stability, and providing a physical substrate for organisms. Additionally there is a clear increases in storms and ocean heat. These physical changes ripple through the food web, shifting the magnitude of primary production and its community composition, altering the abundance of krill and other prey essential for marine mammals and seabirds. Accelerating change in the recent years is predicted to transition the system away from a short polar food web, which not only drives significant deposition of atmospheric carbon into the deep sea but also supports a diverse array of migratory organisms taking advantage of the highly productive summer months. A warmer future is predicted to lead to a lower productivity system. Understanding the pace of change and whether the state transition is reversible remains a critical open question.    Broader Impacts: This program supports the science training of undergraduate students, graduate students, and early-career scientists including postdoctoral researchers. The education and outreach efforts focus on increasing the publics knowledge and excitement for science conducted along the western Antarctic peninsula through partnerships with a wide variety of informal science centers, universities, science museums, aquariums, nonprofit organizations, corporations, broadcast media, community and government leaders. We strive to A) promote understanding of the polar ocean environment though our Polar Literacy Initiative, B) support the next generation of young scientists through rich and innovative field and classroom experiences for K-12 students and C) provide opportunities to pursue lifelong learning through public outreach initiatives, events, and meetings. We infuse the science into effective practices of teaching and learning through our focus on data literacy that highlight the value of long-term ecological research and scientific data collection. Our educational programing builds students data skills. We have been leveraging other National Science Foundation programs to develop Polar Camps & Afterschool Programs (CAP). Our project is developing an educational research-based program designed to develop innovative ways of engaging young learners in exploring scientific data while increasing their understanding of the polar regions. Developed during the 2020 pandemic, the Polar CAP materials were designed to be adaptable for various facilitators and youth groups. The Polar Adventure online modules provide a guided tour through the Polar Regions for youth.Our Facilitator guides offers opportunities and information on how to engage young people in social interaction and collaboration as they learn about the Polar Regions and climate change. We encourage learning through conversation where youth can tap their prior knowledge and share their ideas and insights.        Last Modified: 07/12/2024       Submitted by: OscarSchofield]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
