<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: A Comparative Study of How Context Shapes Responses to COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100218.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100218</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wenda K. Bauchspies</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbauchsp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925034</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The primary objective of this collaborative RAPID research project is to further our understanding of how cultural and political contexts shape the ways people perceive and respond to the COVID-19 pandemic. The research team will conduct 400 interviews across multiple urban and rural areas for an analysis oriented towards understanding how individuals construct and modify their perceptions given information from a wide variety of sources and their network of interactions with friends and family. The results of this project will provide a deeper understanding of the social mechanisms that shape perceptions and behaviors to public policy responses in culturally and politically diverse contexts. Perceptions of disease (i.e., perceived seriousness, susceptibility, and threat) shape perceived barriers and benefits to action, which in turn affect behavior. While it is given that these perceptions are important to understand health-related behaviors as well as support for various treatments and actions, it is crucial to understand how these perceptions are generated. The project interviews and the analysis are to be widely distributed to provide grounded guidance for policy makers and others seeking to understand the diversity of fears, risk perceptions, preparedness, and acceptable actions in pandemics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team will collect qualitative and quantitative data on groups selected for their importance to pandemic processes (transmission and treatment of information and infectious agents). The groups are stratified into five categories: scientists, medical professionals, teachers, the informal sector, and the unemployed. The purposes of the Interviews are to Identify the principal sources of information about COVID-19 transmission, treatment, and risk, including both new and old media as well as the factors associated with their relative importance across regions, occupations, and rural/urban areas; to examine factors that impact the credibility of sources in both absolute and relative terms; and to assess the level of knowledge and preparation for COVID-19 transmission, treatment, and risk. They will be used to Identify primary fears and concerns relevant to the current spectrum of treatment, isolation, and containment technologies. The results of this project will contribute to an understanding of the different ways cultural and political contexts shape response to outbreak information and directives, and they will provide guidance for policy makers seeking to understand these differences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Science and Technology Studied Program, and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027598</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wesley</FirstName>
<LastName>Shrum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wesley M Shrum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shrum@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000394536</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 HIMES HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECQEYCHRNKJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y00</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>915000</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100218</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Why did coronavirus disease diffuse so extensively, both nationally and internationally, despite public and private efforts to prevent its spread?&nbsp;We examined how infection occurs and evaluated three dozen precautionary actions, yielding a general explanation for the course of the pandemic.</p> <p>Precautionary action was rarely considered in relation to the (a) primary sources of infection and (b)&nbsp;common understandings of their usefulness and difficulty. We collected international data on ten countires and combined this with US data from all 50 states on the sources of infection.</p> <p>The problem with alternative explanations of the spread of COVID-19, such as the characteristics of the virus itself or the ineffectual measures of public health authorities, was that they did not take account the most common source of respondent infection, which was generally at home, from someone they lived with.</p> <p>We analyzed three dozen precautionary actions that could be taken or avoided. Internationally, we conclude that most precautions were widely practiced, but avoiding close contact with cohabitants was uncommon. Yet this was the primary source of infection. Further, we analyzed the perceived necessity of each precaution and its perceived degree of difficulty. Avoiding close contact with cohabitants was viewed as the&nbsp;<em>most difficult</em>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<em>least necessary</em>&nbsp;by a wide margin.</p> <p>The primary explanation of the spread of COVID-19 and the futility of efforts to contain it was the mismatch between actions taken to avoid infection and the main source of infection.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 05/07/2024<br> Modified by: Wesley&nbsp;M&nbsp;Shrum</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Why did coronavirus disease diffuse so extensively, both nationally and internationally, despite public and private efforts to prevent its spread?We examined how infection occurs and evaluated three dozen precautionary actions, yielding a general explanation for the course of the pandemic.   Precautionary action was rarely considered in relation to the (a) primary sources of infection and (b)common understandings of their usefulness and difficulty. We collected international data on ten countires and combined this with US data from all 50 states on the sources of infection.   The problem with alternative explanations of the spread of COVID-19, such as the characteristics of the virus itself or the ineffectual measures of public health authorities, was that they did not take account the most common source of respondent infection, which was generally at home, from someone they lived with.   We analyzed three dozen precautionary actions that could be taken or avoided. Internationally, we conclude that most precautions were widely practiced, but avoiding close contact with cohabitants was uncommon. Yet this was the primary source of infection. Further, we analyzed the perceived necessity of each precaution and its perceived degree of difficulty. Avoiding close contact with cohabitants was viewed as themost difficultandleast necessaryby a wide margin.   The primary explanation of the spread of COVID-19 and the futility of efforts to contain it was the mismatch between actions taken to avoid infection and the main source of infection.        Last Modified: 05/07/2024       Submitted by: WesleyMShrum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
