<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Involvement of Developing Country Scientists in Activities of the Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kandace Binkley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbinkley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927577</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funds to the Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research (SCOR) for a long-standing program of travel assistance to qualified and active oceanographic researchers and early-career scientists from developing countries and nations with economies in transition. SCOR travel grants are awarded to enable such individuals to attend international meetings relevant to their scientific interests and to those of SCOR and the Division of Ocean Sciences of NSF. This ongoing project has become the cornerstone of SCOR's efforts to provide assistance to marine scientists in the developing countries and with economies in transition for example eastern European nations and the Commonwealth of Independent States. The impacts of this activity extend beyond the ocean sciences into other scientific topics by stimulating scientific progress in developing countries. In many cases, personal connections and collaborations that can result from contacts made through these travel grants can have long-lasting effects both in international activities as well as in the developing country's science communities as the individuals involved rise through the ranks of science and science policy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funds to the Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research (SCOR) for a long-standing program of travel assistance to qualified and active oceanographic researchers and early-career scientists from developing countries and nations with economies in transition. NSF support has provided an effective mechanism to establish contacts between oceanographers from the developing and the industrialized countries, including the United States, and to facilitate collaborative efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027831</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Urban</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward R Urban</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Ed.Urban@scor-int.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000446848</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
<LastName>Miloslavich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patricia A Miloslavich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[patricia.miloslavich@scor-int.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819100</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/16/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Twigg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily Twigg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[emily.twigg@scor-int.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000937066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research (SCOR)]]></Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>197165200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028317013</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 S COLLEGE AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ELAQL1PM1ZK5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE SCIENTIFIC COMMITTEE ON OCEANIC RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research (SCOR)]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197163501</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[College of Earth, Ocean and Environment]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>541900</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was aimed at training and facilitating professional development in ocean science for developing-country scientists. This was achieved by (1) bringing developing-country scientists to ocean science meetings and trainings to present their research and to network with other scientists; (2) training developing-country scientists in techniques of ocean observations that can be implemented in their home countries (the POGO-SCOR Fellowship Programme); and (3) sending "Visiting Scholars" to developing countries to teach and mentor students and young faculty. Over the lifetime of the grant, 133 students and early-career scientists from 31 developing countries were supported to attend 40 international meetings and trainings. Ten SCOR Visiting Scholars were supported by the grant to visit Argentina, Bangladesh, Brazil, Cameroon, China, Costa Rica, Ecuador, and Seychelles. Sixteen POGO-SCOR Fellows were selected from 2022 to 2024.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;An overarching goal of the programs is to increase the number of qualified individuals and countries involved in internation ocean science. These included support for attendance of early-career, developing-country scientists at trainings and meetings of SCOR&rsquo;s scientific international activities, including GEOTRACES (field program measuring trace elements and isotopes in the ocean), IMBeR (Integrated Marine Biosphere Research project), IQOE (International Quiet Ocean Experiment), SOLAS (Surface Ocean-Lower Atmosphere Study), SOOS (Southern Ocean Observing System), and WG 154 P-OBS (Integration of Plankton-Observing Sensor Systems to Existing Global Sampling Programs), thereby increasing the number of scientists with the capabilities of contributing to the research goals of these activities. In many cases, personal connections and collaborations that result from contacts made through these travel grants can have long-lasting effects, both in international activities as well as in the developing country&rsquo;s science communities as the individuals involved rise through the ranks of science and science policy. By improving scientific capabilities worldwide, scientists from a wider range of countries are able to co-design research to develop science-informed solutions for sustainable development.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/25/2024<br> Modified by: Emily&nbsp;Twigg</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732299461609__ETF2352SOLAS___Summer_school_--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732299461609__ETF2352SOLAS___Summer_school_--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SOLAS 2023 Summer School"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732299461609__ETF2352SOLAS___Summer_school_--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SOLAS 2023 Summer School"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Poster session at the 2023 SOLAS Summer School, where attendance by 10 participants was partially supported by the grant.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Edson Silva Delgado</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Twigg <div class="imageTitle">SOLAS 2023 Summer School</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732541895264_IMG_5980--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732541895264_IMG_5980--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass hands-on activities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732541895264_IMG_5980--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass hands-on activities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Hands-on activities during an eDNA workshop at  the University of Seychelles Blue Economy Research Institute by 2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Glass</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Twigg <div class="imageTitle">2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass hands-on activities</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732221953393_Training_Session_1__1_--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732221953393_Training_Session_1__1_--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="2023 SCOR Visiting Scholar Olusegun Dada"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732221953393_Training_Session_1__1_--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="2023 SCOR Visiting Scholar Olusegun Dada"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SCOR Visiting Scholar Olusegun Dada (Nigeria) holds a short course at the University of Douala, Cameroon on coastal processes and geomorphology.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Olusegun Dada</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Twigg <div class="imageTitle">2023 SCOR Visiting Scholar Olusegun Dada</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732541785591_e951d9e9_31ff_4ebc_bd83_d3383e40341b--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732541785591_e951d9e9_31ff_4ebc_bd83_d3383e40341b--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass lecture"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2027831/2027831_10662271_1732541785591_e951d9e9_31ff_4ebc_bd83_d3383e40341b--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass lecture"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass provides a brief lecture about SCOR during a workshop on eDNA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Glass</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Twigg <div class="imageTitle">2024 SCOR Visiting Scholar Jessica Glass lecture</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project was aimed at training and facilitating professional development in ocean science for developing-country scientists. This was achieved by (1) bringing developing-country scientists to ocean science meetings and trainings to present their research and to network with other scientists; (2) training developing-country scientists in techniques of ocean observations that can be implemented in their home countries (the POGO-SCOR Fellowship Programme); and (3) sending "Visiting Scholars" to developing countries to teach and mentor students and young faculty. Over the lifetime of the grant, 133 students and early-career scientists from 31 developing countries were supported to attend 40 international meetings and trainings. Ten SCOR Visiting Scholars were supported by the grant to visit Argentina, Bangladesh, Brazil, Cameroon, China, Costa Rica, Ecuador, and Seychelles. Sixteen POGO-SCOR Fellows were selected from 2022 to 2024.        An overarching goal of the programs is to increase the number of qualified individuals and countries involved in internation ocean science. These included support for attendance of early-career, developing-country scientists at trainings and meetings of SCORs scientific international activities, including GEOTRACES (field program measuring trace elements and isotopes in the ocean), IMBeR (Integrated Marine Biosphere Research project), IQOE (International Quiet Ocean Experiment), SOLAS (Surface Ocean-Lower Atmosphere Study), SOOS (Southern Ocean Observing System), and WG 154 P-OBS (Integration of Plankton-Observing Sensor Systems to Existing Global Sampling Programs), thereby increasing the number of scientists with the capabilities of contributing to the research goals of these activities. In many cases, personal connections and collaborations that result from contacts made through these travel grants can have long-lasting effects, both in international activities as well as in the developing countrys science communities as the individuals involved rise through the ranks of science and science policy. By improving scientific capabilities worldwide, scientists from a wider range of countries are able to co-design research to develop science-informed solutions for sustainable development.         Last Modified: 11/25/2024       Submitted by: EmilyTwigg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
