<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: A Research-Driven Messaging Campaign to Transform Perceptions of URMs in STEM Innovation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Shearman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshearma@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927403</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This EAGER project engages in research that has the potential to transform the field of innovation of entrepreneurship as it relates to broadening participation of women of color in educational and academic related innovation environments. The goal of this project is to use storytelling to explore which factors influence the access, pursuit, and success of underrepresented populations in innovative STEM spaces and create a research-driven messaging campaign for the National Science Foundation’s (NSF’s) I-Corps program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Innovation and entrepreneurship are major economic drivers in the United States and are essential to ensure the Nation’s standing as a global leader in science and technology. Because of the significant lack of inclusion of under-represented groups in STEM, there is also an absence of innovators with diverse experiences, ideas, perspectives, and stories. Including these groups in the National Innovation Network can add potentially transformative ways of thinking about innovation and entrepreneurship. Results from this study will be used to uncover what factors (stories, ideas, experiences, perceptions) influence/play a role in NSF’s under-represented populations access to, pursuit of, and success in innovative STEM spaces (both academic and professional). It will also inform the planning and implementation of a pilot messaging campaign aimed at broadening participation of under-represented groups in NSF’s I-Corps program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous efforts to address innovation for under-represented women in STEM have not been effective in producing substantive impact that led to measurable increases in this area.  By focusing on stories told by under-represented communities in STEM, this project seeks to uncover specific reasons these groups do not have access to STEM sectors or think they do not fit in these spaces. The outcomes are expected to advance the understanding of the barriers members of under-represented communities face in STEM fields, and have the potential to significantly impact the inclusion of underrepresented groups in STEM and innovation within workplaces, schools, universities, and community spaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028719</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Almesha</FirstName>
<LastName>Campbell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Almesha L Campbell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[almesha.l.campbell@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000755437</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Jackson State University]]></Name>
<CityName>JACKSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>392170002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6019792008</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 J R LYNCH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WFVHMSF6BU45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JACKSON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Jackson State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Jackson</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>392170002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 J R LYNCH ST.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>804600</Code>
<Text>I-Corps-Sites</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">The major goals of this project were to use research to explore the experiences of underrepresented groups, to explore how communication can be used to reach these audiences and create compelling stories that may encourage and broaden their participation in STEM innovation, and to create a pilot messaging campaign that shares the stories of underrepresented groups and may encourage interest and broaden participation of underrepresented groups in STEM innovation.</p> <p>By using a multimedia approach, the project created a platform that featured the experiences of URMs in STEM and inspired others to engage in innovation and entrepreneurship. The centerpiece of this initiative was the <em>Innovate Exchange</em> YouTube show, which shared the stories of URMs in STEM fields. The show was supported by social media outreach and academic contributions, in an effort to create a robust effort to change how URMs are perceived in STEM innovation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Key Outcomes:</strong></p> <p><strong>1. <em>Innovate Exchange</em> YouTube Show (https://www.youtube.com/@InnovateExchange):</strong></p> <p>The <em>Innovate Exchange</em> was launched to provide a platform for URM STEM leaders to share their stories of overcoming challenges and finding success in innovation. The interviews highlighted personal journeys, challenges, and achievements, and serves as an inspiration for younger generations. The show reached thousands of viewers, generating significant engagement through social media.</p> <p><strong>23. Academic Contributions:</strong></p> <p>Dr. Almesha Campbell contributed to a key academic article, <em>Engaging More Women in Academic Innovation: Findings and Recommendations</em>, published in <em>Technology &amp; Innovation</em> (2022). This publication addressed barriers faced by women, especially those from underrepresented groups, in academic innovation. The findings from this article informed the messaging campaign&rsquo;s content, ensuring that narratives reflected the authentic experiences of URMs in STEM innovation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>This project contributed to the growing field of communications by demonstrating the effectiveness of storytelling in changing perceptions and encouraging participation in STEM innovation. By using real-life narratives, the project provided a compelling method for reaching URM audiences and inspiring them to engage in STEM entrepreneurship. This interdisciplinary approach, drawing on STEM fields and communications offered valuable insights into how strategic messaging can foster diversity in STEM.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>The broader impacts of this project will be significant. By increasing visibility and reshaping perceptions of URMs in STEM, the project will continue to contribute to the development of a more inclusive STEM ecosystem. The <em>Innovate Exchange</em> episodes,have reached a wide audience, and feedback suggests that the campaign is well needed to motivate many URM viewers to pursue careers in STEM and pursue STEM innovation opportunities.</p> <p>The campaign also emphasizes the importance of diversity in fostering creativity and innovation, which has the potential to benefit both STEM fields and society at large.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Conclusion:</strong></p> <p>The NSF EAGER project has successfully demonstrated that a targeted, research-driven messaging campaign can positively shift perceptions of URMs in STEM innovation. Through the launch of the <em>Innovate Exchange</em> show, and the dissemination of URM narratives, the project has made meaningful progress toward its goal of increasing URM participation in STEM innovation. Continued efforts in this direction (such as the pending development of an educator toolkit) will contribute to a more diverse and inclusive innovation landscape in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/20/2024<br> Modified by: Almesha&nbsp;L&nbsp;Campbell</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2028719/2028719_10687573_1729465905289_Innovate_Exchange--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2028719/2028719_10687573_1729465905289_Innovate_Exchange--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Innovate Exchange Logo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2028719/2028719_10687573_1729465905289_Innovate_Exchange--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Innovate Exchange Logo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Innovate Exchange</div> <div class="imageCredit">Micah Sanford</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Almesha&nbsp;L&nbsp;Campbell <div class="imageTitle">Innovate Exchange Logo</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2028719/2028719_10687573_1729466301878_Screen_Shot_2024_10_20_at_6.15.46_PM--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2028719/2028719_10687573_1729466301878_Screen_Shot_2024_10_20_at_6.15.46_PM--rgov-800width.png" title="Innovate Exchange YouTube Channel"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2028719/2028719_10687573_1729466301878_Screen_Shot_2024_10_20_at_6.15.46_PM--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Innovate Exchange YouTube Channel"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Innovate Exchange YouTube Channel</div> <div class="imageCredit">Almesha Campbell</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Almesha&nbsp;L&nbsp;Campbell <div class="imageTitle">Innovate Exchange YouTube Channel</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The major goals of this project were to use research to explore the experiences of underrepresented groups, to explore how communication can be used to reach these audiences and create compelling stories that may encourage and broaden their participation in STEM innovation, and to create a pilot messaging campaign that shares the stories of underrepresented groups and may encourage interest and broaden participation of underrepresented groups in STEM innovation.   By using a multimedia approach, the project created a platform that featured the experiences of URMs in STEM and inspired others to engage in innovation and entrepreneurship. The centerpiece of this initiative was the Innovate Exchange YouTube show, which shared the stories of URMs in STEM fields. The show was supported by social media outreach and academic contributions, in an effort to create a robust effort to change how URMs are perceived in STEM innovation.      Key Outcomes:   1. Innovate Exchange YouTube Show (https://www.youtube.com/@InnovateExchange):   The Innovate Exchange was launched to provide a platform for URM STEM leaders to share their stories of overcoming challenges and finding success in innovation. The interviews highlighted personal journeys, challenges, and achievements, and serves as an inspiration for younger generations. The show reached thousands of viewers, generating significant engagement through social media.   23. Academic Contributions:   Dr. Almesha Campbell contributed to a key academic article, Engaging More Women in Academic Innovation: Findings and Recommendations, published in Technology & Innovation (2022). This publication addressed barriers faced by women, especially those from underrepresented groups, in academic innovation. The findings from this article informed the messaging campaigns content, ensuring that narratives reflected the authentic experiences of URMs in STEM innovation.      Intellectual Merit:   This project contributed to the growing field of communications by demonstrating the effectiveness of storytelling in changing perceptions and encouraging participation in STEM innovation. By using real-life narratives, the project provided a compelling method for reaching URM audiences and inspiring them to engage in STEM entrepreneurship. This interdisciplinary approach, drawing on STEM fields and communications offered valuable insights into how strategic messaging can foster diversity in STEM.      Broader Impacts:   The broader impacts of this project will be significant. By increasing visibility and reshaping perceptions of URMs in STEM, the project will continue to contribute to the development of a more inclusive STEM ecosystem. The Innovate Exchange episodes,have reached a wide audience, and feedback suggests that the campaign is well needed to motivate many URM viewers to pursue careers in STEM and pursue STEM innovation opportunities.   The campaign also emphasizes the importance of diversity in fostering creativity and innovation, which has the potential to benefit both STEM fields and society at large.      Conclusion:   The NSF EAGER project has successfully demonstrated that a targeted, research-driven messaging campaign can positively shift perceptions of URMs in STEM innovation. Through the launch of the Innovate Exchange show, and the dissemination of URM narratives, the project has made meaningful progress toward its goal of increasing URM participation in STEM innovation. Continued efforts in this direction (such as the pending development of an educator toolkit) will contribute to a more diverse and inclusive innovation landscape in the future.        Last Modified: 10/20/2024       Submitted by: AlmeshaLCampbell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
