<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Blockchain System for Preserving Integrity of Communication Channels]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>997567.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>997567</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to preserve the integrity of communication channels for business enterprises, financial institutions, and consumers.  Attackers operate like businesses by investing in campaigns and generate returns by using stolen credentials to gain network access, inject ransomware, or commit direct fraud. The innovation aims to prevent $4 B a year in financial scams through robust and enduring countermeasures. 90% of large enterprise customer breaches start from email or p2p/SMS messages that trick customers and employees into revealing sensitive information. An average phishing attack spans 21 hours between the first and last victim and the detection of each attack occurs an average 9 hours after the first victim. This gives attackers a window of opportunity during which most of the damage is done. This project seeks to identify and protect against such attacks through a real-time machine learning system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase II project develops a method for storing data in a blockchain in a high-performing manner, to ensure quality training of ML/AI models, and production level inference.  The innovation addresses the challenge of data drift and adversarial AI attacks where the provenance of the data is unknown. The Phase II project also leverages swarm intelligence as a new consensus mechanism specifically designed for more democratic online group-to-group collaboration in a distributed system.  The project's innovations will expand the understanding of telecommunications, the economics of smishing and vishing, and 5G security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/26/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028451</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Adolphe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric A Adolphe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Eric.Adolphe@outlook.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803325</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/26/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Forward Edge AI, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN ANTONIO</CityName>
<ZipCode>782552458</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039997583</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10108 CARTER CYN]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KRCZZNY5WPZ8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FORWARD EDGE AI INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Forward Edge AI, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782552458</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10108 Carter Canyon]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537300</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7927</Code>
<Text>COMPLEXITY &amp; CRYPTOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~997567</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h1>Project Outcomes Report for the General Public (POR)</h1> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>The SBIR Phase II: Blockchain System for Preserving Integrity of Communication Channels aimed to develop an advanced communication security system utilizing blockchain technology to ensure the integrity and confidentiality of communication channels. The project leveraged the Phase I and II Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) program funding to create a robust framework that can detect and mitigate various cyber threats, thereby preserving the trustworthiness of critical communications.</p> <p>The primary outcomes include the successful design and implementation of a blockchain-based system that ensures secure and verifiable communication across various platforms. This innovation addresses the NSF's intellectual merit criteria by advancing the field of cybersecurity through novel applications of blockchain technology. Additionally, the broader impacts of the SBIR Phase II are significant as it enhances the security infrastructure for both public and private sectors, contributing to the overall resilience against cyber threats.</p> <p>The SBIR Phase II achieved several notable results. Over 13.4 million calls were blocked, protecting users from potential scams and phishing attempts. Nearly one million Purple Alerts were issued to caregivers, enabling them to proactively stop scams in real-time. Additionally, over 47,000 complaints were automatically filed with the Federal Trade Commission (FTC), aiding in regulatory enforcement against cyber threats. The SBIR Phase II also estimated a total financial saving of approximately $73.8 million, assuming that ten percent of caregivers who received a Purple Alert proactively stopped the scam in real-time.</p> <p>The SBIR Phase II has also resulted in the issuance of a United States utility patent (Patent No. US 11,689,660 B2), which covers methods and systems for detecting disinformation and blocking robocalls using blockchain technology&#8203;. <a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US11689660B2/en?oq=11%2c689%2c660">Patent 11,689,660</a></p> <p><strong>Products</strong></p> <p>The SBIR Phase II resulted in the development of several key products, including:</p> <ol> <li><strong>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Blockchain System for Communication Integrity:</strong> A fully functional prototype that leverages blockchain to ensure the authenticity and integrity of communication channels.</li> <li><strong>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Educational Materials:</strong> Comprehensive documentation and training materials for the deployment and maintenance of the blockchain system, aimed at facilitating broader adoption and understanding.</li> <li><strong>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Data Sets:</strong> Collection of data sets used to test and validate the effectiveness of the blockchain system in various scenarios.</li> <li><strong>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Patent:</strong> The project has successfully secured a patent (US 11,689,660 B2) for the methods and systems developed&#8203;. <a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US11689660B2/en?oq=11%2c689%2c660">Patent 11,689,660</a></li> <li><strong>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><a href="https://www.scamadviser.com/">ScamAdviser</a><strong> Integration</strong>: Integration with ScamAdviser enhances our product by associating scam URLs with phone numbers, providing users with robust protection against online threats.</li> </ol> <p>The Gabriel communication security system is now available on multiple platforms, including:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://azuremarketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/apps/forwardedgeaiinc1593641437084.gabrielenterprisetransac?tab=Overview" target="_new">Microsoft Azure Marketplace</a></li> <li><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.forwardedgeai.GabrielRobocallBlocker&amp;hl=en_US" target="_new">Google Play Store</a></li> <li><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/gabriel-the-robocall-blocker/id1532102860">Apple      Store</a></li> </ul> <p>Additional informational material:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://support.forwardedge.ai/en/articles/8783653-phase-i-ii-sbir-blockchain-system-for-preserving-integrity-of-communication-channels?q=Gabriel">Phase I/II SBIR - Blockchain System for Preserving Integrity of Communication Channels</a></li> <li><a href="https://support.forwardedge.ai/en/articles/8766755-gabriel-brochure">Gabriel Brochure</a></li> </ul><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/05/2024<br> Modified by: Eric&nbsp;A&nbsp;Adolphe</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Project Outcomes Report for the General Public (POR)   Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts   The SBIR Phase II: Blockchain System for Preserving Integrity of Communication Channels aimed to develop an advanced communication security system utilizing blockchain technology to ensure the integrity and confidentiality of communication channels. The project leveraged the Phase I and II Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) program funding to create a robust framework that can detect and mitigate various cyber threats, thereby preserving the trustworthiness of critical communications.   The primary outcomes include the successful design and implementation of a blockchain-based system that ensures secure and verifiable communication across various platforms. This innovation addresses the NSF's intellectual merit criteria by advancing the field of cybersecurity through novel applications of blockchain technology. Additionally, the broader impacts of the SBIR Phase II are significant as it enhances the security infrastructure for both public and private sectors, contributing to the overall resilience against cyber threats.   The SBIR Phase II achieved several notable results. Over 13.4 million calls were blocked, protecting users from potential scams and phishing attempts. Nearly one million Purple Alerts were issued to caregivers, enabling them to proactively stop scams in real-time. Additionally, over 47,000 complaints were automatically filed with the Federal Trade Commission (FTC), aiding in regulatory enforcement against cyber threats. The SBIR Phase II also estimated a total financial saving of approximately $73.8 million, assuming that ten percent of caregivers who received a Purple Alert proactively stopped the scam in real-time.   The SBIR Phase II has also resulted in the issuance of a United States utility patent (Patent No. US 11,689,660 B2), which covers methods and systems for detecting disinformation and blocking robocalls using blockchain technology&#8203;. Patent 11,689,660   Products   The SBIR Phase II resulted in the development of several key products, including:  1. Blockchain System for Communication Integrity: A fully functional prototype that leverages blockchain to ensure the authenticity and integrity of communication channels. 2. Educational Materials: Comprehensive documentation and training materials for the deployment and maintenance of the blockchain system, aimed at facilitating broader adoption and understanding. 3. Data Sets: Collection of data sets used to test and validate the effectiveness of the blockchain system in various scenarios. 4. Patent: The project has successfully secured a patent (US 11,689,660 B2) for the methods and systems developed&#8203;. Patent 11,689,660 5. ScamAdviser Integration: Integration with ScamAdviser enhances our product by associating scam URLs with phone numbers, providing users with robust protection against online threats.    The Gabriel communication security system is now available on multiple platforms, including:  Microsoft Azure Marketplace Google Play Store Apple      Store    Additional informational material:  Phase I/II SBIR - Blockchain System for Preserving Integrity of Communication Channels Gabriel Brochure      Last Modified: 07/05/2024       Submitted by: EricAAdolphe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
