<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[From Self-similar Solutions to Turbulent Cascades]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>322696.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>322696</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Turbulent fluid flows are both ubiquitous and immensely important in the modern society. They shape climate and weather, control transmission of many infectious diseases and the spreading of pollution, and determine the fuel-efficiency of our cars, airplanes, and ships. Yet, many of turbulent flows’ properties remain mysterious despite centuries of systematic research. In particular, we do not fully understand the principles that control the motion of fluids such at air and water at very small scales. As a result, despite continuing advances in computing power, numerical simulations resolving the small-scale structure of turbulent flows remains out of reach, limiting our ability to make sustained improvements in numerous civilian and military applications. This project harnesses recent numerical and theoretical advances to describe how fluid motions at one scale can generate motions at another (often much larger or much smaller) scale, yielding a hierarchy of eddies responsible for the unique and beautiful structure of fluid turbulence.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project uses a combination of novel numerical methods and innovative theoretical approaches to addresses several fundamental problems in fluid turbulence that remain largely unsolved despite almost a century of concerted effort. One of the oldest, most fundamental, and least understood issues in fluid turbulence is the multi-scale structure of the flow at high Reynolds numbers. Such structure emerges due to cascades of various quantities, such as energy, vorticity, and helicity, describing the fluid flow. Our understanding of the physical mechanisms of respective cascades is very limited. For instance, it is not entirely clear what determines the direction of the cascades, i.e., whether the flux of a particular quantity is towards large scales (inverse cascade) or small scales (direct cascade). This project aims to develop a dynamical description of direct and inverse cascades in two spatial dimensions. Advanced numerical methods for finding self-similar solutions to inviscid governing equations are used to uncover the fundamental physical mechanisms describing scale interaction in fluid flows that is responsible for the multi-scale nature of developed turbulence. Established tools from dynamical systems theory are leveraged to develop a comprehensive quantitative theory of turbulent cascades that does not rely on unproven assumptions and approximations that underlie existing statistical theories of turbulence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032657</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roman</FirstName>
<LastName>Grigoriev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roman O Grigoriev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[roman.grigoriev@physics.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000486399</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303186395</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[926 DALNEY ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>144300</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~322696</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fluid turbulence is a problem of high practical interest and importance. For instance, the flows of both air in the atmosphere and water in the ocean are highly turbulent. Quantitative description and qualitative understanding of fluid turbulence are challenging, in part, because of its multiscale nature. A typical turbulent flow can exhibit structures with characteristic length and time scales differing by many orders of magnitude. This complicated structure emerges as a result of turbulent cascades that transport various quantities, such as energy and enstrophy (a measure describing the strength of vorticity representing local rotation of the fluid), between scales.</p>  <p>This project investigated turbulent cascades in two-dimensional or nearly two-dimensional flows which are common in many geophysical applications. Such flows feature two cascades, an inverse cascade, which transports energy from small to large scales, and a direct cascade, which transports enstrophy from large scales to small scales. Our focus was on developing a dynamical description of the direct cascade in turbulent flows driven by injection of energy and enstrophy at large scales. While traditional analyses of turbulence relied on largely statistical descriptions, our objective was to develop a dynamical description firmly grounded in the equations governing fluid flows. We have discovered that direct cascade emerges as a result of nonlinear, bidirectional interaction between large-scale coherent structures and small-scale vorticity filaments. Both large- and small-scale structures were found to be described by particular types of solutions of the governing equations. In particular, vorticity filaments are described by self-similar solutions that look the same at different levels of magnification. It is well-known that self-similar, or scale-free, structures are characterized by power-law spectra. In the case of two-dimensional turbulence, the energy of the flow per unit spatial frequency scales as a power of that frequency, over a range of intermediate scales.</p>  <p>The dynamical description of the direct cascade has shown that the exponent of the power law is not universal, as predicted by statistical theories, and takes non-integral values, as observed in many experiments and numerical simulations. The dynamical description has also shown that the value of the exponent depends on the properties of the large-scale coherent structures. Furthermore, we found that, in the direct cascade, the enstrophy is transported from large to small scales only on average. In different regions of the flow, the enstrophy can flow in either direction, with the local inter-scale flux much stronger than the mean value. These findings are important not only because they help us better understand how the multiscale nature of fluid turbulence emerges and how different scales interact with each other. They also inform predictive modeling of fluid turbulence which is essential for a variety of applications such as weather forecasting and climate modeling.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/07/2024<br> Modified by: Roman&nbsp;O&nbsp;Grigoriev</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Fluid turbulence is a problem of high practical interest and importance. For instance, the flows of both air in the atmosphere and water in the ocean are highly turbulent. Quantitative description and qualitative understanding of fluid turbulence are challenging, in part, because of its multiscale nature. A typical turbulent flow can exhibit structures with characteristic length and time scales differing by many orders of magnitude. This complicated structure emerges as a result of turbulent cascades that transport various quantities, such as energy and enstrophy (a measure describing the strength of vorticity representing local rotation of the fluid), between scales.    This project investigated turbulent cascades in two-dimensional or nearly two-dimensional flows which are common in many geophysical applications. Such flows feature two cascades, an inverse cascade, which transports energy from small to large scales, and a direct cascade, which transports enstrophy from large scales to small scales. Our focus was on developing a dynamical description of the direct cascade in turbulent flows driven by injection of energy and enstrophy at large scales. While traditional analyses of turbulence relied on largely statistical descriptions, our objective was to develop a dynamical description firmly grounded in the equations governing fluid flows. We have discovered that direct cascade emerges as a result of nonlinear, bidirectional interaction between large-scale coherent structures and small-scale vorticity filaments. Both large- and small-scale structures were found to be described by particular types of solutions of the governing equations. In particular, vorticity filaments are described by self-similar solutions that look the same at different levels of magnification. It is well-known that self-similar, or scale-free, structures are characterized by power-law spectra. In the case of two-dimensional turbulence, the energy of the flow per unit spatial frequency scales as a power of that frequency, over a range of intermediate scales.    The dynamical description of the direct cascade has shown that the exponent of the power law is not universal, as predicted by statistical theories, and takes non-integral values, as observed in many experiments and numerical simulations. The dynamical description has also shown that the value of the exponent depends on the properties of the large-scale coherent structures. Furthermore, we found that, in the direct cascade, the enstrophy is transported from large to small scales only on average. In different regions of the flow, the enstrophy can flow in either direction, with the local inter-scale flux much stronger than the mean value. These findings are important not only because they help us better understand how the multiscale nature of fluid turbulence emerges and how different scales interact with each other. They also inform predictive modeling of fluid turbulence which is essential for a variety of applications such as weather forecasting and climate modeling.     Last Modified: 12/07/2024       Submitted by: RomanOGrigoriev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
