<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Creep-enabled 3D solid-state Lithium-metal batteries]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>289469.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>289469</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cread@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922418</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The development of all-solid-state rechargeable batteries based on lithium (Li) metal plating and stripping has highlighted a grand challenge: Li metal is chemically highly corrosive and mechanically stressful to the surrounding solid components, causing both electrochemical and mechanical instabilities. This project includes fundamental research to design a solid-state battery architecture in which Li metal functions as “a working fluid” rising and falling during electrochemical cycling with minimal electrochemical corrosion and mechanical stress generation. Insights from this project will potentially result in safer and higher density all-solid-state Li-metal batteries. Further, in this project a diverse group of students will be trained in a multidisciplinary setting and enhance underrepresented minority groups involvement and participation in science and engineering in general and mechanoelectrochemistry in particular at Penn State and MIT. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Li metal is a soft crystal and exhibits either solid-like displacive behavior or fluid-like diffusive behavior. Li metal is also chemically aggressive, causing decomposition of solid electrolytes, consumption of active Li inventory, and uncontrollable growth of solid-electrolyte interphase. Li-metal anodes thus face stress-corrosion cracking under dual aggressive chemical and mechanical driving forces, making stable contact against Li metal challenging. To overcome these limitations, this project aims to construct a three-dimensional (3D) Li-metal host made of mixed ionic-electronic conductors (MIECs) and electronic and Li-ion insulators (ELIs). The project will develop design principles for the 3D MIEC/ELI based battery through integrated multi-faceted experimental characterization and multiscale computational modeling. Experimentally, in-situ transmission electron microscopy (TEM) will be carried out to directly observe Li deposition/stripping in the composite structure and scale up to battery-cell level testing. Computationally, molecular dynamics and multi-field continuum-level models will be coupled to simulate Li deposition/stripping and identify the dominant interfacial processes. Such an in-depth characterization and understanding will offer guidance to the optimization of the 3D MIEC/ELI based Li-metal batteries with improved cycling performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034899</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sulin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sulin Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[suz10@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000300092</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 OLD MAIN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPM2J7MSCF61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Penn State]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Technological Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~289469</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The pursuit of safe and high-energy-density energy storage has driven extensive research into the development of all-solid-state rechargeable batteries based on lithium (Li) metal chemistry. Among various candidates for Li-ion battery anode materials, Li metal stands out due to its low electrochemical potential and highest theoretical specific capacity. However, a significant challenge lies in simultaneously maintaining the electrochemical and mechanical stability of the solid components when they come into direct contact with the corrosive Li metal.</span></p> <p><span>In this project, our research team designed a 3D stable Li metal host constructed from mixed ionic-electronic conductors (MIECs) and electronic and Li-ion insulators (ELIs). We initiated the project with a comprehensive screening of the Materials Project Database to identify ELI candidate materials that are thermodynamically stable when exposed to Li metal. Additionally, we implemented a geometric and interfacial design for the MIEC/ELI components, considering their interaction with the electrolytes, with the aim of minimizing the corrosive impact of Li metal. Our research incorporated in-situ transmission electron microscopy to directly observe and evaluate the performance of the constructed battery engines. Furthermore, we developed an integrated model that couples electrochemical and mechanical processes to characterize Li metal deposition under complex electrochemical conditions. Emphasis was placed on understanding and mitigating abnormal Li dendrite growth, which can lead to short circuits. The MIEC/ELI-based cyclic battery engine we designed facilitates smooth cycling of Li metal by nearly free falling and raising in conductive channels, akin to the working fluid in steam engines. This innovative design reduces direct contact between corrosive Li metal and electrolytes while creating efficient stress-relief pathways through diffusional creep. Our research thus enables a new class of 3D Li-metal batteries characterized by superior electrochemo-mechanical stability and prolonged cyclability.</span></p> <p><span>In summary, the integrated design strategies and experimental and modeling tools developed in this project represent a significant step forward in guiding the design of all-solid-state batteries with enhanced performance and durability. Our research introduced a new class of materials to construct battery engine and initiated a paradigm shift in battery engineering and development. The design strategies developed here hold promise for broader applications in the field of electrochemistry. Additionally, this project provided valuable training opportunities for future scientists and engineers specializing in battery materials and energy storage, both in MIT and Penn State University.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 02/12/2024<br> Modified by: Sulin&nbsp;Zhang</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The pursuit of safe and high-energy-density energy storage has driven extensive research into the development of all-solid-state rechargeable batteries based on lithium (Li) metal chemistry. Among various candidates for Li-ion battery anode materials, Li metal stands out due to its low electrochemical potential and highest theoretical specific capacity. However, a significant challenge lies in simultaneously maintaining the electrochemical and mechanical stability of the solid components when they come into direct contact with the corrosive Li metal.   In this project, our research team designed a 3D stable Li metal host constructed from mixed ionic-electronic conductors (MIECs) and electronic and Li-ion insulators (ELIs). We initiated the project with a comprehensive screening of the Materials Project Database to identify ELI candidate materials that are thermodynamically stable when exposed to Li metal. Additionally, we implemented a geometric and interfacial design for the MIEC/ELI components, considering their interaction with the electrolytes, with the aim of minimizing the corrosive impact of Li metal. Our research incorporated in-situ transmission electron microscopy to directly observe and evaluate the performance of the constructed battery engines. Furthermore, we developed an integrated model that couples electrochemical and mechanical processes to characterize Li metal deposition under complex electrochemical conditions. Emphasis was placed on understanding and mitigating abnormal Li dendrite growth, which can lead to short circuits. The MIEC/ELI-based cyclic battery engine we designed facilitates smooth cycling of Li metal by nearly free falling and raising in conductive channels, akin to the working fluid in steam engines. This innovative design reduces direct contact between corrosive Li metal and electrolytes while creating efficient stress-relief pathways through diffusional creep. Our research thus enables a new class of 3D Li-metal batteries characterized by superior electrochemo-mechanical stability and prolonged cyclability.   In summary, the integrated design strategies and experimental and modeling tools developed in this project represent a significant step forward in guiding the design of all-solid-state batteries with enhanced performance and durability. Our research introduced a new class of materials to construct battery engine and initiated a paradigm shift in battery engineering and development. The design strategies developed here hold promise for broader applications in the field of electrochemistry. Additionally, this project provided valuable training opportunities for future scientists and engineers specializing in battery materials and energy storage, both in MIT and Penn State University.        Last Modified: 02/12/2024       Submitted by: SulinZhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
