<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Investigation of a Novel Pressurized Sand Damper for Sustainable Seismic and Wind Protection of Buildings]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>584827.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>632827</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the last 40 years, a variety of well-engineered structures, designed according to building codes that were valid at the time of their construction, experienced severe damage during earthquakes. Most of this damage was the result of excessive seismic displacements, and subsequent research has sought to enhance the seismic performance of civil structures through the development of various strategies to dampen structural displacements. Many existing technologies, however, are disruptive and costly. This research will perform laboratory testing and computer simulations for a newly developed damper, where the material enclosed within the damper is pressurized sand. This research will advance the state-of-the-art in high-performance structures by using a pressurized sand damper (PSD) device, which can perform well under a wide range of temperatures and is low-cost. Scientific understanding and advancement of the PSD will contribute to the welfare of society by mitigating human and economic losses caused by severe earthquake and prolonged wind loading, while meeting current requirements of longevity and sustainability of built infrastructure. Another advantage of the PSD is that it consists only of traditional materials (sand and steel) along with the established technology of post-tensioning, with which civil engineers are most familiar. Educational, outreach, and research activities will be created for middle and high school, undergraduate, and graduate students, including the university's Summer Camps for Girls.  Experimental and simulation data generated by this project will be made available publicly in the NSF-supported Natural Hazards Engineering Engineering Research Infrastructure (NHERI) Data Depot (https://www.DesignSafe-CI.org). This award contributes to NSF's roles in the National Earthquake Hazards Reduction Program (NEHRP) and the National Windstorm Impact Reduction Program (NWIRP). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The original contribution of this research is the development and the experimental and numerical validation of an innovative, low-cost, long-stroke, environmentally friendly, stable PSD that meets the criteria for sustainable engineering without suffering from the challenge of viscous heating. Energy dissipation in the PSD originates from the shearing action of the pressurized sand that exploits the pressure-dependent shear strength of the sand and its effect on increasing the dissipated energy during cyclic motion. The specific goals of this research are to (a) perform comprehensive testing on various configurations of the prototype damper to identify the physical similarities and scaling laws that govern the prototype design; (b) provide continuous, real-time monitoring and adjustment of the internal pressure of the sand damper; (c) conduct numerical modeling of the sand flow/behavior of the PSD using the discrete element method while utilizing crushable models of sand grains, which upon validation with the experimental data will allow for the design of sand dampers at various scales and configurations; and (d) refine a recently developed macroscopic, phenomenological model of the PSD that can be incorporated in open source codes such as OpenSees.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/03/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036131</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicos</FirstName>
<LastName>Makris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicos Makris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nmakris@smu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000677900</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Usama</FirstName>
<LastName>El Shamy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Usama El Shamy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[uelshamy@lyle.smu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000149980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southern Methodist University]]></Name>
<CityName>DALLAS</CityName>
<ZipCode>752051902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2147684708</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6425 BOAZ ST RM 130]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>D33QGS3Q3DJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTHERN METHODIST UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>S88YPE3BLV66</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southern Methodist University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>752750302</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>073Y00</Code>
<Text>ECI-Engineering for Civil Infr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7231</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~584827</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this research initiative we designed, fabricated, tested, and characterized an innovative, low-cost, fail-safe, sustainable, energy dissipation device in which the material surrounding the moving piston and enclosed within the damper housing is pressurized sand.The proposed sand damper does not suffer from the challenge of viscous heating and failure of its end seals, and it can be implemented in harsh environments with either high or low temperatures. Its symmetric force output is velocity-independent, and it can be continuously monitored and adjusted at will with standard commercially available strain gauges installed along the post-tensioned rods that exert the pressure on the sand. Component testing at various levels of pressure, stroke amplitude, and cycling frequency show that the proposed pressurized sand damper exhibits stable hysteretic cyclic behavior with increasing pinching at larger strokes.</p> <p>The exaustive experimental campaign that we conducted during the course of this project investigated the effects oft the key design parameters of the damper, namely, the effect of the clearance between the moving sphere and the cylindrical tube and the effect of the overall length of the damper to its force output. The recorded force-displacement loops when normalized to the strength of the pressurized sand damper reveal remarkable order with stable behavior and confirm that the force output is nearly rate-independent. During the course of the project we investigated the case where the sphere mounted on the piston rod is replaced with a bolt where only the bolt head and nut are protruding from the moving piston rod. With this configuration, the pinching behavior of the pressurized sand damper at longer strokes is suppressed without generating large forces at longer strokes.</p> <p>During the course of this project we also developed a discrete element method (DEM) numerical model to elucidate mechanical behavior, particle crushing, and anisotropy evolution within a pressurized sand damper (PSD) subjected to cyclic loading. Computational simulations of the PSD under different initial pressures and stroke amplitudes were conducted and compared to experimental results. Good agreement was achieved between the DEM model and experimental results for the different cases. Force-displacement, particle crushing, shear, and normal stresses along with geometric and mechanical anisotropy degrees were closely monitored in different areas of the PSD. Dissipated energy was also monitored and used to calculate the specific damping capacity. Employing spherical particles, crushable clusters, and uncrushable clumps as sand particles revealed that the closest results to the experiments are obtained when using crushable clusters. The results show that the majority of crushing occurs in the vicinity of the center of the PSD and within the first loading cycle. Increasing stroke amplitude significantly influenced particle crushing, whereas increasing initial pressure was less considerable. In addition, a direct relationship between the direction of stroke movement with shear and normal stresses and anisotropy degree was observed. Moreover, the contribution of mechanical anisotropy was more considerable than the geometric anisotropy to the overall anisotropy degree.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts from the successful development of the proposed PSD contributes to the mitigation of economic, property and human losses caused by severe earthquake and wind loading, and providing the required level of earthquake and wind protection; while meeting current requirements of longevity and sustainability as well as improving the well-being of the society. An attractive advantage of the proposed PSD is that while it is a device that serves the modern philosophy of response modification, it consists only of traditional materials (sand and steel) along with the established technology of post-tensioning with which practitioner civil engineers are most familiar. This project also suported the development of a rich educational plan that promotes diversity in engineering and created hands-on educational opportunities for undergraduate student through the associated Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) NSF program and graduate students that worked on this initiative. The hydraulic set-up for cyclic testing of the prototype sand damper that was developed at SMU, was integrated into educational activities to have an impact at the university, local and state levels. These activities are aimed at developing a competitive workforce through (a) the recruitment and training of undergraduate and graduate students, in particular those from underrepresented groups, via curriculum development and research experiences; and (b) outreach activities to inspire K-12 students to pursue STEM careers.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/02/2024<br> Modified by: Nicos&nbsp;Makris</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2036131/2036131_10693690_1727870316187_32_Damper--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2036131/2036131_10693690_1727870316187_32_Damper--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pressurized Sand Damper"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2036131/2036131_10693690_1727870316187_32_Damper--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pressurized Sand Damper"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Double-ended pressurized sand damper during prototype  testing at the SMU Structures Laboratory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nicos Makris</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nicos&nbsp;Makris <div class="imageTitle">Pressurized Sand Damper</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  In this research initiative we designed, fabricated, tested, and characterized an innovative, low-cost, fail-safe, sustainable, energy dissipation device in which the material surrounding the moving piston and enclosed within the damper housing is pressurized sand.The proposed sand damper does not suffer from the challenge of viscous heating and failure of its end seals, and it can be implemented in harsh environments with either high or low temperatures. Its symmetric force output is velocity-independent, and it can be continuously monitored and adjusted at will with standard commercially available strain gauges installed along the post-tensioned rods that exert the pressure on the sand. Component testing at various levels of pressure, stroke amplitude, and cycling frequency show that the proposed pressurized sand damper exhibits stable hysteretic cyclic behavior with increasing pinching at larger strokes.   The exaustive experimental campaign that we conducted during the course of this project investigated the effects oft the key design parameters of the damper, namely, the effect of the clearance between the moving sphere and the cylindrical tube and the effect of the overall length of the damper to its force output. The recorded force-displacement loops when normalized to the strength of the pressurized sand damper reveal remarkable order with stable behavior and confirm that the force output is nearly rate-independent. During the course of the project we investigated the case where the sphere mounted on the piston rod is replaced with a bolt where only the bolt head and nut are protruding from the moving piston rod. With this configuration, the pinching behavior of the pressurized sand damper at longer strokes is suppressed without generating large forces at longer strokes.   During the course of this project we also developed a discrete element method (DEM) numerical model to elucidate mechanical behavior, particle crushing, and anisotropy evolution within a pressurized sand damper (PSD) subjected to cyclic loading. Computational simulations of the PSD under different initial pressures and stroke amplitudes were conducted and compared to experimental results. Good agreement was achieved between the DEM model and experimental results for the different cases. Force-displacement, particle crushing, shear, and normal stresses along with geometric and mechanical anisotropy degrees were closely monitored in different areas of the PSD. Dissipated energy was also monitored and used to calculate the specific damping capacity. Employing spherical particles, crushable clusters, and uncrushable clumps as sand particles revealed that the closest results to the experiments are obtained when using crushable clusters. The results show that the majority of crushing occurs in the vicinity of the center of the PSD and within the first loading cycle. Increasing stroke amplitude significantly influenced particle crushing, whereas increasing initial pressure was less considerable. In addition, a direct relationship between the direction of stroke movement with shear and normal stresses and anisotropy degree was observed. Moreover, the contribution of mechanical anisotropy was more considerable than the geometric anisotropy to the overall anisotropy degree.   The broader impacts from the successful development of the proposed PSD contributes to the mitigation of economic, property and human losses caused by severe earthquake and wind loading, and providing the required level of earthquake and wind protection; while meeting current requirements of longevity and sustainability as well as improving the well-being of the society. An attractive advantage of the proposed PSD is that while it is a device that serves the modern philosophy of response modification, it consists only of traditional materials (sand and steel) along with the established technology of post-tensioning with which practitioner civil engineers are most familiar. This project also suported the development of a rich educational plan that promotes diversity in engineering and created hands-on educational opportunities for undergraduate student through the associated Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) NSF program and graduate students that worked on this initiative. The hydraulic set-up for cyclic testing of the prototype sand damper that was developed at SMU, was integrated into educational activities to have an impact at the university, local and state levels. These activities are aimed at developing a competitive workforce through (a) the recruitment and training of undergraduate and graduate students, in particular those from underrepresented groups, via curriculum development and research experiences; and (b) outreach activities to inspire K-12 students to pursue STEM careers.     Last Modified: 10/02/2024       Submitted by: NicosMakris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
