<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Prehistoric Communities Of Practice]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>187215.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>187215</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to study past development of food strategies, cultural boundary and identity formations, and socio-economic organizations of communities of specialized farmers and maritime fisherfolks. By studying these early complementary food producing communities, researchers seek to better understand how different food strategies coalesced to develop more complex and integrated societies. One of the most impacting events in world history—food production and its consequences—led to significant changes in landscapes and human populations, eventually supporting the spread of a settled lifeway and the rise of great civilizations in the ancient world. Yet, food production was more than just a matter of subsistence and landscape changes. It also led to dramatic shifts in social, ritual and symbolic practices, including challenges such as the maintenance of social cohesion in the face of variable community formations, increased social scale and differentiation, environmental changes, new technologies to meet new economic demands, and the need for different ways of developing new institutions to manage the changing nature of different risks. However, managing those challenges through growing collective action and new community norms and institutions may have been as problematical as arriving at successful food production, especially when societies combined different food strategies, which required different means of negotiation and organization to deal with new challenges beyond those of a single mode of production such as agriculture. Research at archaeological sites is best suited to study these changes and challenges through time because they retain the empirical evidence of past food technologies, people’s social and technological organization strategies, and the practices and institutions they formed to deal with those changes and challenges. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Archaeological knowledge of early food production, inter-community integration, technological exploration, innovation and development, and the antecedents and consequences of these activities remains unclear. The offshore coastal waters provide some of the most diverse and abundant marine resources and adjacent shorelines offer one of the most appropriate places to study the socio-economic challenges and interactions that developed between early fishing and farming communities. Such situations representing the evolution of a settled lifeway, population expansion, different labor demands, greater dependence on marine resources and terrestrial foods, major climate fluctuations provide opportunities to study social movements toward civilization. This research focuses on how these fishing and agriculture communities built social cohesion by non-violent means and how they symbolically expressed their changing social and cultural identities with new food production strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039136</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tom</FirstName>
<LastName>Dillehay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tom D Dillehay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tom.d.dillehay@vanderbilt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000375607</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>NASHVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>372032416</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 21ST AVE S]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GTNBNWXJ12D5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372350001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>139100</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~187215</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;Project Outcomes</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Project Title: Prehistoric Communities of Practice<br />PI: Tom D. Dillehay<br />Awardee: Vanderbilt University&nbsp;<br />Award Number: 2039136</p> <p>Grant period: 2020-2024</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The offshore waters of the Pacific coast from Ecuador to Chile in South America provide some of the most diverse and abundant marine resources in the world due to the cold Humboldt Current and major upwelling, making it one of the most appropriate places in the world to study the socio-economic challenges and interactions that developed between early coastal fishing and farming communities.&nbsp;Our archaeological knowledge of&nbsp;socio-economic integration, technological exploration, innovation and development, and the antecedents and consequences of these activities remains unclear in the study of early Andean civilization.&nbsp;The period of 7,500 to 4,500 years ago is a critical time for this civilization, representing the inception and evolution of sedentism, labor demands and lifestyle, dependence on domesticated plant and animal food sources, climate fluctuations, and growth in a pre-Inka state setting. Our project focused on how different household clusters in varying littoral and wetland habitats strived for access to individual resource zones and the symbolic expression of their social identities with food production, individual household communities, and gender identity-marking, the latter perhaps operating as one means of fostering non-violent intra-and inter-community cohesion.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major goal of the NSF research project, led by Tom D. Dillehay of Vanderbilt University, was to study the development of&nbsp;food strategies, social boundary and identity formations, domestic and public activities, and socio-economic organizations&nbsp;of middle Holocene (7,500-4,500 years ago) communities of specialized farmers and maritime fisherfolks in the Chicama Valley on the north coast of Peru.&nbsp;By studying this early complementary food producing communities, we sought to better understand how different food strategies coalesced to develop more complex societies.&nbsp;One of the most impacting events in world history&mdash;food production and its consequences&mdash;led to significant changes in landscapes and human populations, eventually supporting the spread of sedentism and the rise of social complexity.&nbsp;Yet, food production was more than just a matter of subsistence and landscape changes. It also led to dramatic shifts in social, ritual and symbolic practices,&nbsp;including challenges such as the maintenance of social cohesion in the face of variable community formations, increased social scale and differentiation, environmental changes, new technologies to meet new economic demands, and the need for different ways of developing new institutions to manage the changing nature of risk. Food technologies, mortuary patterns, domestic and public sites, organizational strategies, and symbolic iconographies reflect much of the archaeological evidence of the practices and institutions that were formed in the past to deal with those challenges. Managing those challenges through growing collective action and new community norms and institutions may have been as problematical as arriving at successful food production, especially when societies combined different food strategies (i.e., animal husbandry, agriculture, fishing), which required different means of negotiation and organization to deal with new challenges beyond those of a single mode of production (i.e., agriculture). Our research goals were met by providing new data and insight into these challenges and challenges on the north boast of Peru</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our interdisciplinary research also had the opportunity to continue our fruitful long-term connections and formal relations with local participants and community members in various towns on the north coast of Peru, which provided the foundation for future scientific research in the region. Work opportunities for local community members were provided by the project. Informal presentations and meetings in nearby towns where the research team resided for 2-3 months of fieldwork each year focused on a better understanding of local and regional prehistory, hopefully preventing the destruction of sites by giving lectures on project findings and the value of cultural heritage and harboring a greater appreciation for collaborative scientific and archaeological research. Both United States and Peruvian students from various universities participated in the project, including the Universidad Nacional de Trujillo, the Universidad Catolica del Peru, Vanderbilt University, and others.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/12/2024<br> Modified by: Tom&nbsp;D&nbsp;Dillehay</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[                           Project Outcomes      Project Title: Prehistoric Communities of Practice PI: Tom D. Dillehay Awardee: Vanderbilt University Award Number: 2039136   Grant period: 2020-2024      The offshore waters of the Pacific coast from Ecuador to Chile in South America provide some of the most diverse and abundant marine resources in the world due to the cold Humboldt Current and major upwelling, making it one of the most appropriate places in the world to study the socio-economic challenges and interactions that developed between early coastal fishing and farming communities.Our archaeological knowledge ofsocio-economic integration, technological exploration, innovation and development, and the antecedents and consequences of these activities remains unclear in the study of early Andean civilization.The period of 7,500 to 4,500 years ago is a critical time for this civilization, representing the inception and evolution of sedentism, labor demands and lifestyle, dependence on domesticated plant and animal food sources, climate fluctuations, and growth in a pre-Inka state setting. Our project focused on how different household clusters in varying littoral and wetland habitats strived for access to individual resource zones and the symbolic expression of their social identities with food production, individual household communities, and gender identity-marking, the latter perhaps operating as one means of fostering non-violent intra-and inter-community cohesion.         The major goal of the NSF research project, led by Tom D. Dillehay of Vanderbilt University, was to study the development offood strategies, social boundary and identity formations, domestic and public activities, and socio-economic organizationsof middle Holocene (7,500-4,500 years ago) communities of specialized farmers and maritime fisherfolks in the Chicama Valley on the north coast of Peru.By studying this early complementary food producing communities, we sought to better understand how different food strategies coalesced to develop more complex societies.One of the most impacting events in world historyfood production and its consequencesled to significant changes in landscapes and human populations, eventually supporting the spread of sedentism and the rise of social complexity.Yet, food production was more than just a matter of subsistence and landscape changes. It also led to dramatic shifts in social, ritual and symbolic practices,including challenges such as the maintenance of social cohesion in the face of variable community formations, increased social scale and differentiation, environmental changes, new technologies to meet new economic demands, and the need for different ways of developing new institutions to manage the changing nature of risk. Food technologies, mortuary patterns, domestic and public sites, organizational strategies, and symbolic iconographies reflect much of the archaeological evidence of the practices and institutions that were formed in the past to deal with those challenges. Managing those challenges through growing collective action and new community norms and institutions may have been as problematical as arriving at successful food production, especially when societies combined different food strategies (i.e., animal husbandry, agriculture, fishing), which required different means of negotiation and organization to deal with new challenges beyond those of a single mode of production (i.e., agriculture). Our research goals were met by providing new data and insight into these challenges and challenges on the north boast of Peru      Our interdisciplinary research also had the opportunity to continue our fruitful long-term connections and formal relations with local participants and community members in various towns on the north coast of Peru, which provided the foundation for future scientific research in the region. Work opportunities for local community members were provided by the project. Informal presentations and meetings in nearby towns where the research team resided for 2-3 months of fieldwork each year focused on a better understanding of local and regional prehistory, hopefully preventing the destruction of sites by giving lectures on project findings and the value of cultural heritage and harboring a greater appreciation for collaborative scientific and archaeological research. Both United States and Peruvian students from various universities participated in the project, including the Universidad Nacional de Trujillo, the Universidad Catolica del Peru, Vanderbilt University, and others.           Last Modified: 09/12/2024       Submitted by: TomDDillehay]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
