<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Design and development of a multifunctional nanoplatform for augmented elastic matrix repair]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>220319.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>220319</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie George</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stgeorge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Elastic fibers, which allow tissues to stretch and recoil like rubber bands, are not naturally repaired or regenerated in adults following injury or with degenerative disorders. Systems affected by such disorders, termed proteolytic disorders, include skin (psoriasis), respiratory (emphysema), gastrointestinal (irritable bowel syndrome), auto-immune (rheumatoid arthritis) and vascular (aneurysms). This project will use biodegradable chemically-modified polymer nanoparticles to study cellular processes contributing to the breakdown of elastic fibers or stimulation of new fiber assembly and maturation. The effectiveness of these nanoparticles in influencing elastic matrix repair will be tested in structurally disrupted blood vessels maintained viable in a dynamic/pulsating ex vivo (out of body) system. The broader impact of this work will be the transformative potential of the nanoparticle technology in enabling robust on-site elastic tissue repair in the context of cardiovascular disorders which afflict millions worldwide. Thus interdisciplinary project will provide opportunities for scientific education and research training of high school, undergraduate and graduate students through development of educational modules and through the well-established summer internship and outreach programs at their respective institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project to develop and test an innovative nanoparticle platform designed to augment on-site regenerative elastic tissue repair, a continuing challenge in the field of tissue engineering, and in functional restoration of tissues structurally compromised in proteolytic diseases. The planned approach will (1) identify new mechanistic regulators in proteolytically-injured tissues that can be modulated with nitric oxide donor drugs to increase downstream elastogenesis and inhibit proteolysis towards reversing ECM pathophysiology and (2) design and validate a novel, actively targeted nanotherapeutic platform to enable on-site tissue repair in a non-invasive manner. These approaches will be tested in the context of reversing an example proteolytic disorder, abdominal aortic aneurysm. The investigators have earlier established the pro-elastic matrix regenerative and elastolytic enzyme-inhibiting effects of exogenous nitric oxide (NO), and identified c-Jun-N-terminal kinase (JNK; a stress-activated protein kinase upregulated in proteolytic disorders) as a regulator of elastogenesis and proteolytic activity. In this project, the investigators will test a hypothesis that NO acts through JNK attenuation, and that this is a useful predictive metric to optimize NO donor delivery doses to obtain significant improvements to the quantity and qualitative measures of stimulated elastic matrix regeneration. Biodegradable polymeric nanoparticles chemically modified to provide anti-proteolytic and pro-elastogenic effects, and further modified with cathepsin K (an elastase)-inactivating propeptide-derived sequences for active targeting to the injured vessel wall, will serve to provide predictable, steady, and sustained NO donor release for effecting in-tissue matrix repair.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042602</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anand</FirstName>
<LastName>Ramamurthi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anand Ramamurthi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anr320@lehigh.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000653482</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>BETHLEHEM</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[526 BRODHEAD AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E13MDBKHLDB5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>534500</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~220319</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Elastic fibers, which allow tissues to stretch and recoil, acting like rubber bands, are not naturally repaired or regenerated by adult cells following injury and loss in a number of degenerative (proteolytic) disorders. There are currently no ways to regrow or repair these damaged fibers to restore tissue structure and function. The intellectual merit of this work lies in our goal to identify and target such regrowth with a drug called sodium nitroprusside (SNP) a nitric oxide (NO) donor compound, in cultures of cells isolated from rupture-prone expansions of the human aorta, termed as aortic aneurysms. The study developed sub-microscopic biodegradable polymer beads called nanoparticles, designed to release the SNP in a controlled manner over a long term to the cells within the tissues. We identified and validated methods (small protein fragments of an enzyme called cathepsin K expressed in the aneurysm wall) to specifically bind the nanoparticles to the tissue under repair so as to localize the drug release and effect and avoid potentially adverse body wide side effects. We demonstrated that SNP-releasing nanoparticles modified in this manner are effective in repairing and regenerating new elastic fibers in blood vessel tissues that were artificially disrupted in the lab to mimic an aneurysm disease scenario. This study also resulted in a new understanding of the intracellular signaling mechanisms of SNP and the NO impact processes involved in organization and maintenance of tissue structures such as elastic fibers. The broader impact of this work is the transformative potential of the nanoparticle technology to enable robust on-site regenerative elastic tissue repair, a continuing challenge in restoring tissue structure and function, and more specifically in the context of cardiovascular disorders which afflict millions worldwide. The interdisciplinary work conducted in this research study provided opportunities for research dissemination to the scientific community through journal publications and conference presentations/abstracts, and for scientific education and research training of high school, undergraduate and graduate students through development of educational modules and through the auspices of well-established summer internship &amp; outreach programs at our institutions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 03/11/2024<br> Modified by: Anand&nbsp;Ramamurthi</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Elastic fibers, which allow tissues to stretch and recoil, acting like rubber bands, are not naturally repaired or regenerated by adult cells following injury and loss in a number of degenerative (proteolytic) disorders. There are currently no ways to regrow or repair these damaged fibers to restore tissue structure and function. The intellectual merit of this work lies in our goal to identify and target such regrowth with a drug called sodium nitroprusside (SNP) a nitric oxide (NO) donor compound, in cultures of cells isolated from rupture-prone expansions of the human aorta, termed as aortic aneurysms. The study developed sub-microscopic biodegradable polymer beads called nanoparticles, designed to release the SNP in a controlled manner over a long term to the cells within the tissues. We identified and validated methods (small protein fragments of an enzyme called cathepsin K expressed in the aneurysm wall) to specifically bind the nanoparticles to the tissue under repair so as to localize the drug release and effect and avoid potentially adverse body wide side effects. We demonstrated that SNP-releasing nanoparticles modified in this manner are effective in repairing and regenerating new elastic fibers in blood vessel tissues that were artificially disrupted in the lab to mimic an aneurysm disease scenario. This study also resulted in a new understanding of the intracellular signaling mechanisms of SNP and the NO impact processes involved in organization and maintenance of tissue structures such as elastic fibers. The broader impact of this work is the transformative potential of the nanoparticle technology to enable robust on-site regenerative elastic tissue repair, a continuing challenge in restoring tissue structure and function, and more specifically in the context of cardiovascular disorders which afflict millions worldwide. The interdisciplinary work conducted in this research study provided opportunities for research dissemination to the scientific community through journal publications and conference presentations/abstracts, and for scientific education and research training of high school, undergraduate and graduate students through development of educational modules and through the auspices of well-established summer internship & outreach programs at our institutions.                 Last Modified: 03/11/2024       Submitted by: AnandRamamurthi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
