<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Transforming Integrative Makerspace Education for STEM Pre-service Teachers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>281830.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>281830</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Ellis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jtellis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922125</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest of improving the quality and effectiveness of STEM education for pre-service teachers (education college majors) through a focus on integration of makerspace pedagogy.  Makerspace education involves students working with their hands collaboratively to make, learn, explore, and share to advance their learning and success in STEM areas. Education and STEM faculty will collaborate to integrate makerspace pedagogy into 10 interdisciplinary education core and methods courses to emphasize STEM experiential learning. While this project primarily focuses on undergraduate students majoring in elementary education, undergraduate pre-service teachers preparing for teacher certification in grades 4-8 or 7-12 may also benefit from curricular improvements in these required courses. The project intends to build knowledge about teaching and learning by developing, implementing, and assessing faculty development, interactive instruction, and STEM lesson plan development. This project offers a valuable opportunity to improve STEM thinking skills by formally integrating STEM concepts throughout the pre-service teacher curriculum using an interdisciplinary approach.  The project utilizes a makerspace laboratory at Point Park University (PPR). However, the project design is such that other institutions of higher education should be able to replicate the program with or without a physical makerspace lab as the project’s findings and “maker mindset” are employed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Community partners, the Children’s Museum of Pittsburgh, the Matt’s Makerspace Organization, and the Allegheny Intermediate Unit, will provide maker pedagogy professional development to PPR faculty in the School of Education and the Department of Natural Sciences, Engineering and Technology.  These faculty members will attend 10-15 professional development sessions in STEM learning in makerspaces, and then revise the course content of 10 courses, as well as develop lessons and assessments for the assignments.  Utilizing qualitative research methodology, the project intends to investigate the following research question:  What do pre-service teachers and faculty members identify as areas of pedagogical growth in STEM learning and teaching in a makerspace environment?  This research aims to highlight the impact of makerspace pedagogy on improving STEM education learning outcomes through an interdisciplinary constructivist approach. The project is expected to have a multiplier effect as it impacts STEM disciplinary and education faculty at PPU, pre-service teachers, and teacher preparation programs at other universities that benefit from what is learned at PPU.  Ultimately, the future students of the well-prepared pre-service teachers steeped in maker pedagogy and STEM content will have the potential to develop higher level thinking skills and improve their mathematics and scientific achievement, which are essential for the 21st century STEM workforce. The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.  The Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship (Noyce) Program is providing co-funding for this IUSE: EHR project to support the project's preservice teacher preparation goals, which are well-aligned with Noyce Program goals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042641</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
<LastName>Chambers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Virginia H Chambers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vchambers@pointpark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832022</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Marnich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Marnich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmarnich@pointpark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832023</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kamryn</FirstName>
<LastName>York</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kamryn S York</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kyork@pointpark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832020</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[POINT PARK UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152221912</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4123914100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 WOOD ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZMPHH84J4NN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>POINT PARK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Point Park University]]></Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152221984</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Wood Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>179500</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~281830</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>T.I.M.E. FOR STEM: TRANSFORMING INTEGRATIVE MAKERSPACE EDUCATION</p> <p>The Transforming Integrative Makerspace Education for Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (T.I.M.E. for STEM) project, supported by the National Science Foundation, focused on improving the quality and effectiveness of STEM education for pre-service teachers. The project, a collaborative effort between the School of Education (SOE) and the Department of Natural Sciences and Engineering (NSE) at Point Park University, builds on the knowledge about teaching and learning by creating, implementing, and assessing faculty development, interactive instruction, and STEM lesson plan development. This initiative aimed to elevate the quality of STEM education for pre-service teachers by integrating interdisciplinary learning within a makerspace environment. Drawing on the National Institute for STEM Education (NISE) guiding principles and domains, NSE faculty provided professional development to SOE faculty in the STEM areas of mathematics, biology, and physics while the T.I.M.E. for STEM community partners contributed professional development in makerspace pedagogy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Maker-education offers transformative, creative, and collaborative student-centered hands-on learning experiences that align with real-world STEM practices. Makerspace labs or classrooms are the physical workspaces that utilize high-tech to no-tech tools for making, learning, exploring, and sharing. The utilization of a makerspace provides opportunities for students to engage in problem-solving projects and cultivate a deeper understanding of STEM concepts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This study explored the pedagogical growth of pre-service teachers and faculty members in STEM learning and teaching within a makerspace environment. Utilizing a content analysis approach, pre and post surveys were administered to assess participants' understanding of maker pedagogy and STEM learning. The findings reveal significant improvements in participants' perceptions and practices across key domains outlined by NISE, including creating an environment for learning, building scientific understanding, and engaging students in scientific and engineering practices. The attached graphs detail these improvements.</p> <p>Several key outcomes resulted from the three-year research project that will help advance knowledge and intellectual merit in STEM pedagogy. Additional broader impacts will benefit society by contributing to the achievement of a more STEM informed population.</p> <p>Key Outcome: Point Park University School of Education faculty broadened their understanding of STEM teaching and learning in a makerspace environment because of robust professional development. As a result, ten education courses were revised to include content and practices based on the latest academic and practicing research. The faculty shared their knowledge with the education community through multiple international, national, and local conferences and colloquia.</p> <p>Key Outcome: Pre-service teachers were better prepared to instruct in a makerspace by incorporating the strategies necessary to handle the pedagogical and technological infrastructure of makerspaces.</p> <p>Moreover, the project developed novel learning environments to promote understanding with diverse groups of students.</p> <p>Key Outcome: Point Park University was approved by the Pennsylvania Department of Education (PDE) to deliver a PreK-4 STEM Endorsement for elementary teachers. This initiative underscores the importance of interdisciplinary approaches and technology integration in preparing educators to foster student success in STEM disciplines, thereby addressing the critical need for effective STEM teachers and promoting positive attitudes towards STEM subjects from an early age.</p> <p>Key Outcome: The following tools were created to assist educators when developing makerspace centered STEM educational initiatives:</p> <p>T.I.M.E. for STEM Lesson Plan Template T.I.M.E. for STEM Maker Education Teaching Matrix</p> <p>T.I.M.E. for STEM Observation Rubric T.I.M.E. for STEM Maker Mindset Classroom Guide</p> <p>Curriculum Alignment Matrix for PreK-4 Education Coursework</p> <p>Key Outcome: The creation of a Matt&rsquo;s Maker Space Fellowship Award at the SEK International School in Dublin, Ireland. Each year, three awardees will be given a scholarship to travel to Dublin for the opportunity to study makerspace STEM education in a leading international institution. Awardees will return to the United States and share their knowledge with pre-service teachers and faculty.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impact: Potential for replication and scalability across higher education institutions and teacher training organizations. The T.I.M.E. for STEM project created makerspace activities that were flexible enough to be replicated at institutions with or without their own makerspace labs. By leveraging community partnerships and adaptable makerspace activities, T.I.M.E. for STEM offers a model for enhancing STEM education that is accessible to diverse educational communities. The lesson plans developed as a result of the study were copiously disseminated with the general education community through conference proceedings and professional development events.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/14/2024<br> Modified by: Virginia&nbsp;H&nbsp;Chambers</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2042641/2042641_10749624_1728947556292_TIME_for_STEM_Outcomes_Graphs--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2042641/2042641_10749624_1728947556292_TIME_for_STEM_Outcomes_Graphs--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Outcomes Graphs"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2042641/2042641_10749624_1728947556292_TIME_for_STEM_Outcomes_Graphs--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Outcomes Graphs"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">TIME for STEM Outcomes Graph</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mark Marnich</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Virginia&nbsp;H&nbsp;Chambers <div class="imageTitle">Outcomes Graphs</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  T.I.M.E. FOR STEM: TRANSFORMING INTEGRATIVE MAKERSPACE EDUCATION   The Transforming Integrative Makerspace Education for Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (T.I.M.E. for STEM) project, supported by the National Science Foundation, focused on improving the quality and effectiveness of STEM education for pre-service teachers. The project, a collaborative effort between the School of Education (SOE) and the Department of Natural Sciences and Engineering (NSE) at Point Park University, builds on the knowledge about teaching and learning by creating, implementing, and assessing faculty development, interactive instruction, and STEM lesson plan development. This initiative aimed to elevate the quality of STEM education for pre-service teachers by integrating interdisciplinary learning within a makerspace environment. Drawing on the National Institute for STEM Education (NISE) guiding principles and domains, NSE faculty provided professional development to SOE faculty in the STEM areas of mathematics, biology, and physics while the T.I.M.E. for STEM community partners contributed professional development in makerspace pedagogy.      Maker-education offers transformative, creative, and collaborative student-centered hands-on learning experiences that align with real-world STEM practices. Makerspace labs or classrooms are the physical workspaces that utilize high-tech to no-tech tools for making, learning, exploring, and sharing. The utilization of a makerspace provides opportunities for students to engage in problem-solving projects and cultivate a deeper understanding of STEM concepts.      This study explored the pedagogical growth of pre-service teachers and faculty members in STEM learning and teaching within a makerspace environment. Utilizing a content analysis approach, pre and post surveys were administered to assess participants' understanding of maker pedagogy and STEM learning. The findings reveal significant improvements in participants' perceptions and practices across key domains outlined by NISE, including creating an environment for learning, building scientific understanding, and engaging students in scientific and engineering practices. The attached graphs detail these improvements.   Several key outcomes resulted from the three-year research project that will help advance knowledge and intellectual merit in STEM pedagogy. Additional broader impacts will benefit society by contributing to the achievement of a more STEM informed population.   Key Outcome: Point Park University School of Education faculty broadened their understanding of STEM teaching and learning in a makerspace environment because of robust professional development. As a result, ten education courses were revised to include content and practices based on the latest academic and practicing research. The faculty shared their knowledge with the education community through multiple international, national, and local conferences and colloquia.   Key Outcome: Pre-service teachers were better prepared to instruct in a makerspace by incorporating the strategies necessary to handle the pedagogical and technological infrastructure of makerspaces.   Moreover, the project developed novel learning environments to promote understanding with diverse groups of students.   Key Outcome: Point Park University was approved by the Pennsylvania Department of Education (PDE) to deliver a PreK-4 STEM Endorsement for elementary teachers. This initiative underscores the importance of interdisciplinary approaches and technology integration in preparing educators to foster student success in STEM disciplines, thereby addressing the critical need for effective STEM teachers and promoting positive attitudes towards STEM subjects from an early age.   Key Outcome: The following tools were created to assist educators when developing makerspace centered STEM educational initiatives:   T.I.M.E. for STEM Lesson Plan Template T.I.M.E. for STEM Maker Education Teaching Matrix   T.I.M.E. for STEM Observation Rubric T.I.M.E. for STEM Maker Mindset Classroom Guide   Curriculum Alignment Matrix for PreK-4 Education Coursework   Key Outcome: The creation of a Matts Maker Space Fellowship Award at the SEK International School in Dublin, Ireland. Each year, three awardees will be given a scholarship to travel to Dublin for the opportunity to study makerspace STEM education in a leading international institution. Awardees will return to the United States and share their knowledge with pre-service teachers and faculty.      Broader Impact: Potential for replication and scalability across higher education institutions and teacher training organizations. The T.I.M.E. for STEM project created makerspace activities that were flexible enough to be replicated at institutions with or without their own makerspace labs. By leveraging community partnerships and adaptable makerspace activities, T.I.M.E. for STEM offers a model for enhancing STEM education that is accessible to diverse educational communities. The lesson plans developed as a result of the study were copiously disseminated with the general education community through conference proceedings and professional development events.        Last Modified: 10/14/2024       Submitted by: VirginiaHChambers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
