<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Disability Expertise and Design Justice for Post-COVID Equity]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>618490.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>618490</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christine Leuenberger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cleuenbe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927563</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will analyze the lives of disabled and chronically ill people during the COVID-19 pandemic to understand their experiences and capture the strategies that they have developed for surviving under new, difficult conditions. Disabled people, especially people of color and those living in nursing homes, have been at greatest risk of infection and death from COVID-19. Documenting and interpreting disability expertise and the methods by which by which marginalized groups respond to the pandemic will provide crucial information for helping to address the inequities for people with disabilities as they manage health risk post-COVID and in relation to future pandemics and social crises. Researchers will collaborate with community members to collect memories, stories, artwork, and other materials to build a publicly accessible archive know as the “Disability COVID Chronicles.” Conversations on social media, records of digital public meetings, and photographs of street art and actions that are otherwise ephemeral will also be collected, interpreted, and preserved. This archive will be of value for scholars and for those working to achieve better conditions for disabled citizens in the future. Project findings will be widely disseminated in public and academic publications and through social media, events, and city partnerships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will collect and analyze data about COVID-19 design related issues (e.g., congregate living, telework, tele-therapy) and compare and analyze cases from a “design justice” perspective, focusing on innovative uses of remote technology and infrastructure. It focuses on four social groups that experts and the disabled anticipate will experience prolonged impacts from COVID-19. These groups include: (1) People with chronic fatigue syndrome who can serve as models of post-viral syndromes and survivorship with longstanding expertise in remote work and tele-intimacy; (2) Adults with intellectual disabilities and their families, whose high infection and death rates have highlighted the hazards of congregate housing, and who are actively generating new designs for long-term assisted living; (3) Black Disabled Lives Matter activists who underscore the intersection of race and disability in COVID health risks and are developing accessible physical and digital tools for supporting online advocacy and protests; and (4) Black subjects facing mental health challenges. The project will also consider the potentials for new remote practices in mobile crisis intervention, peer counseling by trained mental health patients, and teletherapy pioneered by groups responding to these challenges to help support the disabled community. Findings will be published in academic journals and publicly accessible white papers and public media.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043833</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rayna</FirstName>
<LastName>Rapp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rayna Rapp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rayna.rapp@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000123806</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Faye</FirstName>
<LastName>Ginsburg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Faye Ginsburg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[faye.ginsburg@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000306573</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mara</FirstName>
<LastName>Mills</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mara C Mills</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmills@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000649512</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[70 WASHINGTON SQ S]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NX9PXMKW5KW8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100036674</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[239 Greene Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y00</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~618490</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>From 2021-2024, PI Mills and co-PIs Ginsburg and Rapp, and former doctoral student Harris Kornstein, assembled a team of 30+ students, postdoctoral fellows, faculty, and community members to conduct qualitative (historical, ethnographic, and sociological) STS research documenting the experiences of disabled and chronically ill people living in an early epicenter of the COVID-19 pandemic: New York City. We ultimately produced a 15-chapter book,&nbsp;<em>How to be Disabled in a Pandemic</em>, forthcoming in print and accessible Open Access versions (NYU Press 2025).&nbsp;</p> <p>In phase one, the grant supported the team's research as the COVID pandemic unfolded, including oral histories and ethnographic interviews with diverse disabled groups. Our initial research culminated in a public website (https://disabilitycovidchronicles.nyu.edu), to be digitally archived at NYU, featuring essays and fieldnotes documenting artistic and disability activist responses to the pandemic.</p> <p>In phase two, team members drafted and revised chapters for&nbsp;<em>How to be Disabled in a Pandemic.&nbsp;</em>The book includes work by STS and disability studies scholars, disability activists and arts experts, a librarian for the NYPL Heiskell Braille and Talking Book Library, an immigration lawyer, and prison educators, among others.</p> <p>Our research focus on one city enabled us to compare disability experiences across factors like neighborhood, age, and race, while situated within a similar geographic location, set of legal constraints, and public health regime. Recognizing that the pandemic was a "mass disabling event" (Barbarin), we explored the structural logics of death, disablement, and survival that become apparent during pandemics, highlighting the unequal tolls of COVID on a "viral underclass" (Thrasher 2022) through entrenched inequalities like racial ableism (Ben-Moshe 2016).</p> <p>We also identified "the disability dialectic":&nbsp;faced with the enormous threats and consequences of the pandemic, disabled people manifested remarkable creativity and resistance. This was unsurprising, given the extensive individual and communal "disability expertise" (Hartblay 2020) achieved through years of navigating, protesting, and reinventing the numerous political, health, media, and other social systems that neglect or exhibit hostility toward disabled people. We saw new and broad audiences taking up these insights from chronically ill and disabled activists and scholars. Many chapters in our volume foreground cross-disability coalitions and "crip doulaing," a form of mutual aid (Milbern).&nbsp;<em>How to be Disabled in a Pandemic</em>&nbsp;also includes significant research with institutionalized disabled people who had few opportunities for creative or public response. Disability&nbsp;is often used to justify confinement (in nursing homes, hospitals, or prisons); that same confinement exacerbates the risks and consequences of illness and injury.&nbsp;</p> <p>Part 1 of the book, "Living with 'Disproportionate Risk': Policies, Institutions, and Congregate Settings," opens with a chapter on incarcerated disabled people and illness in state prisons (Bardelli, Thomas, and Brown). A chapter on disability and COVID in migrant detention centers raises the question: who counts as a New Yorker (Salyer)?. Chapters also examine the present-day legal legacy governing shelter for unhoused people during the early AIDS epidemic (Bhaman); rapidly changing MTA policies for mobility-impaired New Yorkers (Grenier); ableism and racial bias in state and hospital ventilator-allocation protocols (Mills); loss of services and sociality experienced by "special ed" students in the schools (Freidus, Fish, and Turner); and adults with intellectual/developmental disabilities living at home, often with aging family members who resumed caregiving as longstanding paid caregivers became unavailable (Ginsburg and Rapp).&nbsp;</p> <p>In Part 2, "Disability Communities: Expertise, Activism, and Solidarity," our authors focus on pandemic "doulaship" and disability cultural production. It includes a chapter on people with ME/CFS and other chronic illness activists responding to the emergent disabilities of Long COVID (Kornstein and Rogers); and another on the complex experiences of blind New Yorkers regarding remote access (Coklyat and Fleet). There are chapters on immigrants in New York's Chinatown finding community in a local senior center while facing vulnerability from the pandemic and anti-Asian violence (Li); an analysis of the "iron cage" of medical bureaucracy and disparities that challenge Black mothers' mental health in the context of the dual pandemics of COVID and anti-Black racism (Mbonde); and the pandemic sociality and mutual aid of autistic adults, including low-wage essential workers who were temporarily freed by the CARES Act for social and creative pursuits (Ryan). Finally, there is a reflection by Amanda Morris, the first disability reporter at the&nbsp;<em>New York Times</em>, on the stories she was not able to tell and the ongoing deaths of immunocompromised New Yorkers from COVID.</p> <p>Additionally, the book includes a foreword by Pulitzer-winning science journalist Ed Yong and a coda by renowned disability activist Judith Heumann. It also features a timeline and glossary to increase accessibility of these archives and analyses.</p> <p>Ultimately,&nbsp;<em>How to be Disabled in a Pandemic</em>&nbsp;reveals cross-cutting themes: hierarchies of disability "vulnerability," the deployment of disability and care as tools of population management, and many examples of innovative crip pandemic cultural production.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 08/08/2024<br> Modified by: Mara&nbsp;C&nbsp;Mills</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  From 2021-2024, PI Mills and co-PIs Ginsburg and Rapp, and former doctoral student Harris Kornstein, assembled a team of 30+ students, postdoctoral fellows, faculty, and community members to conduct qualitative (historical, ethnographic, and sociological) STS research documenting the experiences of disabled and chronically ill people living in an early epicenter of the COVID-19 pandemic: New York City. We ultimately produced a 15-chapter book,How to be Disabled in a Pandemic, forthcoming in print and accessible Open Access versions (NYU Press 2025).   In phase one, the grant supported the team's research as the COVID pandemic unfolded, including oral histories and ethnographic interviews with diverse disabled groups. Our initial research culminated in a public website (https://disabilitycovidchronicles.nyu.edu), to be digitally archived at NYU, featuring essays and fieldnotes documenting artistic and disability activist responses to the pandemic.   In phase two, team members drafted and revised chapters forHow to be Disabled in a Pandemic.The book includes work by STS and disability studies scholars, disability activists and arts experts, a librarian for the NYPL Heiskell Braille and Talking Book Library, an immigration lawyer, and prison educators, among others.   Our research focus on one city enabled us to compare disability experiences across factors like neighborhood, age, and race, while situated within a similar geographic location, set of legal constraints, and public health regime. Recognizing that the pandemic was a "mass disabling event" (Barbarin), we explored the structural logics of death, disablement, and survival that become apparent during pandemics, highlighting the unequal tolls of COVID on a "viral underclass" (Thrasher 2022) through entrenched inequalities like racial ableism (Ben-Moshe 2016).   We also identified "the disability dialectic":faced with the enormous threats and consequences of the pandemic, disabled people manifested remarkable creativity and resistance. This was unsurprising, given the extensive individual and communal "disability expertise" (Hartblay 2020) achieved through years of navigating, protesting, and reinventing the numerous political, health, media, and other social systems that neglect or exhibit hostility toward disabled people. We saw new and broad audiences taking up these insights from chronically ill and disabled activists and scholars. Many chapters in our volume foreground cross-disability coalitions and "crip doulaing," a form of mutual aid (Milbern).How to be Disabled in a Pandemicalso includes significant research with institutionalized disabled people who had few opportunities for creative or public response. Disabilityis often used to justify confinement (in nursing homes, hospitals, or prisons); that same confinement exacerbates the risks and consequences of illness and injury.   Part 1 of the book, "Living with 'Disproportionate Risk': Policies, Institutions, and Congregate Settings," opens with a chapter on incarcerated disabled people and illness in state prisons (Bardelli, Thomas, and Brown). A chapter on disability and COVID in migrant detention centers raises the question: who counts as a New Yorker (Salyer)?. Chapters also examine the present-day legal legacy governing shelter for unhoused people during the early AIDS epidemic (Bhaman); rapidly changing MTA policies for mobility-impaired New Yorkers (Grenier); ableism and racial bias in state and hospital ventilator-allocation protocols (Mills); loss of services and sociality experienced by "special ed" students in the schools (Freidus, Fish, and Turner); and adults with intellectual/developmental disabilities living at home, often with aging family members who resumed caregiving as longstanding paid caregivers became unavailable (Ginsburg and Rapp).   In Part 2, "Disability Communities: Expertise, Activism, and Solidarity," our authors focus on pandemic "doulaship" and disability cultural production. It includes a chapter on people with ME/CFS and other chronic illness activists responding to the emergent disabilities of Long COVID (Kornstein and Rogers); and another on the complex experiences of blind New Yorkers regarding remote access (Coklyat and Fleet). There are chapters on immigrants in New York's Chinatown finding community in a local senior center while facing vulnerability from the pandemic and anti-Asian violence (Li); an analysis of the "iron cage" of medical bureaucracy and disparities that challenge Black mothers' mental health in the context of the dual pandemics of COVID and anti-Black racism (Mbonde); and the pandemic sociality and mutual aid of autistic adults, including low-wage essential workers who were temporarily freed by the CARES Act for social and creative pursuits (Ryan). Finally, there is a reflection by Amanda Morris, the first disability reporter at theNew York Times, on the stories she was not able to tell and the ongoing deaths of immunocompromised New Yorkers from COVID.   Additionally, the book includes a foreword by Pulitzer-winning science journalist Ed Yong and a coda by renowned disability activist Judith Heumann. It also features a timeline and glossary to increase accessibility of these archives and analyses.   Ultimately,How to be Disabled in a Pandemicreveals cross-cutting themes: hierarchies of disability "vulnerability," the deployment of disability and care as tools of population management, and many examples of innovative crip pandemic cultural production.     Last Modified: 08/08/2024       Submitted by: MaraCMills]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
