<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Gender and Race in the History of Folk Medicine]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15750.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15750</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>During the last few decades, many parts of the world have witnessed the resurgence of midwifery and other traditional healing practices. Even in cities, sites where biomedicine has allegedly taken hold, there is a growing interest in medical alternatives. This contemporary phenomenon challenges the teleological framework of traditional histories of medicine that have long been interested in explaining the emergence of biomedicine, the professionalization of medicine, and relatedly, the medicalization of society, and calls for a longer examination of the history of folk medicine. Following a long tradition of scholarship that questions unilinear narratives of scientific or medical modernity, this project argues that folk healers were, and remain to be, essential medical providers. Progress narratives that have presented them as superseded or ousted by the professional doctor are always created retrospectively by historians and fall into the trap of teleology. This project establishes a conversation between past and present to investigate how present-day concerns shape the knowledge that is produced about the history of folk medicine, and conversely, how the past resonates in the lives of its current practitioners. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This longitudinal study reconstructs the lives of unlicensed midwives, healers, and surgeons, people who provided the bulk of medical care before the rise of biomedicine in towns and villages where there were few or no doctors. Three main questions drive this research: First, who provided the lion's share of medical care regionally before the rise of biomedicine, and what were the key medical practices involved that have so far eluded historical analysis? Second, how did race and gender shape the medical interventions of folk healers? And third, how do contemporary narratives of scientific modernity inform the ways of understanding the history of folk medicine? This project focuses on the role of midwives, healers and surgeons as medical experts in criminal trials, civil trials, and their participation in municipal councils, all instances in which they provided medical certifications to townspeople. Drawing on qualitative data gathered in multiple archives, this project analyzes how diverse actors (patients, judges, lawyers, and witnesses) upheld ideas of proper/improper behavior according to gender and race ideologies, and how medical practitioners challenged or reproduced such imaginaries in their medical practice. This project supplements archival research with interviews involving current folk healers, in order to reflect on: 1) how they conceive of the body, disease, and healing today; 2) how they understand their own past and history. In doing so, this study aims to articulate the role of gender and race in the construction of medical expertise, and to elucidate how present-day concerns shape the knowledge that is produced about the past, and how the past resonates in the present.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043599</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Delbourgo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Delbourgo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jdelbourgo@history.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833447</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisette</FirstName>
<LastName>Varon-Carvajal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisette Varon-Carvajal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lv209@history.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3 RUTGERS PLZ]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RUTGERS UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName>PISCATAWAY</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[33 KNIGHTSBRIDGE ROAD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y00</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~15750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Exploring the Role of Gender and Race in Folk Medicine&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>During my research, I discovered fascinating insights into the medical practices of colonial Colombia, then known as the viceroyalty of New Granada, and I successfully defended my dissertation using these insights. Here are some of the key findings product of the Doctoral Dissertation Impriovement Grant:</p> <p><strong>The Marginal Role of Formal Medical Institutions</strong></p> <ol> <li><strong>Archival Discoveries in Spain:</strong>  <ul> <li>In the Archivo de Simancas, I found a rare medical license issued by the Royal Protomedicato, a regulatory body for medical practitioners. This license, granted to a court physician in Aragon, highlighted the importance of formal medical institutions in peninsular Spain. In contrast, such licenses were nonexistent in Colombian archives, underscoring the marginal role of the Protomedicato in New Granada. This suggests that folk or popular medicine was far more prevalent in colonial Colombia.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Documents from the Archivo de Indias:</strong>  <ul> <li>While exploring the "Indiferente General" section, which contains a mix of documents from across the Spanish Empire, I found only one tome related to physicians and medical licenses out of over 200 examined. Interestingly, none of these documents pertained to New Granada. This further emphasizes the limited influence of formal medical institutions in the region compared to other parts of the empire.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Regulation and Reality:</strong>  <ul> <li>Even where documents existed, the impact of licensed physicians was minimal in Spanish America. Many practitioners operated without formal licenses, often receiving exemptions from royal authorities. This highlights the dominance of informal medical practices and the limited reach of the Protomedicato.</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <p><strong>The Role of Women in Folk Medicine</strong></p> <ol> <li><strong>Interviews with Midwives and Doulas:</strong>  <ul> <li>Through interviews, I learned that midwifery is very much alive in Colombia, especially in cities like Bogota. The COVID-19 pandemic actually boosted the visibility of midwives as more women sought alternatives to hospital births. Urban midwives often combine biomedical training with traditional practices, while midwives from the Pacific region are particularly renowned for their skills.</li> <li>In July 2022, Colombia passed Law 2244, recognizing the rights of birthing women and midwives. While some midwives welcomed the law, others felt it might restrict their practices. This reflects the diverse perspectives within the midwifery community.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Midwives and Feminism:</strong>  <ul> <li>Many Bogota midwives align their work with feminist principles, emphasizing the value of care. However, there is tension between midwives and other feminist movements, particularly regarding abortion rights. Midwives often focus on the value of fetal life, which can conflict with the broader feminist emphasis on a woman's right to choose.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Ethnic and Racial Identity:</strong>  <ul> <li>When discussing their identities, some midwives identified as "mestiza," highlighting a blend of various medical traditions. This term reflects the rich cultural and medical heritage that shapes their practices.</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <div> <hr size="0" /> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p><span>This research creatively blends solid historical analysis, based on extensive archival work in Colombia and Spain, with interviews from modern organizations of female healthcare providers. These findings reveal the complex and dynamic nature of medical practices in colonial Colombia and modern Bogot&aacute;, showing a rich interplay between formal institutions and folk healers.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The results of this study add to the growing body of research on the history of medicine in Latin America. This work is part of a larger movement that challenges the traditional focus on licensed doctors and formal medical institutions. Instead, it highlights the crucial roles played by popular healers, especially women, in the history of healthcare. By focusing on care and especially on female practitioners, this research underscores the enduring role of women in healthcare. It traces their contributions from the past to the present, highlighting both historical roots and current challenges. However, this project does not idealize the work of women or folk healers. Instead, it presents a balanced view, acknowledging the complexities, difficulties, and even problematic aspects of their roles, thus bringing to light often overlooked stories about healthcare and medical knowledge.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/17/2024<br> Modified by: Lisette&nbsp;Varon-Carvajal</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Exploring the Role of Gender and Race in Folk Medicine   During my research, I discovered fascinating insights into the medical practices of colonial Colombia, then known as the viceroyalty of New Granada, and I successfully defended my dissertation using these insights. Here are some of the key findings product of the Doctoral Dissertation Impriovement Grant:   The Marginal Role of Formal Medical Institutions  Archival Discoveries in Spain:   In the Archivo de Simancas, I found a rare medical license issued by the Royal Protomedicato, a regulatory body for medical practitioners. This license, granted to a court physician in Aragon, highlighted the importance of formal medical institutions in peninsular Spain. In contrast, such licenses were nonexistent in Colombian archives, underscoring the marginal role of the Protomedicato in New Granada. This suggests that folk or popular medicine was far more prevalent in colonial Colombia.   Documents from the Archivo de Indias:   While exploring the "Indiferente General" section, which contains a mix of documents from across the Spanish Empire, I found only one tome related to physicians and medical licenses out of over 200 examined. Interestingly, none of these documents pertained to New Granada. This further emphasizes the limited influence of formal medical institutions in the region compared to other parts of the empire.   Regulation and Reality:   Even where documents existed, the impact of licensed physicians was minimal in Spanish America. Many practitioners operated without formal licenses, often receiving exemptions from royal authorities. This highlights the dominance of informal medical practices and the limited reach of the Protomedicato.      The Role of Women in Folk Medicine  Interviews with Midwives and Doulas:   Through interviews, I learned that midwifery is very much alive in Colombia, especially in cities like Bogota. The COVID-19 pandemic actually boosted the visibility of midwives as more women sought alternatives to hospital births. Urban midwives often combine biomedical training with traditional practices, while midwives from the Pacific region are particularly renowned for their skills. In July 2022, Colombia passed Law 2244, recognizing the rights of birthing women and midwives. While some midwives welcomed the law, others felt it might restrict their practices. This reflects the diverse perspectives within the midwifery community.   Midwives and Feminism:   Many Bogota midwives align their work with feminist principles, emphasizing the value of care. However, there is tension between midwives and other feminist movements, particularly regarding abortion rights. Midwives often focus on the value of fetal life, which can conflict with the broader feminist emphasis on a woman's right to choose.   Ethnic and Racial Identity:   When discussing their identities, some midwives identified as "mestiza," highlighting a blend of various medical traditions. This term reflects the rich cultural and medical heritage that shapes their practices.            Outcomes   This research creatively blends solid historical analysis, based on extensive archival work in Colombia and Spain, with interviews from modern organizations of female healthcare providers. These findings reveal the complex and dynamic nature of medical practices in colonial Colombia and modern Bogot, showing a rich interplay between formal institutions and folk healers.   The results of this study add to the growing body of research on the history of medicine in Latin America. This work is part of a larger movement that challenges the traditional focus on licensed doctors and formal medical institutions. Instead, it highlights the crucial roles played by popular healers, especially women, in the history of healthcare. By focusing on care and especially on female practitioners, this research underscores the enduring role of women in healthcare. It traces their contributions from the past to the present, highlighting both historical roots and current challenges. However, this project does not idealize the work of women or folk healers. Instead, it presents a balanced view, acknowledging the complexities, difficulties, and even problematic aspects of their roles, thus bringing to light often overlooked stories about healthcare and medical knowledge.        Last Modified: 07/17/2024       Submitted by: LisetteVaron-Carvajal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
