<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: The Not-So-Inexhaustible Sea: Fisheries Science and Management 1863-present]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20204.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20204</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fish provide the primary source of protein for a billion people, but that crucial food supply is threatened by overfishing. Despite a vast scientific and policy literature arguing that sustainable fisheries are achievable through scientific models and management frameworks, the health of global fisheries continues to decline. This suggests that there may be something fundamentally wrong with the way we have tried to analyze, understand, and manage fishing. This project examines an overlooked but critical factor in the overfishing crisis: the false belief that fisheries are inexhaustible, meaning they can be harvested at contemporary rates indefinitely, year after year, without risk of collapse. The resulting dissertation will: 1) document the history of inexhaustibility and show how resistance to the idea of dwindling fish stocks has taken different forms over the centuries; 2) examine what propels belief in inexhaustible seas; and 3) suggest how its influence might be mitigated to allow for the development of more effective and resilient fisheries management strategies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project finds surprising continuities over a hundred and fifty years of history. Preliminary results from archival research methods show that inexhaustibility appears in diverse forms over time but for similar reasons, including 1) overconfidence in quantitative science and free markets to simplify and solve complex environmental and social problems; 2) failure to account for observed fluctuations in fish populations that may make predictable and sustainable annual catches very difficult in the long term; and 3) an inertia generated by existing models, areas of focus, and management strategies that precludes new ways of thinking. Drawing on historian Thomas Hughes’ notion of technological momentum, this project suggests that the idea of inexhaustibility has had sufficient intellectual momentum that it has proved nearly impossible to dislodge, even in the face of volumes of refuting empirical evidence. Through publications, op-eds, forums, round-table discussions, and oral histories deposited in the NOAA Voices archive, this project will engage scientists, policy-makers, environmentalists, and workers in the fishing industry in rethinking fisheries science to adapt to the reality of an exhaustible—and increasingly exhausted—sea.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043610</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naomi</FirstName>
<LastName>Oreskes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Naomi Oreskes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[oreskes@fas.harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000146828</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Neste</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron G Van Neste</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vanneste@g.harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE STE 3]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LN53LCFJFL45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Oxford St, Science Cntr Rm 371]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y00</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20204</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>INTELLECTUAL MERITS</p> <p>This project used archival sources and oral history to interrogate how fisheries science developed historically and why fisheries have been frequently described as &ldquo;in a state of crisis&rdquo; despite the guidance of fisheries science. The PIs found that fisheries science co-evolved alongside the industrial fishing industry as a set of tools intended to create and support sustainable industrial fishing. In other words, scientists set out to find the quantities of resources that could be extracted to maximize food production and financial profit. This goal &ndash; and the underlying assumption that large sustainable yields were possible &ndash; led to a systematic bias towards overly optimistic expectations of large sustainable catches, or a presumption of plenitude. Manifestations of this bias range from scientific assessments and models designed to yield cornucopian visions of fish abundance and disregard ecological complexity, to an &ldquo;anti-precautionary principle&rdquo; where the burden of proof falls on those who would propose catch limits. This presumption of plenitude has meant that fisheries have been considered abundant until proven otherwise.</p> <p>These presumptions are challenged by an inconvenient truth: marine ecosystems are highly complex, and characterized by nonlinear climatic and ecological dynamics. However, the PIs found this data was largely not incorporated into fisheries science and management. Instead, the possibility of sustainable industrial fishing was assumed theoretically rather than proven empirically, and indeed has never been proven empirically. Moreover, the theory underpinning it relied on assumptions which were known at the time to be false, namely a static balance of nature, consistent annual reproduction within fish stocks, negligible population fluctuations in natural populations, and the ability of ecosystem interactions to withstand the removal of 50-75% of the biomass of key species (as fisheries science recommended for maximum productivity). While sometimes helpful in managing heavily fished populations, the enclosure of territorial waters and the implementation and enforcement of quotas did not fundamentally change the presumption of plenitude, as domestic fleets expanded and quotas frequently overestimated both stock size and reproduction rate.</p> <p>The PIs also found that industry consultants have played and continue to play a large role in both fisheries science and management, including sitting on the scientific committees of regional fishery management organizations and conducting stock assessments. While usually professing dedication to conduct &ldquo;good science&rdquo;, consultants also represent the interests of their clients, and the PIs found evidence that consultant-produced stock assessments, catch quota proposals and ecological theories favored the interests of their clients, former clients, potential clients, or general &ldquo;allies.&rdquo;</p> <p>BROADER IMPACTS</p> <p>The successes and failures of fishery management matter because fish provide the primary source of protein for nearly a billion people worldwide, and many scientists (particularly ecologists) believe the state of marine fisheries is dire. Understanding the history of fisheries science illuminates its limits, and enhances our capacity to make fishing systems more robust and responsive to major fluctuations and sources of uncertainty. Understanding the origins of the presumption of plenitude and the reasons behind its persistence allow us to develop more precautionary, resilient and equitable fishing practices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 02/20/2024<br> Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;G&nbsp;Van Neste</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  INTELLECTUAL MERITS   This project used archival sources and oral history to interrogate how fisheries science developed historically and why fisheries have been frequently described as in a state of crisis despite the guidance of fisheries science. The PIs found that fisheries science co-evolved alongside the industrial fishing industry as a set of tools intended to create and support sustainable industrial fishing. In other words, scientists set out to find the quantities of resources that could be extracted to maximize food production and financial profit. This goal  and the underlying assumption that large sustainable yields were possible  led to a systematic bias towards overly optimistic expectations of large sustainable catches, or a presumption of plenitude. Manifestations of this bias range from scientific assessments and models designed to yield cornucopian visions of fish abundance and disregard ecological complexity, to an anti-precautionary principle where the burden of proof falls on those who would propose catch limits. This presumption of plenitude has meant that fisheries have been considered abundant until proven otherwise.   These presumptions are challenged by an inconvenient truth: marine ecosystems are highly complex, and characterized by nonlinear climatic and ecological dynamics. However, the PIs found this data was largely not incorporated into fisheries science and management. Instead, the possibility of sustainable industrial fishing was assumed theoretically rather than proven empirically, and indeed has never been proven empirically. Moreover, the theory underpinning it relied on assumptions which were known at the time to be false, namely a static balance of nature, consistent annual reproduction within fish stocks, negligible population fluctuations in natural populations, and the ability of ecosystem interactions to withstand the removal of 50-75% of the biomass of key species (as fisheries science recommended for maximum productivity). While sometimes helpful in managing heavily fished populations, the enclosure of territorial waters and the implementation and enforcement of quotas did not fundamentally change the presumption of plenitude, as domestic fleets expanded and quotas frequently overestimated both stock size and reproduction rate.   The PIs also found that industry consultants have played and continue to play a large role in both fisheries science and management, including sitting on the scientific committees of regional fishery management organizations and conducting stock assessments. While usually professing dedication to conduct good science, consultants also represent the interests of their clients, and the PIs found evidence that consultant-produced stock assessments, catch quota proposals and ecological theories favored the interests of their clients, former clients, potential clients, or general allies.   BROADER IMPACTS   The successes and failures of fishery management matter because fish provide the primary source of protein for nearly a billion people worldwide, and many scientists (particularly ecologists) believe the state of marine fisheries is dire. Understanding the history of fisheries science illuminates its limits, and enhances our capacity to make fishing systems more robust and responsive to major fluctuations and sources of uncertainty. Understanding the origins of the presumption of plenitude and the reasons behind its persistence allow us to develop more precautionary, resilient and equitable fishing practices.        Last Modified: 02/20/2024       Submitted by: AaronGVan Neste]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
