<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[REU Site: Advanced Manufacture of Novel Materials and Bio-Nano Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>414893.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>414893</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia Simmons</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>psimmons@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925143</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This three-year summer REU renewal Site at Milwaukee School of Engineering (MSOE) will involve a broad mix of students to conduct research in advanced manufacture of novel materials and bio-nano applications in a strongly mentored environment. MSOE 3D Printing complements metal laser-wire deposition at Midwest Engineered Systems and collaboration with Northwest University’s Neuroimaging, provides opportunities for students to gain insight into customer discovery and exploration that culminate in unique solutions. All projects focus on impacting society by improving life standards through human health and efficient, sustainable systems. The REU team hopes that the diverse cohort - from primarily undergraduate institutions - will get to meet and present at a national conferences on undergraduate research. The Site provides a unique perspective on state-of-the-art 3DP research to all participants. New features of this site include the current participants being mentored by prior REU participants in Ph.D. programs and beyond, and being provided with opportunities to engage in K-12 outreach activities through the MSOE STEM Center.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A technically diverse group of eight undergraduate students per year will participate in transformative problem solving of interdisciplinary projects involving additive manufacturing research at Milwaukee School of Engineering Rapid Prototyping Center, its Bioprinting lab and its synergistic centers of collaboration with industry and other institutions. The projects are uniquely poised for cross-pollination and customer discovery and creativity. With the unprecedented technological advances in 3DP affecting our daily lives, along with its features such as accuracy, reduction in development and delivery time, and reliability, it is becoming cost-effective because of the advancement of materials. Students will receive a career-enriching experience from a well-established and well-run program culminating in a national conference presentation and a strong desire to pursue a graduate degree. MSOE-REU has served as a research incubator for several first-generation and underrepresented students, especially from primarily undergraduate institutions (PUIs). This renewal site will build on previous success motivating participants to pursue continued education and careers in science and engineering. Not only does this project feature geographical diversity and technical diversity of the participants, but it has also embedded transformative research potential in many applications of 3DP with strong collaboration from both academia and industry. All projects impact society in improving life standards − human health and efficient, sustainable systems. New features of this site include the current participants being mentored by prior REU participants in Ph.D. programs and beyond, and being provided with opportunities to engage in K-12 outreach activities through the MSOE STEM Center.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2045738</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Subha</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumpaty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Subha K Kumpaty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[subha.kumpaty@cuw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000355283</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Milwaukee School of Engineering]]></Name>
<CityName>MILWAUKEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>532023109</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142777300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1025 N BROADWAY]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M6RCJVHKTHJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MILWAUKEE SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Milwaukee School of Engineering]]></Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532023109</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1025 N Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>136000</Code>
<Text>EWFD-Eng Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~414893</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>EEC-2045738</strong>, <em>REU Site: Advanced Manufacture of Novel Materials and Bio-Nano Applications</em> (March 2021-February 2024, $414,893, PI Kumpaty) has had REU participants (9 each) in all three summers 2021-2023, in which a technically diverse group of undergraduate students participated successfully in transformative problem solving of interdisciplinary projects involving additive manufacturing (AM) research at MSOE RPC, Bioprinting lab, and its synergistic centers of collaboration with industry and other institutions. The REU program at MSOE has proven to be an&nbsp;<strong><em>ideal model</em></strong>&nbsp;for a good research experience with faculty interacting directly with students.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong>: All projects undertaken have direct bearing on society, with a focus on the well-being of people or efficient processes and sustainable systems. Studies on post-processing of parts from fused deposition modeling directly impact the AM industry. Beta testing of materials at MSOE RPC directly guides the Original Equipment Manufacturers. The research on diclofenac cytotoxicity impacts the pharmaceutical and medical industry.&nbsp;Diversity and inclusion are always prioritized in REU sites by PI Kumpaty. The demographics represent Women (41%), Minorities (33%), Outside of MSOE (74%), and Primarily Undergraduate Institutions (67%). Several projects have resulted in journal and conference publications, including two ASME publications and four journal papers, along with eighteen conference presentations by the participants, with 100% acceptance at the National Conference on Undergraduate Research.&nbsp; In the words of the External Evaluator, &ldquo;MSOE&rsquo;s REU has been a robust and rigorous experience with far-reaching benefits for all stakeholders.&nbsp;It has positively impacted the lives and future paths of the participant cohorts.&nbsp; Its greatest success is manifested in the lives of its alumni as they pursue graduate degrees and STEM-careers.&rdquo;</p> <p>Of the 27 participants, while some are in the junior or senior year of the undergraduate programs, many are employed in STEM careers and a few are pursuing graduate school. Here are some examples. Azaria Wagner is pursuing Ph.D. in Analytical Chemistry at Purdue University. Andrew Gray is at UT-Austin pursuing Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering. Alayna Willitzer is a Post-Baccalaureate Research Education Program scholar at the University of Cincinnati. Levee Callahan completed an accelerated master degree in engineering at Northern Illinois University and is currently working as Project Engineer at Allied Partners, LLC.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>: This site provided integrated research opportunities in advanced manufacturing to three undergraduate cohorts (27 students). Interdisciplinary approaches were implemented. All projects were uniquely poised for cross-pollination, customer discovery, and creativity. Please see the MSOE REU website for details of projects. The unique feature of this REU site is the mentoring of the cohort by prior MSOE REU participants such as Dr. Tyler Capek (REU 2012, Senior Scientist, Kidde), Dr. David Rutkowski (REU 2013, Lead Engineer, Calimetrix), Dr. Clough (REU 2013, now at Wright-Patterson Base Air Force Research Laboratory), Dr. Huffmaster (REU 2006, now at the University of Minnesota) and Dr. Margaret Clapham (REU 2016, now at Du Pont). Participants grew in research, interpersonal and communication skills. Participants presented orally in Week 9, which was live telecast for the benefit of a global audience, and at a poster presentation in Week 10. For all three cohorts, final papers were accepted for presentation at the <em>National Conference on Undergraduate Research</em>.</p> <p>Recent Publications from this grant:</p> <p>1. Chai, A., Schmidt, K., Brewster, G., Xiong, LSP., Church, B., Wahl, T., Sadabadi, H., Kumpaty, S., Zhang, W. (2023 Sep 1). Design of Pectin-Based Hydrogel Microspheres for Targeted Pulmonary Delivery.&nbsp;<em>Gels</em>. 9(9) PubMed Central PMCID: PMC10529711.</p> <p>2. Zieman, J., Cohan, M., Wang, M., De La Sancha,A., Kanungo, M., Azzouz, R., Smith, R., Schmidt, K., Kumpaty, S., Chen, J. and Zhang, W. (2022 Dec 27). Development of Gelatin-Coated Hydrogel Microspheres for Novel Bioink Design: A Crosslinker Study,&nbsp;<em>Pharmaceutics</em>, 15(1). PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9864922.</p> <p>3. Hutchinson, N., Wu, Y., Wang, Y., Kanungo, M., DeBruine, A., Kroll,E., Gilmore, D., Eckrose, Z., Gaston, S., Matel, P., Kaltchev, M., Nickel, A., Kumpaty, S., Hua, X. and Zhang, W. (2022). Green Synthesis of Gold Nanoparticles Using Upland Cress and their Biochemical Characterization and Assessment,&nbsp;<em>Nanomaterials (Basel)</em>, 12(1) PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8746345.</p> <p>4. Kanungo, M., Wang, Y., Hutchinson, N., Kroll, E., DeBruine, A., Kumpaty, S., Ren, L., Wu, Y., Hua, X. and Zhang, W.&nbsp;(2021).&nbsp;Development of Gelatin-Coated Microspheres for Novel Bioink Design.&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Polymers</em>.&nbsp;13(19): 3339.&nbsp;</p> <p>5. Foster, J., Kumpaty, S., Coen, L., Perkins, A., Gengler, M. and S. Woida (November 2022). Characterization of Additively Manufactured Metals from ADDERE Printing,&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition</em>, IMECE2022-88299, Columbus, OH.</p> <p>&nbsp;6. Dana, E., Kumpaty, S. and Weston, J. (November 2022). Characterization of Additively Manufactured Beta Materials,&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition</em>, IMECE2022-88301, Columbus, OH.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 04/25/2024<br> Modified by: Subha&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumpaty</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809487393_IMG_6168_2021_REU_group--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809487393_IMG_6168_2021_REU_group--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU Summer 2021"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809487393_IMG_6168_2021_REU_group--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU Summer 2021"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2021 Summer REU Participants and Advisors and Collaborators</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subha Kumpaty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subha&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumpaty <div class="imageTitle">REU Summer 2021</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1712527906713_20230414_173928--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1712527906713_20230414_173928--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU 2022 at NCUR April 2023"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1712527906713_20230414_173928--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU 2022 at NCUR April 2023"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Presenting at the National Conference on Undergraduate Research, UW-Eau Claire, WI April 2023</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subha Kumpaty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subha&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumpaty <div class="imageTitle">REU 2022 at NCUR April 2023</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809695372_PictureREU2023--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809695372_PictureREU2023--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU Summer 2023"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809695372_PictureREU2023--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU Summer 2023"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">REU 2023 Participants and Advisors and Other Collaborators</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subha Kumpaty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subha&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumpaty <div class="imageTitle">REU Summer 2023</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809880400_Ti64_Print--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809880400_Ti64_Print--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Laser Wire Metal Deposition"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809880400_Ti64_Print--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Laser Wire Metal Deposition"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A block of Ti-6Al-4V printed by the custom ADDERE process at Midwest Engineered Systems</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subha Kumpaty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subha&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumpaty <div class="imageTitle">Laser Wire Metal Deposition</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1713017397877_20240409_151603--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1713017397877_20240409_151603--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU 2023 at NCUR April 2024"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1713017397877_20240409_151603--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU 2023 at NCUR April 2024"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">REU participants and PI Kumpaty at the National Conf on Undergraduate Research, April 8-10, 2024</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subha Kumpaty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subha&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumpaty <div class="imageTitle">REU 2023 at NCUR April 2024</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809576517_REU2022--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809576517_REU2022--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU Summer 2022"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2045738/2045738_10720480_1711809576517_REU2022--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU Summer 2022"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">REU 2022 Participants and Advisors and other Collaborators</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subha Kumpaty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subha&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumpaty <div class="imageTitle">REU Summer 2022</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  EEC-2045738, REU Site: Advanced Manufacture of Novel Materials and Bio-Nano Applications (March 2021-February 2024, $414,893, PI Kumpaty) has had REU participants (9 each) in all three summers 2021-2023, in which a technically diverse group of undergraduate students participated successfully in transformative problem solving of interdisciplinary projects involving additive manufacturing (AM) research at MSOE RPC, Bioprinting lab, and its synergistic centers of collaboration with industry and other institutions. The REU program at MSOE has proven to be anideal modelfor a good research experience with faculty interacting directly with students.   Broader Impact: All projects undertaken have direct bearing on society, with a focus on the well-being of people or efficient processes and sustainable systems. Studies on post-processing of parts from fused deposition modeling directly impact the AM industry. Beta testing of materials at MSOE RPC directly guides the Original Equipment Manufacturers. The research on diclofenac cytotoxicity impacts the pharmaceutical and medical industry.Diversity and inclusion are always prioritized in REU sites by PI Kumpaty. The demographics represent Women (41%), Minorities (33%), Outside of MSOE (74%), and Primarily Undergraduate Institutions (67%). Several projects have resulted in journal and conference publications, including two ASME publications and four journal papers, along with eighteen conference presentations by the participants, with 100% acceptance at the National Conference on Undergraduate Research. In the words of the External Evaluator, MSOEs REU has been a robust and rigorous experience with far-reaching benefits for all stakeholders.It has positively impacted the lives and future paths of the participant cohorts. Its greatest success is manifested in the lives of its alumni as they pursue graduate degrees and STEM-careers.   Of the 27 participants, while some are in the junior or senior year of the undergraduate programs, many are employed in STEM careers and a few are pursuing graduate school. Here are some examples. Azaria Wagner is pursuing Ph.D. in Analytical Chemistry at Purdue University. Andrew Gray is at UT-Austin pursuing Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering. Alayna Willitzer is a Post-Baccalaureate Research Education Program scholar at the University of Cincinnati. Levee Callahan completed an accelerated master degree in engineering at Northern Illinois University and is currently working as Project Engineer at Allied Partners, LLC.   Intellectual Merit: This site provided integrated research opportunities in advanced manufacturing to three undergraduate cohorts (27 students). Interdisciplinary approaches were implemented. All projects were uniquely poised for cross-pollination, customer discovery, and creativity. Please see the MSOE REU website for details of projects. The unique feature of this REU site is the mentoring of the cohort by prior MSOE REU participants such as Dr. Tyler Capek (REU 2012, Senior Scientist, Kidde), Dr. David Rutkowski (REU 2013, Lead Engineer, Calimetrix), Dr. Clough (REU 2013, now at Wright-Patterson Base Air Force Research Laboratory), Dr. Huffmaster (REU 2006, now at the University of Minnesota) and Dr. Margaret Clapham (REU 2016, now at Du Pont). Participants grew in research, interpersonal and communication skills. Participants presented orally in Week 9, which was live telecast for the benefit of a global audience, and at a poster presentation in Week 10. For all three cohorts, final papers were accepted for presentation at the National Conference on Undergraduate Research.   Recent Publications from this grant:   1. Chai, A., Schmidt, K., Brewster, G., Xiong, LSP., Church, B., Wahl, T., Sadabadi, H., Kumpaty, S., Zhang, W. (2023 Sep 1). Design of Pectin-Based Hydrogel Microspheres for Targeted Pulmonary Delivery.Gels. 9(9) PubMed Central PMCID: PMC10529711.   2. Zieman, J., Cohan, M., Wang, M., De La Sancha,A., Kanungo, M., Azzouz, R., Smith, R., Schmidt, K., Kumpaty, S., Chen, J. and Zhang, W. (2022 Dec 27). Development of Gelatin-Coated Hydrogel Microspheres for Novel Bioink Design: A Crosslinker Study,Pharmaceutics, 15(1). PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9864922.   3. Hutchinson, N., Wu, Y., Wang, Y., Kanungo, M., DeBruine, A., Kroll,E., Gilmore, D., Eckrose, Z., Gaston, S., Matel, P., Kaltchev, M., Nickel, A., Kumpaty, S., Hua, X. and Zhang, W. (2022). Green Synthesis of Gold Nanoparticles Using Upland Cress and their Biochemical Characterization and Assessment,Nanomaterials (Basel), 12(1) PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8746345.   4. Kanungo, M., Wang, Y., Hutchinson, N., Kroll, E., DeBruine, A., Kumpaty, S., Ren, L., Wu, Y., Hua, X. and Zhang, W.(2021).Development of Gelatin-Coated Microspheres for Novel Bioink Design.Polymers.13(19): 3339.   5. Foster, J., Kumpaty, S., Coen, L., Perkins, A., Gengler, M. and S. Woida (November 2022). Characterization of Additively Manufactured Metals from ADDERE Printing,Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition, IMECE2022-88299, Columbus, OH.   6. Dana, E., Kumpaty, S. and Weston, J. (November 2022). Characterization of Additively Manufactured Beta Materials,Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition, IMECE2022-88301, Columbus, OH.        Last Modified: 04/25/2024       Submitted by: SubhaKKumpaty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
