<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Brookings Papers on Economic Activity Conferences]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>425000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>425000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Support from the National Science Foundation will provide partial funding for the Brookings Papers on Economic Activity (BPEA), which will consist of semiannual conferences with subsequent publication of the papers and discussion. The conferences will be designed to bring together economic scientists to focus on the scientific analysis of economic policy issues. These issues include: labor market mobility and challenges and lessons from COVID; new challenges for monetary policy; determinants of inflation; lessons from crisis relief programs; an assessment of the effect of epidemiological policy on the economic crisis; long-term implications of the federal debt; dynamics of post-pandemic recovery; economic dynamism; productivity and the economics of technological innovation; macroeconomics of climate change; and, the economics of race and gender.  The papers will be presented at the conference and will be available online to the public. They will develop empirical analysis, will employ a wide range of research methods, and will focus on real world problems that affect the U.S. economy including the future of growth and productivity in the U.S. and abroad. The award will promote the national interest by improving the quality of the economics used in making policy decisions and will provide better evidence for policies that contribute to the competitiveness of the U.S. economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the Brookings Papers is to support economic research that directly informs economic policy, with a focus on macroeconomic policy broadly interpreted. The BPEA conferences will be marked by a high degree of interaction among the organizers, researchers, discussants, and attendees. Each researcher invited to present will engage in an intensive process of three rounds of review, criticism, discussion and editing. BPEA will encourage scientists to apply the best knowledge of the profession to pressing policy issues and will use policy concerns to point the profession's way toward new science. The broader impacts of the Brookings Papers conference occur at three levels. First, the papers themselves can have direct impact by informing current policy makers. Second, the conference will play a broader role in the policy and economic education of the general public; this role is enabled because of the relevance of the papers and the considerable press attention the conference receives. Third, the conference series will provide important support in the academic community for research that directly tackles policy issues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2048708</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Steinsson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon Steinsson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jsteinsson@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000523552</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Stock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Stock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[james_stock@harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000690229</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/09/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
<LastName>Eberly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janice Eberly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hnchen@brookings.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000703724</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brookings Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200362103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2027976000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1775 MASSACHUSETTS AVE NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DRF8L4LUMKK8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE BROOKINGS INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>DRF8L4LUMKK8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brookings Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200362103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1775 Massachusetts Ave NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>132000</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~425000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The&nbsp;Brookings Papers on Economic Activity&nbsp;(BPEA)&nbsp;is a semi-annual academic conference and journal that pairs rigorous research on a broad range of macroeconomic issues with policy analysis to address urgent economic challenges of the day.&nbsp;Working drafts of BPEA papers are presented and discussed at conferences held twice each year, and the final versions of the papers and comments, along with summaries of the general discussions, are published in the journal several months later. Founded in 1970, BPEA is a long-time flagship project of the Economic Studies program at the Brookings Institution ("Brookings").&nbsp;</p> <p>From September 2021 to August 2024, BPEA hosted six conferences at which 33 regular papers, 67 discussion comments, and three thematic panels that featured a total of eight short papers were presented. The BPEA content produced by this project contributed to the existing research and policymaking discourse on enhancing economic opportunity and upward mobility, increasing economic growth, and understanding the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. As of November 2024, all papers and comments produced by this project have been published in the BPEA journal.&nbsp;</p> <p>To increase BPEA<em> </em>papers' immediate policy impact and disseminate research findings more broadly, starting with the Summer 2020 conference, BPEA opened its conference proceedings to the public by livestreaming the main sessions and posting recordings on the Brookings website. The Fall 2021 and Spring 2022 conferences were held virtually on Zoom with livestream due to the pandemic.&nbsp;</p> <p>BPEA resumed its in-person activities starting with the Fall 2022 conference, while providing our invitation-only participants with the option to join in person or virtually and livestreaming the main sessions on the Brookings website. The Fall 2022 papers discussed the U.S. inflation during the pandemic, the impact of Economic Impact Payments on household spending, the rise of remote work, the effect of dollar appreciation shocks on the global economy, and measuring the U.S. fiscal capacity through discounted cash flow analysis. This conference also included a panel on shrinking the Federal Reserve balance sheet. To Fall 2022 papers, <em>Understanding U.S. Inflation During the COVID-19 Era</em> and <em>The Global Dollar Cycle</em> were cited in the World Bank's January 2023 <em>Global Economic Prospects </em>report just a few months after the conference.&nbsp;</p> <p>As a testament to BPEA's impact on policymakers and its ability to inform policy, BPEA papers are often cited by the leadership of the Federal Reserve in their remarks, congressional testimonies, as well as major economic reports by international financial institutions and the executive and legislative branches of the government. For example, the Fall 2023 paper, <em>Hidden Exposure: Measuring U.S. Supply Chain Reliance </em>was cited in the November 2023 issue brief on supply chain resilience by the President's Council of Economic Advisers and the 2024 <em>Economic Report of the President</em>.&nbsp;</p> <p>BPEA conferences and papers produced by this project were covered by top-tier media outlets, including the Wall Street Journal, The Economist, Bloomberg, Politico, Axios, Reuters, Washington Post, New York Times, and MarketWatch.&nbsp;</p> <p>BPEA provides both the conference version and published version of each paper on the Brookings website. Data/programs for replication are posted along with published papers. BPEA also created additional educational and promotional material to share the economists&rsquo; insights with the public. We produced a news-article style policy summary for each paper that highlights its key findings and potential policy impact.&nbsp;</p> <p>We also launched a podcast series, <em>Brookings Podcast on Economic Activity, </em>at the Fall 2022 conference, which aims to showcase BPEA scholars and to promote the depth and breadth of BPEA research. Under this project, we released four seasons, one for each conference, with a total of 21 episodes. As of early July 2024, the average number of downloads for all episodes had reached over 1,400. The Spring 2024 season had the highest average number of downloads per episode compared to others in any time period (3-days, 5-days, 10-days, etc.). BPEA's podcast is the second-most downloaded podcast of Brookings, after its semi-monthly news-focused show, <em>The Current</em>. All these materials are available on the Brookings website to anyone within or outside of the economics community who wish to learn or teach about economic theories and/or implications of specific economic policies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/19/2024<br> Modified by: Janice&nbsp;Eberly</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  TheBrookings Papers on Economic Activity(BPEA)is a semi-annual academic conference and journal that pairs rigorous research on a broad range of macroeconomic issues with policy analysis to address urgent economic challenges of the day.Working drafts of BPEA papers are presented and discussed at conferences held twice each year, and the final versions of the papers and comments, along with summaries of the general discussions, are published in the journal several months later. Founded in 1970, BPEA is a long-time flagship project of the Economic Studies program at the Brookings Institution ("Brookings").   From September 2021 to August 2024, BPEA hosted six conferences at which 33 regular papers, 67 discussion comments, and three thematic panels that featured a total of eight short papers were presented. The BPEA content produced by this project contributed to the existing research and policymaking discourse on enhancing economic opportunity and upward mobility, increasing economic growth, and understanding the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. As of November 2024, all papers and comments produced by this project have been published in the BPEA journal.   To increase BPEA papers' immediate policy impact and disseminate research findings more broadly, starting with the Summer 2020 conference, BPEA opened its conference proceedings to the public by livestreaming the main sessions and posting recordings on the Brookings website. The Fall 2021 and Spring 2022 conferences were held virtually on Zoom with livestream due to the pandemic.   BPEA resumed its in-person activities starting with the Fall 2022 conference, while providing our invitation-only participants with the option to join in person or virtually and livestreaming the main sessions on the Brookings website. The Fall 2022 papers discussed the U.S. inflation during the pandemic, the impact of Economic Impact Payments on household spending, the rise of remote work, the effect of dollar appreciation shocks on the global economy, and measuring the U.S. fiscal capacity through discounted cash flow analysis. This conference also included a panel on shrinking the Federal Reserve balance sheet. To Fall 2022 papers, Understanding U.S. Inflation During the COVID-19 Era and The Global Dollar Cycle were cited in the World Bank's January 2023 Global Economic Prospects report just a few months after the conference.   As a testament to BPEA's impact on policymakers and its ability to inform policy, BPEA papers are often cited by the leadership of the Federal Reserve in their remarks, congressional testimonies, as well as major economic reports by international financial institutions and the executive and legislative branches of the government. For example, the Fall 2023 paper, Hidden Exposure: Measuring U.S. Supply Chain Reliance was cited in the November 2023 issue brief on supply chain resilience by the President's Council of Economic Advisers and the 2024 Economic Report of the President.   BPEA conferences and papers produced by this project were covered by top-tier media outlets, including the Wall Street Journal, The Economist, Bloomberg, Politico, Axios, Reuters, Washington Post, New York Times, and MarketWatch.   BPEA provides both the conference version and published version of each paper on the Brookings website. Data/programs for replication are posted along with published papers. BPEA also created additional educational and promotional material to share the economists insights with the public. We produced a news-article style policy summary for each paper that highlights its key findings and potential policy impact.   We also launched a podcast series, Brookings Podcast on Economic Activity, at the Fall 2022 conference, which aims to showcase BPEA scholars and to promote the depth and breadth of BPEA research. Under this project, we released four seasons, one for each conference, with a total of 21 episodes. As of early July 2024, the average number of downloads for all episodes had reached over 1,400. The Spring 2024 season had the highest average number of downloads per episode compared to others in any time period (3-days, 5-days, 10-days, etc.). BPEA's podcast is the second-most downloaded podcast of Brookings, after its semi-monthly news-focused show, The Current. All these materials are available on the Brookings website to anyone within or outside of the economics community who wish to learn or teach about economic theories and/or implications of specific economic policies.           Last Modified: 11/19/2024       Submitted by: JaniceEberly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
