<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Continuity and Change in Remote Work]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>322101.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>322101</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Antwan Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aajones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924973</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>For millions of U.S. workers, the COVID-19 pandemic has ushered in a new era of remote work, which has shifted irreversibly the culture and technologies of work. This project will investigate continuities, changes, and disparities in remote work and its effects on quality of life. It will study workers’ preferences for remote work, how people adapt to working remotely, and how remote work affects workers’ well-being. The research will illuminate inequalities in remote work by considering varied experiences across life-course stages, educational levels, and demographic backgrounds. This project aims to provide decision-makers with strategic insights into the expectations and preferences of the American workforce, and to help employers optimize remote work arrangements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will field three new survey waves drawing from a nationally representative survey of 3,023 Americans who worked remotely in some form after the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic. The three survey waves build on a baseline survey fielded in October 2020. Respondents are drawn from KnowledgePanel, the largest probability-based online panel in the U.S. The survey combines widely used scales that measure working conditions, well-being, and worker preferences, with open-ended questions designed to capture workers’ experiences of working from home and returning to in-person work. The study will track population trends in remote work across various subgroups. Researchers will also use multivariate regression models to examine continuities, changes, and disparities in respondents’ working conditions, quality of life, and adaptive strategies. The findings will inform sociological theories of work, health and wellbeing, and social and economic inequalities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049125</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wen</FirstName>
<LastName>Fan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wen Fan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wen.fan@bc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826776</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>CHESTNUT HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 COMMONWEALTH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJ3JH8CRJBZ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673859</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>133100</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>803100</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~322101</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF-funded project has two primary objectives. The first is to collect three additional waves of panel data following a baseline online survey conducted in October 2020, which was funded by an NSF RAPID grant (#2032639). The second objective is to examine the continuities, changes, and disparities in the experiences and impacts of U.S. remote work during and beyond the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To achieve the first objective, we fielded three follow-up survey waves after our baseline survey in October 2020. At baseline, we surveyed 3,017 randomly selected respondents who had worked remotely at any point since the onset of COVID-19. These respondents were then surveyed again six months later (April 2021), with a follow-up rate of 76% (n = 2,286), once more after an additional six months (October 2021) with a follow-up rate of 74% (n = 2,232), and a final time six months after that (April 2022) with a follow-up rate of 70% (n = 2,107). This effort produced an exceptional national panel data set on remote workers, tracking their transitions between continuing to work remotely or in a hybrid manner, being required to return to on-site work, or leaving their jobs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>For the second objective, we have analyzed the resulting nationally representative pane data to promote understanding how remote work evolved from October 2020 to April 2022 and its well-being effects. To date, we have published four peer-reviewed articles in high-impact journals, have one article under review, three additional in draft stages, and several more in preparation. These publications have produced four significant insights regarding the dynamics of remote work over three years.</p> <p>First, we document that remote/hybrid work models generally promote improved working conditions and enhanced well-being for employees.&nbsp;In a series of articles&nbsp;(Fan and Moen 2022, 2023,&nbsp;forthcoming), we drew on continuities and changes in location of work across survey waves to provide robust evidence on the effects of remote/hybrid work. Compared with returning to working at work, ongoing remote and moving to hybrid work lead to reductions in workers&rsquo; psychological job demands, as well as increases in decision latitude and schedule control for women&nbsp;(Fan and Moen forthcoming).&nbsp;Ongoing remote work is additionally linked to a significant improvement in well-being&nbsp;(Fan and Moen 2023).&nbsp;</p> <p>Second, historically disadvantaged workers appear to find remote/hybrid work especially beneficial. This means that remote work has the potential to reduce social inequities in work- and well-being-related outcomes. For example, compared with white women or men in general, Black and Hispanic women moving back to the office experience the greatest loss of decision latitude and schedule control&nbsp;(Fan and Moen forthcoming). While white workers see increased coworker support when returning to the office, returning Black and Hispanic men report a decline in coworker support&nbsp;(Fan and Moen forthcoming)&nbsp;, and moving to hybrid is especially salutary for men of color and less-educated men in terms of subjective well-being&nbsp;(Fan and Moen 2023). These findings suggest that organizational and public policies that create more equitable access to remote/hybrid work, and those promoting more equitable working-from-home experiences, may be important avenues for improving well-being among disadvantaged workers.</p> <p>Third, our evidence suggests that caregiving obligations may suppress benefits from remote work. We find the well-being gains from working remotely or hybrid, for example, are largely concentrated among non-parents&nbsp;(Fan and Moen 2023). Exploiting cross-state and over-time variation in school closure policies, we show that while mothers (but not fathers) working in remote/hybrid arrangements are less apt to experience work&shy;-life stress in the absence of mandated school closures, this is not the case when schools are required to close. In that case, remote working mothers report greater stress compared with their working-at-work peers&nbsp;(Fan and Moen 2024a). This suggests that while remote/hybrid work can potentially help workers better manage work and family responsibilities, it is not a complete solution. Increased access to good, affordable childcare, in conjunction with better, more equitable remote/hybrid work policies, may be essential to maximize the benefits of remote/hybrid work for parents, and especially for mothers.</p> <p>Fourth,&nbsp;despite clear evidence we find of workers&rsquo; overall preference for working from home,&nbsp;mandated return to working on site has created place mismatch&mdash;a gap between where one works and where one would prefer to work (Fan and Moen 2024b).&nbsp;Our analysis shows that place&nbsp;mismatch&nbsp;is widespread: As many as half of the workers in our sample have a disjuncture between their preferred and actual work locations, mostly in the form of working at the work place but wanting remote/hybrid arrangements. Most at risk of such a mismatch&nbsp;are minoritized workers and less-educated women working at work. Place mismatch also appears to contribute to the Great Resignation, of people exiting jobs because they can&rsquo;t work how they want to, especially among white men.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 04/10/2024<br> Modified by: Wen&nbsp;Fan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This NSF-funded project has two primary objectives. The first is to collect three additional waves of panel data following a baseline online survey conducted in October 2020, which was funded by an NSF RAPID grant (#2032639). The second objective is to examine the continuities, changes, and disparities in the experiences and impacts of U.S. remote work during and beyond the COVID-19 pandemic.      To achieve the first objective, we fielded three follow-up survey waves after our baseline survey in October 2020. At baseline, we surveyed 3,017 randomly selected respondents who had worked remotely at any point since the onset of COVID-19. These respondents were then surveyed again six months later (April 2021), with a follow-up rate of 76% (n = 2,286), once more after an additional six months (October 2021) with a follow-up rate of 74% (n = 2,232), and a final time six months after that (April 2022) with a follow-up rate of 70% (n = 2,107). This effort produced an exceptional national panel data set on remote workers, tracking their transitions between continuing to work remotely or in a hybrid manner, being required to return to on-site work, or leaving their jobs.      For the second objective, we have analyzed the resulting nationally representative pane data to promote understanding how remote work evolved from October 2020 to April 2022 and its well-being effects. To date, we have published four peer-reviewed articles in high-impact journals, have one article under review, three additional in draft stages, and several more in preparation. These publications have produced four significant insights regarding the dynamics of remote work over three years.   First, we document that remote/hybrid work models generally promote improved working conditions and enhanced well-being for employees.In a series of articles(Fan and Moen 2022, 2023,forthcoming), we drew on continuities and changes in location of work across survey waves to provide robust evidence on the effects of remote/hybrid work. Compared with returning to working at work, ongoing remote and moving to hybrid work lead to reductions in workers psychological job demands, as well as increases in decision latitude and schedule control for women(Fan and Moen forthcoming).Ongoing remote work is additionally linked to a significant improvement in well-being(Fan and Moen 2023).   Second, historically disadvantaged workers appear to find remote/hybrid work especially beneficial. This means that remote work has the potential to reduce social inequities in work- and well-being-related outcomes. For example, compared with white women or men in general, Black and Hispanic women moving back to the office experience the greatest loss of decision latitude and schedule control(Fan and Moen forthcoming). While white workers see increased coworker support when returning to the office, returning Black and Hispanic men report a decline in coworker support(Fan and Moen forthcoming), and moving to hybrid is especially salutary for men of color and less-educated men in terms of subjective well-being(Fan and Moen 2023). These findings suggest that organizational and public policies that create more equitable access to remote/hybrid work, and those promoting more equitable working-from-home experiences, may be important avenues for improving well-being among disadvantaged workers.   Third, our evidence suggests that caregiving obligations may suppress benefits from remote work. We find the well-being gains from working remotely or hybrid, for example, are largely concentrated among non-parents(Fan and Moen 2023). Exploiting cross-state and over-time variation in school closure policies, we show that while mothers (but not fathers) working in remote/hybrid arrangements are less apt to experience work-life stress in the absence of mandated school closures, this is not the case when schools are required to close. In that case, remote working mothers report greater stress compared with their working-at-work peers(Fan and Moen 2024a). This suggests that while remote/hybrid work can potentially help workers better manage work and family responsibilities, it is not a complete solution. Increased access to good, affordable childcare, in conjunction with better, more equitable remote/hybrid work policies, may be essential to maximize the benefits of remote/hybrid work for parents, and especially for mothers.   Fourth,despite clear evidence we find of workers overall preference for working from home,mandated return to working on site has created place mismatcha gap between where one works and where one would prefer to work (Fan and Moen 2024b).Our analysis shows that placemismatchis widespread: As many as half of the workers in our sample have a disjuncture between their preferred and actual work locations, mostly in the form of working at the work place but wanting remote/hybrid arrangements. Most at risk of such a mismatchare minoritized workers and less-educated women working at work. Place mismatch also appears to contribute to the Great Resignation, of people exiting jobs because they cant work how they want to, especially among white men.     Last Modified: 04/10/2024       Submitted by: WenFan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
