<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Towards the Understanding of Deep Crustal Faulting and Fluid Movement through the Analysis of Long Period Earthquakes at Clearlake, CA]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>139000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>139000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Panero</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wpanero@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925058</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Volcanos pose serious threats to human societies yet can be sources of geothermal energy. Clear Lake Volcanic Field is a volcanic steam field located in California.  It hosts numerous geothermal power plants. Although it has not erupted for 11,000 years, it exhibits volcanic-type seismic activity such as tremors and long-period (LP) events.  LP events are produced by fluids surging through cracks and faults in the Earth’s crust. Studying these events allows better understanding fluid movement and fault dynamics. This is important economically and to better assess seismic and volcanic hazards. However, seismic signals from LP events are small and challenging to detect and analyze. Here the researchers investigate these events at Clear Lake Volcanic Field.  They use seismology which is the study of seismic waves generated by earthquakes and travelling through the Earth.  The waves are detected at the surface and analyzed.  The researchers leverage on existing data. They combine state-of-the-art analytical techniques to better identify and locate the LP events. They examine the dynamic properties of the events (stress drops), their scaling with magnitude, and when possible the focal mechanisms of the earthquakes that produced them. The improved catalog of LP events, high-resolution locations, and focal mechanisms is used to investigate the fluid transport system in the region. The project outcomes – which include refined methods and development of hybrid approaches to improve LP event analysis – could be applied at other volcanic systems. The one-year project also supports a collaboration between academia and the industry, and educational outreach to the public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study is based on existing catalog of seismic waveform data that have shown to include LP events. These events are compared to non-volcanic tremor and low-frequency earthquakes at other places along the San Andreas fault system. The researchers search the continuous waveform data set using adaptive waveform template matching to identify LP events related to events already in the catalog. They develop new templates - based on waveform similarity - to further interrogate the data and detect and catalog new LP events. They use the double-difference location method to develop a high-resolution catalog. The detected events are analyzed using spectral modeling methods to estimate the scalar seismic moment and corner frequency; the goal is to assess possible scaling properties of the LP earthquakes. The team also utilizes three-component waveform data to determine focal parameters from moment tensor inversion. LP events are small and challenging to model and therefore require efforts toward the refinement of methods and the development of hybrid approaches to extract more reliable results. Because of their small magnitude, the researchers need to explore combined inversion scheme that utilizes a source-type inversion of both waveforms and first-motion polarities, possibly expanding the method to utilize body wave amplitude ratios. The results of the multipronged analysis will be used to investigate potential fault structure and the fluid transport system of the Clear Lake Volcanic Field.  It will also allow evaluating whether continued study is warranted with a possible portable array deployment to improve coverage to better investigate LP earthquake seismicity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051759</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Dreger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas S Dreger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dreger@seismo.berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000452363</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Takaaki</FirstName>
<LastName>Taira</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Takaaki Taira</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[taira@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000516312</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1608 4TH ST STE 201]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Univ of California, Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947204767</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University of California, Berkel]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>157400</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~139000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Clear Lake Volcanic Field (CLVF) is located 150 km northwest of San Francisco in the Mayacamas Mountains and Clear Lake region. The area is host to The Geysers, the largest geothermal reservoir in the world generating 850 Mwe. Over the past decades unusual deep long-period earthquakes (LPE) have been detected in the CLVF (e.g. Pitt et al., 2002). These events are small with magnitude (M) up to about 3.0, and they are typically located in the 15-25 km depth range. They are unusual in that the radiated energy is longer period than is typical of similar sized earthquakes elsewhere. This pilot study sought to 1) detect additional LPE using pattern matching techniques, 2) locate newly discovered events with sufficient signal-to-noise, and 3) analyze the source properties of the LPE to investigate whether the LPE may reveal the information about fluid flux in the volcanic system. To detect new LPE we used waveforms from previously detected LPE to use as templates to search for additional events using a cross-correlation technique applied to the continuous dataset for the period from 1993 through 2023.&nbsp; This pattern matching approach has more than 1500 new LPEs based on the original template waveforms as well as templates from newly identified events. For the period from 2012-2013 newly detected LPEs were analyzed picking P and S wave arrivals and 15 events had sufficient signal-to-noise to warrant determining locations. The locations show two clusters of LPE located at the northern end of Clearlake, CA. While clustered in the horizontal dimension the events are drawn out in depth ranging from 25 km to approximately 10 km, illuminating a narrow vertical trend that is suggestive of fluid migration from depth.</p> <p>We examined the source characteristics of a relatively large M2.39 LPE that occurred on October 1, 2007 at a depth of 19.2 km. We studied waveform data from the Northern California Seismic System (NCSS) and the Berkeley Digital Seismic Network (BDSN). Examination of the temporal variation in spectral content of the seismic waveforms the event is found to be complex with several episodes of long-period radiation with a total duration of about 30s, which is more than 100 times longer than a typical M2.4 earthquake. The spectra also reveal excitation at discrete frequencies notably at approximately 0.4 and 1 Hz although there is evidence of higher overtones. These quasi-harmonic signatures are strongly suggestive of fluid flow as a component of the earthquake source process, and are reminiscent of studies of LPE in other volcanic systems (e.g. Chouet, 1992). The spectra were fit with a standard source model, which revealed the long-period or low-frequency nature of the event where in this case the corner frequency was approximately 2.0 Hz, which is about 10 times lower than a typical M2.4 earthquake. The low corner frequency indicates a low average stress drop of 0.01-0.1 MPa, whereas a typical event would be ~1 MPa. The very low stress drop is suggestive of high fluid pressure as proposed by Thomas et al. (2015) for LPE located elsewhere on the San Andreas fault system.</p> <p>To investigate the mechanism of the LPE we applied a time variable moment tensor inversion on the data in the 0.25-0.50 Hz band, isolating the 0.4 Hz quasi harmonic signature observed in the waveforms. The non-volumetric part of the solution indicates an oblique, predominantly strike-slip shear mechanism, but in addition there is an oscillating volumetric mechanism over an approximately 20s duration, where the isotropic moment fluctuates between -30 to 30% of the total radiated moment. This mechanism may be described as a dilating and contracting shear crack in which the relatively large volumetric component maybe due to pulsing fluid transport. The data is sparse for these small LPE, and some caution is warranted in the interpretation of these quite remarkable results. To gain confidence we applied a variety of statistical tests to evaluate the significance of solutions with and without the volumetric component, and find the volumetric solution is statistically significant at the 93% level, and the results are stable considering perturbations in the data used in the inversion.</p> <p>Overall, the results show that there are two clusters of LPE events located at the northern end of Clearlake. The LPE are distributed in depth from approximately 25 to 10 km, and form narrow vertically elongate structure that may be associated with fluid flux upward from the deeper magmatic source. The source characteristics of the studied LPE indicates very low stress drop, consistent with high fluid pressure, and the spectral analysis indicates the presence of harmonic elements to the source. The mechanism of a large LPE revealed a complex source process that may be described as an opening and closing shear-crack. Taken together the evidence from these analyses suggests that the LPE may be in response to upward fluid transport.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 06/04/2024<br> Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;S&nbsp;Dreger</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Clear Lake Volcanic Field (CLVF) is located 150 km northwest of San Francisco in the Mayacamas Mountains and Clear Lake region. The area is host to The Geysers, the largest geothermal reservoir in the world generating 850 Mwe. Over the past decades unusual deep long-period earthquakes (LPE) have been detected in the CLVF (e.g. Pitt et al., 2002). These events are small with magnitude (M) up to about 3.0, and they are typically located in the 15-25 km depth range. They are unusual in that the radiated energy is longer period than is typical of similar sized earthquakes elsewhere. This pilot study sought to 1) detect additional LPE using pattern matching techniques, 2) locate newly discovered events with sufficient signal-to-noise, and 3) analyze the source properties of the LPE to investigate whether the LPE may reveal the information about fluid flux in the volcanic system. To detect new LPE we used waveforms from previously detected LPE to use as templates to search for additional events using a cross-correlation technique applied to the continuous dataset for the period from 1993 through 2023. This pattern matching approach has more than 1500 new LPEs based on the original template waveforms as well as templates from newly identified events. For the period from 2012-2013 newly detected LPEs were analyzed picking P and S wave arrivals and 15 events had sufficient signal-to-noise to warrant determining locations. The locations show two clusters of LPE located at the northern end of Clearlake, CA. While clustered in the horizontal dimension the events are drawn out in depth ranging from 25 km to approximately 10 km, illuminating a narrow vertical trend that is suggestive of fluid migration from depth.   We examined the source characteristics of a relatively large M2.39 LPE that occurred on October 1, 2007 at a depth of 19.2 km. We studied waveform data from the Northern California Seismic System (NCSS) and the Berkeley Digital Seismic Network (BDSN). Examination of the temporal variation in spectral content of the seismic waveforms the event is found to be complex with several episodes of long-period radiation with a total duration of about 30s, which is more than 100 times longer than a typical M2.4 earthquake. The spectra also reveal excitation at discrete frequencies notably at approximately 0.4 and 1 Hz although there is evidence of higher overtones. These quasi-harmonic signatures are strongly suggestive of fluid flow as a component of the earthquake source process, and are reminiscent of studies of LPE in other volcanic systems (e.g. Chouet, 1992). The spectra were fit with a standard source model, which revealed the long-period or low-frequency nature of the event where in this case the corner frequency was approximately 2.0 Hz, which is about 10 times lower than a typical M2.4 earthquake. The low corner frequency indicates a low average stress drop of 0.01-0.1 MPa, whereas a typical event would be ~1 MPa. The very low stress drop is suggestive of high fluid pressure as proposed by Thomas et al. (2015) for LPE located elsewhere on the San Andreas fault system.   To investigate the mechanism of the LPE we applied a time variable moment tensor inversion on the data in the 0.25-0.50 Hz band, isolating the 0.4 Hz quasi harmonic signature observed in the waveforms. The non-volumetric part of the solution indicates an oblique, predominantly strike-slip shear mechanism, but in addition there is an oscillating volumetric mechanism over an approximately 20s duration, where the isotropic moment fluctuates between -30 to 30% of the total radiated moment. This mechanism may be described as a dilating and contracting shear crack in which the relatively large volumetric component maybe due to pulsing fluid transport. The data is sparse for these small LPE, and some caution is warranted in the interpretation of these quite remarkable results. To gain confidence we applied a variety of statistical tests to evaluate the significance of solutions with and without the volumetric component, and find the volumetric solution is statistically significant at the 93% level, and the results are stable considering perturbations in the data used in the inversion.   Overall, the results show that there are two clusters of LPE events located at the northern end of Clearlake. The LPE are distributed in depth from approximately 25 to 10 km, and form narrow vertically elongate structure that may be associated with fluid flux upward from the deeper magmatic source. The source characteristics of the studied LPE indicates very low stress drop, consistent with high fluid pressure, and the spectral analysis indicates the presence of harmonic elements to the source. The mechanism of a large LPE revealed a complex source process that may be described as an opening and closing shear-crack. Taken together the evidence from these analyses suggests that the LPE may be in response to upward fluid transport.     Last Modified: 06/04/2024       Submitted by: DouglasSDreger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
