<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Well-Posedness for Integrable Dispersive Partial Differential Equations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>294956.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>294956</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marian Bocea</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbocea@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922595</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Korteweg-de Vries equation was introduced in the 1890s to explain the experimental observation of solitary waves on the surface of shallow channels of water. These waves travel large distances while maintaining their profile. Still more astounding is the fact that such waves undergo particle-like interactions; this prompted researchers to introduce the term "soliton" to describe them. The goal of this project is to deepen our understanding of other equations that exhibit the same phenomenology. One particular challenge that the project seeks to overcome is the fact that existing methods are poorly suited to the study of waves that are not well localized in space. The project provides research training opportunities for graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The problems to be studied lie at the intersection of nonlinear dispersive PDE, completely integrable systems, and probability theory. These problems are of well-established interest and chosen both because they have resisted previous technology and because the principal investigator believes that the new techniques she helped develop make them finally accessible. Among the topics that will be investigated as part of the project are large-data sharp well-posedness for the derivative nonlinear Schrodinger equation, well-posedness for periodic and tidal completely integrable systems, constructing Gibbs dynamics for the Landau-Lifshitz model, and understanding the long-time behavior of solutions to both defocusing and focusing completely integrable systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2054194</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
<LastName>Visan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Monica Visan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[visan@math.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000512653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[520 Portola Plaza, MS 7620D]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128100</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~294956</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merits:<br />Completely integrable systems are ubiquitous in the sciences. They describe a broad spectrum of phenomena ranging from planetary motion, to many-body systems, to the Kerr effect in optical fibers, to water waves. A notable example is the Korteweg-de Vries equation which was derived more than 200 years ago to explain the experimental observation of solitary waves; these are isolated humps of water that travel large distances without changing shape.<br />The most significant outcome of the PI's previous two NSF grants was the introduction of the method of commuting flows, which enabled us to obtain the definitive result on the existence and uniqueness of solutions to three of the most conspicuous completely integrable equations: Korteweg-de Vries, the cubic Schrodinger, and the modified Korteweg-de Vries equations.&nbsp; As part of this project, the PI has further expanded the methods she introduced to obtain the optimal well-posedness results for several other well-established and much-studied completely integrable systems such as the Benjamin-Ono and the derivative nonlinear Schrodinger equation.&nbsp;<br />The problem of determining the structure of physical bodies from the manner in which they scatter waves has a long and illustrious history; applications include medical imaging. As part of this project, the PI introduced a new approach to recovering the full nonlinear behavior of a material from the manner in which it scatters waves. Notably, we are able to recover the structure of nonlinear materials that are confined to a localized region and surrounded by vacuum from distant measurements.<br /><br />Broader Impacts:<br />In total, the project supported the scientific advancement of six graduate students and four postdoctoral researchers.<br />The PI delivered a mini-course at the Eighteenth Prairie Analysis Seminar held at the University of Kansas in Lawrence in 2022 and two mini-courses at Peking University in 2021 and 2022, respectively.&nbsp; For all these events, the audience was comprised of young mathematicians, mostly graduate students and postdoctoral researchers.<br />The PI organized with A. Ionescu, Y. Martel, and K. Nakanishi the workshop ``Hamiltonian Methods and Asymptotic Dynamics" held at the Institute for Computational &amp; Experimental Research in Mathematics, Providence, 2021. She also organized&nbsp; with H. Koch, P. Raphael, and D. Tataru a conference on ``Nonlinear Waves and Dispersive Equations" in Oberwolfach, Germany, 2022. Finally, in 2022 she organized with Z. Guo, R. Killip, and B. Wang a virtual workshop on Nonlinear Dispersive Wave Equations, whose focus was the dissemination of the recent methods introduced by the PI and collaborators in the study of dispersive completely integrable systems. As part of this workshop, the PI also delivered a mini-course.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/26/2024<br> Modified by: Monica&nbsp;Visan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merits: Completely integrable systems are ubiquitous in the sciences. They describe a broad spectrum of phenomena ranging from planetary motion, to many-body systems, to the Kerr effect in optical fibers, to water waves. A notable example is the Korteweg-de Vries equation which was derived more than 200 years ago to explain the experimental observation of solitary waves; these are isolated humps of water that travel large distances without changing shape. The most significant outcome of the PI's previous two NSF grants was the introduction of the method of commuting flows, which enabled us to obtain the definitive result on the existence and uniqueness of solutions to three of the most conspicuous completely integrable equations: Korteweg-de Vries, the cubic Schrodinger, and the modified Korteweg-de Vries equations. As part of this project, the PI has further expanded the methods she introduced to obtain the optimal well-posedness results for several other well-established and much-studied completely integrable systems such as the Benjamin-Ono and the derivative nonlinear Schrodinger equation. The problem of determining the structure of physical bodies from the manner in which they scatter waves has a long and illustrious history; applications include medical imaging. As part of this project, the PI introduced a new approach to recovering the full nonlinear behavior of a material from the manner in which it scatters waves. Notably, we are able to recover the structure of nonlinear materials that are confined to a localized region and surrounded by vacuum from distant measurements.  Broader Impacts: In total, the project supported the scientific advancement of six graduate students and four postdoctoral researchers. The PI delivered a mini-course at the Eighteenth Prairie Analysis Seminar held at the University of Kansas in Lawrence in 2022 and two mini-courses at Peking University in 2021 and 2022, respectively. For all these events, the audience was comprised of young mathematicians, mostly graduate students and postdoctoral researchers. The PI organized with A. Ionescu, Y. Martel, and K. Nakanishi the workshop ``Hamiltonian Methods and Asymptotic Dynamics" held at the Institute for Computational & Experimental Research in Mathematics, Providence, 2021. She also organized with H. Koch, P. Raphael, and D. Tataru a conference on ``Nonlinear Waves and Dispersive Equations" in Oberwolfach, Germany, 2022. Finally, in 2022 she organized with Z. Guo, R. Killip, and B. Wang a virtual workshop on Nonlinear Dispersive Wave Equations, whose focus was the dissemination of the recent methods introduced by the PI and collaborators in the study of dispersive completely integrable systems. As part of this workshop, the PI also delivered a mini-course.     Last Modified: 07/26/2024       Submitted by: MonicaVisan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
