<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Investigating How to Better Prepare Undergraduate Students for Physics Labs that Focus on Experimental Science]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>147865.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>147865</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dawn Rickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drickey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924674</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest by identifying strategies to support students’ understanding of experimental science. The major goal is to identify instructional strategies that better prepare undergraduate students for doing authentic scientific experimentation in physics labs. Traditional laboratory exercises have trained students to view instructional laboratories as places to do rote procedures that lead to known results. This project will probe how to help students reframe their expectations so that they consider physics labs as places to engage in scientific experiementation.  Specifically, this project intends to identify strategies that help students think of physics labs as places where they will design their own experiments and draw their own conclusions from the data they collect. By working across multiple institutions, the project will provide many examples of students’ authentic science laboratory activities, as well an extensive database of students' work and engagement. The latter will document the rich diversity of resources and experiences students bring from their diverse backgrounds to their science laboratory work.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project aims to understand student experiences in non-traditional science labs, specifically physics, through the theoretical lens of framing. A person's frame is defined here as a stable (either local or more global) set of expectations about the activity taking place. Prior literature suggests that small things can influence the ways students frame an instructional activity, which in turn can have a large impact on student learning. This research project is designed to (a) identify the various ways students frame activities in a diverse set of non-traditional labs, (b) identify ways students shift or change how they frame lab activities, and (c) formulate testable predictions for ways to help students develop stable, productive frames for experimental science. This project is supported by the EHR Core Research program, which supports work that advances fundamental research on STEM learning and learning environments, broadening participation in STEM, and STEM workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000394</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Hammer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Hammer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[david.hammer@tufts.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000548799</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>SOMERVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021442401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[169 HOLLAND ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WL9FLBRVPJJ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>WL9FLBRVPJJ7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>Medford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021555807</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Paige Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>798000</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~147865</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Laboratory assignments in science classes have traditionally guided students through clear procedures toward confirming known results. That contrasts sharply with professional science, which involves grappling with uncertainties and confusion, and students trained over many years of schooling in traditional contexts are generally not prepared for authentic research.</p> <p>This project studied students&rsquo; learning in laboratories redesigned to focus on cultivating scientific attitudes and practices. Rather than provide step-by-step instructions, the assignments presented students with empirical challenges and gave them responsibility for deciding how to meet them, building toward their finding their own challenges. The work was collaborative across three institutions, each of which had its own versions of assignments, which provided a rich variety of examples of student work for study.</p> <p>The main approach to analyzing students&rsquo; work was to focus on students&rsquo; &ldquo;framing,&rdquo; that is how they understand what was taking place and their roles in it. For a key example, students accustomed to traditional labs often framed what was taking place as satisfying arbitrary requirements, with their roles limited to following the instructor&rsquo;s authority. Part of the design of these labs was to shift that framing toward doing science, such that students framed what was taking place as trying to find something out about the physical world, with their roles as active agents of exploration and experimentation.</p> <p>The main, overarching outcome from this project is that students can and do shift in how they frame what is taking place, in contexts of these redesigned labs, toward their taking up roles and aims of authentic science. In contrast to prior findings regarding student thinking in traditional highly-guided labs, cases from this project show students working as novice scientists, forming and re-forming their own ideas and questions, becoming curious, inventive, and persistent.&nbsp;</p> <p>One particular finding is that students&rsquo; expecting their experiments to confirm known results can motivate their investigations in productive ways. If they understood what was taking place as genuinely their own work, an unexpected finding could motivate their efforts in problem-solving. Like professional scientists finding a contradiction to an established theory, it happened that students showed appropriate caution and rigor in examining their methods.</p> <p>Another finding is the relevance of various social and emotional dynamics to support students&rsquo; productive engagement. In traditional course settings, feelings of confusion are liabilities, risking poor evaluations by the instructors or disrespect from their peers. Part of students&rsquo; shifts of their framing involves their coming to experience those feelings as opportunities for pleasurable intellectual pursuit, expecting positive support from teachers and fellow students.</p> <p>Finally, the dynamics of the how different students working in different groups frame and shift in their framings of what is taking place are complex and idiosyncratic. Small things can make dramatic differences: A student&rsquo;s watching a collision up close having her notice it in a way that surprises and confuses her; a teaching assistant&rsquo;s offhand reference to instructional expectations tipping the group back into &ldquo;jumping through hoops&rdquo;; a mismatch of data prompting a group to persist insistently in trying to find the reason, staying past the lab period.</p> <p>There is a great deal more to study in these dynamics. For now, the implications point toward the importance of responsive teaching approaches that allow and engage with idiosyncrasies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/02/2024<br> Modified by: David&nbsp;Hammer</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Laboratory assignments in science classes have traditionally guided students through clear procedures toward confirming known results. That contrasts sharply with professional science, which involves grappling with uncertainties and confusion, and students trained over many years of schooling in traditional contexts are generally not prepared for authentic research.   This project studied students learning in laboratories redesigned to focus on cultivating scientific attitudes and practices. Rather than provide step-by-step instructions, the assignments presented students with empirical challenges and gave them responsibility for deciding how to meet them, building toward their finding their own challenges. The work was collaborative across three institutions, each of which had its own versions of assignments, which provided a rich variety of examples of student work for study.   The main approach to analyzing students work was to focus on students framing, that is how they understand what was taking place and their roles in it. For a key example, students accustomed to traditional labs often framed what was taking place as satisfying arbitrary requirements, with their roles limited to following the instructors authority. Part of the design of these labs was to shift that framing toward doing science, such that students framed what was taking place as trying to find something out about the physical world, with their roles as active agents of exploration and experimentation.   The main, overarching outcome from this project is that students can and do shift in how they frame what is taking place, in contexts of these redesigned labs, toward their taking up roles and aims of authentic science. In contrast to prior findings regarding student thinking in traditional highly-guided labs, cases from this project show students working as novice scientists, forming and re-forming their own ideas and questions, becoming curious, inventive, and persistent.   One particular finding is that students expecting their experiments to confirm known results can motivate their investigations in productive ways. If they understood what was taking place as genuinely their own work, an unexpected finding could motivate their efforts in problem-solving. Like professional scientists finding a contradiction to an established theory, it happened that students showed appropriate caution and rigor in examining their methods.   Another finding is the relevance of various social and emotional dynamics to support students productive engagement. In traditional course settings, feelings of confusion are liabilities, risking poor evaluations by the instructors or disrespect from their peers. Part of students shifts of their framing involves their coming to experience those feelings as opportunities for pleasurable intellectual pursuit, expecting positive support from teachers and fellow students.   Finally, the dynamics of the how different students working in different groups frame and shift in their framings of what is taking place are complex and idiosyncratic. Small things can make dramatic differences: A students watching a collision up close having her notice it in a way that surprises and confuses her; a teaching assistants offhand reference to instructional expectations tipping the group back into jumping through hoops; a mismatch of data prompting a group to persist insistently in trying to find the reason, staying past the lab period.   There is a great deal more to study in these dynamics. For now, the implications point toward the importance of responsive teaching approaches that allow and engage with idiosyncrasies.        Last Modified: 10/02/2024       Submitted by: DavidHammer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
