<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CCSS: Collaborative Research:  Sketching for High Dimensional Data Analysis in IoT]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Huaiyu Dai</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hdai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924568</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proliferation of IoT devices generates enormous amount of data, which leads to a tremendous demand on resources for the transmission, processing and storage. In order to extract useful information and fully achieve the potential of IoT for intelligent decisions, it is critical to develop novel systems to efficiently transmit, store and process this large volume of data. Fortunately, the data generated by IoT and many other applications typically possesses certain low dimensional parsimonious structures. Leveraging on these low dimensional structures of IoT data, this project will develop methods based on low dimensional sketches to infer information of interest. This sketching based framework will enable quick and accurate information extraction with greatly reduced sampling rates, transmission and storage costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a sketching based framework for the efficient processing of high dimensional data generated by IoT and investigate its theoretical and algorithmic properties. The core idea is to take low dimensional projections or sketches of random variables, rather than to directly and fully observe high dimensional random variables. This project will develop both non-adaptive and adaptive low dimensional sketching methods, and will make the following intellectual contributions: 1) deriving fundamental limits on sampling rates for recovering statistical information of high dimensional random variables; 2) designing explicit sampling schemes that achieve the corresponding fundamental limits on sampling rates; 3) providing fast algorithms with performance guarantees for recovering statistical information from sketches of random variables. The PIs will leverage their research experience in compressed sensing, low-rank matrix recovery and sequential analysis in solving these challenging problems. The generated results are expected to extend compressed sensing from sketching of deterministic values to a broader context of sketching of random variables.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000425</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weiyu</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weiyu Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[weiyu-xu@uiowa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000623834</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[105 JESSUP HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z1H9VJS8NG16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF IOWA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>756400</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project has developed a sketching based framework for the efficient processing of high dimensional data generated by IoT and has investigated its theoretical and algorithmic properties. The core idea is to take low dimensional projections or sketches of random variables, rather than to directly and fully observe high dimensional random variables. This project has developed both non-adaptive and adaptive low dimensional sketching methods, and has made the following intellectual contributions: 1) deriving fundamental limits on sampling rates for recovering statistical information of high dimensional random variables; 2) designing explicit sampling schemes that achieve the corresponding fundamental limits on sampling rates; 3) providing fast algorithms with performance guarantees for recovering statistical information from sketches of random variables.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>More specifically,&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>1) We have explicitly derived the error exponents for using sketching for hypothesis testing. This is the first time that in the literature that error exponent has been derived for hypothesis tesing using sketching.&nbsp;</p> <p>2) We have derived data compression schemes for classifications in semantic communications.&nbsp;</p> <p>3) We have designed linear pregrogressive coding/error correction codes for compression for classifications in semantic communications.&nbsp;</p> <p>4) We have proposed a theoretical analysis framework for explaining the adversarial fragility of deep neural networks based classifiers.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>5)&nbsp; We have proposed to design a tree network for the&nbsp;<span>designing an optimized tree network, enabling the fast convergence of Distributed Dual Coordinate Ascent on a general tree network (DDCA-Tree) for distributed Machine Learning.</span></p> <p>6) Through this project, we have studied adversarial robustness of reinforcement learning algorithms, in particular we developed camoufalge adversarial attack and optimal cost constrained adversarial attacks for multiple agent systems.</p> <p>7) We have developed&nbsp;<span>a "trust but verify" method for verifying the output of a deep neural network for medical image segmentation that is robust to several classes of random as well as worst-case perturbations i.e. adversarial attacks.</span></p> <p><span>8) We have provided theoretical performance guarantees for outlider detection using neural network based generative models.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project has supported research of Ph.D. students (including from under-represented groups),&nbsp; in data analytics, and help them complete doctoral thesis. Research outputs from this research can be used for data analytics and signal processing courses.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/05/2024<br> Modified by: Weiyu&nbsp;Xu</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project has developed a sketching based framework for the efficient processing of high dimensional data generated by IoT and has investigated its theoretical and algorithmic properties. The core idea is to take low dimensional projections or sketches of random variables, rather than to directly and fully observe high dimensional random variables. This project has developed both non-adaptive and adaptive low dimensional sketching methods, and has made the following intellectual contributions: 1) deriving fundamental limits on sampling rates for recovering statistical information of high dimensional random variables; 2) designing explicit sampling schemes that achieve the corresponding fundamental limits on sampling rates; 3) providing fast algorithms with performance guarantees for recovering statistical information from sketches of random variables.   More specifically,   1) We have explicitly derived the error exponents for using sketching for hypothesis testing. This is the first time that in the literature that error exponent has been derived for hypothesis tesing using sketching.   2) We have derived data compression schemes for classifications in semantic communications.   3) We have designed linear pregrogressive coding/error correction codes for compression for classifications in semantic communications.   4) We have proposed a theoretical analysis framework for explaining the adversarial fragility of deep neural networks based classifiers.   5) We have proposed to design a tree network for thedesigning an optimized tree network, enabling the fast convergence of Distributed Dual Coordinate Ascent on a general tree network (DDCA-Tree) for distributed Machine Learning.   6) Through this project, we have studied adversarial robustness of reinforcement learning algorithms, in particular we developed camoufalge adversarial attack and optimal cost constrained adversarial attacks for multiple agent systems.   7) We have developeda "trust but verify" method for verifying the output of a deep neural network for medical image segmentation that is robust to several classes of random as well as worst-case perturbations i.e. adversarial attacks.   8) We have provided theoretical performance guarantees for outlider detection using neural network based generative models.      This project has supported research of Ph.D. students (including from under-represented groups), in data analytics, and help them complete doctoral thesis. Research outputs from this research can be used for data analytics and signal processing courses.     Last Modified: 10/05/2024       Submitted by: WeiyuXu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
