<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Broadening Participation in the 10th International Congress of Arctic Social Sciences (ICASS X)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>305102.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>305102</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Liam Frink</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lfrink@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports broadening participation in the Tenth International Congress of Arctic Social Science (ICASS X), co-organized by the University of Northern Iowa and Northern (Arctic) Federal University and scheduled for June 2021. Since 1992, ICASS has provided an opportunity for Arctic researchers from around the world to share research results, develop collaborations and, increasingly, interact with Arctic community members, including Indigenous peoples. The Congress also provides an arena in which  both established and early career U.S. scholars and students may interact and exchange views with their counterparts from other Arctic countries. These interactions enable the US to continue to lead the world in advancing Arctic social science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of ICASS X is "Arctic Generations: Looking Back and Looking Forward," which promotes a long-term view of Arctic change and adaptation. A particular focus of many IASSA scientists is resilience, sustainability and sustainable development in the Arctic, issues of critical concern to the United States generally and to Alaska in particular. This award supports the participation of early career researchers, Indigenous community members, and students in a high-profile international conference that fosters the exchange of knowledge and the development of scholarly, social, and cultural connections that extend across the circumpolar North.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001989</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Petrov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrey Petrov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andrey.petrov@uni.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000517008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Northern Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>CEDAR FALLS</CityName>
<ZipCode>506140012</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3192733217</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1227 W 27TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PLZ1BS2RC597</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTHERN IOWA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FRALVAFNF2H9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Northern Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>Cedar Falls</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>506140406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1227 W 27th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>522100</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~305102</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to broaden the participation in the International 10<sup>th</sup> Congress of Arctic Social Sciences. ICASS X brought together scholars and others from around the world to share ideas about social science and humanities research in the Arctic. The organizers supported the participation of a diverse body of scholars, community activists, policy makers, and northern stakeholders from other sectors. The Congress emphasized providing participation opportunities to early career and Indigenous scholars.&nbsp;ICASS X encouraged dialog among researchers, Indigenous knowledge holders and other stakeholders, in order to advance our understanding of human conditions in the Arctic.</p> <p>The ICASS X took place on June 15-20, 2021 in a hybrid format: an in-person site with limited participation in Arkhangelsk, Russia and online, and was the largest Arctic Social Sciences Congress by participation. It also had the largest number of participating countries. The total number of attendees was 920 who presented 833 papers/posters/exhibits in 187 breakout sessions.</p> <p>ICASS X theme was "Arctic Generations: Looking Back and Looking Forward." Research in social sciences and humanities have a great responsibility to address the challenges for sustainable development in the Arctic, with a specific focus on past, present and future generations of Arctic residents. The purpose was to counteract the short-term focus of research and policy actions in the Arctic. A emphasis on generations highlights the long-term, fundamental nature and scope of changes, impacts and adaptation strategies. ICASS X welcomed sessions and papers on all facets of the Arctic and Sub-Arctic. ICASS X brought together social scientists and humanities scholars, health researchers, northern residents and other knowledge, rights- and stakeholders, to share their latest research on all aspects of human life in the Arctic. ICASS X held a plenary and sessions on knowledge co-production and produced a special statement on knowledge co-production in Arctic research. The Congress served as a key venue to discuss and critique research results, to be exposed to new ideas, to network with colleagues, and to develop new collaborative ties and projects. ICASS X also provided a venue for the dissemination of knowledge and cross-fertilization of thought on human systems and their coupling with the natural environment in the Arctic and Sub-Arctic. The Congress produced an edited volume of proceedings: <em>Petrov, A.N. and Pelyasov, A.N. Arctic Generations: Looking Back and Looking Forward. ICASS X Proceedings. Topics in Arctic Social Sciences, Volume 10, 2024. IASSA and ARCTICenter: Cedar Falls, USA.</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/11/2024<br> Modified by: Andrey&nbsp;Petrov</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The goal of this project was to broaden the participation in the International 10th Congress of Arctic Social Sciences. ICASS X brought together scholars and others from around the world to share ideas about social science and humanities research in the Arctic. The organizers supported the participation of a diverse body of scholars, community activists, policy makers, and northern stakeholders from other sectors. The Congress emphasized providing participation opportunities to early career and Indigenous scholars.ICASS X encouraged dialog among researchers, Indigenous knowledge holders and other stakeholders, in order to advance our understanding of human conditions in the Arctic.   The ICASS X took place on June 15-20, 2021 in a hybrid format: an in-person site with limited participation in Arkhangelsk, Russia and online, and was the largest Arctic Social Sciences Congress by participation. It also had the largest number of participating countries. The total number of attendees was 920 who presented 833 papers/posters/exhibits in 187 breakout sessions.   ICASS X theme was "Arctic Generations: Looking Back and Looking Forward." Research in social sciences and humanities have a great responsibility to address the challenges for sustainable development in the Arctic, with a specific focus on past, present and future generations of Arctic residents. The purpose was to counteract the short-term focus of research and policy actions in the Arctic. A emphasis on generations highlights the long-term, fundamental nature and scope of changes, impacts and adaptation strategies. ICASS X welcomed sessions and papers on all facets of the Arctic and Sub-Arctic. ICASS X brought together social scientists and humanities scholars, health researchers, northern residents and other knowledge, rights- and stakeholders, to share their latest research on all aspects of human life in the Arctic. ICASS X held a plenary and sessions on knowledge co-production and produced a special statement on knowledge co-production in Arctic research. The Congress served as a key venue to discuss and critique research results, to be exposed to new ideas, to network with colleagues, and to develop new collaborative ties and projects. ICASS X also provided a venue for the dissemination of knowledge and cross-fertilization of thought on human systems and their coupling with the natural environment in the Arctic and Sub-Arctic. The Congress produced an edited volume of proceedings: Petrov, A.N. and Pelyasov, A.N. Arctic Generations: Looking Back and Looking Forward. ICASS X Proceedings. Topics in Arctic Social Sciences, Volume 10, 2024. IASSA and ARCTICenter: Cedar Falls, USA.        Last Modified: 10/11/2024       Submitted by: AndreyPetrov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
