<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PostDoctoral Research Fellowship]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgdewint@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922599</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is made as part of the FY 2020 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The title of the project for this fellowship to Christopher Eur is " Hodge theory for matroids of arbitrary Lie type." The host institution for the fellowship is Stanford University, and the sponsoring scientist is June Huh.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001854</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Eur</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Eur</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000811771</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Eur, Christopher]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<ZipCode>94709</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University Mathematics Dept]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>060Y00</Code>
<Text>Workforce (MSPRF) MathSciPDFel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project sought to understand combinatorial objects called "matroids." &nbsp;They underpin structures in many mathematical disciplines such as discrete optimization, graph theory, and singularity theory. &nbsp;The new aspect of the proposed research was the approach of combining the newly developed tool of tropical Hodge theory with Lie theory to study generalizations of matroids known as "Coxeter matroids."</p> <p>Some highlights of the scientific outcomes are as follows. &nbsp;It led to a new perspective of studying matroids by considering them as geometric objects called "vector bundles." &nbsp;This new viewpoint unified, recovered, and extended several previous results about matroids and their geometry. &nbsp;More importantly, it opened doors to several new research directions, which have been pursued by the PI and by groups not involving the PI. &nbsp;These directions include Gromov--Witten theory of matroids, K-theory of matroids, augmented geometry of matroids, etc. &nbsp;Another development is an extensive generalization of the tropical geometry of matroids to those of delta-matroids, which are the Coxeter matroids of type B. &nbsp;Lastly, the project also produced a work on the positive flag varieties, whose structure is closely tied to flag matroids, which spawned a direction of study that continues to be developed.</p> <p>More broadly, with the wealth of new directions to pursue afforded by some of the works done through this project, and through conferences and summer school lectures, the PI has contributed to inviting students and researchers into the field that continues to grow rapidly.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/26/2024<br> Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Eur</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The project sought to understand combinatorial objects called "matroids." They underpin structures in many mathematical disciplines such as discrete optimization, graph theory, and singularity theory. The new aspect of the proposed research was the approach of combining the newly developed tool of tropical Hodge theory with Lie theory to study generalizations of matroids known as "Coxeter matroids."   Some highlights of the scientific outcomes are as follows. It led to a new perspective of studying matroids by considering them as geometric objects called "vector bundles." This new viewpoint unified, recovered, and extended several previous results about matroids and their geometry. More importantly, it opened doors to several new research directions, which have been pursued by the PI and by groups not involving the PI. These directions include Gromov--Witten theory of matroids, K-theory of matroids, augmented geometry of matroids, etc. Another development is an extensive generalization of the tropical geometry of matroids to those of delta-matroids, which are the Coxeter matroids of type B. Lastly, the project also produced a work on the positive flag varieties, whose structure is closely tied to flag matroids, which spawned a direction of study that continues to be developed.   More broadly, with the wealth of new directions to pursue afforded by some of the works done through this project, and through conferences and summer school lectures, the PI has contributed to inviting students and researchers into the field that continues to grow rapidly.        Last Modified: 07/26/2024       Submitted by: ChristopherEur]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
