<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: CSEDI: Understanding the Role of Hydrogen and Melting in the Water Transport Across the Transition Zone-Lower Mantle Boundary]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>330000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Panero</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wpanero@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925058</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The aim of this project is to conduct new experimental and theoretical studies on the properties of mineral in the deep interior of Earth that will help us to understand the nature of global water circulation in Earth’s mantle. Not only on the surface, water (hydrogen) is present inside of Earth and slowly circulates. This global water circulation creates and maintains oceans on Earth. Based on a number of studies during the last a few decades, there is a clear idea about the water circulation in the shallow part of Earth’s interior. However, the nature of water circulation in the largest part of the mantle, the lower mantle, remains poorly constrained. A key in the global water circulation is the role of melting. Melting removes water from minerals to melt, and melt migrates a long distance to cause large-scale water transport. However, the nature of global water circulation in the deep mantle is very poorly understood mainly because our understanding of water in the minerals in the deep mantle is limited.  The PI team will bring together a suite of theoretical and experimental methods to address these questions, and will train both graduate and undergraduate students at three institutions on a cross-cutting research project.  The PIs will also engage in public outreach events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this new project, the water solubility in bridgmanite (dominant lower mantle mineral) will be determined under the shallow lower mantle conditions from ~660 km to ~1000 km depth, and also the role of water (hydrogen) on electrical conductivity in bridgmanite will be investigated. Experimental studies will be made on clean single crystals of bridgmanite and the hydrogen content and solubility mechanisms will be studied using FTIR and SIMS. Electrical conductivity will be measured on these samples for different orientations using the AC impedance spectroscopy. First-principle computational studies will also be made on hydrogen solubility and mobility in bridgmanite to help interpreting the experimental results. These results will help us to develop a model of global water circulation and to test models against geophysical estimates of water distribution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001339</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shun-ichiro</FirstName>
<LastName>Karato</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shun-ichiro Karato</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shun-ichiro.karato@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000382602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065113572</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[150 MUNSON ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIV</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208109</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Whitney Avenue, KGL 319]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158500</Code>
<Text>STUDIES OF THE EARTHS DEEP INT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~330000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project is to provide new experimental data on hydrogen dissolution in ilower mantle minerals and new theoretical calculations on melt properties under the deep mantle conditions to help understand the nature of global water circulation.</p> <p>It is well recognized that both the atmosphere and the oceans on Earth have been there as a result of global water circulation.This implies that both atmosphere and the oceans aren on Earth's suface as a result of the dynamic balance not by static equilibrium: rate of addition of atmosphere and the oceans (degassing) and the rate of removal of those volatile materials back into Earth's interior (regassing) seem to make a balance. However, when dynamic balance controls the mass of atmosphere and the oceans, consequence of these competing processes needs to be understand in detail. Ocean mass (and atomsphetre mass) would be nearly constant only when these two competing processes result in the negative feedback.</p> <p>Geological observations provide a data set indicating that the sea level as been nearly constant at least for the last ~600 Myrs. However, the sea levels also show large fluctions (a few 100s m) with short timescales (100-200 Myrs). Sea level has been going down for the last ~200 Myrs, and if this trend contiues, oceans will be dried up in less than 1 billion years. This implies that theer are some procsses that stabilize.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the past, when scientists investigate these processes, they considered degassing (loss of gass (water etc.) from the mantle to the surface) at mid-oceani ridges and reagssing (return of gasses back to hte mantle) at subduction zones. However, a simple calculation shows that the degassing rate at mid-ocean ridges is too small to explain the observed fast recovery of the sea level. This is large due to the fact that mid-ocean ridge basalts contain only a small amount fo water (~0.1 wt%) and its upwelling rate is slow.</p> <p>In the meantime, high-pressure studies showed that minerals in the mantle transition zone (the MTZ) have much higher water solubility than minerals above or below the MTZ. Also based on geophysically inferred electrical conductivity distribution, it was shown that the MTZ has a higher water content than regions both below and above. These observations predict that partial melting likely occurs both above and below the MTZ. Melts formed in regions should have much higher water content (to ~10 wt%), and consequently, melting and melt transport actoss the MTZ would play a key role in the global water circulation.</p> <p>The key issues that we have focused our attebation in this project include (i) detailed charactyerization of hydrogendissolution in bridgmanite (a key mineral in the lower mantle), (ii) partial melting experiments to explore the consequence of partial melting under these conditions, (iii) computational studies on the melt structure and density under the lower mantle conditions, and (iv) the synthesis of these results.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/13/2024<br> Modified by: Shun-Ichiro&nbsp;Karato</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The goal of this project is to provide new experimental data on hydrogen dissolution in ilower mantle minerals and new theoretical calculations on melt properties under the deep mantle conditions to help understand the nature of global water circulation.   It is well recognized that both the atmosphere and the oceans on Earth have been there as a result of global water circulation.This implies that both atmosphere and the oceans aren on Earth's suface as a result of the dynamic balance not by static equilibrium: rate of addition of atmosphere and the oceans (degassing) and the rate of removal of those volatile materials back into Earth's interior (regassing) seem to make a balance. However, when dynamic balance controls the mass of atmosphere and the oceans, consequence of these competing processes needs to be understand in detail. Ocean mass (and atomsphetre mass) would be nearly constant only when these two competing processes result in the negative feedback.   Geological observations provide a data set indicating that the sea level as been nearly constant at least for the last ~600 Myrs. However, the sea levels also show large fluctions (a few 100s m) with short timescales (100-200 Myrs). Sea level has been going down for the last ~200 Myrs, and if this trend contiues, oceans will be dried up in less than 1 billion years. This implies that theer are some procsses that stabilize.   In the past, when scientists investigate these processes, they considered degassing (loss of gass (water etc.) from the mantle to the surface) at mid-oceani ridges and reagssing (return of gasses back to hte mantle) at subduction zones. However, a simple calculation shows that the degassing rate at mid-ocean ridges is too small to explain the observed fast recovery of the sea level. This is large due to the fact that mid-ocean ridge basalts contain only a small amount fo water (~0.1 wt%) and its upwelling rate is slow.   In the meantime, high-pressure studies showed that minerals in the mantle transition zone (the MTZ) have much higher water solubility than minerals above or below the MTZ. Also based on geophysically inferred electrical conductivity distribution, it was shown that the MTZ has a higher water content than regions both below and above. These observations predict that partial melting likely occurs both above and below the MTZ. Melts formed in regions should have much higher water content (to ~10 wt%), and consequently, melting and melt transport actoss the MTZ would play a key role in the global water circulation.   The key issues that we have focused our attebation in this project include (i) detailed charactyerization of hydrogendissolution in bridgmanite (a key mineral in the lower mantle), (ii) partial melting experiments to explore the consequence of partial melting under these conditions, (iii) computational studies on the melt structure and density under the lower mantle conditions, and (iv) the synthesis of these results.     Last Modified: 11/13/2024       Submitted by: Shun-IchiroKarato]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
