<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Period Domains, Motives, and Ramification Theory in Arithmetic Geometry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>414000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>414000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Adriana Salerno</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asalerno@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922271</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the principal investigators' research in arithmetic geometry. At its heart, arithmetic geometry is concerned with integer (or rational) solutions of polynomial equations, seeking to better understand numbers through their geometric structure. Famous questions in arithmetic geometry include the celebrated Fermat's Last Theorem. In particular, the PIs will study branching behavior (called "ramification")  of these geometric objects, and they will investigate parameter spaces that describe them (called "period domains"). New technology developed by the PIs and others -- including upper ramiﬁcation groups of an arbitrary henselian valuation ring, heights of motives, and motive versions of the Manin conjecture and the Vojta conjecture -- should allow for major progress on open questions in these areas. The project also provides support for the PIs to write books for researchers working in similar areas and provides research training opportunities for graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal investigator intends to strengthen his study of ramification theory of schemes and of ell-adic sheaves, various extended period domains, and motives over number fields in arithmetic geometry connecting these subjects, and to study related problems (heights of motives, heights of variation of Hodge structures, Hodge theoretic Nevanlinna theory, zeta functions, Tamagawa number conjecture, Iwasawa theory, Sharifi conjecture, asymptotic behaviors of Beilinson regulators and period integrals which appear in physics etc.). The PI defined heights of motives, and formulated motive versions of the Manin conjecture and the Vojta conjecture about heights of points of an algebraic variety. He intends to obtain non-trivial results on these motive versions. The PI started the Hodge theoretic Nevanliina theory. He plans to make new progress in Hodge theory basing on this Nevanlinna point of view. The PI will collaborate with the co-principal investigator T. Fukaya to study Sharifi conjectures and to study the arithmetic of non-commutative rings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001182</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kazuya</FirstName>
<LastName>Kato</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kazuya Kato</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kkato@math.uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000546455</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Takako</FirstName>
<LastName>Fukaya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Takako Fukaya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[takako@math.uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000546456</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5801 S ELLIS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371505</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5734 South University Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>126400</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~182098</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~115951</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~115951</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Period domains are moduli spaces (classifying spaces) of Hodge structures and they are important in the complex analytic geometry. They are also important in arithmetic geometry and number theory. For example, Shimura varieties are special cases of period domains and have&nbsp; structures of algebraic varieties over number fields, and are of particular importance in number theory. Compactifications and partial compactifications of period domains are important. The boundary of the (partial) compactification are closely related to the degeneration of Hodge structure which has been an important subject with many applications.</p> <p>In this project, K. Kato studied the period domains and applications to the arithmetic. In the works with C. Nakayama and S. Usui, K. Kato constructed extended period domains (partial compactifications, which are sometimes compactifications) of the period domains. In this project, in Part 5 (submitted) of series of papers (Part 1--Part 6) by these three researchers, we studied extended period domains associated to linear algebraic groups. As an application, we completed a paper (submitted)&nbsp; in which we give a refinement of the classical result of Garesky and Tai on the comparison of the toroidal compactifications and Borel-Serre compactifications of Shimura varieties.&nbsp; In the last&nbsp; paper, we also obtained a generalizations of this refined comparison for general period domains associated to reductive algebraic groups. We almost completed a paper on the generalization of it to non-reductive linear algebraic groups.&nbsp; The last work contains a Borel-Serre orbit theorem, which is a refinement of the SL(2)-orbit theorem on degeneration of Hodge structure (the SL(2)-orbit theorem is due to E. Cattani, A. Kaplan, W. Schmid and to K. Kato, C. Nakayama, S. Usui).&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>In 1988, with J. -M. Fontaine and L. Illusie, K. Kato started the log geometry (the theory of log structures). This is a theory which can treat degenerations nicely.&nbsp;</p> <p>In Part 6 (accepted) of the above series of papers, we obtained the the theory of integration&nbsp; which works for variations of log Hodge structure&nbsp; (degenerate Hodge structure) on singular spaces and obtained a new method to study the higher direct images of log Hodge structures.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, we&nbsp; completed a paper (accepted) in which we obtained new relations between pure log Hodge stuructures and mixed log Hodge structures and based on it, we obtained a definition of mixed motives using log pure motives.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;These studies have ell-adic analogues. In this project, with C. Nakayama and S. Usui, K. Kato completed a paper (submitted) in which we defined a category of log ell-adic sheaves, which are analogous to the category of variations of mixed log Hodge&nbsp; structure,&nbsp; and obtained the analogue of the SL(2)-orbit theorem, and studied the higher direct images. We are studying the higher direct images more, following the&nbsp; analogy with the above studies of log Hodge theory, hoping to obtain results on the monodromy-weight conjecture.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, K. Kajiwara,&nbsp; K. Kato, and C. Nakayama published a paper in which we obtained new constructions of the arithmetic toroidal compactifications of the moduli spaces of abelian varieties and completed a paper (submitted) on the generalization of it to the situation with endomorphism rings. These compactifications are constructed as the moduli space of log abelian varieties (nice formulation of degenerate abelian variety in log geometry). Since log abelian varieties in log geometry have group structures (which degenerate abelian varieties in the usual algebraic geometry do not have), our theory of compactification becomes transparent, and we expect that we can have good applications to the theory of Shimura varieties. K. Kato completed a paper (submitted) which studies finite flat log group schemes including the $n$-torsion parts of log abelian varieties. A young mathrmatician K. Inoue is applying these works to the study of Shimura varieties.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, T. Fukaya, K. Kato and R. Sharifi submitted&nbsp; a paper&nbsp; in which we constructed long expected compactifications of the moduli spaces of Drinfeld modules. This compactification is the moduli space of log Drinfeld modules and this theory is similar to the theory of log abelian varieties. This will have applications to the study of Sharifi conjectures for GL(n) of global fields of positive characteristics.</p> <p>In this project, T. Fukaya and K. Kato published a paper in which we obtained a strong result on Sharifi conjecture (a refinement of Iwasawa main conjecture). We expect that the above compactification of the moduli space of Drinfeld modules is useful in the study of Sharifi conjecture for GL(n) of global fields of positive characteristic.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, K. Kato and V. Thatte completed a&nbsp; paper (accepted) on the upper ramification groups of arbitrary valuation rings. This generalizes the theory of Abbes-Saito for complete discrete valuation rings and give strong results on defect extensions. We expect that this has applications to the ramification theory of schemes and the problem of local uniformization.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/02/2024<br> Modified by: Kazuya&nbsp;Kato</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Period domains are moduli spaces (classifying spaces) of Hodge structures and they are important in the complex analytic geometry. They are also important in arithmetic geometry and number theory. For example, Shimura varieties are special cases of period domains and have structures of algebraic varieties over number fields, and are of particular importance in number theory. Compactifications and partial compactifications of period domains are important. The boundary of the (partial) compactification are closely related to the degeneration of Hodge structure which has been an important subject with many applications.   In this project, K. Kato studied the period domains and applications to the arithmetic. In the works with C. Nakayama and S. Usui, K. Kato constructed extended period domains (partial compactifications, which are sometimes compactifications) of the period domains. In this project, in Part 5 (submitted) of series of papers (Part 1--Part 6) by these three researchers, we studied extended period domains associated to linear algebraic groups. As an application, we completed a paper (submitted) in which we give a refinement of the classical result of Garesky and Tai on the comparison of the toroidal compactifications and Borel-Serre compactifications of Shimura varieties. In the last paper, we also obtained a generalizations of this refined comparison for general period domains associated to reductive algebraic groups. We almost completed a paper on the generalization of it to non-reductive linear algebraic groups. The last work contains a Borel-Serre orbit theorem, which is a refinement of the SL(2)-orbit theorem on degeneration of Hodge structure (the SL(2)-orbit theorem is due to E. Cattani, A. Kaplan, W. Schmid and to K. Kato, C. Nakayama, S. Usui).    In 1988, with J. -M. Fontaine and L. Illusie, K. Kato started the log geometry (the theory of log structures). This is a theory which can treat degenerations nicely.   In Part 6 (accepted) of the above series of papers, we obtained the the theory of integration which works for variations of log Hodge structure (degenerate Hodge structure) on singular spaces and obtained a new method to study the higher direct images of log Hodge structures.   In this project, we completed a paper (accepted) in which we obtained new relations between pure log Hodge stuructures and mixed log Hodge structures and based on it, we obtained a definition of mixed motives using log pure motives.These studies have ell-adic analogues. In this project, with C. Nakayama and S. Usui, K. Kato completed a paper (submitted) in which we defined a category of log ell-adic sheaves, which are analogous to the category of variations of mixed log Hodge structure, and obtained the analogue of the SL(2)-orbit theorem, and studied the higher direct images. We are studying the higher direct images more, following the analogy with the above studies of log Hodge theory, hoping to obtain results on the monodromy-weight conjecture.   In this project, K. Kajiwara, K. Kato, and C. Nakayama published a paper in which we obtained new constructions of the arithmetic toroidal compactifications of the moduli spaces of abelian varieties and completed a paper (submitted) on the generalization of it to the situation with endomorphism rings. These compactifications are constructed as the moduli space of log abelian varieties (nice formulation of degenerate abelian variety in log geometry). Since log abelian varieties in log geometry have group structures (which degenerate abelian varieties in the usual algebraic geometry do not have), our theory of compactification becomes transparent, and we expect that we can have good applications to the theory of Shimura varieties. K. Kato completed a paper (submitted) which studies finite flat log group schemes including the $n$-torsion parts of log abelian varieties. A young mathrmatician K. Inoue is applying these works to the study of Shimura varieties.   In this project, T. Fukaya, K. Kato and R. Sharifi submitted a paper in which we constructed long expected compactifications of the moduli spaces of Drinfeld modules. This compactification is the moduli space of log Drinfeld modules and this theory is similar to the theory of log abelian varieties. This will have applications to the study of Sharifi conjectures for GL(n) of global fields of positive characteristics.   In this project, T. Fukaya and K. Kato published a paper in which we obtained a strong result on Sharifi conjecture (a refinement of Iwasawa main conjecture). We expect that the above compactification of the moduli space of Drinfeld modules is useful in the study of Sharifi conjecture for GL(n) of global fields of positive characteristic.   In this project, K. Kato and V. Thatte completed a paper (accepted) on the upper ramification groups of arbitrary valuation rings. This generalizes the theory of Abbes-Saito for complete discrete valuation rings and give strong results on defect extensions. We expect that this has applications to the ramification theory of schemes and the problem of local uniformization.     Last Modified: 11/02/2024       Submitted by: KazuyaKato]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
