<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: P2C2--Summer Temperature Reconstructions for Eastern North America]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>117607.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>117607</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020108</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Verardo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dverardo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924695</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project broadly seeks to use blue light intensity measured in tree rings—a proxy for wood density—to produce multiple, annually-resolved, regional summer temperature reconstructions (e.g. Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, Northeast United States/Canadian Maritimes) over the past, approximately, 500 years.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary motivation for conducting this research is the need to better understand the current climatic warming trend across eastern North America with regard to pre-instrumental conditions, as well as to better understand the effects of climatic variability on temperature-sensitive tree species across the region.  Understanding the broader temporal and spatial patterns, timing, and amplitude of cool and warm periods across eastern North America may aid in constraining model scenarios of future temperature change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Longer temperature records (e.g. that extend beyond the instrumental period) may provide information on: (i) past and current spatiotemporal characteristics of temperature variability; (ii) the full range and amplitude of pre-instrumental temperatures; (iii) the timing and direction of temperature rate changes; and (iv) the influence of ocean and atmosphere forcing mechanisms on centennial-scale temperature variability and the sensitivity of temperature changes to these climatic forcing mechanisms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The potential Broader Impacts include developing data from a data poor geographic location that are well situated to advance knowledge on North American climate, supporting graduate students from underrepresented groups, and providing outreach to K-12 STEM audiences including those involving Native American communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002524</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Grant</FirstName>
<LastName>Harley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Grant Harley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gharley@uidaho.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000543798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Idaho]]></Name>
<CityName>MOSCOW</CityName>
<ZipCode>838449803</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2088856651</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[875 PERIMETER DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QWYKRJH5NNJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF IDAHO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Idaho]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>838433021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>153000</Code>
<Text>Paleoclimate</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7754</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY &amp; CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8070</Code>
<Text>P2C2 Proposals</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~117607</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We use annual growth rings from trees to produce a record of summer temperature variability across 3 distinct regions of the eastern United States (US): Southeast, Mid-Atlantic/Northeast and Upper Midwest. By using a technique developed recently in the field of dendrochronology (e.g. tree-ring science) called blue light intensity (BI), we were able to extract a temperature signal from eastern hemlock and red spruce trees located across these 3 regions going back 300-500 years, depending on the ages of trees in each region.</p> <p>This project generated a dense network database of ring widths (earlywood width, latewood width, total ring-width) and BI (earlywood BI, latewood BI) from hemlock and spruce at 55 total site locations: 12 from the Southeast (Virginia, North Carolina, Tennessee, Alabama), 12 from the Mid-Atlantic (Maryland, Pennsylvania), 17 from the Northeast (Connecticut, New York, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Vermont, Maine), and 14 from the Upper Midwest(Indiana, Wisconsin, Michigan).</p> <p>Across the Mid-Atlantic/Northeast regions (hereafter MANE), we developed 29 BI records and used them to reconstruct average March-September air temperatures back to 1461 CE based on a model that explains 62% of the instrumental temperature variance since 1901 CE. Since 1998 CE, MANE summer temperatures are consistently the warmest within the context of the past 561 years exceeding the 1951&minus;1980 mean of +1.3 &deg;C. Cool summers across MANE were frequently volcanically forced, with significant (<em>p</em>&lt;0.05) temperature departures associated with 80% of the largest tropical (<em>n</em>=13) and extratropical (<em>n</em>=15) eruptions since 1461 CE. Yet, we find that more of the identified cool events in the record were likely unforced by volcanism and either related to stochastic variability or atmospheric circulation via significant associations (<em>p</em>&lt;0.05) to regional, coastal sea-surface temperatures, 500-hpa geopotential height, and 300-hpa meridional and zonal wind vectors.</p> <p>Across the 12 Southeast US sites, BI records show positive and temporally-stable correlations (<em>r</em>&nbsp;=&nbsp;0.28&ndash;0.54,&nbsp;<em>p</em>&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;0.01) with summer maximum temperatures. As such, we use the network of BI chronologies to reconstruct August-September average maximum temperatures for the Southeast spanning the period 1760&ndash;2010 CE. Our work demonstrates the utility of applying novel dendrochronological techniques to improve the understanding of the multi-centennial temperature history of the Southeast. Further, we demonstrate that BI from tree rings can effectively be used to develop paleotemperature estimates for the Southeast US, a region previously devoid of high-resolution summer temperature proxy records. We also find that the reliability of tree-ring density parameters for paleoclimate reconstruction are influenced by disturbance regimes and microsite conditions. Finally, compared to the last 260 years, regional 20th-century maximum late summer temperatures are not characterized by unprecedented positive trend, a contrary finding to that found in the MANE region.</p> <p>This project supported teaching and training of a doctoral student at the University of Idaho, who successfully produced a doctoral dissertation. The project also contributed to field, laboratory, and analytical training for 3 additional undergraduate students and 2 additional graduate students, all of whom helped collect samples from the field, processed those samples and generated data, and contributed to drafting manuscripts derived from this project; hence, these students are included as co-authors on manuscripts from this project. To date, project results have been presented at 3 national science conferences and disseminated in 4 published, peer-reviewed manuscripts. A 5<sup>th</sup> manuscript is under review at a scientific journal.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/05/2024<br> Modified by: Grant&nbsp;Harley</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581511769_VideoCapture_20210502_225913_01--rgov-214x142.jpeg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581511769_VideoCapture_20210502_225913_01--rgov-800width.jpeg" title="Eastern hemlock core sampling"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581511769_VideoCapture_20210502_225913_01--rgov-66x44.jpeg" alt="Eastern hemlock core sampling"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Drs. Stockton Maxwell and Justin Maxwell, brothers, collect a core from an eastern hemlock tree in Pennsylvania to be used to reconstruct summer temperature.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Grant Harley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Grant&nbsp;Harley <div class="imageTitle">Eastern hemlock core sampling</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725582082059_20210502_142548_01--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725582082059_20210502_142548_01--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Coring an eastern hemlock tree, Maryland"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725582082059_20210502_142548_01--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Coring an eastern hemlock tree, Maryland"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Dr. Karen King collects a tree core from an old hemlock growing in Maryland, a site used to reconstruct temperatures for the Mid-Atlantic and Northeast regions of the US.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Grant Harley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Grant&nbsp;Harley <div class="imageTitle">Coring an eastern hemlock tree, Maryland</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581264356_20210505_152348--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581264356_20210505_152348--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Exchanging tree core samples"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581264356_20210505_152348--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Exchanging tree core samples"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Dr. Ed Cook meets with project PIs in a parking lot during COVID to lend cores from the Lamont-Doherty archives previously collected from hemlock and spruce throughout he eastern US.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Grant Harley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Grant&nbsp;Harley <div class="imageTitle">Exchanging tree core samples</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581349198_20210509_135427--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581349198_20210509_135427--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Collecting tree cores in the snow"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581349198_20210509_135427--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Collecting tree cores in the snow"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">University of Idaho students pose in the snow at an eastern hemlock site in Pennsylvania that we re-collected and updated from a previous collection.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Grant Harley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Grant&nbsp;Harley <div class="imageTitle">Collecting tree cores in the snow</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581042273_20220520_110800--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581042273_20220520_110800--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Eastern tamarack bog, Michigan"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725581042273_20220520_110800--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Eastern tamarack bog, Michigan"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students from the University of Idaho collect tree cores from eastern tamarack trees growing in a big in Michican.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Grant Harley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Grant&nbsp;Harley <div class="imageTitle">Eastern tamarack bog, Michigan</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725580950852_20220704_103150--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725580950852_20220704_103150--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sampling eastern hemlock in Maine, USA"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2002524/2002524_10654525_1725580950852_20220704_103150--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sampling eastern hemlock in Maine, USA"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Two students from the University of Idaho collected tree cores for temperature reconstructions in a hemlock forest in Maine, USA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Grant Harley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Grant&nbsp;Harley <div class="imageTitle">Sampling eastern hemlock in Maine, USA</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  We use annual growth rings from trees to produce a record of summer temperature variability across 3 distinct regions of the eastern United States (US): Southeast, Mid-Atlantic/Northeast and Upper Midwest. By using a technique developed recently in the field of dendrochronology (e.g. tree-ring science) called blue light intensity (BI), we were able to extract a temperature signal from eastern hemlock and red spruce trees located across these 3 regions going back 300-500 years, depending on the ages of trees in each region.   This project generated a dense network database of ring widths (earlywood width, latewood width, total ring-width) and BI (earlywood BI, latewood BI) from hemlock and spruce at 55 total site locations: 12 from the Southeast (Virginia, North Carolina, Tennessee, Alabama), 12 from the Mid-Atlantic (Maryland, Pennsylvania), 17 from the Northeast (Connecticut, New York, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Vermont, Maine), and 14 from the Upper Midwest(Indiana, Wisconsin, Michigan).   Across the Mid-Atlantic/Northeast regions (hereafter MANE), we developed 29 BI records and used them to reconstruct average March-September air temperatures back to 1461 CE based on a model that explains 62% of the instrumental temperature variance since 1901 CE. Since 1998 CE, MANE summer temperatures are consistently the warmest within the context of the past 561 years exceeding the 19511980 mean of +1.3 C. Cool summers across MANE were frequently volcanically forced, with significant (pn=13) and extratropical (n=15) eruptions since 1461 CE. Yet, we find that more of the identified cool events in the record were likely unforced by volcanism and either related to stochastic variability or atmospheric circulation via significant associations (p   Across the 12 Southeast US sites, BI records show positive and temporally-stable correlations (r=0.280.54,p   This project supported teaching and training of a doctoral student at the University of Idaho, who successfully produced a doctoral dissertation. The project also contributed to field, laboratory, and analytical training for 3 additional undergraduate students and 2 additional graduate students, all of whom helped collect samples from the field, processed those samples and generated data, and contributed to drafting manuscripts derived from this project; hence, these students are included as co-authors on manuscripts from this project. To date, project results have been presented at 3 national science conferences and disseminated in 4 published, peer-reviewed manuscripts. A 5th manuscript is under review at a scientific journal.     Last Modified: 09/05/2024       Submitted by: GrantHarley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
