<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[P2C2: Pan-American Precipitation Extremes and Multi-Decadal Regimes Reconstructed with Tree Ring Chronologies from the Amazon]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399747.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399747</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Verardo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dverardo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924695</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to develop new tree-ring chronologies in the Amazon to reconstruct precipitation, document coherence in tropical and extratropical precipitation extremes across the Americas, and examine multi-decadal variability of Amazon rainfall in observations, reconstructions, and model simulations.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The rationale behind the research is that climate model simulations of hydroclimatic variability in the Amazon indicate that anthropogenic forcing may amplify the hydrologic cycle, resulting in more severe drought, extreme floods, and a decline in annual precipitation over most of the watershed.  However, instrumental observations are limited before 1950 and may not represent the full range of inter-annual to multi-decadal rainfall variability over the Amazon.  High-resolution climate proxies are rare in the Amazon, but tree-ring chronologies have been widely used to reconstruct past megadroughts and pluvials in mid-latitude North and South America.  These dendroclimatic reconstructions have proven valuable for testing model simulations of the climate dynamics responsible for decadal moisture regimes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The potential Broader Impacts include furthering the understanding of Amazonian hydroclimate to the broader scientific community and public. The data generated by this project will be used far beyond the specific aims of the research. The capacity building with South American researchers is a strong aspect of the project as is website development and video production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002374</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Stahle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David W Stahle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dstahle@uark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000418506</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Song</FirstName>
<LastName>Feng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Song Feng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[songfeng@uark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000545503</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1125 W MAPLE ST STE 316]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MECEHTM8DB17</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Ozark Hall 216]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>153000</Code>
<Text>Paleoclimate</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7754</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY &amp; CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8070</Code>
<Text>P2C2 Proposals</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~399747</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>P2C2:&nbsp; Pan-American precipitation extremes and multi-decadal regimes reconstructed with tree ring chronologies from the Amazon</strong></p> <p>The Amazon River is the greatest river system on Earth. It has an average annual discharge of 216,000 cubic meters per second, which is greater than the<em> combined</em> discharge of the next six largest rivers in the world. Climate model simulations indicate that human activity may alter the hydrology of the Amazon River basin, resulting in more severe droughts, extreme floods, and a long-term decline in annual rainfall over most of the watershed. Some of these hydrological changes may already be happening. For example, three extreme droughts and five <em>once-in-a-century</em> floods were witnessed in the Amazon in just the last 30-years. Unfortunately, direct instrument-based measurements of temperature, rainfall, and river flow that extend earlier than 1980 are very rare over most of the Amazon watershed. This project has been funded by the National Science Foundation and has used annual ring width data from long lived trees native to the Amazon to serve as a proxy for rainfall over the past 250-years, well before the beginning of weather or streamflow measurements.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have found tropical hardwood trees in the Rio Paru drainage of the eastern Amazon that live for 200- to 300-years. These <em>Cedrela odorata</em> trees and have distinctive annual growth rings that are directly correlated with rainfall totals (their common name is <em>cedro</em>).&nbsp; The Rio Paru watershed is part of a huge area of pristine forests in the eastern Amazon that is nearly the size of California and contains the tallest trees in all of Amazonia. These Giant Tree Sanctuaries (<em>Santuarios das Avores Gigantes) </em>are very remote, difficult to access, and little known, but have captivated public interest in Brazil and abroad. We have taken small and harmless core samples from some of these forest giants and estimate that many are 200- to 400-years old (both <em>Cedrela</em> and <em>Denezia excelsa</em>).</p> <p>We have used the ring-width data from the Rio Paru watershed to reconstruct wet season rainfall amounts over the eastern Amazon region from the mid-eighteenth century to present. These rainfall reconstructions are even better when based on oxygen isotope ratios measured on the wood cellulose contained within each annual growth band. Both types of records, ring width and oxygen isotopes, are also influenced by global scale climate systems, most importantly by the El Nino/Southern Oscillation (ENSO). Because of this strong influence from ENSO, the instrumental rainfall and proxy tree growth records in the eastern Amazon are significantly correlated with precipitation and tree growth anomalies of opposite sign in mid-latitude North and South America. When drought and poor tree growth occur in the Amazon, wetness and abundant tree growth are usually observed in subtropical North and South America, which is a direct expression of the power of the El Nino/Southern Oscillation, the great air-sea interaction that orchestrates climate and environmental variability in the Americas and around the world. However, because the global climate impacts of El Nino events are never precisely the same, the new tropical and extratropical tree-ring proxies will allow us to investigate variability in the ENSO forcing of climate over the Americas for the past 300-years.</p> <p>Our project has also consulted historical documentary records available through the Brazilian Digital Library (BDL) to provide graphic details on several drought and flood years of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries first identified with the tree-ring data in the Amazon. The worst Amazon River floods in the modern record occurred in 2009 and 2021, but our tree-ring estimates and historical documentary accounts indicate that both may have been exceeded by the extreme floods of 1859 and 1892. The drought of 1925-1926 featured an unparalleled reduction of the seasonal high flow, but that event may too have been exceeded by the <em>Forgotten Drought</em> of 1865. The agreement of the tree ring and historical evidence for extreme droughts and floods over the Amazon in the eighteenth and nineteenth century underscores the value of the new proxy and historical records. This tree ring and historical information indicates that the droughts and floods witnessed in the Amazon River basin over the past 30-years may have been exceeded by climate and river flow extremes during the eighteenth and nineteenth century.</p> <p>To read more about this research project and to view homemade videos of our research and exciting boat trips in the Amazon River basin, please visit:&nbsp; <em>https://wordpressua.uark.edu/amazon/</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/28/2024<br> Modified by: David&nbsp;W&nbsp;Stahle</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  P2C2: Pan-American precipitation extremes and multi-decadal regimes reconstructed with tree ring chronologies from the Amazon   The Amazon River is the greatest river system on Earth. It has an average annual discharge of 216,000 cubic meters per second, which is greater than the combined discharge of the next six largest rivers in the world. Climate model simulations indicate that human activity may alter the hydrology of the Amazon River basin, resulting in more severe droughts, extreme floods, and a long-term decline in annual rainfall over most of the watershed. Some of these hydrological changes may already be happening. For example, three extreme droughts and five once-in-a-century floods were witnessed in the Amazon in just the last 30-years. Unfortunately, direct instrument-based measurements of temperature, rainfall, and river flow that extend earlier than 1980 are very rare over most of the Amazon watershed. This project has been funded by the National Science Foundation and has used annual ring width data from long lived trees native to the Amazon to serve as a proxy for rainfall over the past 250-years, well before the beginning of weather or streamflow measurements.   We have found tropical hardwood trees in the Rio Paru drainage of the eastern Amazon that live for 200- to 300-years. These Cedrela odorata trees and have distinctive annual growth rings that are directly correlated with rainfall totals (their common name is cedro). The Rio Paru watershed is part of a huge area of pristine forests in the eastern Amazon that is nearly the size of California and contains the tallest trees in all of Amazonia. These Giant Tree Sanctuaries (Santuarios das Avores Gigantes) are very remote, difficult to access, and little known, but have captivated public interest in Brazil and abroad. We have taken small and harmless core samples from some of these forest giants and estimate that many are 200- to 400-years old (both Cedrela and Denezia excelsa).   We have used the ring-width data from the Rio Paru watershed to reconstruct wet season rainfall amounts over the eastern Amazon region from the mid-eighteenth century to present. These rainfall reconstructions are even better when based on oxygen isotope ratios measured on the wood cellulose contained within each annual growth band. Both types of records, ring width and oxygen isotopes, are also influenced by global scale climate systems, most importantly by the El Nino/Southern Oscillation (ENSO). Because of this strong influence from ENSO, the instrumental rainfall and proxy tree growth records in the eastern Amazon are significantly correlated with precipitation and tree growth anomalies of opposite sign in mid-latitude North and South America. When drought and poor tree growth occur in the Amazon, wetness and abundant tree growth are usually observed in subtropical North and South America, which is a direct expression of the power of the El Nino/Southern Oscillation, the great air-sea interaction that orchestrates climate and environmental variability in the Americas and around the world. However, because the global climate impacts of El Nino events are never precisely the same, the new tropical and extratropical tree-ring proxies will allow us to investigate variability in the ENSO forcing of climate over the Americas for the past 300-years.   Our project has also consulted historical documentary records available through the Brazilian Digital Library (BDL) to provide graphic details on several drought and flood years of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries first identified with the tree-ring data in the Amazon. The worst Amazon River floods in the modern record occurred in 2009 and 2021, but our tree-ring estimates and historical documentary accounts indicate that both may have been exceeded by the extreme floods of 1859 and 1892. The drought of 1925-1926 featured an unparalleled reduction of the seasonal high flow, but that event may too have been exceeded by the Forgotten Drought of 1865. The agreement of the tree ring and historical evidence for extreme droughts and floods over the Amazon in the eighteenth and nineteenth century underscores the value of the new proxy and historical records. This tree ring and historical information indicates that the droughts and floods witnessed in the Amazon River basin over the past 30-years may have been exceeded by climate and river flow extremes during the eighteenth and nineteenth century.   To read more about this research project and to view homemade videos of our research and exciting boat trips in the Amazon River basin, please visit: https://wordpressua.uark.edu/amazon/           Last Modified: 07/28/2024       Submitted by: DavidWStahle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
