<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: The saboteur's tools: mechanisms for host reproductive manipulation by the bacterial arthropod endosymbiont Cardinium hertigii]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>440281.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>440281</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Shisler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshisler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925368</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Most insects carry bacteria that live within their cells; these bacteria are inherited from their mothers. The bacteria may manipulate their insect hosts’ reproduction in ways that improves the health or number of female hosts carrying the bacterium. Relevant to this study, these bacterial “symbionts” can sabotage host sperm such that fertilized eggs laid by females without the bacterium die early in life (“cytoplasmic incompatibility,” or “CI”). Currently, two common, unrelated bacteria are known to cause CI in insects: Wolbachia, and Cardinium hertigii, the focus of this study. The main goal of this project is to discover the molecular mechanism by which Cardinium causes CI in insects. The benefits of this work are at least two-fold. Bacteria such as Cardinium target animal cell division, a fundamental process that can be understood better when examining how Cardinium interferes with it. Secondly, CI-causing bacteria may be used for pest or vector management. The CI agent Wolbachia reduces the susceptibility to viruses of insects that carry it, and is currently being introduced around the world to mosquito populations, with major implications for reduction of vector-borne disease and the global bioeconomy. The project will also provide engaging science education targeted for under-represented groups through outreach programs for elementary school (U Arizona Insect Discovery and Insect Festival), high school (production of a book “Animal Manipulating Parasites at NC State, and Iowa State George Washington Carver Internship program) and undergraduate students (via research opportunities at all three institutions). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For Cardinium strains that infect Encarsia spp., parasitic wasps of whiteflies, genomic and transcriptomic studies have identified candidate genes that are likely to be important in CI and/or symbiosis. The central hypotheses are that (1) Cardinium effector proteins involved in modifying host DNA during spermatogenesis are associated with the testes, and other Cardinium effectors involved with rescue of modified sperm are present in the ovaries of infected wasps, (2) the role of these proteins can be inferred by identifying the host proteins they interact with and (3) that the B vitamin biotin has a critical role in CI and/or the symbiosis. The project presents a unique opportunity to test these hypotheses with a diverse array of approaches, in four objectives: (1) Compare Cardinium localization and CI candidate gene expression in male pupal Encarsia, the “modification” stage, with patterns observed in adults.(2) Identify Cardinium and Encarsia proteins involved in CI with differential proteomics. (3) Use heterologous expression to identify interacting host proteins of CI candidate proteins. (4) Investigate the role of Cardinium synthesized biotin in modification of host proteins. This project will shed light on the sophisticated CI reproductive manipulation by Cardinium. Cardinium has received comparatively little attention, but produces a virtually identical CI phenotype to Wolbachia with what appears to be completely independent eukaryote-interacting genes, a plasmid and not a phage, and an unusual type 6 secretion system. What is learned about Cardinium candidate gene function, expression and host targets will illuminate CI and symbiosis in both systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003107</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kleiner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manuel Kleiner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[manuel_kleiner@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000761008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>276950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2601 WOLF VILLAGE WAY]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NVH931QJJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U3NVH931QJJ3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957615</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[112 Derieux Pl]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>765600</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~440281</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many insects carry bacteria that are inherited from their mothers. These symbiotic bacteria live within the insects&rsquo; cells. Several symbiotic bacteria manipulate their insect hosts&rsquo; reproduction in ways that favors their transmission to the next generation. Some of these symbionts sabotage host sperm such that fertilized eggs laid by females without the bacterium die early in life (&ldquo;cytoplasmic incompatibility,&rdquo; or &ldquo;CI&rdquo;). In this interaction, eggs that contain the bacterium are able to &ldquo;rescue&rdquo; the sperm and normal development occurs. Of the six bacteria known to cause CI, <em>Wolbachia</em> is best studied, and genes involved in causing CI in <em>Wolbachia</em> have been discovered.<em> Cardinium hertigii, </em>the focus of this project, causes CI without the same genes <em>Wolbachia </em>uses. The overall goal of this proposal was to discover the genes involved in CI in <em>Cardinium</em>.</p>  <p>We analyzed the localization of two different CI-causing <em>Cardinium</em> strains in the reproductive tract of pupae and adult <em>Encarsia</em> wasps and found that the two different <em>Cardinium</em> strains show distinct patterns in where they are found in the reproductive tract. Further, the finding that sperm development is complete by the end of the pupal stage indicated that pupal males should be examined for <em>Cardinium</em> protein expression.</p>  <p>We developed a protein sequence database for both the symbiont and the host, critical for protein identification. This database will also be highly valuable beyond this project as a reference for other scientists working with <em>Encarsia</em> wasps.</p>  <p>We detected <em>Cardinium</em> proteins in whole pupal and adult <em>Encarsia</em> wasps and in <em>Encarsia</em> tissues such as ovaries and testes. Among the proteins detected, five were most abundant and showed expression patterns that were indicative of being potentially involved in CI.</p>  <p>These five proteins were cloned and expressed in yeast (<em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</em>) to investigate if these proteins have a toxic effect on yeast cells. We reasoned that a protein secreted by <em>Cardinium</em> into sperm may serve as a toxin during early cell division of the embryo if no <em>Cardinium</em> are present in the egg to neutralize the toxin. Since cell division in yeast is similar to cell division in animals we used yeast cells to test if expression of suspected <em>Cardinium</em> toxin proteins would lead to toxicity in yeast. Out of those five proteins, one (CAHE_0406) resulted in a toxic effect when expressed in yeast cells. Homologs of this protein in other <em>Cardinium</em> strains that were similar (but not identical), did not show a toxic effect to yeast cells. A protein encoded by the gene adjacent to CAHE_0406, CAHE_0405, was detected in pupal testes in much lower quantities than CAHE_0406. This gene did not have a toxic effect on yeast and is currently being evaluated as a possible &ldquo;rescue&rdquo; or &ldquo;antidote&rdquo; gene.</p>  <p>Broader Impacts</p>  <p>As part of the project, Dr. Eleanor Spicer-Rice, together with the project team, developed a book about microbes and animals for middle school age student and the book was picked up by MIT Kids Press, an imprint of the well-established children&rsquo;s publisher Candlewick Press. The book was released in May 2023 and has been very successful. It is titled &ldquo;Unseen Jungle: The Microbes That Secretly Control Our World&rdquo;. The book features many engaging stories on the important and weird things that microbes do particularly in interaction with animals and plants. Additionally, the book features five interviews with scientists from diverse backgrounds including an interview with the PI Martha (Molly) Hunter.</p>  <p class="Default">The project also supported several other training and outreach activities. The PhD student employed in the Hunter laboratory as a graduate student and first year postdoc went on to complete a postdoc and is now transitioning to a tenure track faculty position. Two graduate students have been supported in the Schmitz-Esser and Kleiner laboratory and have completed or are completing first authored manuscripts. Five undergraduates were employed on the project in the Hunter laboratory, two in the Schmitz-Esser laboratory and three in the Kleiner laboratory. The Schmitz-Esser lab hosted two Hispanic high school students through the Iowa State University Science Bound Internship program for underrepresented groups for a six-week summer internship. Hunter and the graduate student in the Hunter laboratory both participated for multiple years in the Arizona Insect Festival, a one-day outreach event to the local community which attracts between three and five thousand people, mostly families, to engage in exhibits and activities showcasing research on insects and insect diversity. They also both participated in Insect Discovery, a semester long series of interactive workshops about insect diversity and behavior for elementary school children.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/23/2024<br> Modified by: Manuel&nbsp;Kleiner</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Many insects carry bacteria that are inherited from their mothers. These symbiotic bacteria live within the insects cells. Several symbiotic bacteria manipulate their insect hosts reproduction in ways that favors their transmission to the next generation. Some of these symbionts sabotage host sperm such that fertilized eggs laid by females without the bacterium die early in life (cytoplasmic incompatibility, or CI). In this interaction, eggs that contain the bacterium are able to rescue the sperm and normal development occurs. Of the six bacteria known to cause CI, Wolbachia is best studied, and genes involved in causing CI in Wolbachia have been discovered. Cardinium hertigii, the focus of this project, causes CI without the same genes Wolbachia uses. The overall goal of this proposal was to discover the genes involved in CI in Cardinium.    We analyzed the localization of two different CI-causing Cardinium strains in the reproductive tract of pupae and adult Encarsia wasps and found that the two different Cardinium strains show distinct patterns in where they are found in the reproductive tract. Further, the finding that sperm development is complete by the end of the pupal stage indicated that pupal males should be examined for Cardinium protein expression.    We developed a protein sequence database for both the symbiont and the host, critical for protein identification. This database will also be highly valuable beyond this project as a reference for other scientists working with Encarsia wasps.    We detected Cardinium proteins in whole pupal and adult Encarsia wasps and in Encarsia tissues such as ovaries and testes. Among the proteins detected, five were most abundant and showed expression patterns that were indicative of being potentially involved in CI.    These five proteins were cloned and expressed in yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae) to investigate if these proteins have a toxic effect on yeast cells. We reasoned that a protein secreted by Cardinium into sperm may serve as a toxin during early cell division of the embryo if no Cardinium are present in the egg to neutralize the toxin. Since cell division in yeast is similar to cell division in animals we used yeast cells to test if expression of suspected Cardinium toxin proteins would lead to toxicity in yeast. Out of those five proteins, one (CAHE_0406) resulted in a toxic effect when expressed in yeast cells. Homologs of this protein in other Cardinium strains that were similar (but not identical), did not show a toxic effect to yeast cells. A protein encoded by the gene adjacent to CAHE_0406, CAHE_0405, was detected in pupal testes in much lower quantities than CAHE_0406. This gene did not have a toxic effect on yeast and is currently being evaluated as a possible rescue or antidote gene.    Broader Impacts    As part of the project, Dr. Eleanor Spicer-Rice, together with the project team, developed a book about microbes and animals for middle school age student and the book was picked up by MIT Kids Press, an imprint of the well-established childrens publisher Candlewick Press. The book was released in May 2023 and has been very successful. It is titled Unseen Jungle: The Microbes That Secretly Control Our World. The book features many engaging stories on the important and weird things that microbes do particularly in interaction with animals and plants. Additionally, the book features five interviews with scientists from diverse backgrounds including an interview with the PI Martha (Molly) Hunter.    The project also supported several other training and outreach activities. The PhD student employed in the Hunter laboratory as a graduate student and first year postdoc went on to complete a postdoc and is now transitioning to a tenure track faculty position. Two graduate students have been supported in the Schmitz-Esser and Kleiner laboratory and have completed or are completing first authored manuscripts. Five undergraduates were employed on the project in the Hunter laboratory, two in the Schmitz-Esser laboratory and three in the Kleiner laboratory. The Schmitz-Esser lab hosted two Hispanic high school students through the Iowa State University Science Bound Internship program for underrepresented groups for a six-week summer internship. Hunter and the graduate student in the Hunter laboratory both participated for multiple years in the Arizona Insect Festival, a one-day outreach event to the local community which attracts between three and five thousand people, mostly families, to engage in exhibits and activities showcasing research on insects and insect diversity. They also both participated in Insect Discovery, a semester long series of interactive workshops about insect diversity and behavior for elementary school children.     Last Modified: 11/23/2024       Submitted by: ManuelKleiner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
