<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Probing moire flat bands with optical spectroscopy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>392423.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>392423</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yaroslav Koshka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ykoshka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924986</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical Description: &lt;br/&gt;When a layer with a periodic pattern is laid on top of another similar pattern with minor difference(s) in pitch or orientation, moiré interference patterns appear. Such moiré patterns can occur even at an atomic scale by slightly misaligning the stacking of two 2D (two-dimensional) crystals, which can dramatically modify the properties of the atomic stacks. For example, on its own, graphene (a layer of carbon a single atom thick) conducts electricity like metal does, but with a moiré pattern it can behave either like plastics which don’t conduct electricity or like a superconductor which conducts electricity without generating any heat. This research investigates the unusual behaviors of electronic structures due to moiré patterns. Knowledge acquired through this study will reveal fundamental properties of moiré-patterned 2D systems and pave the way for developing devices that make use of these surprising phenomena. Beyond scientific and technological impacts, this project brings modern materials physics education to the broader Western Massachusetts community through workshops and lab visits. A new summer research internship will be established in collaboration with a Hispanic-serving regional community college, to provide promising underrepresented minority students with a science research experience in the principle investigator’s 2D materials lab. The objective of this internship is to provide educational enrichment opportunities and increase access to science careers to students who are traditionally underrepresented, so that they will be better prepared for matriculating into a four-year institution and later to graduate schools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: &lt;br/&gt;Moiré superlattices with relatively long wavelength of ~10nm in 2D crystals can create almost dispersionless electronic bands, where the kinetic energies of the charges are strongly suppressed, giving way to Coulomb interaction that drives strongly correlated phases. In this project, the PI uses versatile optical spectroscopy techniques to investigate these moiré flat bands formed in stacked atomic layers of graphene and transition metal dichalcogenides. Quantum states such as Mott insulators, superconductivity, and Chern insulators are continuously tuned by the electric fields. Fundamental properties of these states are probed by measuring exciton polarons, magneto-phonon resonances and electronic Raman susceptibility. This project advances scientific knowledge of the quantum materials physics by focusing on three main questions regarding the nature of the moiré flat bands: 1) What is the size and nature of the spontaneously opened gaps in partially filled moiré bands? 2) Can the interaction break the spin and valley degeneracy in the absence of an external magnetic field, and what is the spin and valley polarization? 3) What kind of novel excitations can the correlated states host? Understanding and tuning these properties by the electric field effect are important not only for fundamental physics, but also for future device applications harnessing these unusual properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004474</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jun</FirstName>
<LastName>Yan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jun Yan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yan@physics.umass.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000655882</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>010039252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 COMMONWEALTH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VGJHK59NMPK9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[690 N. Pleasant Street, PSB 039]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>177500</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~124591</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~128901</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~138931</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research supported by this award studied behaviors of particles confined in atomic layers that are stacked on top of each other, with or without a twist angle. We make use of light-matter interactions to probe these interesting two-dimensional (2D) systems. Of particular interest is excitons: bound states of an electron and a hole (a missing electron) moving around each other, just like a hydrogen atom. We observe effects of the excitons in both metallic graphene and semiconducting transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs).</p> <p>In graphene, the exciton energy depends sensitively on the twist angle. When optical excitation or emission has the same energy as the exciton, the interaction between light and graphene is greatly enhanced, a signature of which is a strong enhancement of the Raman scattering signals. The excitons in graphene are short lived. From our measurements we determine a lifetime of ~10 femtoseconds.</p> <p>Excitons in semiconductor TMD and its heterojunctions are much longer lived, especially for interlayer excitons trapped in moire superlattices, on the order of 100 nanoseconds. Our studies placed an emphasis on the valley degree of freedom for the excitons, a quantum property that is analogous to the intrinsic spin of fermions. The valley pseudo-spin sees a pseudo-magnetic field provided by the Coulomb exchange interaction between the electron and the hole in the exciton. The pseudo-magnetic field exerts a torque on the valley pseudospin, which changes the angular momentum of the exciton and causes valley depolarization. We were able to assess the strength of the Coulomb exchange interaction quantitatively. With a good understanding of the exchange interaction, we found a few approaches to combat its valley depolarization effects during the project period. These include charge doping, applying an external magnetic field, populating the moire lattice with two-exciton states, and valley polarization enhancement via scattering with phonons.</p> <p>The completed research project provided rigorous training for two graduate students; both defended their dissertation recently. This award also supported, both during the semester and in the summer, research projects for five undergraduate students, several of whom are unrepresented minorities and/or first-generation college students. A few of them have now joined prestigious institutions to continue their graduate research in related fields. The research project has led to nine peer-reviewed publications, and students working on this project have reported the research findings in a number of conference presentations. Beyond these core members of the project, we hosted multiple lab visits each year for freshman and/or junior/senior undergraduate students, as well as minority students from community colleges and high schools in the greater Springfield area. These activities introduce to these young minds the ideas of 2D materials, how to engineer them with homo- and hetero-junctions, and how to unveil their interesting properties with optical and electronic measurements.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/09/2024<br> Modified by: Jun&nbsp;Yan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The research supported by this award studied behaviors of particles confined in atomic layers that are stacked on top of each other, with or without a twist angle. We make use of light-matter interactions to probe these interesting two-dimensional (2D) systems. Of particular interest is excitons: bound states of an electron and a hole (a missing electron) moving around each other, just like a hydrogen atom. We observe effects of the excitons in both metallic graphene and semiconducting transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs).   In graphene, the exciton energy depends sensitively on the twist angle. When optical excitation or emission has the same energy as the exciton, the interaction between light and graphene is greatly enhanced, a signature of which is a strong enhancement of the Raman scattering signals. The excitons in graphene are short lived. From our measurements we determine a lifetime of ~10 femtoseconds.   Excitons in semiconductor TMD and its heterojunctions are much longer lived, especially for interlayer excitons trapped in moire superlattices, on the order of 100 nanoseconds. Our studies placed an emphasis on the valley degree of freedom for the excitons, a quantum property that is analogous to the intrinsic spin of fermions. The valley pseudo-spin sees a pseudo-magnetic field provided by the Coulomb exchange interaction between the electron and the hole in the exciton. The pseudo-magnetic field exerts a torque on the valley pseudospin, which changes the angular momentum of the exciton and causes valley depolarization. We were able to assess the strength of the Coulomb exchange interaction quantitatively. With a good understanding of the exchange interaction, we found a few approaches to combat its valley depolarization effects during the project period. These include charge doping, applying an external magnetic field, populating the moire lattice with two-exciton states, and valley polarization enhancement via scattering with phonons.   The completed research project provided rigorous training for two graduate students; both defended their dissertation recently. This award also supported, both during the semester and in the summer, research projects for five undergraduate students, several of whom are unrepresented minorities and/or first-generation college students. A few of them have now joined prestigious institutions to continue their graduate research in related fields. The research project has led to nine peer-reviewed publications, and students working on this project have reported the research findings in a number of conference presentations. Beyond these core members of the project, we hosted multiple lab visits each year for freshman and/or junior/senior undergraduate students, as well as minority students from community colleges and high schools in the greater Springfield area. These activities introduce to these young minds the ideas of 2D materials, how to engineer them with homo- and hetero-junctions, and how to unveil their interesting properties with optical and electronic measurements.        Last Modified: 10/09/2024       Submitted by: JunYan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
