<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Exploring the Effects of Impacts onto Phaethon and Other Near Earth Asteroids]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>373560.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>373560</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jacqueline Keane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkeane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928123</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Geminid Meteor Shower is rare in that its parent body, 3200 Phaethon, is an asteroid, not a comet. Most meteor showers are generated by particles expelled from comets by solar heating and evaporation. In Phaethon’s case, the mechanism is less obvious. The team previously explained mass loss at 101955 Bennu as arising due to micrometeoroid impacts from comet particles. The team will now model this idea for Phaethon using NASA’s Meteoriod Engineering Model (MEM). Their hypothesis is that the Geminids are formed through micrometeorite impacts, causing Phaethon to leave a trail of particles, much like a comet. The team will also model mass loss and evolution for weakly-bound primitive bodies that pass close to the Sun. The team will also participate in SwRI’s Summer Science Program (SSP) and conduct a two-day computational session for high-school students in the program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team will use NASA’s Meteoroid Engineering Model to model micrometeoroid impact on a weak primitive surface as is thought to represent 3200 Phaethon in a region at 0.14 AU from the Sun. In prior work with MEM, the team found mm-sized meteoroids strike Bennu frequently enough at &gt; 40 km/s to explain all particle ejection event constraints. Using the Bennu study to guide their work, the team will (i) use the MEM model to determine the mass/direction of ejected debris from Phaethon per perihelion passage, (ii) use dynamical models to determine whether Phaethon debris can reproduce the Geminids over the last ~1000 years, and (iii) use dynamical models to explore Phaethon’s origin, which they argue is probably not from the Pallas asteroid family.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2009775</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Bottke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William F Bottke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bottke@boulder.swri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000385461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southwest Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN ANTONIO</CityName>
<ZipCode>782385166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2105222231</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6220 CULEBRA RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PB11V1KH3KV4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTHWEST RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PB11V1KH3KV4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southwest Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782385166</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6220 Culebra Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>121400</Code>
<Text>PLANETARY ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~373560</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In our work, we made several major advances in understanding the origin of the asteroid (3200) Phaethon.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>  <p>First, we discuss its origin. Previously, it was thought that Phaethon and other large water-rich near-Earth asteroids had to come from the inner or central main belt, given the dynamical pathways that produce such bodies. Our work showed that instead there are dynamical "backroads" that allow asteroids larger than 5 km bodies out of the outer main belt in greater abundance than previously thought. Our work has key implications for not only Phaethon but also the origin of the K-Pg impactor that killed the dinosaurs. Using dynamical modeling work, we showed how such bodies could get to the Earth with much higher probability than expected. We also demonstrated how this same dynamical pathway was the most likely to reproduce the current orbit of Phaethon.&nbsp; This resulted in a published paper in the journal Icarus, and it led to substantial press coverage in newspapers such as the New York Times.</p>  <p>Second, to fully understand what happens to the Phaethon-like objects following the dynamical pathways described above, we decided we needed to model the disruption of all near-Earth objects (NEO) that closely approach the Sun. This would give us a set of model constraints that could be used to test different disruption scenarios. The only way to do this is to model the NEO population itself and compare our results to observations, here from the Catalina Sky Survey for NEOs detected before 2012. We have done so in several published journal papers.</p>  <p>In those papers, we created the best available model of the orbital and size distribution of the NEO population. Our results showed that there is a size-dependent disruption mechanism at work on NEOs that come close to the Sun. Objects that are a few tens of meters disrupt at when they approach the Sun at distances of 0.2 to 0.25 times the distance of the Sun to the Earth, or what we call an astronomical unit (au).&nbsp; Kilometer-sized objects disrupt at smaller distances from the Sun (at 0.1 au), while multi-kilometer objects disrupt at 0.03 au. Our work showed there is also a preference for the destruction of carbonaceous-chondrite like objects over ordinary chondrite-like objects.</p>  <p>One consequence of the size-dependent disruption is that small and large NEOs also have different orbital distributions.These results make sense, in that Phaethon's perihelion distance is 0.14 au, which is within the disruption distance seen for small NEOs. Phaethon itself will not disrupt from such encounters, but it will shed mass, as observed. The question is how to explain the abundance of mass shed from Phaethon. The mechanism producing the disruption is likely to be a combination of the thermal cracking of water-rich rocks combined with meteoroid impacts.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>  <p>Third, a key mystery regarding Phaethon is the disruption process, and how the presence or absence of a regolith can change the survivability of a NEO.&nbsp; We decided that one of the key places to look for answers was Bennu, the target of the OSIRIS-REx mission. Both Bennu and Phaethon are B-class asteroids, and so Bennu's properties give us insights into those of Phaethon.&nbsp;</p>  <p>One of the more remarkable discoveries of the OSIRIS-REx is that Bennu, a 0.5 diameter water-rich NEO, lacks fine-grain material on their surfaces. We thought their surfaces would be abundant in fine sand and pebbles, which would have been perfect for collecting samples. But when OSIRIS-REx arrived, we instead saw a surface covered in boulders. The lack of fine regolith is curious because there is evidence that difference processes (thermal cracking, meteoroid impacts) are capable of grinding boulders into fine regolith.We think the solution may be the nature of Bennu&rsquo;s highly porous rocks. Basically, the fine regolith is not randomly distributed on Bennu but instead is lower where rocks are more porous, which was on most of the surface. This makes us believe that Bennu's highly porous rocks are compressed rather than fragmented by meteoroid impacts. Like a sponge, the voids in rocks cushion the blow from incoming meteors. These findings are also in agreement with laboratory experiments from other research groups. Much of the energy of the impact goes into crushing the pores restricting the fragmentation of the rocks and the production of new fine regolith.&nbsp;&nbsp;From this work, we can assume that Phaethon is also likely to be regolith-free, and that its likely porous rocks are playing in a role in its outbursts. This work was published in the journal Nature.&nbsp;</p>  <p>We made several additional discoveries that are described in our final progress report to NSF that deal with how small carbonaceous chondrite-like asteroids react to cratering and the physical strength of small asteroids.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/26/2024<br> Modified by: William&nbsp;F&nbsp;Bottke</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  In our work, we made several major advances in understanding the origin of the asteroid (3200) Phaethon.    First, we discuss its origin. Previously, it was thought that Phaethon and other large water-rich near-Earth asteroids had to come from the inner or central main belt, given the dynamical pathways that produce such bodies. Our work showed that instead there are dynamical "backroads" that allow asteroids larger than 5 km bodies out of the outer main belt in greater abundance than previously thought. Our work has key implications for not only Phaethon but also the origin of the K-Pg impactor that killed the dinosaurs. Using dynamical modeling work, we showed how such bodies could get to the Earth with much higher probability than expected. We also demonstrated how this same dynamical pathway was the most likely to reproduce the current orbit of Phaethon. This resulted in a published paper in the journal Icarus, and it led to substantial press coverage in newspapers such as the New York Times.    Second, to fully understand what happens to the Phaethon-like objects following the dynamical pathways described above, we decided we needed to model the disruption of all near-Earth objects (NEO) that closely approach the Sun. This would give us a set of model constraints that could be used to test different disruption scenarios. The only way to do this is to model the NEO population itself and compare our results to observations, here from the Catalina Sky Survey for NEOs detected before 2012. We have done so in several published journal papers.    In those papers, we created the best available model of the orbital and size distribution of the NEO population. Our results showed that there is a size-dependent disruption mechanism at work on NEOs that come close to the Sun. Objects that are a few tens of meters disrupt at when they approach the Sun at distances of 0.2 to 0.25 times the distance of the Sun to the Earth, or what we call an astronomical unit (au). Kilometer-sized objects disrupt at smaller distances from the Sun (at 0.1 au), while multi-kilometer objects disrupt at 0.03 au. Our work showed there is also a preference for the destruction of carbonaceous-chondrite like objects over ordinary chondrite-like objects.    One consequence of the size-dependent disruption is that small and large NEOs also have different orbital distributions.These results make sense, in that Phaethon's perihelion distance is 0.14 au, which is within the disruption distance seen for small NEOs. Phaethon itself will not disrupt from such encounters, but it will shed mass, as observed. The question is how to explain the abundance of mass shed from Phaethon. The mechanism producing the disruption is likely to be a combination of the thermal cracking of water-rich rocks combined with meteoroid impacts.    Third, a key mystery regarding Phaethon is the disruption process, and how the presence or absence of a regolith can change the survivability of a NEO. We decided that one of the key places to look for answers was Bennu, the target of the OSIRIS-REx mission. Both Bennu and Phaethon are B-class asteroids, and so Bennu's properties give us insights into those of Phaethon.    One of the more remarkable discoveries of the OSIRIS-REx is that Bennu, a 0.5 diameter water-rich NEO, lacks fine-grain material on their surfaces. We thought their surfaces would be abundant in fine sand and pebbles, which would have been perfect for collecting samples. But when OSIRIS-REx arrived, we instead saw a surface covered in boulders. The lack of fine regolith is curious because there is evidence that difference processes (thermal cracking, meteoroid impacts) are capable of grinding boulders into fine regolith.We think the solution may be the nature of Bennus highly porous rocks. Basically, the fine regolith is not randomly distributed on Bennu but instead is lower where rocks are more porous, which was on most of the surface. This makes us believe that Bennu's highly porous rocks are compressed rather than fragmented by meteoroid impacts. Like a sponge, the voids in rocks cushion the blow from incoming meteors. These findings are also in agreement with laboratory experiments from other research groups. Much of the energy of the impact goes into crushing the pores restricting the fragmentation of the rocks and the production of new fine regolith.From this work, we can assume that Phaethon is also likely to be regolith-free, and that its likely porous rocks are playing in a role in its outbursts. This work was published in the journal Nature.    We made several additional discoveries that are described in our final progress report to NSF that deal with how small carbonaceous chondrite-like asteroids react to cratering and the physical strength of small asteroids.     Last Modified: 12/26/2024       Submitted by: WilliamFBottke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
