<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Targeted Infusion Project: Developing the Biotechnology Certificate Program at Harris-Stowe State University]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>342699.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>342699</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alfred Hall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alfhall@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924895</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. This project at Harris-Stowe State University will develop a Biotechnology Certificate for STEM students that will provide a skill set which they may use to gain employment in the St. Louis Biotechnology environment.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work intends to use CURES (Classroom Undergraduate Research Experiences) to achieve three aims. The first aim is to develop advanced laboratory courses to support a biotechnology certificate program. The second aim is to establish the biotechnology certificate at Harris-Stowe State University. The third aim is to provide CURES that will increase workplace readiness and opportunity placement for students. The implementation of CURES will assist students in developing critical thinking skills, project management and tolerance for ambiguity. The proposed implementation at Harris-Stowe State University will broaden the participation of underrepresented minorities in the STEM workforce. Students who successfully complete the program will be granted a biotechnology certificate that will provide them with a competitive advantage in pursuing STEM opportunities such as graduate school employment and internships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011870</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Leal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sandra M Leal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[leals@hssu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000715813</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Horrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Horrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[horrells@hssu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000784547</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rekha</FirstName>
<LastName>Meyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rekha R Meyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[meyerre@hssu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carmel</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin-Fairey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carmel Martin-Fairey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[martinca@hssu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816739</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[HARRIS-STOWE STATE UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>631032199</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3143403544</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3026 LACLEDE AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U27FC9RA48L3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HARRIS-STOWE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harris-Stowe State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631032199</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3026 Laclede Avenue, Sponsored P]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>159400</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~342699</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The STEM workplace is growing increasingly competitive and it is essential that universities provide its graduates with the skills necessary to compete in this evolving space. Additionally, it is a national imperative that we prepare underrepresented minority students to thrive in this environment and develop robust careers so we can broaden participation in in the STEM workplace. Classroom Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs), courses where students conduct novel research in a classroom setting, provide an excellent opportunity to provide advanced, formative experiences to undergraduate STEM students so they can acquire the skill sets necessary to thrive in STEM. The goal of this grant was to develop a Biotechnology Certificate Program at Harris-Stowe State University (HSSU) that would utilize CUREs to provide specialized, focused training and help prepare recipients for success in STEM. The primary aims of the were 1) to develop advanced laboratory courses (CUREs) to support a Biotechnology Certificate Program, 2) to establish the Biotechnology Certificate at HSSU, and 3) to provide CUREs that increase workplace readiness and opportunity placement.</p>  <p>In order to provide specialized training opportunities to students, different faculty developed CUREs in their domain of expertise. Over the summer, faculty participated in Faculty CURE Forum where they presented their approaches to one another and reviewed literature highlighting best practices in laboratory instruction. In particular, instructors discussed how to foster and assess workplace readiness in their classroom environment. Once developed, these courses were approved to be offered at HSSU. The following courses were developed through this grant: Genetic Manipulation, Introduction to Microscopy, Endocrinology Laboratory, Introduction to Plant Biotechnology, Genes and Genomics, Applied STEM Statistics, Research Ethics in Biology, and Molecular and Cellular Biology Laboratory. Microbiology Laboratory and Neurobiology laboratory were re-developed and enhanced as well. This robust list of courses offerings has greatly expanded potential student experiences within STEM at HSSU.</p>  <p>Utilizing these newly developed courses as well as drawing on existing courses, a Biotechnology Certificate was created. The Certificate requires students to take two introductory laboratory courses, the Molecular and Cellular Biology Laboratory, Research Ethics in Biology, and one of the advanced CUREs paired with its appropriate lecture course. It is designed to be completed as part of an undergraduate STEM student&rsquo;s studies as they progress to a Bachelor&rsquo;s Degree but can also be done in one calendar year as a stand-alone certificate. The Certificate was presented to the Education Policy Committee of HSSU and after revision was accepted to be offered at HSSU. The State of Missouri approved the Certificate as well and HSSU is currently able to offer the certificate. We anticipate granting our first Biotechnology Certificate during the Spring 2025 semester.</p>  <p>CUREs can serve as formative experiences for undergraduate STEM students and help prepare them for lasting success in their field. A major aspect of the intellectual merit of our grant was to investigate this relationship and help to craft a model of how to use CUREs to broaden participation of underrepresented minority students in STEM. However, we were unable to deeply address this aim because of unforeseen circumstances. The grant was awarded during Summer 2020 near the height of the Covid-19 pandemic which created delays in planned laboratory renovations and ordering equipment. This delayed our ability to offer advanced courses which rely on advanced laboratory spaces and equipment. Regardless, laboratory renovations have now been completed, we have obtained the necessary equipment, and we are ready to offer our courses and continue investigating our education research questions. We anticipate gathering data regarding workplace readiness and opportunity place over the next few years as students take courses and obtain Biotechnology Certificates.</p>  <p>By achieving the aims set out in the grant, we have provided additional opportunities for training to the undergraduate STEM students at HSSU and greatly expanded our course offerings. Students can obtain a Biotechnology Certificate indicative of the specialized training they have received during their studies. We hypothesize that students earning this certificate will have both improved workplace readiness and see increased placement into other research training experiences, graduate school, and jobs in the biotechnology sector. We will continue to pursue this research question in the coming years. This grant built on a previous TIP grant focused on enhancing HSSU&rsquo;s ability to offer introductory laboratory courses by continuing to purchase advanced equipment. These grants have also greatly enhanced the ability of HSSU faculty to conduct their own research and offer undergraduate research opportunities to its students. Subsequently, several faculty have applied for grants which represent extensions of their work on this grant. Thus, this grant has helped continue the advancement of STEM at HSSU.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/02/2024<br> Modified by: Scott&nbsp;Horrell</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The STEM workplace is growing increasingly competitive and it is essential that universities provide its graduates with the skills necessary to compete in this evolving space. Additionally, it is a national imperative that we prepare underrepresented minority students to thrive in this environment and develop robust careers so we can broaden participation in in the STEM workplace. Classroom Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs), courses where students conduct novel research in a classroom setting, provide an excellent opportunity to provide advanced, formative experiences to undergraduate STEM students so they can acquire the skill sets necessary to thrive in STEM. The goal of this grant was to develop a Biotechnology Certificate Program at Harris-Stowe State University (HSSU) that would utilize CUREs to provide specialized, focused training and help prepare recipients for success in STEM. The primary aims of the were 1) to develop advanced laboratory courses (CUREs) to support a Biotechnology Certificate Program, 2) to establish the Biotechnology Certificate at HSSU, and 3) to provide CUREs that increase workplace readiness and opportunity placement.    In order to provide specialized training opportunities to students, different faculty developed CUREs in their domain of expertise. Over the summer, faculty participated in Faculty CURE Forum where they presented their approaches to one another and reviewed literature highlighting best practices in laboratory instruction. In particular, instructors discussed how to foster and assess workplace readiness in their classroom environment. Once developed, these courses were approved to be offered at HSSU. The following courses were developed through this grant: Genetic Manipulation, Introduction to Microscopy, Endocrinology Laboratory, Introduction to Plant Biotechnology, Genes and Genomics, Applied STEM Statistics, Research Ethics in Biology, and Molecular and Cellular Biology Laboratory. Microbiology Laboratory and Neurobiology laboratory were re-developed and enhanced as well. This robust list of courses offerings has greatly expanded potential student experiences within STEM at HSSU.    Utilizing these newly developed courses as well as drawing on existing courses, a Biotechnology Certificate was created. The Certificate requires students to take two introductory laboratory courses, the Molecular and Cellular Biology Laboratory, Research Ethics in Biology, and one of the advanced CUREs paired with its appropriate lecture course. It is designed to be completed as part of an undergraduate STEM students studies as they progress to a Bachelors Degree but can also be done in one calendar year as a stand-alone certificate. The Certificate was presented to the Education Policy Committee of HSSU and after revision was accepted to be offered at HSSU. The State of Missouri approved the Certificate as well and HSSU is currently able to offer the certificate. We anticipate granting our first Biotechnology Certificate during the Spring 2025 semester.    CUREs can serve as formative experiences for undergraduate STEM students and help prepare them for lasting success in their field. A major aspect of the intellectual merit of our grant was to investigate this relationship and help to craft a model of how to use CUREs to broaden participation of underrepresented minority students in STEM. However, we were unable to deeply address this aim because of unforeseen circumstances. The grant was awarded during Summer 2020 near the height of the Covid-19 pandemic which created delays in planned laboratory renovations and ordering equipment. This delayed our ability to offer advanced courses which rely on advanced laboratory spaces and equipment. Regardless, laboratory renovations have now been completed, we have obtained the necessary equipment, and we are ready to offer our courses and continue investigating our education research questions. We anticipate gathering data regarding workplace readiness and opportunity place over the next few years as students take courses and obtain Biotechnology Certificates.    By achieving the aims set out in the grant, we have provided additional opportunities for training to the undergraduate STEM students at HSSU and greatly expanded our course offerings. Students can obtain a Biotechnology Certificate indicative of the specialized training they have received during their studies. We hypothesize that students earning this certificate will have both improved workplace readiness and see increased placement into other research training experiences, graduate school, and jobs in the biotechnology sector. We will continue to pursue this research question in the coming years. This grant built on a previous TIP grant focused on enhancing HSSUs ability to offer introductory laboratory courses by continuing to purchase advanced equipment. These grants have also greatly enhanced the ability of HSSU faculty to conduct their own research and offer undergraduate research opportunities to its students. Subsequently, several faculty have applied for grants which represent extensions of their work on this grant. Thus, this grant has helped continue the advancement of STEM at HSSU.         Last Modified: 12/02/2024       Submitted by: ScottHorrell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
