<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Resonant Few-Body Systems from the Lattice]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmihaila@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Strong forces are responsible for the formation of matter as we know it, but the precise mechanism of how this occurs remain a mystery. Strong forces bind nucleons together in atomic nuclei, but they also lead to the emergence of resonant phenomena at higher energies that are studied, e.g., at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (JLab). The experimental and theoretical quest for resonances to understand the strong force focuses on few-body systems and their dynamics. This project aims at closing the gap between theoretical calculations on few-body systems, called lattice QCD, and phenomenology. The main technical challenge addressed in this proposal concerns the problem that these calculations are performed in a small cubic volume instead of infinite space, and how to remove the corresponding artifacts so that lattice QCD can be compared to Nature. Deviations of these predictions from measurements are hints for new physics. The project also aims to conceptually improve the analysis of three-body data from experiment.  The PI will in parallel develop simulations of simple quantum mechanical systems to illustrate the undergraduate and graduate curriculum along the lines of standard textbooks to help develop a diverse, globally competitive STEM workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theory underlying the strong force, Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD), can be calculated using Lattice QCD. However, finite-volume effects for the case of three particles are poorly understood. This project aims to further develop three-body methods to enable the extrapolation of Lattice QCD results to the physical world and to help answer fundamental questions regarding QCD predictions for the properties of excited mesons and baryons. For this, the principle of unitarity, related to the conservation of probability in nuclear reactions, can be efficiently used as the guiding principle, and can be extended to the three- or more particle sector. In this project, methods will be conceptually upgraded to be applied to emblematic resonances. To highlight one, the Roper resonance has been under investigation for decades due to its unusually light mass and its debated nature as radial excitation of the nucleon or hadronic molecule. Furthermore, there is no clear signal for it in ab-initio lattice QCD calculations. The focus of this project is to quantify the finite-volume effects to solve this puzzle. Other lines of investigation address axial resonances that, in their three-body dynamics, resemble the supposed exotic mesons – a new type of particle sought for at JLab and other experiments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012289</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Doering</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Doering</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[doring@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000658855</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maxim</FirstName>
<LastName>Mai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maxim Mai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[maximmai@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815914</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1918 F ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[725 21st St, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128500</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Hadronic resonances give us a glimpse at the inner workings of the Strong Interaction - one of the fundamental forces that is responsible for the formation of matter as we know it. Understanding resonance dynamics bears a key to the emergent phenomena of strong interactions like protons and neutrons. Using modern high-performance computing tools, spectra of resonances could be calculated that were translated to the physical world, removing simulation artifacts such as the fiinite volume. </span></p>  <p><span>A highlight of this project was the&nbsp;<a rel="noopener" href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/1879418" target="_blank">first determination of a three-body resonance from lattice QCD</a>, published in Physics. Rev. Letters.</span></p>  <p><span><img class="media__element b-lazy b-responsive img-fluid b-loaded" src="https://physics.columbian.gwu.edu/sites/g/files/zaxdzs4791/files/2022-08/lattice_webpage.jpg" alt="lattice a1" width="500" height="306" /></span></p>  <p><span><span>The blue arrow indicates the workflow from lattice QCD to phenomenology. The amplitude obtained in the small cubic lattice volume is&nbsp;</span><a rel="noopener" href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/1625299" target="_blank">mapped to the physical, infinite volume</a><span>. The resonance is found as a pole in the complex energy plane (blue shaded area).&nbsp;</span></span></p>  <p><span><span>Other notable achievements include the generalization of a three-body formalism to coupled-channels with spin - up to nine channels in several different spin and isospin configurations <a class="result-item-title" href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/2806793">with pions and kaons</a>. Progress was reported in an invited <a class="result-item-title" href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/1849284">review</a> article.&nbsp;</span></span></p>  <p>Graduate student Yuchuan Feng contributed significantly to the results of the grant. Outreach in form of of a statistics course at GWU, undergraduate research on quantum mechanical simulations, teaching at summer schools, and work on a<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://blogs.gwu.edu/doring/" target="_blank">blog</a> on quantum mechanics provided opportunities for outreach and student education.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/05/2024<br> Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Doering</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Hadronic resonances give us a glimpse at the inner workings of the Strong Interaction - one of the fundamental forces that is responsible for the formation of matter as we know it. Understanding resonance dynamics bears a key to the emergent phenomena of strong interactions like protons and neutrons. Using modern high-performance computing tools, spectra of resonances could be calculated that were translated to the physical world, removing simulation artifacts such as the fiinite volume.     A highlight of this project was thefirst determination of a three-body resonance from lattice QCD, published in Physics. Rev. Letters.        The blue arrow indicates the workflow from lattice QCD to phenomenology. The amplitude obtained in the small cubic lattice volume ismapped to the physical, infinite volume. The resonance is found as a pole in the complex energy plane (blue shaded area).    Other notable achievements include the generalization of a three-body formalism to coupled-channels with spin - up to nine channels in several different spin and isospin configurations with pions and kaons. Progress was reported in an invited review article.    Graduate student Yuchuan Feng contributed significantly to the results of the grant. Outreach in form of of a statistics course at GWU, undergraduate research on quantum mechanical simulations, teaching at summer schools, and work on ablog on quantum mechanics provided opportunities for outreach and student education.     Last Modified: 12/05/2024       Submitted by: MichaelDoering]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
