<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Innovative Numerical Methods for High-Dimensional Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>293120.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>293120</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yuliya Gorb</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ygorb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922113</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to develop efficient numerical algorithms for a class of important systems in science and engineering that are modeled with high-dimensional partial differential equations (PDE) such as the many-body Schrödinger equation. Examples of such systems include many-body quantum mechanics, dynamics of chemical systems, learning and control of complex systems, and spectral methods for high-dimensional data. The numerical solution of high-dimensional PDE has been one of the greatest challenges in computational science and remains a formidable task even with today's computational power and algorithmic advances. Efficient numerical simulations present opportunities for major breakthroughs in scientific understanding. This project will employ modern techniques to develop novel efficient numerical algorithms for such important systems. Graduate students will be trained through involvement in the research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research project combines mathematical analysis and algorithmic design to make progress in numerical methods for high-dimensional PDE. The research will draw from and further develop ideas and tools from recent advances in computational physics, quantum chemistry, and machine learning. In particular, the project will use modern techniques for large-scale optimization and nonlinear parameterization of high-dimensional functions. Specifically, the PI will (1) develop novel highly efficient coordinate algorithms for large-scale eigenvalue problems, and (2) develop and analyze efficient methods based on neural-network parameterization of the solutions for high-dimensional PDE.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012286</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jianfeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jianfeng Lu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jianfeng@math.duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000580742</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054640</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TP7EK8DZV6N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W. Main St., Suite 710]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>127100</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>079Z</Code>
<Text>Machine Learning Theory</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100968</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~94931</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~97221</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>The overarching goal of the project is to design and analyze novel algorithms for high dimensional partial differential equations, with applications in various domains such as quantum mechanics and stochastic control. It has been a timely project thanks to the recent vast development in various related fields, including machine learning, computational physics, and quantum chemistry, in particular, modern techniques for large-scale optmization and nonlinear parametrization (such as artificial neural networks) for high dimensional functions.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project leads to a number of important advances in algorithms for high dimensional problems, including&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>Coordinate based algorithms for large scale eigenvalue problems arising from quantum chemistry; those algorithms achieve state-of-the-art performance for full configuration interaction calculations;&nbsp;</li> <li>Learning-based algorithms for high dimensional partial differential equations, including electronic Schrodinger equations and Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman type equations.&nbsp;</li> <li>Theoretical analysis of representation power of neural-network based ansatz for solutions to PDEs in high dimensions, including efficient represetnations for high-dimensional anti-symmetric functions.&nbsp;</li> <li>Analysis for score-based generative models for high dimensional distributions which yields theoretical guarantees of the performance of these learning algorithms. &nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>In addition to these scientific highlights, the project also provides training opportutinies to a new generation of applied mathematicians working at the interface of several fields. The project also leads to the development of new graduate course in applied mathematics curriculum. &nbsp;</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/30/2024<br> Modified by: Jianfeng&nbsp;Lu</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The overarching goal of the project is to design and analyze novel algorithms for high dimensional partial differential equations, with applications in various domains such as quantum mechanics and stochastic control. It has been a timely project thanks to the recent vast development in various related fields, including machine learning, computational physics, and quantum chemistry, in particular, modern techniques for large-scale optmization and nonlinear parametrization (such as artificial neural networks) for high dimensional functions.   The project leads to a number of important advances in algorithms for high dimensional problems, including  Coordinate based algorithms for large scale eigenvalue problems arising from quantum chemistry; those algorithms achieve state-of-the-art performance for full configuration interaction calculations; Learning-based algorithms for high dimensional partial differential equations, including electronic Schrodinger equations and Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman type equations. Theoretical analysis of representation power of neural-network based ansatz for solutions to PDEs in high dimensions, including efficient represetnations for high-dimensional anti-symmetric functions. Analysis for score-based generative models for high dimensional distributions which yields theoretical guarantees of the performance of these learning algorithms.     In addition to these scientific highlights, the project also provides training opportutinies to a new generation of applied mathematicians working at the interface of several fields. The project also leads to the development of new graduate course in applied mathematics curriculum.             Last Modified: 10/30/2024       Submitted by: JianfengLu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
