<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Reactive Sulfur Species: Challenging the Reactive Oxygen Species Paradigm]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>833240.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>833240</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Dickson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdickson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927380</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed research will use biochemical and cellular techniques to examine metabolism and biochemical pathways of reactive sulfur species (RSS) in cells under physiologically relevant oxygen levels. Derivatives of oxygen form reactive oxygen species (ROS), the most biologically relevant oxidant and the target of most antioxidants, which are thought to improve human health. Natural and synthetic antioxidants, however, have either had limited therapeutic value or their activity appears independent of ROS. This research proposes that many of the assumed actions of reactive oxygen species are better explained by reactive sulfur species. This hypothesis builds upon recent work by the principal researcher, and is based on the following observations: sulfur and oxygen are chemically and biologically similar, cellular antioxidant pathways efficiently metabolize RSS, ‘antioxidant’ health foods affect RSS, many ROS assays cannot distinguish between ROS and RSS and thereby overestimate ROS, and most experiments are performed in room air where oxygen levels are many times greater than the levels within cells, which artificially increases ROS and depletes RSS. In this research project, RSS metabolism by canonical antioxidant pathways will be examined in greater detail and the effects of antioxidant health food ‘nutraceuticals’ on cellular RSS will be examined in detail. The results will have broad implications for basic biology as well as for human health and nutrition. This research will help train one graduate student, one postdoctoral fellow, and several undergraduate students. A solid postdoctoral mentoring program guided by senior faculty will ensure future success in any professional setting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Oxidants, antioxidants, and oxidative stress from reactive oxygen species (ROS) are implicated in endogenous signaling systems and associated with pathophysiological conditions in virtually all organ systems. Work, mainly from the principal investigator’s laboratory, has shown that many of the effects attributed to ROS can be mediated by reactive sulfur species (RSS) due to their chemical similarity, interchangeability in cysteine-mediated signaling systems (hydrogen peroxide ~ hydrogen disulfide), inability to analytically distinguish between the two, and the preponderance of experiments performed under supra-physiological oxygen tensions (room air). The proposed research will show that canonical ROS antioxidant pathways affect RSS metabolism independent of ROS and identify these catalytic mechanisms, will examine RSS metabolism by nutraceutical and synthetic antioxidants, and will show that cellular RSS metabolism is greatly enhanced and diversified when experiments are conducted in ‘physioxic’ environments. Combinations of antioxidants, antioxidant pathway inhibitors, hydrogen sulfide scavengers, and genetically altered cells will be used to manipulate and understand RSS metabolism, measured in buffer and in cells under physiological oxygen concentrations, using specific fluorophores, amperometric electrodes, and mass spectrometry. The proposed research will provide the biochemical and physiological basis for the role of RSS in cell signaling and homeostasis under physiologically relevant conditions. These results will broaden our understanding of RSS in health and disease and open novel areas in biological and biomedical research. It will also provide training for one postdoctoral fellow, one graduate student, and numerous undergraduate students, preparing them for professional careers in the biomedical sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012106</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Olson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth R Olson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kolson@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000334250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLOOMINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>474057000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[107 S INDIANA AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YH86RTW2YVJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana U Sch Medicine South Bend]]></Name>
<CityName>South Bend</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>466171404</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1234 Notre Dame Ave, Raclin Carm]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>765800</Code>
<Text>Physiol Mechs &amp; Biomechanics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~521247</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~311993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>Oxidants and antioxidants are familiar terms that encompass a variety of chemicals. Most notably in biological systems these are derivatives of oxygen, reactive oxygen species (ROS), and they are purportedly involved in both physiological and pathophysiological processes. Reactive sulfur species (RSS) are chemically similar to ROS and although they are more prevalent in cells, they have not been extensively studied, in part because they are degraded by room-air levels of oxygen and in part because RSS methods are still being developed. Work from this project, using state-of-the-art mass spectrometry among other methods has shown that, 1) RSS become more prevalent and reactive at lower, physiological oxygen levels, 2) many intracellular pathways thought to produce or catabolize ROS are as, or often more effective at metabolizing RSS, 3) many health food antioxidants (nutraceuticals), and other &lsquo;natural&rsquo; compounds, some of which are used clinically as anticancer drugs efficiently produce or remove RSS, either directly or catalytically, and the catalytic mechanisms for many of these reactions have been identified, 4) mitochondrially-targeted synthetic carbon nanoparticles designed to manipulate ROS efficiently metabolize RSS, and 5) a drug designed to selectively inhibit ROS catabolism efficiently produces RSS. The emerging significance of RSS and its sensitivity to elevated oxygen support the recent conclusion that the cardiorespiratory system is designed to keep cellular oxygen levels well below room air, as recently promulgated in an opinion article &ldquo;just enough but never too much&rdquo;. Collectively, this work has laid the groundwork for numerous investigations into the role of RSS in physiological and pathophysiological processes as exemplified by per-reviewed publications, invited reviews and presentations at international meetings.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong>Basic research from this grant has fostered collaborative studies with direct clinical implications. These have resulted in research publications and continue to the present, including, 1) the role of RSS metabolism and stem cell activation, with positive outcomes, in an animal model of necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC), an ischemic, debilitating condition in preterm infants that results in high morbidity and mortality, 2) manipulation of RSS metabolism with cell targeted carbon nanoparticles for treatment of traumatic brain injury, where oxygen levels are low, or in Down Syndrome where RSS are elevated, 3) manipulation of RSS metabolism in solid tumors, such as pancreatic cancers where oxygen levels are very low. Collectively, these collaborations show the broad clinical applicability of RSS research, and they provide needed background for redirected therapeutic approaches. This research has provided a training and mentoring environment for a postdoctoral fellow who recently accepted a faculty appointment, and a woman PhD graduate student. Research experience has also been provided to over 25 undergraduate students, over half of which are women or minorities.&nbsp; Nearly all these students have been included as coauthors on research papers and they have matriculated into advanced degree programs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/01/2024<br> Modified by: Kenneth&nbsp;R&nbsp;Olson</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merit: Oxidants and antioxidants are familiar terms that encompass a variety of chemicals. Most notably in biological systems these are derivatives of oxygen, reactive oxygen species (ROS), and they are purportedly involved in both physiological and pathophysiological processes. Reactive sulfur species (RSS) are chemically similar to ROS and although they are more prevalent in cells, they have not been extensively studied, in part because they are degraded by room-air levels of oxygen and in part because RSS methods are still being developed. Work from this project, using state-of-the-art mass spectrometry among other methods has shown that, 1) RSS become more prevalent and reactive at lower, physiological oxygen levels, 2) many intracellular pathways thought to produce or catabolize ROS are as, or often more effective at metabolizing RSS, 3) many health food antioxidants (nutraceuticals), and other natural compounds, some of which are used clinically as anticancer drugs efficiently produce or remove RSS, either directly or catalytically, and the catalytic mechanisms for many of these reactions have been identified, 4) mitochondrially-targeted synthetic carbon nanoparticles designed to manipulate ROS efficiently metabolize RSS, and 5) a drug designed to selectively inhibit ROS catabolism efficiently produces RSS. The emerging significance of RSS and its sensitivity to elevated oxygen support the recent conclusion that the cardiorespiratory system is designed to keep cellular oxygen levels well below room air, as recently promulgated in an opinion article just enough but never too much. Collectively, this work has laid the groundwork for numerous investigations into the role of RSS in physiological and pathophysiological processes as exemplified by per-reviewed publications, invited reviews and presentations at international meetings.      Broader Impacts: Basic research from this grant has fostered collaborative studies with direct clinical implications. These have resulted in research publications and continue to the present, including, 1) the role of RSS metabolism and stem cell activation, with positive outcomes, in an animal model of necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC), an ischemic, debilitating condition in preterm infants that results in high morbidity and mortality, 2) manipulation of RSS metabolism with cell targeted carbon nanoparticles for treatment of traumatic brain injury, where oxygen levels are low, or in Down Syndrome where RSS are elevated, 3) manipulation of RSS metabolism in solid tumors, such as pancreatic cancers where oxygen levels are very low. Collectively, these collaborations show the broad clinical applicability of RSS research, and they provide needed background for redirected therapeutic approaches. This research has provided a training and mentoring environment for a postdoctoral fellow who recently accepted a faculty appointment, and a woman PhD graduate student. Research experience has also been provided to over 25 undergraduate students, over half of which are women or minorities. Nearly all these students have been included as coauthors on research papers and they have matriculated into advanced degree programs.        Last Modified: 10/01/2024       Submitted by: KennethROlson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
