<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Experimental Studies of the Higgs Mechanism in the Standard Model and Beyond]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1850000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1855000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Shank</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshank@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924516</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The start-up of the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) a decade ago ushered in a new era of research in hitherto inaccessible energy regimes. The discovery of the Higgs boson is the first major highlight of the LHC program, which established that the predicted particle content and interactions of the Standard Model (SM) are complete. Despite this success, the SM is widely believed to be an incomplete theory. Ongoing studies must determine whether or not this new Higgs boson is that of the SM, and new experimental data are essential to discover if and how Nature has chosen to extend the SM. These studies include new measurements and searches for new physics, primarily using data recorded at a center-of-mass energy of 13 TeV. The physics analysis activities form a comprehensive program to extend characterization of Higgs boson properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will analyze data collected with the ATLAS experiment at CERN’s Large Hadron Collider. The research includes standard model di-boson measurements, Higgs boson decay properties, and speculative Beyond–the–Standard–Model searches involving Higgs boson production and decay. In addition, the Stony Brook group will lead activities in ATLAS maintenance and operations, algorithm development, and detector upgrades. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the Higgs’ key role in standard model electroweak symmetry breaking, as well as being the only known elementary scalar particle, exploration of its properties is central to particle physics. To that end, this project includes studies of WW production to understand the role of the Higgs boson in vector boson scattering and searches for new physics through modified quartic couplings in boson scattering, studies of the properties of the Higgs boson in associated production focusing on the newly established bottom-antibottom decay mode, extending the sensitivity to higher transverse momenta based on jet substructure techniques and improved b-tagging, and searches for the rare and BSM modes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Stony Brook group has responsibilities for liquid argon calorimeter operations including the installation and commissioning of the Phase I upgrade liquid argon Back End upgrade electronics, and responsibilities for silicon detector operations. They are involved in the ATLAS tracker upgrade R&amp;D and have design, testing and production responsibilities for the HL-LHC liquid argon calorimeter read-out digital processor system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work provides undergraduate and graduate students with the opportunity to participate in leading edge scientific research and instrumentation development. Undergraduate students have the opportunity to participate both through academic year research activities and through the group’s participation in the Stony Brook REU program. This project includes a program of student and community education to be initially hosted at Stony Brook and then more broadly. The group also participates in the local QuarkNet efforts and will host the Higgs Couplings 2020 conference, which will include a public day with lectures and a panel discussion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012055</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dmitri</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsybychev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dmitri Tsybychev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Dmitri.Tsybychev@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000511584</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Hobbs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Hobbs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hobbs@sbhep.physics.sunysb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000333814</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicola Giacinto</FirstName>
<LastName>Piacquadio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicola Giacinto Piacquadio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[giacinto.piacquadio@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000726533</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117943800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[West 510 Frank Melville Library]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>122100</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>075Z</Code>
<Text>Artificial Intelligence (AI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~470000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~690000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~690000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes from this project include results from studies of the Higgs Boson properties and searches for new physics involving the Higgs Bosons in the decay chain. In addition, we are involved in ATLAS experiment particle identification algorithm development, operation of the ATLAS detector apparatus and design and production of upgrades for the apparatus.</p> <p>The Higgs Boson has unique properties, and among them is predicted to be responsible for generating all mass in the universe. Our Stony Brook group, with ATLAS collaborators, measured the Higgs Boson decay fractions to b-quarks and to tau leptons and bounded the decay fraction of decay to mu leptons (muons). In addition to the measurements from production of single Higgs Bosons, we are involved in nascent studies of simultaneous production of a pair of Higgs Bosons. This measurement ultimately relates to the strength of the Higgs Boson interacting with itself and thus to stability of the universe. Thus far all of these measurement are, with varying precision, consistent with the predictions of our best theory.</p> <p>However, the precision of the measurements does allow for limited deviations from the theory which could arise from new, unknown physics. Our group also carries out searches for new particles arising from Higgs Boson decay and for deviations in the predicted rate of pair production of Higgs Bosons. We also analyze reactions from which we can infer properties of the Higgs Boson without directly detecting Higgs Boson decay. Similarly, we search for other reactions indicative of new physics in final states involving vector bosons.</p> <p>Beyond our direct analysis contributions, we contribute to development of algorithms for identifying b-quark (and c-quark) production. These algorithms are in the suite of algorithms used by ATLAS to identify different particle types.</p> <p>The analyses would not be possible without a high quality, efficient experimental apparatus. Our group contributed to the data recording, particularly for the tracking system and the electromagnetic calorimeter. Group members worked in the ATLAS control room and performed data quality analysis.</p> <p>The intensity of the proton beams colliding within ATLAS is already above the design goal and is expected to increase further. Because of this additional upgrades are needed to the experiment. Stony Brook group members are engaged in development of upgrades for the inner tracking system (which measures particle trajectories) and of the read out electronics of the electromagnetic calorimeter (which measures energies of photons and electrons). These are targeted for installation starting in 2027.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/27/2024<br> Modified by: John&nbsp;Hobbs</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The outcomes from this project include results from studies of the Higgs Boson properties and searches for new physics involving the Higgs Bosons in the decay chain. In addition, we are involved in ATLAS experiment particle identification algorithm development, operation of the ATLAS detector apparatus and design and production of upgrades for the apparatus.   The Higgs Boson has unique properties, and among them is predicted to be responsible for generating all mass in the universe. Our Stony Brook group, with ATLAS collaborators, measured the Higgs Boson decay fractions to b-quarks and to tau leptons and bounded the decay fraction of decay to mu leptons (muons). In addition to the measurements from production of single Higgs Bosons, we are involved in nascent studies of simultaneous production of a pair of Higgs Bosons. This measurement ultimately relates to the strength of the Higgs Boson interacting with itself and thus to stability of the universe. Thus far all of these measurement are, with varying precision, consistent with the predictions of our best theory.   However, the precision of the measurements does allow for limited deviations from the theory which could arise from new, unknown physics. Our group also carries out searches for new particles arising from Higgs Boson decay and for deviations in the predicted rate of pair production of Higgs Bosons. We also analyze reactions from which we can infer properties of the Higgs Boson without directly detecting Higgs Boson decay. Similarly, we search for other reactions indicative of new physics in final states involving vector bosons.   Beyond our direct analysis contributions, we contribute to development of algorithms for identifying b-quark (and c-quark) production. These algorithms are in the suite of algorithms used by ATLAS to identify different particle types.   The analyses would not be possible without a high quality, efficient experimental apparatus. Our group contributed to the data recording, particularly for the tracking system and the electromagnetic calorimeter. Group members worked in the ATLAS control room and performed data quality analysis.   The intensity of the proton beams colliding within ATLAS is already above the design goal and is expected to increase further. Because of this additional upgrades are needed to the experiment. Stony Brook group members are engaged in development of upgrades for the inner tracking system (which measures particle trajectories) and of the read out electronics of the electromagnetic calorimeter (which measures energies of photons and electrons). These are targeted for installation starting in 2027.        Last Modified: 09/27/2024       Submitted by: JohnHobbs]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
