<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Numerical Algorithms and Simulations for Multiphase Flows of Multiple Immiscible Incompressible Fluids]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>205349.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>205349</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yuliya Gorb</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ygorb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922113</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project aims to develop mathematical and computational tools, methods, and algorithms for simulating and understanding a class of multiphase multicomponent flow problems that are of practical engineering significance and fundamental physical importance. The systems under study in this project have relevance to the environment, energy, and materials science. For example, such multiphase systems occur in modeling for remediation of oil spills. Another example is the novel class of functional surfaces called liquid infused surfaces discovered in the past decade, which exhibit a variety of attractive properties such as self-cleaning, anti-icing and anti-fouling. These multiphase multicomponent problems underlie numerous technological advances, from printed electronic circuits and sensors, to opto-fluidic microscopes and waveguides, to water-resistant fabrics, to oil recovery and carbon sequestration. The project aims to develop improved efficient and effective computational methods to tackle the challenges in simulations for such systems. This project provides research training opportunities for graduate and undergraduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research aims at devising efficient and effective methods for simulating and understanding the dynamics of a system of three or more immiscible incompressible fluids with different physical properties such as densities, viscosities, and pairwise surface tensions. These systems pose enormous computational and algorithmic challenges to numerical simulations, because of the multitude of fluid interfaces, three-phase lines, and contact lines and contact angles involved. The project builds upon the reduction-consistent and thermodynamically-consistent formulations developed in recent years and will provide computational prediction capability and effective techniques for illuminating and understanding the interactions among multiple fluid components, multiple types of fluid interfaces, and multiple types of contact lines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012415</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suchuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Dong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Suchuan Dong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sdong@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000408798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE # 1100]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072067</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[150 N. University Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>127100</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~67228</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~68410</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~69711</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We have developed in this project effective and efficient computational techniques, mathematical tools, scientific software, and physically consistent models for exploring, understanding, and controlling a class of physical processes and phenomena that are of practical importance to science and engineering. These techniques enable the solution of a wide class of practical problems through computer simulations and have provided the foundational methods and tools.</p> <p>Our research has advanced the frontiers of science and mathematics in the following aspects. First, we have established physically consistent mathematical models and effective computational algorithms for two-phase dielectric fluids and their interactions with external electric fields. By incorporating thermodynamic consistency and reduction consistency, the model provides a rigorous foundation for the simulation and analysis of dielectric systems. This has wide application potentials in many areas of science and engineering (e.g. electric vehicles). Second, we have established a class of highly accurate and cost-effective computational methods through scientific machine learning. Leveraging a special type of artificial neural networks and novel computation algorithms, our methods are not only highly accurate, with spectral-like accuracy, but also computationally fast. These methods are highly effective for forward and inverse problems, as well as for applications in high dimensions. This class of methods has profound implications to vast areas of computational science and engineering. Third, we have developed a framework for theoretically analyzing scientific machine learning methods for solving a class of application problems. This contributes to the fundamental understanding of these techniques, fostering the development of more robust and effective computation algorithms.</p> <p>This project has also provided valuable opportunities for the growth and training of next-generation applied mathematicians and computational scientists. It offers a rich source of research topics for several students at graduate and undergraduate levels. Working on this project, they have gained scientific expertise and invaluable technical skills. The research findings, data, and scientific software attained in this project have been widely disseminated and shared with researchers from many universities in the US and around the world. Research findings of this project have also contributed to the math curriculum, and part of them has been incorporated into the math courses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/17/2024<br> Modified by: Suchuan&nbsp;Dong</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  We have developed in this project effective and efficient computational techniques, mathematical tools, scientific software, and physically consistent models for exploring, understanding, and controlling a class of physical processes and phenomena that are of practical importance to science and engineering. These techniques enable the solution of a wide class of practical problems through computer simulations and have provided the foundational methods and tools.   Our research has advanced the frontiers of science and mathematics in the following aspects. First, we have established physically consistent mathematical models and effective computational algorithms for two-phase dielectric fluids and their interactions with external electric fields. By incorporating thermodynamic consistency and reduction consistency, the model provides a rigorous foundation for the simulation and analysis of dielectric systems. This has wide application potentials in many areas of science and engineering (e.g. electric vehicles). Second, we have established a class of highly accurate and cost-effective computational methods through scientific machine learning. Leveraging a special type of artificial neural networks and novel computation algorithms, our methods are not only highly accurate, with spectral-like accuracy, but also computationally fast. These methods are highly effective for forward and inverse problems, as well as for applications in high dimensions. This class of methods has profound implications to vast areas of computational science and engineering. Third, we have developed a framework for theoretically analyzing scientific machine learning methods for solving a class of application problems. This contributes to the fundamental understanding of these techniques, fostering the development of more robust and effective computation algorithms.   This project has also provided valuable opportunities for the growth and training of next-generation applied mathematicians and computational scientists. It offers a rich source of research topics for several students at graduate and undergraduate levels. Working on this project, they have gained scientific expertise and invaluable technical skills. The research findings, data, and scientific software attained in this project have been widely disseminated and shared with researchers from many universities in the US and around the world. Research findings of this project have also contributed to the math curriculum, and part of them has been incorporated into the math courses.        Last Modified: 11/17/2024       Submitted by: SuchuanDong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
