<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Non-Ideal Majorana Fermions: A Practical Approach to Topological Quantum Computation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark S. Byrd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>msbyrd@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927421</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main obstacle to quantum computation is the “noise” affecting the basic units of a quantum computer – the so-called qubits – as a result of their weak, but nonzero coupling to the environment. Since this coupling is essentially local, a promising approach to overcoming the noise problem is to encode the information using topological quantum phenomena – robust global properties characterizing certain types of quantum systems that are immune to local perturbations. A promising platform for realizing robust topological qubits is based on a special kind of quantum quasiparticle called a Majorana fermion or Majorana zero mode (MZM). Recent theoretical studies by the PIs and other groups indicate that experiments may have already uncovered non-ideal versions of MZMs, the so-called quasi-Majorana modes. In this project the PIs will examine fundamental aspects of topological protection and practical design questions related to maximizing qubit lifetime and minimizing noise rates in quantum devices with non-ideal Majorana fermions. With most of the ongoing research in the field focusing on ideal Majorana fermions, which in practice may be hard to realize, the present studies will be critical to engineering the first generation of topological qubits using what may be already available, namely, non-ideal Majorana fermions. The project will serve the national interest and promote the NSF mission of progress of science by deepening our understanding of topological quantum matter in condensed matter systems and investigating the feasibility of topological quantum computation based on experimentally available devices. The project will provide excellent education and training opportunities to undergraduate and graduate students at Clemson University, including economically disadvantaged students and underrepresented minorities who constitute a significant percentage of the student population. This project is jointly funded by the Quantum Information Science Program (Physics Division), and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Majorana zero modes (MZMs) in semiconductor-superconductor (SM-SC) nanowire heterostructures are currently being investigated as possible building blocks for topological qubits in a future quantum computer. Theoretical studies by the PIs and others have shown that much of the parameter space of the experimentally investigated SM-SC heterostructures is in fact occupied by so-called quasi-Majorana zero modes, which are separated from each other by a length scale well below the nanowire length. Since the principle of fault tolerance in topological quantum computation (TQC) depends critically on the non-local encoding of quantum information using topological MZMs separated by the length of the nanowire, this situation presents a major problem for the feasibility of TQC, as quasi-Majoranas do not enjoy sufficient topological protection for fault-tolerant qubit operations. Nonetheless, quasi-Majoranas are likely to be present in the first generation of Majorana-based qubit devices either by design, or by accident. This project fills the critical void created by the near absence of studies of topological qubit designs and schemes for braiding and error correction when the constituent building blocks are quasi-Majoranas, rather than ideal topological MZMs. The PIs will perform analytical and numerical research with the following intellectual goals: (1) Designing and modeling SM-SC qubit devices based on controllable quasi-Majorana zero modes, (2) Understanding and characterizing the key physical processes that control the quasi-Majorana qubit lifetimes, and (3) Error analysis in measurement-only TQC schemes with quasi-Majorana zero modes. The overarching goal is to investigate the feasibility of fault tolerant TQC with quasi-Majorana zero modes (rather than ideal MZMs) and to better understand practical aspects of engineering Majorana-based topological qubits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014157</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sumanta</FirstName>
<LastName>Tewari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sumanta Tewari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stewari@clemson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000515118</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 SIKES HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H2BMNX7DSKU8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clemson</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[118 Kinard Laboratory, Physics a]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>728100</Code>
<Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>915000</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Brief Summary of Outcomes: A class of exotic quasiparticles called Majorana zero modes (MZMs) were proposed earlier as building blocks for fault-tolerant topological quantum computation (TQC). But experimentally, it has now become apparent that the topological quasiparticles seen in the proposed Majorana platform known as semiconductor-superconductor (SM-SC) heterostructure are not the ideal quasiparticles needed for TQC. They are, rather, approximate MZMs, known as quasi-Majorana zero modes, or sometimes called partially-separated Andreev modes, and whether or not they can be effectively used in fault-tolerant TQC is an ongoing research topic of great technological interest. In this proposal, the PIs extensively investigated the SM-SC heterostructure in the presence of disorder and investigated the occurence of quasi-MZMs and topological MZMs in exhaustive phase diagrams as a function of Zeeman field and chemical potential. Several papers were written in peer-reviewed international journals and a review article was written as part of a book chapter published by Elsevier.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: In one of the main outcomes of this proposal, by numerically calculating the zero-bias conductance (ZBC) maps as a function of Zeeman splitting and chemical potential for different disorder realizations, it is shown that the large topological region associated with the clean system, which is characterized by a quantized ZBC height of 2e^2/h, breaks up into progressively smaller &ldquo;islands&rdquo; as the disorder strength increases. Based on this result, we conclude that the observation of quantized islands with ZBC value approximately equal to 2e^2/h demonstrates unambiguously the presence of the key ingredients necessary for Majorana physics, provides an excellent diagnostic tool for evaluating the disorder strength, and, consequently, represents the next natural milestone in Majorana search.</p> <p>In another important outcome of this proposal, we investigate theoretically a one-dimensional SM-SC heterostructure with Rashba spin-orbit coupling and parallel Zeeman field in the presence of disorder generated by random charged impurities and identify the optimal regimes for realizing topological superconductivity and MZMs.&nbsp;Using a Green&rsquo;s function approach, we show that upon increasing the disorder strength the stable topological superconducting phase characterized byrobust end-to-end Majorana correlations &ldquo;migrates&rdquo; toward larger values of the Zeeman field and can be stabilized by increasing the effective SM-SC coupling. Based on these findings, we propose a strategy for accessing a regime characterized by well-separated MZMs that is based on (a) enhancing the strength of the effective SM-SC coupling (e.g., through interface engineering) and (b) expanding the range of accessible Zeeman fields (e.g., by enhancing the gyromagnetic ratio or optimizing the parent superconductor, to enable the application of larger magnetic fields).</p> <p>Borader Impact: As Broader Impact 9 papers were published in peer-reviewed international journals including a review article on topological quantum computation and Majorana fermions as a book chapter published by Elsevier. The PI taught and developed two new courses in Clemson open to both graduate and undergraduate students. They are (1) Introduction to Topological Physics in Condensed Matter and (2) Introduction to Quantum Computation. The published (or under review) papers are book chapters are (Semiconductors and Semimetals (Chapter 4), Volume 108, Page 125, Elsevier (2021);&nbsp;Phys. Rev. B 105, 205122 (2022); Phys. Rev. B 107, 144206 (2023); arXiv: 2402.18549 (under review in PRB);&nbsp;Phys. Rev. B 105, 235420 (2022);&nbsp;Phys. Rev. B 107, 115161 (2023);&nbsp;Phys. Rev. B 104, 205124 (2021);&nbsp;Phys. Rev. B 107, L081107 (2023))&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 08/09/2024<br> Modified by: Sumanta&nbsp;Tewari</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Brief Summary of Outcomes: A class of exotic quasiparticles called Majorana zero modes (MZMs) were proposed earlier as building blocks for fault-tolerant topological quantum computation (TQC). But experimentally, it has now become apparent that the topological quasiparticles seen in the proposed Majorana platform known as semiconductor-superconductor (SM-SC) heterostructure are not the ideal quasiparticles needed for TQC. They are, rather, approximate MZMs, known as quasi-Majorana zero modes, or sometimes called partially-separated Andreev modes, and whether or not they can be effectively used in fault-tolerant TQC is an ongoing research topic of great technological interest. In this proposal, the PIs extensively investigated the SM-SC heterostructure in the presence of disorder and investigated the occurence of quasi-MZMs and topological MZMs in exhaustive phase diagrams as a function of Zeeman field and chemical potential. Several papers were written in peer-reviewed international journals and a review article was written as part of a book chapter published by Elsevier.   Intellectual Merit: In one of the main outcomes of this proposal, by numerically calculating the zero-bias conductance (ZBC) maps as a function of Zeeman splitting and chemical potential for different disorder realizations, it is shown that the large topological region associated with the clean system, which is characterized by a quantized ZBC height of 2e^2/h, breaks up into progressively smaller islands as the disorder strength increases. Based on this result, we conclude that the observation of quantized islands with ZBC value approximately equal to 2e^2/h demonstrates unambiguously the presence of the key ingredients necessary for Majorana physics, provides an excellent diagnostic tool for evaluating the disorder strength, and, consequently, represents the next natural milestone in Majorana search.   In another important outcome of this proposal, we investigate theoretically a one-dimensional SM-SC heterostructure with Rashba spin-orbit coupling and parallel Zeeman field in the presence of disorder generated by random charged impurities and identify the optimal regimes for realizing topological superconductivity and MZMs.Using a Greens function approach, we show that upon increasing the disorder strength the stable topological superconducting phase characterized byrobust end-to-end Majorana correlations migrates toward larger values of the Zeeman field and can be stabilized by increasing the effective SM-SC coupling. Based on these findings, we propose a strategy for accessing a regime characterized by well-separated MZMs that is based on (a) enhancing the strength of the effective SM-SC coupling (e.g., through interface engineering) and (b) expanding the range of accessible Zeeman fields (e.g., by enhancing the gyromagnetic ratio or optimizing the parent superconductor, to enable the application of larger magnetic fields).   Borader Impact: As Broader Impact 9 papers were published in peer-reviewed international journals including a review article on topological quantum computation and Majorana fermions as a book chapter published by Elsevier. The PI taught and developed two new courses in Clemson open to both graduate and undergraduate students. They are (1) Introduction to Topological Physics in Condensed Matter and (2) Introduction to Quantum Computation. The published (or under review) papers are book chapters are (Semiconductors and Semimetals (Chapter 4), Volume 108, Page 125, Elsevier (2021);Phys. Rev. B 105, 205122 (2022); Phys. Rev. B 107, 144206 (2023); arXiv: 2402.18549 (under review in PRB);Phys. Rev. B 105, 235420 (2022);Phys. Rev. B 107, 115161 (2023);Phys. Rev. B 104, 205124 (2021);Phys. Rev. B 107, L081107 (2023))     Last Modified: 08/09/2024       Submitted by: SumantaTewari]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
