<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCH:INT: Collaborative Research: Deep Sense: Interpretable Deep Learning for Zero-effort Phenotype Sensing and Its Application to Sleep Medicine]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Goli Yamini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gyamini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925367</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Sleep represents one third of everyone’s life and affects the quality and the health of everyone’s life. Traditionally, long-term characteristics of sleep patterns (sleep phenotypes) are largely unknown due to the lack of convenient monitoring devices and automatic algorithms.  Recently, massive health sensing data such as activity data, electroencephalogram, respiratory monitoring data and electrocardiography are being collected in clinics and at home, which brings unprecedented opportunities for understanding sleep phenotypes outside clinics. However, there are tremendous challenges to translate these noisy and unreliable multimodal sensing data into accurate phenotypes such as sleep stages and apnea events. Beyond sleep, many neurological conditions such as Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s all expect objective tracking of long-term disease progression, which is currently impossible. This project will provide the computational capability to conduct phenotype tracking at home with the focus on sleep phenotypes. Machine learning methods and software will be developed to conduct accurate phenotyping of sleep with minimal effort on sensor instrumentation, data collection and analysis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims at developing DeepSense, a deep learning toolbox to model massive data streams including in-clinic monitoring data such as polysomnography and novel radio frequency signals from a wireless sensing device. The research team will develop accurate deep learning methods to automate sleep monitoring using polysomnography data. They will invent adversarial deep learning methods for modeling radio frequency  signals and leverage large historical polysomnography data to help improve models for radio frequency signals. They will develop interpretable models that leverage and expand medical knowledge on sleep phenotypes. Finally, all the proposed models will be validated through a prospective study with a goal of automating manual sleep studies and assessing the feasibility of sleep studies via radio frequency signal data. The research team plans to release the open-source software and large datasets from this project that can benefit computer science, engineering and medical community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014438</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jimeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jimeng Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jimeng@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000653017</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S WRIGHT ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>V2PHZ2CSCH63</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>801800</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8062</Code>
<Text>SCH Type II: INT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Deep Sense project, titled "SCH:INT: Collaborative Research: Deep Sense: Interpretable Deep Learning for Zero-effort Phenotype Sensing and Its Application to Sleep Medicine," aimed to revolutionize the way we understand and treat sleep-related health issues by developing innovative, contactless, and interpretable deep learning models. The project ran from October 2020 to September 2024 and was a collaborative effort involving the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, MIT, and Harvard Medical School. It focused on the intersection of artificial intelligence, sleep medicine, and wireless sensing technologies.</p> <p>One of the primary achievements of the project was the development of deep learning algorithms to automate the analysis of sleep data collected through standard polysomnography (PSG) and radio frequency (RF) signals. These methods successfully created accurate automation models that reduced the workload for clinicians by providing reliable sleep staging and apnea detection. The RF-based sleep monitoring approach introduced a novel, contactless way to conduct sleep studies, which could greatly benefit home-based sleep diagnostics. This has the potential to make sleep health assessments more accessible, especially for populations unable to easily attend clinical sleep centers.</p> <p>The project's models achieved high accuracy in sleep staging (80.5%) using RF signals, comparable to the agreement between different human experts. Furthermore, the models demonstrated equitable performance across different demographics, including variations in race, sex, and age. They also successfully detected sleep apnea (achieving an Area Under the Receiver Operating Characteristic curve of 0.89) and provided accurate measures of the Apnea-Hypopnea Index (Intraclass Correlation Coefficient of 0.90). The robustness of the models across a range of health conditions&mdash;including respiratory, cardiovascular, immune, and neurological diseases&mdash;highlights the broad applicability of this technology.</p> <p>The project also made significant strides in training the next generation of researchers. It provided interdisciplinary training for PhD students and postdoctoral researchers across the participating institutions, fostering expertise in AI-driven healthcare solutions, non-invasive monitoring technologies, and clinical research. Students and researchers gained hands-on experience in machine learning for healthcare applications, resulting in a number of high-impact publications and presentations.</p> <p>The research findings were widely disseminated, with eight peer-reviewed articles published in prestigious journals such as Sleep, Neurology Clinical Practice, JMIR AI, and Scientific Reports and top AI conferences such as NeurIPS. The project also emphasized open access, making the findings available to both academic and clinical communities to ensure the broadest possible impact.</p> <p>Overall, the Deep Sense project has demonstrated significant advancements in sleep medicine and artificial intelligence, providing new tools for non-contact health monitoring and contributing valuable insights into the relationship between sleep and various health conditions. These findings are expected to foster further research and development in non-invasive health monitoring and personalized medicine, ultimately improving healthcare accessibility and quality.</p> <p><span>This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.</span></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/08/2024<br> Modified by: Jimeng&nbsp;Sun</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Deep Sense project, titled "SCH:INT: Collaborative Research: Deep Sense: Interpretable Deep Learning for Zero-effort Phenotype Sensing and Its Application to Sleep Medicine," aimed to revolutionize the way we understand and treat sleep-related health issues by developing innovative, contactless, and interpretable deep learning models. The project ran from October 2020 to September 2024 and was a collaborative effort involving the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, MIT, and Harvard Medical School. It focused on the intersection of artificial intelligence, sleep medicine, and wireless sensing technologies.   One of the primary achievements of the project was the development of deep learning algorithms to automate the analysis of sleep data collected through standard polysomnography (PSG) and radio frequency (RF) signals. These methods successfully created accurate automation models that reduced the workload for clinicians by providing reliable sleep staging and apnea detection. The RF-based sleep monitoring approach introduced a novel, contactless way to conduct sleep studies, which could greatly benefit home-based sleep diagnostics. This has the potential to make sleep health assessments more accessible, especially for populations unable to easily attend clinical sleep centers.   The project's models achieved high accuracy in sleep staging (80.5%) using RF signals, comparable to the agreement between different human experts. Furthermore, the models demonstrated equitable performance across different demographics, including variations in race, sex, and age. They also successfully detected sleep apnea (achieving an Area Under the Receiver Operating Characteristic curve of 0.89) and provided accurate measures of the Apnea-Hypopnea Index (Intraclass Correlation Coefficient of 0.90). The robustness of the models across a range of health conditionsincluding respiratory, cardiovascular, immune, and neurological diseaseshighlights the broad applicability of this technology.   The project also made significant strides in training the next generation of researchers. It provided interdisciplinary training for PhD students and postdoctoral researchers across the participating institutions, fostering expertise in AI-driven healthcare solutions, non-invasive monitoring technologies, and clinical research. Students and researchers gained hands-on experience in machine learning for healthcare applications, resulting in a number of high-impact publications and presentations.   The research findings were widely disseminated, with eight peer-reviewed articles published in prestigious journals such as Sleep, Neurology Clinical Practice, JMIR AI, and Scientific Reports and top AI conferences such as NeurIPS. The project also emphasized open access, making the findings available to both academic and clinical communities to ensure the broadest possible impact.   Overall, the Deep Sense project has demonstrated significant advancements in sleep medicine and artificial intelligence, providing new tools for non-contact health monitoring and contributing valuable insights into the relationship between sleep and various health conditions. These findings are expected to foster further research and development in non-invasive health monitoring and personalized medicine, ultimately improving healthcare accessibility and quality.   This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.     Last Modified: 10/08/2024       Submitted by: JimengSun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
