<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Context Dependence across Categories: Bridging Developmental, Experimental, and Theoretical Perspectives]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150945.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150945</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rachel M. Theodore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rtheodor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924770</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ability to categorize entities in the world is a fundamental part of human cognition. Language plays a central role in this process. Yet in many cases in natural language, categorization is impossible without further information from the context. Such is the case, for example, with gradable adjectives such as 'tall', where meaning shifts from context to context, and even with nouns. How do children succeed at assembling their lexicon and determining reference when faced with such shifting, context-dependent meanings? This project pursues this question by examining the context-dependence that arises in one of the most basic and earliest-acquired categories: count nouns. The study of such nouns and corresponding concepts has stood at the center of research on infancy, the count/mass and object/substance distinctions, and language typology. Thus, the anticipated results from this research will have broad and interdisciplinary impact. In particular, the findings will offer insights into the ways language and cognition are intertwined in the course of development, and deepen our understanding of how contextual information influences meaning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project takes as its starting point a well-established finding that young children allow object fragments to be treated on par with whole objects as referents for corresponding nouns like 'fork' or 'cup'. The key hypothesis of this research is that this apparent non-adult behavior stems from children's difficulties in using contextual information to enrich an inherently context-dependent nominal meaning. A series of behavioral experiments with children and adults compares nominal gradability with gradable adjectives, with the goal of using these behavioral responses to (a) identify a developmental linguistic trajectory, (b) dissociate category/concept-specific from more general aspects of gradability and context-dependence, and (c) tease apart parts of meaning contributed by semantics and pragmatics. Significant efforts will be directed towards mentoring, hands-on training, and education at the undergraduate, graduate, and post-doctoral levels, as well as community outreach. The findings will advance scientific discovery by being incorporated into classes and will be disseminated broadly in scholarly venues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Athulya</FirstName>
<LastName>Aravind</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Athulya Aravind</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[athulya.aravind@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000742605</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey – New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>New Brunswick</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>089018554</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[57 US Highway 1]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>131100</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~150945</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Some of the first words children understand and use are common count nouns like "ball" and "fork." Strikingly, children sometimes use of these words quite differently from adults. For example, when shown a collection of whole forks and broken fork pieces and asked to count "the forks," children count the whole forks like adults, but then go on to count the pieces as well, as if they were actual usable forks. This might seem surprising, but our research shows that it reflects something fundamental about language&mdash;and it turns out that children are not that different from adults after all.</p>  <p>Count nouns like "fork" or "plate" are inherently vague and flexible, with meanings that shift depending on context &ndash; so flexible that in fact that sometimes even adults use them to describe such &lsquo;partial&rsquo;, broken objects. For instance, in the context of an archaeological dig, a fragment of a plate might be called a "plate." Adults, however, are generally more restrictive than children, as they have become accustomed to prioritizing whole objects across varied contexts. Children, by contrast, are initially more permissive, suggesting a developmental trajectory shaped by changes in their ability to integrate contextual information and infer a speaker&rsquo;s intent.</p>  <p>To explore this flexibility in count noun application, this project compared children&rsquo;s and adults&rsquo; interpretations of these nouns to two types of adjectives that have specified standards for when they can be used:</p>  <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gradable adjectives with maximal<strong> </strong>standards, like "full," which only applies to things that are completely full. If a glass is half-full, we cannot call it &ldquo;full&rdquo;.</p>  <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gradable adjectives with minimal standards, like "striped," which applies as long as there are any stripes. If a cat has only a few stripes, we can already call it &ldquo;striped&rdquo;</p>  <p>The key question was whether children and adults think nouns like &ldquo;fork&rdquo; are more like maximal standard adjectives like &ldquo;full&rdquo;, or like minimal standard adjectives just like &ldquo;striped&rdquo;. Findings from this project show that both children and adults can adopt a minimal standard when interpreting count nouns. What they differ in is figuring out when the conversation calls for a maximal standard. Adults are very skilled at using contextual cues&mdash;like the goal of the conversation or functional relevance of the object&mdash;to decide when a broken fork should not count as a fork (e.g. when someone asks for a utensil at dinner). &nbsp;Children, on the other hand, tend to default to minimal standards, and require much more explicit contextual information to use &lsquo;maximal&rsquo; standards &ndash; they effectively have to be told <em>why</em> only full forks matter for the current situation. We also know that this is not from a lack of understanding differences in standards, because with maximal and minimal standard adjectives where context-based flexibility is not needed, children were adult-like.&nbsp; These findings reveal that children&rsquo;s apparent mistakes in using count nouns is due to the intrinsic vagueness and context-sensitivity of nouns rather than an issue with understanding the meanings of nouns. As children grow, they become more attuned to contextual cues, and their behavior becomes more adult-like. Overall, this research advances our understanding of the role of context in the interpretation of adjectival and nominal expressions and how it shifts over the course of development.</p>  <p>The project has resulted in 2 publications, 3 manuscripts in the pipeline, 1 master&rsquo;s thesis, and several conference presentations at interdisciplinary venues. The PIs have taught findings from this work their classes, including a focused 2-week summer school course. In addition to these intellectual merits, the project has provided valuable training opportunities to a post-doc, two post-bac RAs, and several graduate and undergraduate students. These trainees appear as co-authors on conference and research papers reflecting the project&rsquo;s results.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/15/2024<br> Modified by: Athulya&nbsp;Aravind</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Some of the first words children understand and use are common count nouns like "ball" and "fork." Strikingly, children sometimes use of these words quite differently from adults. For example, when shown a collection of whole forks and broken fork pieces and asked to count "the forks," children count the whole forks like adults, but then go on to count the pieces as well, as if they were actual usable forks. This might seem surprising, but our research shows that it reflects something fundamental about languageand it turns out that children are not that different from adults after all.    Count nouns like "fork" or "plate" are inherently vague and flexible, with meanings that shift depending on context  so flexible that in fact that sometimes even adults use them to describe such partial, broken objects. For instance, in the context of an archaeological dig, a fragment of a plate might be called a "plate." Adults, however, are generally more restrictive than children, as they have become accustomed to prioritizing whole objects across varied contexts. Children, by contrast, are initially more permissive, suggesting a developmental trajectory shaped by changes in their ability to integrate contextual information and infer a speakers intent.    To explore this flexibility in count noun application, this project compared childrens and adults interpretations of these nouns to two types of adjectives that have specified standards for when they can be used:    - Gradable adjectives with maximal standards, like "full," which only applies to things that are completely full. If a glass is half-full, we cannot call it full.    - Gradable adjectives with minimal standards, like "striped," which applies as long as there are any stripes. If a cat has only a few stripes, we can already call it striped    The key question was whether children and adults think nouns like fork are more like maximal standard adjectives like full, or like minimal standard adjectives just like striped. Findings from this project show that both children and adults can adopt a minimal standard when interpreting count nouns. What they differ in is figuring out when the conversation calls for a maximal standard. Adults are very skilled at using contextual cueslike the goal of the conversation or functional relevance of the objectto decide when a broken fork should not count as a fork (e.g. when someone asks for a utensil at dinner). Children, on the other hand, tend to default to minimal standards, and require much more explicit contextual information to use maximal standards  they effectively have to be told why only full forks matter for the current situation. We also know that this is not from a lack of understanding differences in standards, because with maximal and minimal standard adjectives where context-based flexibility is not needed, children were adult-like. These findings reveal that childrens apparent mistakes in using count nouns is due to the intrinsic vagueness and context-sensitivity of nouns rather than an issue with understanding the meanings of nouns. As children grow, they become more attuned to contextual cues, and their behavior becomes more adult-like. Overall, this research advances our understanding of the role of context in the interpretation of adjectival and nominal expressions and how it shifts over the course of development.    The project has resulted in 2 publications, 3 manuscripts in the pipeline, 1 masters thesis, and several conference presentations at interdisciplinary venues. The PIs have taught findings from this work their classes, including a focused 2-week summer school course. In addition to these intellectual merits, the project has provided valuable training opportunities to a post-doc, two post-bac RAs, and several graduate and undergraduate students. These trainees appear as co-authors on conference and research papers reflecting the projects results.     Last Modified: 12/15/2024       Submitted by: AthulyaAravind]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
