<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID/Collaborative Research: Estuarine dam removal as an ecosystem disturbance: Examining the impacts of seawater intrusion on functional stability of benthic N cycle communities]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>136808.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>165835</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Large dams (&gt; 15m high) are a major man-made disturbance to watersheds altering the structure and function of river ecosystems. The Nakdong River is one of the watersheds heavily affected by the dam constructed at the mouth of the river to stop tidal seawater exchange. When it was built in 1987, the dam caused dramatic shifts in lower river ecosystems converting the area to a man-made freshwater reservoir. The alteration of river water flows resulted in seasonal harmful algal blooms and water quality degradation. Increasing concerns about these negative impacts along with associated social and economic demands have led to restoring the river ecosystem by removing the dam. The dam removal will be done in a controlled way through a series of events that open the dam's gates, thereby allowing seawater intrusion into upstream ecosystems. This provides a unique and immediate opportunity to study the impacts of seawater intrusion on a freshwater ecosystem. The series of planned dam openings can be effectively used as a large-scale, unprecedented, manipulative ecosystem experiment. This RAPID project takes advantage of this unique opportunity to study the sediment microbial communities responding to the programmed seawater intrusion in the river. The project will include training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, and results will disseminated via public lectures and a scientific network for river researchers.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project aims to study the functional stability of sediment nitrogen (N) cycling communities responding to the disturbance of seawater intrusion in the Nakdong River, where dam removal is in progress via a series openings of dam gates. Multi-omic approaches including metagenomic, metatranscriptomic and metaproteomic analyses will be conducted to evaluate both sensitivity and resilience of individual N metabolisms in a community, while the measurements of N cycling processes (fluxes and rates), including denitrification and dissimilatory nitrate reduction to ammonium, reveal a whole community metabolism responding to the seawater intrusion. This is a unique and transformative project to determine the functional stability of different metabolisms within the community exposed to a programmed seawater intrusion in a freshwater ecosystem. The combined multi-omics and biogeochemical measurements will provide novel knowledge of sensitivity and resilience in different systematic levels from genes to individual organisms to the community level. Dissimilatory N cycling metabolisms in sediment communities are selected as a model of microbial functions since benthic N cycling is critical to attenuate excess N loading, a cause of eutrophication. Given the importance of benthic N cycle, the impacts of seawater intrusion on sediment N cycling communities and their functions have been mainly examined with ex-situ experimental designs such as microcosms and mesocosms or field survey along salinity gradients of rivers and estuaries. This first project represents the first ecosystem-scale manipulation examining sediment N cycling communities responding to seawater intrusion. Two graduate students will be involved in the project and will be trained in multi-omic and biogeochemcial methods. The project will also include training activities for undergraduates at the two institutions, dissemination of results in public outreach lectures and via the Worldwide Hydrobiogeochemical Observatory Network for Dynamic River Systems (WHONDRS).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016246</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bongkeun</FirstName>
<LastName>Song</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bongkeun Song</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[songb@vims.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000336999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Stegen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Stegen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[james.stegen@pnnl.gov]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000618990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of William & Mary Virginia Institute of Marine Science]]></Name>
<CityName>GLOUCESTER POINT</CityName>
<ZipCode>230622026</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8046847000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1375 GREATE RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XGE9T6KCMSR4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA INSTITUTE OF MARINE SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Y5P1L2NZAHV9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of William & Mary Virginia Institute of Marine Science]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>230621346</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>738100</Code>
<Text>Ecosystem Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~136808</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~29027</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merits</p>  <p>Large dams have long been integral to societal needs, providing water for cities and agriculture, and generating renewable hydropower. However, their construction has profoundly disrupted natural ecosystems, altering aquatic food webs and nutrient cycling processes. As many dams age and awareness grows about their environmental consequences, dam removal has become a common strategy for restoring ecosystems. Despite this trend, there has been limited scientific study on the effects of dam opening or removal on aquatic ecosystems and biogeochemical processes.</p>  <p>This project provided groundbreaking insights by examining the effects of a programmed dam opening on the Nakdong River in South Korea. Using cutting-edge multi-omics techniques (metagenomics, metatranscriptomics, and metaproteomics) alongside biogeochemical rate measurements and hydrodynamic and biogeochemical modeling, we studied how microbial communities in sediments responded to the intrusion of seawater following the dam opening. Microbial communities play a critical role in nutrient cycling, including nitrogen, which affects water quality and ecosystem health.</p>  <p>Our findings revealed notable shifts in nitrogen cycling processes. Over three years, denitrification activity&mdash;a process that removes excess nitrogen by converting it into harmless nitrogen gas&mdash;increased steadily. This suggests that opening the dam supported the restoration of estuarine conditions, helping mitigate long-term nitrogen pollution. Conversely, communities involved in DNRA (dissimilatory nitrate reduction to ammonium), which recycles nitrogen back into the ecosystem, also expanded, particularly through sulfate- and iron-reducing bacteria.</p>  <p>A particularly novel discovery was the growing importance of complete ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (coammox), which played a key role in nitrogen cycling under changing conditions. These findings not only advanced our understanding of microbial nitrogen dynamics but also provided evidence that estuarine restoration can lead to long-term ecological recovery. Importantly, metatranscriptomics (studying gene activity) proved to be the most effective method for linking microbial processes to real-world nitrogen cycling rates, demonstrating the value of advanced molecular techniques in environmental research.</p>  <p>Broader Impact</p>  <p>This project provided opportunities to train and develop two graduate students at the Virginia Institute of Marine Science.&nbsp; One graduate student completed her Ph.D. degree and another student is continuously working on this project as part of his Ph.D. project. In addition, the PI has mentored a Chinese graduate student to complete her Ph.D. degree at Pusan University, South Korea.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>  <p>Our findings provide critical evidence that controlled dam openings or removals can support ecosystem restoration. By enhancing denitrification and restoring natural nitrogen cycles, dam management can mitigate the harmful effects of nitrogen pollution, including algal blooms and eutrophication. This research underscores the importance of managing dam operations for ecological and water quality benefits, which is relevant for regions worldwide facing similar challenges.</p>  <p>Many dams in the United States and globally are being considered for removal due to aging infrastructure and environmental concerns. However, the ecological effects of such actions are often uncertain. This project provides a much-needed evidence base for policymakers and planners, offering guidance on the potential ecological benefits and challenges of dam removals. By demonstrating how dam opening enhances natural nitrogen cycling and estuarine restoration, this research supports the development of strategies to manage dam operations and removals sustainably.</p>  <p>The general public often perceives dams as purely beneficial structures, but this project highlights their ecological costs and the potential for environmental recovery when dams are removed or opened. By sharing these findings with the public, we aim to foster greater awareness of the importance of balancing human infrastructure needs with ecological sustainability. This research emphasizes the value of estuaries as critical ecosystems that provide services such as water filtration, habitat for wildlife, and protection against coastal erosion.</p>  <p>In conclusion, this project advanced scientific understanding of how dam operations influence microbial communities and nutrient cycling, while providing practical guidance for ecosystem restoration and management. As society continues to address the challenges of aging infrastructure and environmental sustainability, this research offers a framework for balancing human needs with ecological health, ultimately supporting efforts to restore and protect vital aquatic ecosystems worldwide.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/27/2024<br> Modified by: Bongkeun&nbsp;Song</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merits    Large dams have long been integral to societal needs, providing water for cities and agriculture, and generating renewable hydropower. However, their construction has profoundly disrupted natural ecosystems, altering aquatic food webs and nutrient cycling processes. As many dams age and awareness grows about their environmental consequences, dam removal has become a common strategy for restoring ecosystems. Despite this trend, there has been limited scientific study on the effects of dam opening or removal on aquatic ecosystems and biogeochemical processes.    This project provided groundbreaking insights by examining the effects of a programmed dam opening on the Nakdong River in South Korea. Using cutting-edge multi-omics techniques (metagenomics, metatranscriptomics, and metaproteomics) alongside biogeochemical rate measurements and hydrodynamic and biogeochemical modeling, we studied how microbial communities in sediments responded to the intrusion of seawater following the dam opening. Microbial communities play a critical role in nutrient cycling, including nitrogen, which affects water quality and ecosystem health.    Our findings revealed notable shifts in nitrogen cycling processes. Over three years, denitrification activitya process that removes excess nitrogen by converting it into harmless nitrogen gasincreased steadily. This suggests that opening the dam supported the restoration of estuarine conditions, helping mitigate long-term nitrogen pollution. Conversely, communities involved in DNRA (dissimilatory nitrate reduction to ammonium), which recycles nitrogen back into the ecosystem, also expanded, particularly through sulfate- and iron-reducing bacteria.    A particularly novel discovery was the growing importance of complete ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (coammox), which played a key role in nitrogen cycling under changing conditions. These findings not only advanced our understanding of microbial nitrogen dynamics but also provided evidence that estuarine restoration can lead to long-term ecological recovery. Importantly, metatranscriptomics (studying gene activity) proved to be the most effective method for linking microbial processes to real-world nitrogen cycling rates, demonstrating the value of advanced molecular techniques in environmental research.    Broader Impact    This project provided opportunities to train and develop two graduate students at the Virginia Institute of Marine Science. One graduate student completed her Ph.D. degree and another student is continuously working on this project as part of his Ph.D. project. In addition, the PI has mentored a Chinese graduate student to complete her Ph.D. degree at Pusan University, South Korea.    Our findings provide critical evidence that controlled dam openings or removals can support ecosystem restoration. By enhancing denitrification and restoring natural nitrogen cycles, dam management can mitigate the harmful effects of nitrogen pollution, including algal blooms and eutrophication. This research underscores the importance of managing dam operations for ecological and water quality benefits, which is relevant for regions worldwide facing similar challenges.    Many dams in the United States and globally are being considered for removal due to aging infrastructure and environmental concerns. However, the ecological effects of such actions are often uncertain. This project provides a much-needed evidence base for policymakers and planners, offering guidance on the potential ecological benefits and challenges of dam removals. By demonstrating how dam opening enhances natural nitrogen cycling and estuarine restoration, this research supports the development of strategies to manage dam operations and removals sustainably.    The general public often perceives dams as purely beneficial structures, but this project highlights their ecological costs and the potential for environmental recovery when dams are removed or opened. By sharing these findings with the public, we aim to foster greater awareness of the importance of balancing human infrastructure needs with ecological sustainability. This research emphasizes the value of estuaries as critical ecosystems that provide services such as water filtration, habitat for wildlife, and protection against coastal erosion.    In conclusion, this project advanced scientific understanding of how dam operations influence microbial communities and nutrient cycling, while providing practical guidance for ecosystem restoration and management. As society continues to address the challenges of aging infrastructure and environmental sustainability, this research offers a framework for balancing human needs with ecological health, ultimately supporting efforts to restore and protect vital aquatic ecosystems worldwide.     Last Modified: 11/27/2024       Submitted by: BongkeunSong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
