<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Promoting Equity in the Social Sciences]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>963414.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>963414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keri Ann Sather-Wagstaff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ksatherw@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922534</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Social Science Research Council (SSRC) in partnership with the American Anthropological Association (AAA), the American Economic Association (AEA), the American Historical Association (AHA), the American Political Science Association (APSA), and the American Sociological Association (ASA), plan to implement an ADVANCE project to address norms and practices that have been shown to inhibit career advancement of women and intersectional scholars.  The project will educate society staff and members as well as adapt promising practices from ADVANCE projects into the organizational operations of the SSRC and the collaborating societies. The goal is to implement structural changes that will positively impact the culture and climate of the social sciences and ensure practices and processes within these organizations are equitable and inclusive, especially those related to publishing and professional recognition.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In collaboration with six disciplinary societies of the social sciences, the SSRC will build awareness and disseminate information on strategies to address bias in the academic decision-making processes tailored to the social science discipline areas.  This project will build upon and adapt successful ADVANCE institutional transformation strategies that were developed for changes within institutions of higher education to increase the representation and advancement of women and intersectional scholars in the social sciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NSF ADVANCE program is designed to foster gender equity through a focus on the identification and elimination of organizational barriers that impede the full participation and advancement of diverse faculty in academic institutions. Organizational barriers that inhibit equity may exist in policies, processes, practices, and the organizational culture and climate. ADVANCE "Partnership" awards provide support to collaborations among STEM professional societies and academic and non-academic non-profit organizations designed to broaden the implementation of evidence-based equity strategies and have a national or regional reach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017663</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicole</FirstName>
<LastName>Levit</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicole Levit</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[levit@ssrc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carl Johan</FirstName>
<LastName>Palm</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carl Johan F Palm</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[palm@ssrc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814336</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alma</FirstName>
<LastName>Granado</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alma M Granado</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[granado@ssrc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vina</FirstName>
<LastName>Tran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vina Tran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vtran@ssrc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819880</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Social Science Research Council]]></Name>
<CityName>BROOKLYN</CityName>
<ZipCode>112012790</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2123772700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 PIERREPONT PLZ FL 15]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JRJDPT749TH7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOCIAL SCIENCE RESEARCH COUNCIL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>JRJDPT749TH7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Social Science Research Council]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112013226</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>016Y00</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>011Z</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE PLAN D</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7568</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE-PAID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7650</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE PLAN IHE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~963414</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-6c37e2ba-7fff-49ef-7b4b-6605fd05b65c"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Peer Review Objectives and Guidelines for Representation and Equity in the Social Sciences (PROGRESS) was a three-year NSF Adaptation grant project that identified and addressed institutional processes that inhibit the advancement of women and intersectional scholars in the social sciences. PROGRESS, housed within the Social Science Research Council, worked in partnership with five academic disciplinary associations, to develop working models to reduce inequities within selection processes. The program also addressed organizational policies and procedures related to advisory board formation, peer review, and fellowship/awards conferment to ensure that diversity, equity, and inclusion measures are meaningful and effective.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Disseminating fundamental awareness of bias in academic decision-making processes:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>PROGRESS worked with academic disciplinary association leadership in anthropology, economics, history, political science and sociology to create resources and implement successful DEI initiatives. During year one of the grant, </span><span>PROGRESS conducted an in-depth review of partner disciplinary associations&rsquo; current DEI and peer-review practices through </span><span>independent research on each association, listening sessions with association leaders, and review of available demographic data. From this, the grant team developed a </span><span>Disciplinary Association Activities Document, detailing current interventions and areas for further development. </span><span>A </span><span>formal meeting with partner association leadership provided an avenue for disciplinary cross-collaboration and idea exchange.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To make DEI research in social science fields more widely accessible, PROGRESS built</span><a href="https://progress.ssrc.org/"><span> DEI in the Social Sciences</span></a><span>, an online research tool, using the SSRC&rsquo;s Research Area Mapping Platform technology. The site functions as a digital, open-source Zotero library for scholarship specifically related to diversity, equity, and inclusion in the social sciences. Interested parties are able to easily find journal publications, news articles, books, etc., sorted by relevance to each social science partner discipline on a variety of DEI topics.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>PROGRESS published three academic posters outlining the grant&rsquo;s objectives, distributing supplementary resource lists, and showcasing the ResearchAMP site at national conferences including the American Political Science Association Annual Meeting. The grant team also published an implicit bias primer document.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Revision and standardization of selection procedures for 20+ SSRC programs:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>PROGRESS conducted a thorough internal review of the SSRC's current DEI practices and selection procedures. With the support of SSRC executive management, the grant team implemented necessary revisions to promote more equitable selection processes. The grant program hosted</span><span> three staff workshops encouraging people to collectively think about DEI issues and the programs at the SSRC: DEI Challenges in Council Programming; Creating Fair and Inclusive Selection Processes; and Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion and Data Collection. PROGRESS also created a new folder of resources for staff including </span><span>staff diversity metrics, the SSRC's implicit bias primer, revised principles for data collection, and fellowship demographic data.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>PROGRESS revised demographic data collection practices for all competitive applications at the SSRC. This data includes the gender and race/ethnicity breakdowns of the applicant pools and finalists for each competition at the SSRC. The grant team also reviewed application instructions. By explixitly stating what is expected in terms of proposal sections and CV content, the SSRC aims to level the playing field for those who may be new to the application process.</span><span><br /></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Development of DEI initiatives and leadership of interdisciplinary collaboration across the social science academic associations:</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>PROGRESS hosted two DEI discussions for a Department Chairs' Workshop. The first year&rsquo;s session featured three discussion groups led by field experts in Recruiting and Hiring, Decision-making and Department Climate, and Equity in Service and Value (Invisible Labor). The following year, another discussion session featured the topics of Community and Belonging, Working with Legal Counsel, and Departmental Shifts. </span><span>The grant team also hosted a workshop session at an association&rsquo;s annual meeting with three breakout groups facilitated by field experts.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The </span><span>grant team hosted a webinar on navigating department climate issues</span><span> structured around a participant-led discussion of a two-part case study. PROGRESS also </span><span>partnered with a research funding organization to support a project</span><span> </span><span>which </span><span>conducted a survey collecting data on demographics in relation to experiences obtaining academic funding.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>PROGRESS collaborated with a disciplinary association&rsquo;s DEI Officer on a day-long convening featuring insights into how changes to the journal submission process were made to eliminate implicit bias in the journal selection process, all while increasing the journal&rsquo;s impact factor. The convening was attended by 30+ faculty members and an executive director from another PROGRESS disciplinary association partner.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>PROGRESS worked to organize a new SSRC grant program - the Women in Economics Research Consortium. The 1M grant from the Sloan Foundation supports research grants that test, replicate, and scale interventions designed to increase women&rsquo;s representation in economics.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><br /><br /><br /><br /><br /></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 04/30/2024<br> Modified by: Nicole&nbsp;Levit</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714488588684_DEI_in_the_Social_Sciences--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714488588684_DEI_in_the_Social_Sciences--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DEI in the Social Sciences Poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714488588684_DEI_in_the_Social_Sciences--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DEI in the Social Sciences Poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Image of informative poster on the DEI in the Social Sciences ResearchAMP.</div> <div class="imageCredit">T Shukla</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nicole&nbsp;Levit <div class="imageTitle">DEI in the Social Sciences Poster</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714484590751_PROGRESSResearchAMPScreenshot--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714484590751_PROGRESSResearchAMPScreenshot--rgov-800width.png" title="Screenshot of SSRC PROGRESS in the Social Sciences Research AMP"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714484590751_PROGRESSResearchAMPScreenshot--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Screenshot of SSRC PROGRESS in the Social Sciences Research AMP"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PROGRESS in the Social Sciences is an online hub for resources relevant to DEI in the social sciences. Funded by an NSF ADVANCE Adaptation Grant, this site highlights the disciplines of Anthropology, Economics, History, Political Science and Sociology.</div> <div class="imageCredit">N Levit</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nicole&nbsp;Levit <div class="imageTitle">Screenshot of SSRC PROGRESS in the Social Sciences Research AMP</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714488670663_rps_peer_review_objectives_guidelines__4_--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714488670663_rps_peer_review_objectives_guidelines__4_--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Peer Review Objectives and Guidelines for Representation and Equity in the Social Sciences (PROGRESS)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2017663/2017663_10716751_1714488670663_rps_peer_review_objectives_guidelines__4_--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Peer Review Objectives and Guidelines for Representation and Equity in the Social Sciences (PROGRESS)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Poster about the Peer Review Objectives and Guidelines for Representation and Equity in the Social Sciences (PROGRESS) NSF Advance Grant.</div> <div class="imageCredit">T Shukla</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nicole&nbsp;Levit <div class="imageTitle">Peer Review Objectives and Guidelines for Representation and Equity in the Social Sciences (PROGRESS)</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Peer Review Objectives and Guidelines for Representation and Equity in the Social Sciences (PROGRESS) was a three-year NSF Adaptation grant project that identified and addressed institutional processes that inhibit the advancement of women and intersectional scholars in the social sciences. PROGRESS, housed within the Social Science Research Council, worked in partnership with five academic disciplinary associations, to develop working models to reduce inequities within selection processes. The program also addressed organizational policies and procedures related to advisory board formation, peer review, and fellowship/awards conferment to ensure that diversity, equity, and inclusion measures are meaningful and effective.   Disseminating fundamental awareness of bias in academic decision-making processes:   PROGRESS worked with academic disciplinary association leadership in anthropology, economics, history, political science and sociology to create resources and implement successful DEI initiatives. During year one of the grant, PROGRESS conducted an in-depth review of partner disciplinary associations current DEI and peer-review practices through independent research on each association, listening sessions with association leaders, and review of available demographic data. From this, the grant team developed a Disciplinary Association Activities Document, detailing current interventions and areas for further development. A formal meeting with partner association leadership provided an avenue for disciplinary cross-collaboration and idea exchange.   To make DEI research in social science fields more widely accessible, PROGRESS built DEI in the Social Sciences, an online research tool, using the SSRCs Research Area Mapping Platform technology. The site functions as a digital, open-source Zotero library for scholarship specifically related to diversity, equity, and inclusion in the social sciences. Interested parties are able to easily find journal publications, news articles, books, etc., sorted by relevance to each social science partner discipline on a variety of DEI topics.   PROGRESS published three academic posters outlining the grants objectives, distributing supplementary resource lists, and showcasing the ResearchAMP site at national conferences including the American Political Science Association Annual Meeting. The grant team also published an implicit bias primer document.   Revision and standardization of selection procedures for 20+ SSRC programs:   PROGRESS conducted a thorough internal review of the SSRC's current DEI practices and selection procedures. With the support of SSRC executive management, the grant team implemented necessary revisions to promote more equitable selection processes. The grant program hosted three staff workshops encouraging people to collectively think about DEI issues and the programs at the SSRC: DEI Challenges in Council Programming; Creating Fair and Inclusive Selection Processes; and Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion and Data Collection. PROGRESS also created a new folder of resources for staff including staff diversity metrics, the SSRC's implicit bias primer, revised principles for data collection, and fellowship demographic data.   PROGRESS revised demographic data collection practices for all competitive applications at the SSRC. This data includes the gender and race/ethnicity breakdowns of the applicant pools and finalists for each competition at the SSRC. The grant team also reviewed application instructions. By explixitly stating what is expected in terms of proposal sections and CV content, the SSRC aims to level the playing field for those who may be new to the application process.    Development of DEI initiatives and leadership of interdisciplinary collaboration across the social science academic associations:   PROGRESS hosted two DEI discussions for a Department Chairs' Workshop. The first years session featured three discussion groups led by field experts in Recruiting and Hiring, Decision-making and Department Climate, and Equity in Service and Value (Invisible Labor). The following year, another discussion session featured the topics of Community and Belonging, Working with Legal Counsel, and Departmental Shifts. The grant team also hosted a workshop session at an associations annual meeting with three breakout groups facilitated by field experts.   The grant team hosted a webinar on navigating department climate issues structured around a participant-led discussion of a two-part case study. PROGRESS also partnered with a research funding organization to support a project which conducted a survey collecting data on demographics in relation to experiences obtaining academic funding.   PROGRESS collaborated with a disciplinary associations DEI Officer on a day-long convening featuring insights into how changes to the journal submission process were made to eliminate implicit bias in the journal selection process, all while increasing the journals impact factor. The convening was attended by 30+ faculty members and an executive director from another PROGRESS disciplinary association partner.   PROGRESS worked to organize a new SSRC grant program - the Women in Economics Research Consortium. The 1M grant from the Sloan Foundation supports research grants that test, replicate, and scale interventions designed to increase womens representation in economics.                   Last Modified: 04/30/2024       Submitted by: NicoleLevit]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
