<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Does Registration and Notification Policy Deter Adolescent Sexual Offending? A Prospective Study of Integrated Criminological and Psychological Theories]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>122295.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>122295</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Despite controversy over whether even adults should be required to register as sex offenders, currently 41 states have some form of policy requiring adolescents adjudicated or convicted of sexual offenses to register with local law enforcement agencies upon completing their sentences. Moreover, 30 states allow or require online community notification of adolescents who committed sexual offenses, posting information on public websites or “registries” to inform residents about the young offenders living in their communities. Registration and notification policies are partly rooted in deterrence theory, which presumes that the risk of these outcomes will prevent potential sexual offenders from offending in the first place. However, criminological and psychological theories predict different outcomes of these policies, and whether they actually deter adolescent sexual offending remains unknown. Prior research suggests that many adolescents are not aware of the risk of registration and notification posed by their sexual behavior. Moreover, even if they are aware, psychological science suggests that their developmental immaturity may override that knowledge and result in offending anyway. This interdisciplinary project investigates whether and how registration and notification policies deter adolescents from engaging in criminalized sexual behaviors that are common in their age group. Findings will inform policymakers working to develop evidence-based strategies that effectively achieve justice while also protecting developmentally vulnerable adolescents from excessively punitive and stigmatizing outcomes.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This study explicates the criminological processes that are prerequisite to general deterrence as well as the developmental psychological mechanisms that may condition those processes. Specifically, it experimentally manipulates whether adolescents are exposed to educational information about the risk of criminal justice involvement and sex offender registration and notification associated with illegal sexual behaviors. The results will reveal whether and how, even when adolescents are aware that certain sexual behaviors are prohibited and carry legal risks, their ability to engage in rational choice and their perceptions of the net cost of sexual offending moderate the impact of registration and notification over the course of one year. This project’s experimental and longitudinal approach will allow for causal determinations about the criminological processes that are thought to underlie general deterrence as well as the developmental psychological mechanisms that may condition the ability of sex offender registration and notification policy to affect adolescents’ risky sexual behavior. This will transform current understanding of relations between criminological theory on deterrence, social-developmental psychology, and legal policy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017122</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Najdowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cynthia J Najdowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cnajdowski@albany.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000586146</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Albany]]></Name>
<CityName>ALBANY</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184374974</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 WASHINGTON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NHH3T1Z96H29</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NHH3T1Z96H29</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Albany]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y00</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~122295</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Despite controversy over whether even adults should be required to register as sex offenders, most states have some form of policy requiring adolescents adjudicated or convicted of sexual offenses to register with local law enforcement agencies upon completing their sentences. Moreover, most states allow or require online community notification of adolescents who committed sexual offenses, posting information on public websites or &ldquo;registries&rdquo; to inform residents about the young offenders living in their communities. Registration and notification policies are partly rooted in deterrence theory&mdash;the idea that the threat of severe punishment will prevent potential sexual offenders from committing these acts in the first place. However, past research had indicated that many adolescents are not aware of the risk of registration and notification posed by their sexual behavior. Moreover, even if they are aware, psychological science suggests that their developmental immaturity may override that knowledge and result in offending anyway.</p>  <p>The Sexual Awareness and Viewpoints of Virginia Youth (SAVVY) Study was an interdisciplinary project that investigated whether registration and notification policies deterred adolescents from engaging in criminalized sexual behaviors, with a particular interest in behaviors that are common in their age group. A total of 339 Virginia adolescents aged 14-17 years old completed two 30-minute online surveys, administered approximately nine months apart. The surveys included questions about youths&rsquo; sexual attitudes, behaviors, and legal knowledge. In addition, some youth were exposed to an educational intervention designed to enhance their legal knowledge. The goal of this research was to gather information that can be used to inform state and federal policy, legal system interactions with youth, and teen education and intervention programs.</p>  <p>The study&rsquo;s findings demonstrated that many adolescents lacked awareness of juvenile sex offender registration and notification policies. Furthermore, the data collected revealed no significant differences in self-reported sexual offending behaviors based on youths&rsquo; knowledge of registration policies, suggesting these policies do not act as deterrents to reduce such behaviors. Indeed, illegal sexual behaviors were common in our sample, with 28% of adolescents reporting they had engaged in illegal sexual behaviors in the year preceding the initial study as well as in the nine months between the two survey administrations. Although an educational intervention administered through the first survey was effective at increasing youths&rsquo; legal knowledge over time, it did not reduce their likelihood of engaging in illegal sexual behaviors in the nine months following the intervention. The results speak to the discipline of criminology, supporting the premise within Robinson and Darley&rsquo;s (2004) general deterrence framework that merely being aware of a legal consequence is not sufficient to deter individuals from engaging in risky behavior.</p>  <p>To examine why this might be the case, analyses also examined the role of psychosocial maturity constructs derived from Steinberg and Cauffman&rsquo;s (1996) developmental theory. Results showed that neither impulse control, future orientation, resistance to peer influence, perceptions of sanction certainty, nor risk ambiguity related to the frequency with which adolescents had engaged in registerable sexual behaviors. Instead, adolescents&rsquo; behaviors were driven by their beliefs about positive peer expectations and their perceptions of how prevalent the illegal sexual behaviors under study were among their peers.</p>  <p>Juvenile sex offender registration and notification policies have become more restrictive and more frequently applied to adolescent offenders, so a main objective of this project was to understand whether the policies actually deter youth from sexual offending. Findings suggest that juvenile sex offender registration and notification policies are not successfully deterring adolescents from engaging in registerable offenses. The results from this interdisciplinary research can be used to inform policymaking on this heavily contested issue. Moreover, the findings advance basic scientific knowledge in criminology and psychology by linking two separate theoretical frameworks together to understand when and why adolescents may engage in risky and illegal behaviors. This study&rsquo;s findings illuminate pathways for future policy development and reform, such as determining whether widespread intervention with parents or changing youths&rsquo; perceptions regarding their peers&rsquo; attitudes and behaviors is needed to assist youth in managing registration and notification risk.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/02/2024<br> Modified by: Cynthia&nbsp;J&nbsp;Najdowski</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Despite controversy over whether even adults should be required to register as sex offenders, most states have some form of policy requiring adolescents adjudicated or convicted of sexual offenses to register with local law enforcement agencies upon completing their sentences. Moreover, most states allow or require online community notification of adolescents who committed sexual offenses, posting information on public websites or registries to inform residents about the young offenders living in their communities. Registration and notification policies are partly rooted in deterrence theorythe idea that the threat of severe punishment will prevent potential sexual offenders from committing these acts in the first place. However, past research had indicated that many adolescents are not aware of the risk of registration and notification posed by their sexual behavior. Moreover, even if they are aware, psychological science suggests that their developmental immaturity may override that knowledge and result in offending anyway.    The Sexual Awareness and Viewpoints of Virginia Youth (SAVVY) Study was an interdisciplinary project that investigated whether registration and notification policies deterred adolescents from engaging in criminalized sexual behaviors, with a particular interest in behaviors that are common in their age group. A total of 339 Virginia adolescents aged 14-17 years old completed two 30-minute online surveys, administered approximately nine months apart. The surveys included questions about youths sexual attitudes, behaviors, and legal knowledge. In addition, some youth were exposed to an educational intervention designed to enhance their legal knowledge. The goal of this research was to gather information that can be used to inform state and federal policy, legal system interactions with youth, and teen education and intervention programs.    The studys findings demonstrated that many adolescents lacked awareness of juvenile sex offender registration and notification policies. Furthermore, the data collected revealed no significant differences in self-reported sexual offending behaviors based on youths knowledge of registration policies, suggesting these policies do not act as deterrents to reduce such behaviors. Indeed, illegal sexual behaviors were common in our sample, with 28% of adolescents reporting they had engaged in illegal sexual behaviors in the year preceding the initial study as well as in the nine months between the two survey administrations. Although an educational intervention administered through the first survey was effective at increasing youths legal knowledge over time, it did not reduce their likelihood of engaging in illegal sexual behaviors in the nine months following the intervention. The results speak to the discipline of criminology, supporting the premise within Robinson and Darleys (2004) general deterrence framework that merely being aware of a legal consequence is not sufficient to deter individuals from engaging in risky behavior.    To examine why this might be the case, analyses also examined the role of psychosocial maturity constructs derived from Steinberg and Cauffmans (1996) developmental theory. Results showed that neither impulse control, future orientation, resistance to peer influence, perceptions of sanction certainty, nor risk ambiguity related to the frequency with which adolescents had engaged in registerable sexual behaviors. Instead, adolescents behaviors were driven by their beliefs about positive peer expectations and their perceptions of how prevalent the illegal sexual behaviors under study were among their peers.    Juvenile sex offender registration and notification policies have become more restrictive and more frequently applied to adolescent offenders, so a main objective of this project was to understand whether the policies actually deter youth from sexual offending. Findings suggest that juvenile sex offender registration and notification policies are not successfully deterring adolescents from engaging in registerable offenses. The results from this interdisciplinary research can be used to inform policymaking on this heavily contested issue. Moreover, the findings advance basic scientific knowledge in criminology and psychology by linking two separate theoretical frameworks together to understand when and why adolescents may engage in risky and illegal behaviors. This studys findings illuminate pathways for future policy development and reform, such as determining whether widespread intervention with parents or changing youths perceptions regarding their peers attitudes and behaviors is needed to assist youth in managing registration and notification risk.     Last Modified: 12/02/2024       Submitted by: CynthiaJNajdowski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
