<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: The expression of temporal-modal semantics in an endangered language]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6673.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6673</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rachel M. Theodore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rtheodor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924770</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Whenever we speak, we communicate complex temporal-modal information about the events and situations we are describing: Did this event occur in the past, or will it occur in the future? Is it a hypothetical event, a guaranteed event, or something that truly happened? The goal of this dissertation project is to enhance our understanding of how speakers express temporal-modal semantics, and how they manage this information within a discourse. The co-PI will create new language infrastructure for an endangered and underdocumented language; using this documentation, the co-PI will analyze the expression of temporal-modal semantics in the language. Thorough descriptions of temporal-modal systems in the world's languages help linguists analyze global variation and grammatical change, and this in turn can illuminate underlying cognitive structures. Furthermore, the language infrastructure created by this project can serve as the basis for future research in other areas of linguistics. This project incorporates research training for both US undergraduate students and indigenous language speakers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Following established methods for language documentation and semantic fieldwork, the co-PI will record naturalistic speech in the target language, including conversation, narratives, and procedural discourse. The recordings will be transcribed, translated, and analyzed in consultation with native speakers. This corpus of naturalistic speech will be supplemented by elicited speech, structured experiments, and previously-existing documentation from social media. Data from related languages will allow for a comparative perspective on the temporal-modal system. The dissertation will contribute to the typological study of temporal-modal semantics: the language has primarily aspectual TAM categories, and so this research furthers our understanding of how tense and modality are communicated in an aspect-based system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019441</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Woodbury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony C Woodbury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[acw@mail.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000155087</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>May</FirstName>
<LastName>Plumb</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>May H Plumb</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mayhplumb@utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000807450</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 INNER CAMPUS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 W Braker Lane, Suite 3340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>123Y00</Code>
<Text>DLI DDRIG-DynLangInfrast DDRIG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~6673</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Normal tm5">Whenever we speak, we communicate complex temporal-modal information about the events and situations we are describing: Did this event occur in the past, or will it occur in the future? Is it a hypothetical event, a promised event, or something that truly happened? This dissertation project investigated the grammar of temporal-modal semantics by means of a descriptive case study on Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, a language spoken in southern Mexico.</p> <p class="Normal tm5">Descriptions of this type help linguists analyze global variation and grammatical change, and this in turn can illuminate underlying cognitive structures. Zapotec languages are primarily aspectual, that is they focus on the &ldquo;shape&rdquo; or &ldquo;structure&rdquo; of events rather than on the temporal location of an event in the past or present. However, the workings of this system have not been robustly studied by linguists. This project thus furthered our understanding of how temporal information is communicated in a aspect-focus system.</p> <p class="Normal tm5">A secondary outcome of the project is the language infrastructure realized by the co-PI&rsquo;s research records. The project used established methods for language documentation and semantic fieldwork to probe the grammar of Tlacochahuaya Zapotec through structured experiments with native speakers and analysis of natural speech, such as storytelling. Recordings of research activities were placed in a publicly accessible digital reposition (The Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin America), which can serve as a basis for future research in other areas of linguistics.</p> <!-- .Normal { margin:1.0pt; margin-top:1.0pt; margin-bottom:1.0pt; margin-left:0.0pt; margin-right:0.0pt; text-indent:0.0pt; font-family:"Basic Roman"; font-size:10.0pt; color:Black; font-weight:normal; border:none; }h1 { margin:1.0pt; margin-top:12.0pt; margin-bottom:3.0pt; margin-left:0.0pt; margin-right:0.0pt; text-indent:0.0pt; font-family:"Basic Sans"; font-size:18.0pt; color:Black; font-weight:bold; border:none; }h2 { margin:1.0pt; margin-top:12.0pt; margin-bottom:3.0pt; margin-left:0.0pt; margin-right:0.0pt; text-indent:0.0pt; font-family:"Basic Sans"; font-size:16.0pt; color:Black; font-weight:bold; border:none; }h3 { margin:1.0pt; margin-top:12.0pt; margin-bottom:3.0pt; margin-left:0.0pt; margin-right:0.0pt; text-indent:0.0pt; font-family:"Basic Sans"; font-size:14.0pt; color:Black; font-weight:bold; border:none; }.PageBreak { page-break-after:always; }.tm5 { border:none; } --><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/13/2024<br> Modified by: Anthony&nbsp;C&nbsp;Woodbury</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Whenever we speak, we communicate complex temporal-modal information about the events and situations we are describing: Did this event occur in the past, or will it occur in the future? Is it a hypothetical event, a promised event, or something that truly happened? This dissertation project investigated the grammar of temporal-modal semantics by means of a descriptive case study on Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, a language spoken in southern Mexico.   Descriptions of this type help linguists analyze global variation and grammatical change, and this in turn can illuminate underlying cognitive structures. Zapotec languages are primarily aspectual, that is they focus on the shape or structure of events rather than on the temporal location of an event in the past or present. However, the workings of this system have not been robustly studied by linguists. This project thus furthered our understanding of how temporal information is communicated in a aspect-focus system.   A secondary outcome of the project is the language infrastructure realized by the co-PIs research records. The project used established methods for language documentation and semantic fieldwork to probe the grammar of Tlacochahuaya Zapotec through structured experiments with native speakers and analysis of natural speech, such as storytelling. Recordings of research activities were placed in a publicly accessible digital reposition (The Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin America), which can serve as a basis for future research in other areas of linguistics.      Last Modified: 11/13/2024       Submitted by: AnthonyCWoodbury]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
