<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Using Complex Problem Based Learning in Undergraduate Engineering Classrooms to Prepare Creative Engineers with the Skills to Solve Global Problems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abby Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ailumoka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922703</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest by improving undergraduate engineering education.  Specifically, it will create a new teaching approach called Complex Problem Based Learning and use it in undergraduate civil engineering courses.  The approach is designed to enhance students' ability to solve transdisciplinary, complex problems.  Such problems often have a global scope and can only be solved through the work of collaborative teams that include scientists, engineers, social scientists, humanities experts, and others. The ability to tackle such complex, global problems is important in today’s workplace.  As a result, engineering graduates need both disciplinary knowledge and skills such as creativity, design thinking, trans-disciplinary teamwork skills, and the ability to communicate with non-technical stakeholders. The goal of the project is to use the Complex Problem Based Learning approach to provide multiple opportunities for civil engineering students to develop and practice these skills. This goal is well aligned with the National Academy of Engineering’s vision for engineering (The Engineer of 2020), which encourages recognition of the leadership role engineers will have in industry, government, and the non-profit sectors of the future economy.  The project will also contribute new knowledge about engineering education by investigating the impact of this Complex Problem Based Learning approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Complex Problem Based Learning approach will be implemented in five engineering design courses ranging from freshman to senior year, enabling its impact to be evaluated across a range of student proficiency levels. Through this approach, students will be guided through a facilitated problem-solving process built around consensus, problem driven research, and stakeholder-driven problems. Multiple sources of data will be collected to evaluate the success of the Complex Problem Based Learning approach.  Data from student self-assessments will be collected via survey tools. The CATME platform hosted by Purdue will be used to collect student self-assessments of teams and participatory decision-making. A factorial experimental design methodology will be used to investigate impacts of Complex Problem Based Learning on civil engineering education and outcomes. The assessments of creativity will focus on both the person and the product, and evaluate whether there is a strong correlation between the two. The Kaufman Domains of Creativity Scale instrument will be used for self-assessment of personal creativity and the Consensual Assessment Technique will be used for assessment of the product’s creativity. The broader impact of this award includes the development of the Complex Problem Based Learning approach, which might be used for education of students at any age and in any STEM discipline.  By fostering creative mindsets and creative problem-solving skills, this approach can help develop a creative and reflective STEM workforce that can thrive in the future of increased automation. The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021135</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Surovek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea E Surovek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[surovek@sdsmt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000294282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bret</FirstName>
<LastName>Lingwall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bret N Lingwall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Bret.Lingwall@sdsmt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000701387</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[South Dakota School of Mines and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>RAPID CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>577013901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6053941218</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[501 E SAINT JOSEPH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CJAJYT2KW771</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH DAKOTA SCHOOL OF MINES &amp; TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>CJAJYT2KW771</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[South Dakota School of Mines and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this award we focus on the critical engineering practice skills of creativity, design thinking and working in convergent teams. Our proposed solution to the formation of engineers addresses all three of these practice skills directly wherein the Design Thinking Double Diamond and the Participatory Decision-Making Diamond proposed by Kaner are integrated into a single framework.&nbsp;To compete in the AI driven changing marketplace, the engineer must do what automation cannot: convergently work across boundaries, be creative and communicate effectively with diverse teams audiences. Meanwhile, engineering design problems are becoming increasing complex. Complex problems (transcending <span style="text-decoration: underline;">complicated</span>) are those that cannot be arrived at through traditional linear modes of problem solving and require the human dimension to be central to the problem-solving approach. In this award we focus on the critical engineering practice skills of creativity, design thinking and working in convergent teams.&nbsp;</p> <p><span>intellectual merit of this award focues on formation of engineers and improving undergraduate STEM education.&nbsp;</span>The merit of this award is to provide the field of Civil Engineering a means to retrain themselves and the coming generations of engineers with a set of skills and mentalities to push boundaries in creative ways that embrace complexity and stakeholder driving research. The approach posed in this award is an innovative and novel tool to do this. However, Civil is not the only field in which the approach will yield dividends. Researchers and experts have proposed many means and methods to build the skills described in this award, but the unique framework of this award builds them all simultaneously. This award is meritorious and novel in other ways, as this research into the formation of engineers includes an expert in psychology and creative pedagogies, who helps the engineering faculty navigate the complex nature of the developing human mind. In recent years, the concepts of team creativity and working in interdisciplinary teams have received much attention. While theories and propositions abound, actual empirical evidence on interventions is limited. This project will allow us to improve knowledge in this area, understand team functioning and cognitive functioning across a variety of levels of knowledge, in teams that are engaged outside the laboratory.&nbsp;</p> <p><span> Broader of impacts of this award&nbsp;addresses an NAE need, The engineer of 2040. As stated in the introductory remarks of this proposal, there are urgent societal needs, engineering, workforce needs, and educational needs that challenge including but not limited to changes to engineering from automated design and complexity. The Societal Impacts of the award are: development creative/inclusive/diverse/collaborative members of society, forming engineers that are equipped to tackle complex problems, continuing education outreach to practicing professional engineers, and STEM outreach to middle school and high school students. The Engineering workforce impact of this award is an engineering formation tool that can be used at any age or experience level in any discipline of engineering. A tool that transfers to other design disciplines outside of engineering. Educational Impacts of the award include: an exchange of pedagogical techniques and method between engineering and medicine. The outreach to practicing engineers introduces them to Design Thinking, Participatory Stakeholder-Driven Decision-Making, and how-to de-silo in the workplace, while simultaneously spreading innovation and raising the bar of the workforce. This award is a vital step to developing a creative and reflective STEM workforce that can thrive in the coming age of automated engineering. Instilling creativity and reflection in a K-16-Professional framework is intended to be an innovation incubator for US international competitiveness</span></p> <p><span>The outcomes of this award is that o</span>ur work has shown that design fixity is a persistent problem in both engineering students and engineering practitioners (and faculty). Design fixity is a shortcoming that can be resolved by critical thinking tools and by being mindful of creative problem solving processes. Our significant impact to the profession is the identification of solutions to design fixity and increasing creativity in engineering products as a function of improved and more creative processes. This applies to both students and practitioners. The CASPER rubric is an ideal tool that we are showing can be used to guide problem solving processes in individuals and in teams. In September of 2023, the PI was able to use interim results of this research for a training and professional development seminars with professional engineers. Attendees received PDH credits of 1 hour for attending the lecture. This hour long workshop was attended by over 250 professional engineers. It was very well recieved. These professional engineers were most impressed by the CASPER rubric and the emphasis on avoiding design fixity. The rubric, developed by previous research, was the key instrument in helping more than 400 undergraduate students and 120 graduate students receive measurable training in these critical practice skills and creativity especially. This was implemented in problem and project based settings, including a freshmen laboratory AquaDucks project.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/20/2024<br> Modified by: Bret&nbsp;N&nbsp;Lingwall</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2021135/2021135_10694871_1726861606589_AquaDuck_Project_Example--rgov-214x142.JPG" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2021135/2021135_10694871_1726861606589_AquaDuck_Project_Example--rgov-800width.JPG" title="AquaDuck Project Example"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2021135/2021135_10694871_1726861606589_AquaDuck_Project_Example--rgov-66x44.JPG" alt="AquaDuck Project Example"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An example of a Freshmen Design AquaDuck project</div> <div class="imageCredit">Bret Lingwall</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bret&nbsp;N&nbsp;Lingwall <div class="imageTitle">AquaDuck Project Example</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  In this award we focus on the critical engineering practice skills of creativity, design thinking and working in convergent teams. Our proposed solution to the formation of engineers addresses all three of these practice skills directly wherein the Design Thinking Double Diamond and the Participatory Decision-Making Diamond proposed by Kaner are integrated into a single framework.To compete in the AI driven changing marketplace, the engineer must do what automation cannot: convergently work across boundaries, be creative and communicate effectively with diverse teams audiences. Meanwhile, engineering design problems are becoming increasing complex. Complex problems (transcending complicated) are those that cannot be arrived at through traditional linear modes of problem solving and require the human dimension to be central to the problem-solving approach. In this award we focus on the critical engineering practice skills of creativity, design thinking and working in convergent teams.   intellectual merit of this award focues on formation of engineers and improving undergraduate STEM education.The merit of this award is to provide the field of Civil Engineering a means to retrain themselves and the coming generations of engineers with a set of skills and mentalities to push boundaries in creative ways that embrace complexity and stakeholder driving research. The approach posed in this award is an innovative and novel tool to do this. However, Civil is not the only field in which the approach will yield dividends. Researchers and experts have proposed many means and methods to build the skills described in this award, but the unique framework of this award builds them all simultaneously. This award is meritorious and novel in other ways, as this research into the formation of engineers includes an expert in psychology and creative pedagogies, who helps the engineering faculty navigate the complex nature of the developing human mind. In recent years, the concepts of team creativity and working in interdisciplinary teams have received much attention. While theories and propositions abound, actual empirical evidence on interventions is limited. This project will allow us to improve knowledge in this area, understand team functioning and cognitive functioning across a variety of levels of knowledge, in teams that are engaged outside the laboratory.    Broader of impacts of this awardaddresses an NAE need, The engineer of 2040. As stated in the introductory remarks of this proposal, there are urgent societal needs, engineering, workforce needs, and educational needs that challenge including but not limited to changes to engineering from automated design and complexity. The Societal Impacts of the award are: development creative/inclusive/diverse/collaborative members of society, forming engineers that are equipped to tackle complex problems, continuing education outreach to practicing professional engineers, and STEM outreach to middle school and high school students. The Engineering workforce impact of this award is an engineering formation tool that can be used at any age or experience level in any discipline of engineering. A tool that transfers to other design disciplines outside of engineering. Educational Impacts of the award include: an exchange of pedagogical techniques and method between engineering and medicine. The outreach to practicing engineers introduces them to Design Thinking, Participatory Stakeholder-Driven Decision-Making, and how-to de-silo in the workplace, while simultaneously spreading innovation and raising the bar of the workforce. This award is a vital step to developing a creative and reflective STEM workforce that can thrive in the coming age of automated engineering. Instilling creativity and reflection in a K-16-Professional framework is intended to be an innovation incubator for US international competitiveness   The outcomes of this award is that our work has shown that design fixity is a persistent problem in both engineering students and engineering practitioners (and faculty). Design fixity is a shortcoming that can be resolved by critical thinking tools and by being mindful of creative problem solving processes. Our significant impact to the profession is the identification of solutions to design fixity and increasing creativity in engineering products as a function of improved and more creative processes. This applies to both students and practitioners. The CASPER rubric is an ideal tool that we are showing can be used to guide problem solving processes in individuals and in teams. In September of 2023, the PI was able to use interim results of this research for a training and professional development seminars with professional engineers. Attendees received PDH credits of 1 hour for attending the lecture. This hour long workshop was attended by over 250 professional engineers. It was very well recieved. These professional engineers were most impressed by the CASPER rubric and the emphasis on avoiding design fixity. The rubric, developed by previous research, was the key instrument in helping more than 400 undergraduate students and 120 graduate students receive measurable training in these critical practice skills and creativity especially. This was implemented in problem and project based settings, including a freshmen laboratory AquaDucks project.     Last Modified: 09/20/2024       Submitted by: BretNLingwall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
