<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Building Capacity to Improve STEM Education through Citizen Science by Scaling Up University-Community Partnerships]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>262661.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>262661</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kimberly Tanner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ktanner@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922262</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest by enhancing STEM education outcomes for all students, including women and underrepresented minorities. Research suggests that increased persistence in STEM fields could be achieved by better connecting STEM content to broader issues in students’ communities. A feasible way to make these connections is through citizen science.  Citizen science projects create opportunities for anyone to participate in collecting and analyzing data to support a scientific project.  Such projects have the potential to link scientific content and process to real world problems that are relevant to students’ communities.  Furthermore, these projects require students to engage in active learning, which is also known to improve student learning outcomes in STEM fields. This project is a collaboration between North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University and North Carolina State University.  It is designed to lay the foundation for establishing University-community partnerships to establish citizen science communities that connect undergraduate STEM learning to underserved communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Capacity building efforts focus on three domains: 1) needs assessment for scaling up the project; 2) knowledge and relationship building; and 3) information technology infrastructure. Capacity building efforts will target barriers and identify bridges needed at social, organizational, and individual levels. This change effort will focus on further developing inclusive learning environments.  Specifically the project aims to enable undergraduates to more highly value their educational experiences through increased awareness of the relationship between STEM course content (i.e., knowledge, skills, and perspectives) and the issues impacting underserved communities.  The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students.  Through the Institutional and Community Transformation track, the program supports efforts to transform and improve STEM education across institutions of higher education and disciplinary communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021481</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aklee1@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000710313</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tobin</FirstName>
<LastName>Walton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tobin N Walton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tnwalton@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Parker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon D Parker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sdparke3@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811887</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrienne</FirstName>
<LastName>Morgan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrienne A Morgan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adrienne_aikenmorgan@med.unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000770970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Teixeira-Poit</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie M Teixeira-Poit</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[steixeirapoit@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788293</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina Agricultural & Technical State University]]></Name>
<CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
<ZipCode>274110002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1601 E MARKET ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SKH5GMBR9GL3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA AGRICULTURAL AND TECHNICAL STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1601 East Market Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~262661</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>University courses in Science Technology Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) fields such as Sociology, Psychology, Biology, and Engineering are often very challenging for students. This is true for the most capable students, and it is especially true for students who have been historically underrepresented in these fields such as African Americans, Women, and others. The challenges students face in STEM courses derives not only from the rigor and complexity of the material, but also from broader issues that are grounded in the experiences students have both in and outside of the classroom as individuals in society. For instance, students not only come to STEM courses with varying levels of academic capability, but also, with different values, beliefs, identities, and &nbsp;communities of belonging. This results in many students feeling alienated by the rigorous and complex content within STEM courses. Course content can appear as though it is not directly connected to who students are as individuals, where they come from, and where they see themselves in the future. This rich diversity among students thus presents significant challenges to instructors of STEM courses as they work to improve all students&rsquo; learning of the course content.</p> <p>This project sought to address these challenges head-on by building the capacity of faculty within a large public Historically Black University to incorporate Citizen Science into their courses.&nbsp; Citizen Science is a form of Participatory Science that engages the public in the scientific process. The extent to which the public gets involved varies across the thousands of existing projects and approaches to Citizen Science. In some instances, the public may be involved by merely contributing observations in a crowd-sourced effort to gather information for a scientific project.&nbsp; Members of the public may also be more deeply involved and work directly with researchers to identify research questions, gather and analyze data, and disseminate results. In this way, citizen science can demystify the scientific process (and its outcomes) by directly connecting with people and communities. In the same way then, using citizen science to help deliver rigorous and complex course content, offers a way for students to experience and learn course material in a hands-on way that directly connects to the real world and their place in it.</p> <p>Over the course of this 3-year National Science Foundation funded project, citizen science learning modules were incorporated into nearly 30 sections of 11 different courses which contained a combined 500 students across diverse disciplines such as Sociology, Psychology, Biology, Biomedical Engineering, Mathematics, and Education. Faculty who incorporated these citizen science learning modules into their courses invited students to complete an online exit survey assessing their experience. Results of the survey are very encouraging.&nbsp; For instance, most students strongly or somewhat agreed that completing the citizen science learning module in their course <em>provided knowledge</em> <em>and skills</em> that will improve their ability to succeed in their chosen major (62% and 64% respectively). &nbsp;Furthermore, most students strongly or somewhat agreed that completing the citizen science learning module in their course improved their <em>attitude</em> toward science (73%) and <em>ability</em> to do science (70%), helped them <em>better understand</em> the scientific process (80%), and helped improve their <em>ability</em> to understand and interpret scientific information (78%).&nbsp; As one faculty member reflected, &ldquo;When students have real-world experiences like these citizen science projects, it can help to incorporate lessons into memory.&rdquo;</p> <p>In sum, this project and its results demonstrate that innovative approaches to teaching can have positive impacts on student learning, even when the course content is highly rigorous and complex.&nbsp; In particular, we believe that giving students hands-on experiences that directly connect course content to the real world and their place in it can enhance student learning in a way that is inclusive of today&rsquo;s diverse university classroom.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 05/02/2024<br> Modified by: Tobin&nbsp;N&nbsp;Walton</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  University courses in Science Technology Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) fields such as Sociology, Psychology, Biology, and Engineering are often very challenging for students. This is true for the most capable students, and it is especially true for students who have been historically underrepresented in these fields such as African Americans, Women, and others. The challenges students face in STEM courses derives not only from the rigor and complexity of the material, but also from broader issues that are grounded in the experiences students have both in and outside of the classroom as individuals in society. For instance, students not only come to STEM courses with varying levels of academic capability, but also, with different values, beliefs, identities, and communities of belonging. This results in many students feeling alienated by the rigorous and complex content within STEM courses. Course content can appear as though it is not directly connected to who students are as individuals, where they come from, and where they see themselves in the future. This rich diversity among students thus presents significant challenges to instructors of STEM courses as they work to improve all students learning of the course content.   This project sought to address these challenges head-on by building the capacity of faculty within a large public Historically Black University to incorporate Citizen Science into their courses. Citizen Science is a form of Participatory Science that engages the public in the scientific process. The extent to which the public gets involved varies across the thousands of existing projects and approaches to Citizen Science. In some instances, the public may be involved by merely contributing observations in a crowd-sourced effort to gather information for a scientific project. Members of the public may also be more deeply involved and work directly with researchers to identify research questions, gather and analyze data, and disseminate results. In this way, citizen science can demystify the scientific process (and its outcomes) by directly connecting with people and communities. In the same way then, using citizen science to help deliver rigorous and complex course content, offers a way for students to experience and learn course material in a hands-on way that directly connects to the real world and their place in it.   Over the course of this 3-year National Science Foundation funded project, citizen science learning modules were incorporated into nearly 30 sections of 11 different courses which contained a combined 500 students across diverse disciplines such as Sociology, Psychology, Biology, Biomedical Engineering, Mathematics, and Education. Faculty who incorporated these citizen science learning modules into their courses invited students to complete an online exit survey assessing their experience. Results of the survey are very encouraging. For instance, most students strongly or somewhat agreed that completing the citizen science learning module in their course provided knowledge and skills that will improve their ability to succeed in their chosen major (62% and 64% respectively). Furthermore, most students strongly or somewhat agreed that completing the citizen science learning module in their course improved their attitude toward science (73%) and ability to do science (70%), helped them better understand the scientific process (80%), and helped improve their ability to understand and interpret scientific information (78%). As one faculty member reflected, When students have real-world experiences like these citizen science projects, it can help to incorporate lessons into memory.   In sum, this project and its results demonstrate that innovative approaches to teaching can have positive impacts on student learning, even when the course content is highly rigorous and complex. In particular, we believe that giving students hands-on experiences that directly connect course content to the real world and their place in it can enhance student learning in a way that is inclusive of todays diverse university classroom.        Last Modified: 05/02/2024       Submitted by: TobinNWalton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
