<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Service Learning Projects to Improve Engineering Students' Civic Engagement and Capacity for Innovation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kcrosby@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922124</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest by improving engineering students’ learning.  To do so, it will engage students in an interdisciplinary engineering service-learning model focused on civic engagement. The project will seek to develop students’ capacity for innovation while they use their engineering skills and knowledge to decrease suffering, marginalization, or exclusion of particular groups. Many engineering programs emphasize the economic opportunities that engineering degrees will open to graduates, such as working for the private sector.  However, engineering students are increasingly interested in ways to use their engineering education to pursue careers in which they can see the human impact of their work. The premise of this project is that opportunities for civic engagement can improve student engagement in engineering education.  These opportunities require students to learn new approaches and skills that are not typically taught in the engineering curriculum, such as human centered design and problem solving with empathy. By helping students develop these skills, students will be better positioned to use their engineering knowledge in the future to benefit society. The project will test the hypothesis that mentoring, oriented towards civic engagement and addressing societal challenges, will enhance the engagement of undergraduate engineering students in STEM learning. This project expects to enhance students’ learning experiences and provide opportunities to strengthen communities, while simultaneously encouraging students’ development of civic responsibility.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the goal of improving engineering education through the cultivation of innovative civic engagement, this project will:  (i) develop, implement, and evaluate a pedagogical intervention that engages students in service learning projects; (ii) assess the effectiveness of the intervention in supporting student learning with respect to engagement in their engineering program and capacity for innovation; and (iii) refine a theoretical model of how the intervention helps students develop civic responsibility. This project will contribute to constructs of learning by combining theories on social learning into an “engagement by innovation and situated cognition” theory. The intervention will include two one-credit seminar courses designed to promote students’ innovation and civic engagement. The courses will use case-based learning based on cases drawn from local studies in the DC-metro region. Students will learn problem-solving based on principles of systems thinking, human-centered design, and ethnographic field research. In this study, quantitative and qualitative data will be collected through regular surveys, interviews, and video diaries to assess student engagement, development of civic responsibility, and capacity for innovation. The service-learning projects will benefit the region by generating engineering solutions that address community challenges. The problem-solving experiences will help prepare engineering students for success in the engineering workforce. The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021317</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ekundayo</FirstName>
<LastName>Shittu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ekundayo Shittu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eshittu@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000559450</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tiffany-Rose</FirstName>
<LastName>Sikorski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tiffany-Rose Sikorski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tsikorski@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000643253</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erica</FirstName>
<LastName>Wortham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erica C Wortham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ewortham@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000797183</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1918 F ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 22nd St.,]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Accomplishments</strong></p>  <p>Project Goals and Objectives</p>  <p>The primary objective of this project was to create and implement an innovative interdisciplinary engineering service-learning model that promotes student engagement through social innovation. The project sought to identify and employ pedagogical approaches that integrate service learning with human-centered design in an interdisciplinary framework. The overarching goals included enhancing the learning experience, fostering civic responsibility, and equipping engineering students with the capacity for addressing societal challenges through innovative solutions.</p>  <p>The specific objectives were:</p>  <ol>  <li>  <p>Develop, implement, and evaluate a pedagogical intervention that successfully engages students in social innovation.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Assess the effectiveness of this intervention in fostering student engagement in their engineering program and enhancing their capacity for social innovation.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Refine a theoretical model to explain how the intervention supports student engagement and capacity for social innovation.</p>  </li>  </ol>  <p><strong>Major Activities</strong></p>  <p>Objective 1: Development, Implementation, and Evaluation</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>The curriculum materials for Social Innovation II were evaluated and updated based on feedback from participants, evaluators, and instructor notes.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>A complete syllabus, slide decks, assignments, and associated materials were developed for Social Innovation II.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>The Social Innovation II course was successfully run in Fall 2022 for the second cohort of participants. The timing adjustment accommodated participants&rsquo; study-abroad schedules and a faculty sabbatical.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p>Objective 2: Effectiveness Assessment</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Surveys, application responses, and vlog data were analyzed to gauge students' knowledge and capacity for social innovation.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Results were disseminated at two NSF-sponsored sessions at the 2023 ASEE conference.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>One peer-reviewed paper was accepted for the FIE conference, while another manuscript was submitted to JEE for review.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p>Objective 3: Refinement of Theoretical Model</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>The "Becoming an Engineer" framework (Stevens et al., 2013) was applied to analyze data, focusing on students' perceptions of social innovation as a core competency in engineering. Findings are under review for a prominent education research conference.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Significant Results</strong></p>  <ol>  <li>  <p>The intervention effectively highlighted the importance of community connections and partnerships in professional engineering.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Students recognized the need for engineers to:</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Address societal issues causing marginalization.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Collaborate with marginalized communities to design solutions.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Understand the policy implications of their work.</p>  </li>  </ul>  </li>  <li>  <p>The deployment of the Engineering Professional Responsibility Assessment (EPRA) revealed increased appreciation for societal context among participants, with professional ethics, cultural awareness, and technical skills being rated as essential to engineering.</p>  </li>  </ol>  <p><strong>Key Outcomes</strong></p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Enhanced student perception of their role in addressing societal challenges through engineering.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Development of Accountable Disciplinary Knowledge (ADK), with students increasingly valuing societal and cultural awareness.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Significant improvements in students&rsquo; capacity for social innovation as evidenced by survey and vlog data.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Opportunities for Training and Professional Development</strong></p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Graduate research assistants received training in qualitative data analysis, literature review, and AI-driven Natural Language Processing (NLP).</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>A graduate student employed NLP methods for vlog data analysis, culminating in a paper titled &ldquo;Analysis of Vlog Transcripts using Topic Modeling, Summarizer, and Cluster Analysis,&rdquo; which is now published in a proceedings of the IEEE FIE conference.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Dissemination of Results</strong></p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>2022: Findings were shared at the National Association for Research in Science Teaching (NARST) conference and the STEM Video Showcase.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>2023: Results were included in two manuscripts, one accepted for the IEEE FIE proceedings and another under second round of reviews at IJEE.&nbsp;</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Next Steps&nbsp;</strong></p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Develop a large-scale proposal for expanding this program across multiple STEM-focused departments.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Impacts</strong></p>  <p>Disciplinary Development</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Extended research applications to new domains, including collaboration on a KEEN-funded project emphasizing entrepreneurial mindsets in engineering.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>PIs engaged in broader research initiatives, with one becoming a KEEN network Fellow.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p>Human Resources Development</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Students demonstrated increased interest in using engineering knowledge to address societal challenges, with some pursuing related employment and research opportunities.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>One student collaborated on the "Medicine, Equity, and Technology (MET)" program, addressing health inequities and the role of AI in medicine.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p>Teaching and Educational Experiences</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Highlighted the value of interdisciplinary engagement, such as storytelling, in fostering deeper learning and student engagement beyond traditional engineering curricula.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p>Institutional Challenges</p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Scalability remains a key challenge due to institutional hurdles, including curriculum integration and scheduling conflicts.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Partnerships and Collaborations</strong></p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>Rock Creek Conservancy: Students addressed stormwater overflow issues and proposed green infrastructure solutions for the community.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>Food Research &amp; Action Center (FRAC): A guest speaker highlighted innovations in anti-hunger efforts and their societal impacts.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>ArtReach GW: Students incorporated STEM learning into an art-based afterschool program.</p>  </li>  <li>  <p>GW Office of Diversity and Inclusion: Students tackled issues of discrimination within the engineering school, proposing strategies for fostering inclusivity.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Changes and Challenges</strong></p>  <ul>  <li>  <p>The second seminar course&rsquo;s schedule was adjusted to accommodate faculty sabbaticals and student study-abroad plans, with no adverse effects on the program.</p>  </li>  </ul>  <p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>  <p>This project successfully developed an interdisciplinary engineering service-learning model that fosters student engagement and enhances their capacity for social innovation. The outcomes demonstrate the potential for such pedagogical interventions to prepare engineering students as socially responsible innovators. Continued efforts will focus on scaling the program and further refining the theoretical model.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/31/2024<br> Modified by: Ekundayo&nbsp;Shittu</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Accomplishments    Project Goals and Objectives    The primary objective of this project was to create and implement an innovative interdisciplinary engineering service-learning model that promotes student engagement through social innovation. The project sought to identify and employ pedagogical approaches that integrate service learning with human-centered design in an interdisciplinary framework. The overarching goals included enhancing the learning experience, fostering civic responsibility, and equipping engineering students with the capacity for addressing societal challenges through innovative solutions.    The specific objectives were:        Develop, implement, and evaluate a pedagogical intervention that successfully engages students in social innovation.        Assess the effectiveness of this intervention in fostering student engagement in their engineering program and enhancing their capacity for social innovation.        Refine a theoretical model to explain how the intervention supports student engagement and capacity for social innovation.        Major Activities    Objective 1: Development, Implementation, and Evaluation        The curriculum materials for Social Innovation II were evaluated and updated based on feedback from participants, evaluators, and instructor notes.        A complete syllabus, slide decks, assignments, and associated materials were developed for Social Innovation II.        The Social Innovation II course was successfully run in Fall 2022 for the second cohort of participants. The timing adjustment accommodated participants study-abroad schedules and a faculty sabbatical.        Objective 2: Effectiveness Assessment        Surveys, application responses, and vlog data were analyzed to gauge students' knowledge and capacity for social innovation.        Results were disseminated at two NSF-sponsored sessions at the 2023 ASEE conference.        One peer-reviewed paper was accepted for the FIE conference, while another manuscript was submitted to JEE for review.        Objective 3: Refinement of Theoretical Model        The "Becoming an Engineer" framework (Stevens et al., 2013) was applied to analyze data, focusing on students' perceptions of social innovation as a core competency in engineering. Findings are under review for a prominent education research conference.        Significant Results        The intervention effectively highlighted the importance of community connections and partnerships in professional engineering.        Students recognized the need for engineers to:        Address societal issues causing marginalization.        Collaborate with marginalized communities to design solutions.        Understand the policy implications of their work.            The deployment of the Engineering Professional Responsibility Assessment (EPRA) revealed increased appreciation for societal context among participants, with professional ethics, cultural awareness, and technical skills being rated as essential to engineering.        Key Outcomes        Enhanced student perception of their role in addressing societal challenges through engineering.        Development of Accountable Disciplinary Knowledge (ADK), with students increasingly valuing societal and cultural awareness.        Significant improvements in students capacity for social innovation as evidenced by survey and vlog data.        Opportunities for Training and Professional Development        Graduate research assistants received training in qualitative data analysis, literature review, and AI-driven Natural Language Processing (NLP).        A graduate student employed NLP methods for vlog data analysis, culminating in a paper titled Analysis of Vlog Transcripts using Topic Modeling, Summarizer, and Cluster Analysis, which is now published in a proceedings of the IEEE FIE conference.        Dissemination of Results        2022: Findings were shared at the National Association for Research in Science Teaching (NARST) conference and the STEM Video Showcase.        2023: Results were included in two manuscripts, one accepted for the IEEE FIE proceedings and another under second round of reviews at IJEE.        Next Steps        Develop a large-scale proposal for expanding this program across multiple STEM-focused departments.        Impacts    Disciplinary Development        Extended research applications to new domains, including collaboration on a KEEN-funded project emphasizing entrepreneurial mindsets in engineering.        PIs engaged in broader research initiatives, with one becoming a KEEN network Fellow.        Human Resources Development        Students demonstrated increased interest in using engineering knowledge to address societal challenges, with some pursuing related employment and research opportunities.        One student collaborated on the "Medicine, Equity, and Technology (MET)" program, addressing health inequities and the role of AI in medicine.        Teaching and Educational Experiences        Highlighted the value of interdisciplinary engagement, such as storytelling, in fostering deeper learning and student engagement beyond traditional engineering curricula.        Institutional Challenges        Scalability remains a key challenge due to institutional hurdles, including curriculum integration and scheduling conflicts.        Partnerships and Collaborations        Rock Creek Conservancy: Students addressed stormwater overflow issues and proposed green infrastructure solutions for the community.        Food Research & Action Center (FRAC): A guest speaker highlighted innovations in anti-hunger efforts and their societal impacts.        ArtReach GW: Students incorporated STEM learning into an art-based afterschool program.        GW Office of Diversity and Inclusion: Students tackled issues of discrimination within the engineering school, proposing strategies for fostering inclusivity.        Changes and Challenges        The second seminar courses schedule was adjusted to accommodate faculty sabbaticals and student study-abroad plans, with no adverse effects on the program.        Conclusion    This project successfully developed an interdisciplinary engineering service-learning model that fosters student engagement and enhances their capacity for social innovation. The outcomes demonstrate the potential for such pedagogical interventions to prepare engineering students as socially responsible innovators. Continued efforts will focus on scaling the program and further refining the theoretical model.             Last Modified: 12/31/2024       Submitted by: EkundayoShittu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
