<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NNA Track 2: Collaborative Research: Seismic Resilience and Adaptation of Infrastructure and Social Systems to Changing Arctic Environments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>37959.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>37959</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan G Wynn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwynn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924725</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Navigating the New Arctic (NNA) is one of NSF's 10 Big Ideas. NNA projects address convergence scientific challenges in the rapidly changing Arctic. The Arctic research is needed to inform the economy, security and resilience of the Nation, the larger region and the globe. NNA empowers new research partnerships from local to international scales, diversifies the next generation of Arctic researchers, enhances efforts in formal and informal education, and integrates the co-production of knowledge where appropriate. This award fulfills part of that aim by supporting planning activities with clear potential to develop novel, leading edge research ideas and approaches to address NNA goals. It integrates aspects of the natural environment, built environment, and social systems to address important societal challenges at this intersection, and engages internationally and with local and Indigenous communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Alaska experiences thousands of earthquakes every year, including historical major events that have disrupted and severely damaged infrastructure and lifeline networks. Given the accelerating environmental, ecological, and social changes as the Arctic climate warms, including changes in soil properties, it is critical to understand how infrastructure and society respond to seismic events. Seismic assessments of infrastructure, post-earthquake recovery, and future planning must simultaneously consider natural environment, built infrastructure, and social systems. This project addresses an urgent need for Arctic residents to develop strategies to respond to seismic events. Resilient infrastructure linked with social systems is crucial to the state of Alaska and beyond, which will impact the state’s economic competitiveness, national security, and residents’ safety and health. The project engages Indigenous communities through surveys, local tribal conferences, and public forums as an important way to increase public awareness and involvement in the decision-making process. In addition, the project involves education and outreach efforts including graduate student training in interdisciplinary research, curriculum enhancement and communicating with Indigenous communities to build foundations for future collaboration and engagement.&lt;br/&gt;This award funds the development of a diverse and convergent research team, builds technical and community capacity, and enables planning for an integrated cross-disciplinary and well-defined research strategy to address seismic resilience of Arctic infrastructure and social systems influenced by changes in climate. An initial survey from the University of Alaska at Fairbanks (UAF) students, governmental agencies, and industry along with a discussion session at an Alaska Tribal Conference on Environmental Management informs the planned workshop designed to assess the state-of-the-art and practice and determine research needs, challenges, and priorities. An international workshop is being organized where subject experts from different disciplines and perspectives will collectively envision future research needs and action items to enhance seismic resiliency of Arctic at the intersection of natural, built, and social environments. The workshop brings a group of researchers, stakeholders, and decision makers from the U.S., internationally, and from Alaskan Indigenous communities to exchange knowledge, experience, expectations. The project scope engages Arctic residents through town-hall forums in three local communities, which is a necessary step to build the relationships needed for future co-production of knowledge.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022628</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Kholodov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Kholodov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alkholodov@alaska.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000631177</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>FAIRBANKS</CityName>
<ZipCode>997750001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 N TANANA LOOP]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FDLEQSJ8FF63</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALASKA FAIRBANKS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alaska Fairbanks]]></Name>
<CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[West Ridge Research Bldg 008]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>104Y00</Code>
<Text>NNA-Navigating the New Arctic</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~37959</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Arctic change is accelerating environmentally, ecologically, and socially. In order to understand howthese changes interact and how they influence seismic response and consequences, a holisticinvestigation is required that incorporates human impacts, natural system, and built infrastructure. Inorder to protect Arctic infrastructure and environmental systems, and also design new sustainablesystems, scientists and engineers need to deal with the threats facing the infrastructure andcommunities due to natural hazards like earthquakes. This includes resilient systems that considernatural, built, and social environments and adaptation practices that reduce the risks and uncertaintyin dealing with these hazards, while considering the local and global climatic changes.Alaska is one of the most seismically active states in the U.S. with some of the largest historicearthquakes, especially in North America. Seismically induced hazards can impact both naturalenvironments. As the built environment expands worldwide and becomes more interdependent, therisk of earthquake-induced damage becomes harder to evaluate. Thus, an ideal resiliency modelrequires consideration of multiple interdependent variables, including climate variability,infrastructure management and planning, risk assessment and uncertainty measures, disaster responseand mitigation, institutional capacity, and social-economic repercussions. A robust understanding ofcommunity response requires involvement of diverse interest groups with differing priorities,capacities, and social positions.This collaborative planning project formed convergent research team and built technical andcommunity capacity to investigate the resilience of Arctic infrastructure and social systems inresponse to seismic events in light of a changing climate. The project brought together a researchcommunity across disciplines to set the groundwork for future research in seismic resiliency ofArctic systems. The specific outcomes of the project include:- In-depth semi-structured interviews were conducted using a dedicated protocol and array ofquestions to guide interviews. These were performed via videoconference, transcribed, andthematically coded using qualitative data management software. The interviews identifiedmajor challenges and opportunities in addressing Arctic seismic resilience.- A workshop was hosted by the University of New Hampshire in Anchorage, Alaska onSeptember 20-22, 2021, to facilitate convergent discussions and to assess and prioritize theresearch needs and future directions of seismic resilience in the Arctic. The core objectiveswere to (1) foster collaboration among the diverse group of participants; (2) identify, define,and prioritize research needs and ideas; and (3) propose strategies for outreach to Indigenouscommunities and best practices for co-production of knowledge. Live survey questionsthroughout the workshop helped to understand attendees&rsquo; big picture perspectives andprepare participants for insightful discussions and follow-on group activities. Participantswere asked to share their main concerns or priority topics for (a) seismic resilience of Arcticand sub-Arctic built infrastructure and (b) seismic resilience of the Arctic and sub-Arcticsocial systems and whether those are significantly impacted by climate change. Theworkshop identified priority concerns in the seismic resilience of built infrastructure andsocial systems and how climate change will affect these concerns. Participants drafted sixconvergent research ideas to address the highest priority concerns and motivate futureresearch initiatives. More data is available on the workshop website athttps://sites.google.com/view/1st-arctic-seismic-resiliency/home. This workshop broughttogether about 50 participants from different sectors including researchers, policy makers,first responders and disaster recovery planners, industry partners, local and Indigenous<br />community representatives, and other related stakeholders. The participants&rsquo; expertisecovered a wide range of disciplines ranging from earthquake engineers, seismologists,permafrost experts, geo-hydrologists, climate scientists, disaster managers and urbandevelopers, social scientists, risk and uncertainty experts, economists and communitydevelopment professionals. Although most of the attendees were from the United States,researchers from Greenland (Denmark), Iceland, and Japan also participated.- Interaction between local communities and natural and built environments is certainly thekey to the success of convergence research. To address the community&rsquo;s apprehensionsconcerning climate change and the resilience of infrastructure in Alaska, a communityoutreach initiative was undertaken in Copper River Valley, Alaska, on June 1, 2023. Duringthis gathering, participants engaged in various group activities aimed at deliberating theirconcerns and perspectives. The primary focus was on understanding their most critical needsduring emergency (i.e., earthquake) scenarios. Participants were prompted to think about fourkey questions including climate stressors in their locality, seismic events, damages, andworks to be done.- The findings from the workshop and other activities were integrated to identify influentialvariables for seismic infrastructure resilience in the Arctic, considering both engineering andcoupled human-environment perspectives. This knowledge and data were leveraged todevelop a preliminary system dynamics model to simulate seismic resilience processes.- Three PhD students and three undergraduate researchers were involved in this project. Theyreceived mentoring and training, gained knowledge, and engaged in experiences on seismicresiliency and earthquake impacts on civil infrastructure and social systems. The graduatestudents were also involved in publications and dissemination of the research outcome.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 03/05/2024<br> Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;Kholodov</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Arctic change is accelerating environmentally, ecologically, and socially. In order to understand howthese changes interact and how they influence seismic response and consequences, a holisticinvestigation is required that incorporates human impacts, natural system, and built infrastructure. Inorder to protect Arctic infrastructure and environmental systems, and also design new sustainablesystems, scientists and engineers need to deal with the threats facing the infrastructure andcommunities due to natural hazards like earthquakes. This includes resilient systems that considernatural, built, and social environments and adaptation practices that reduce the risks and uncertaintyin dealing with these hazards, while considering the local and global climatic changes.Alaska is one of the most seismically active states in the U.S. with some of the largest historicearthquakes, especially in North America. Seismically induced hazards can impact both naturalenvironments. As the built environment expands worldwide and becomes more interdependent, therisk of earthquake-induced damage becomes harder to evaluate. Thus, an ideal resiliency modelrequires consideration of multiple interdependent variables, including climate variability,infrastructure management and planning, risk assessment and uncertainty measures, disaster responseand mitigation, institutional capacity, and social-economic repercussions. A robust understanding ofcommunity response requires involvement of diverse interest groups with differing priorities,capacities, and social positions.This collaborative planning project formed convergent research team and built technical andcommunity capacity to investigate the resilience of Arctic infrastructure and social systems inresponse to seismic events in light of a changing climate. The project brought together a researchcommunity across disciplines to set the groundwork for future research in seismic resiliency ofArctic systems. The specific outcomes of the project include:- In-depth semi-structured interviews were conducted using a dedicated protocol and array ofquestions to guide interviews. These were performed via videoconference, transcribed, andthematically coded using qualitative data management software. The interviews identifiedmajor challenges and opportunities in addressing Arctic seismic resilience.- A workshop was hosted by the University of New Hampshire in Anchorage, Alaska onSeptember 20-22, 2021, to facilitate convergent discussions and to assess and prioritize theresearch needs and future directions of seismic resilience in the Arctic. The core objectiveswere to (1) foster collaboration among the diverse group of participants; (2) identify, define,and prioritize research needs and ideas; and (3) propose strategies for outreach to Indigenouscommunities and best practices for co-production of knowledge. Live survey questionsthroughout the workshop helped to understand attendees big picture perspectives andprepare participants for insightful discussions and follow-on group activities. Participantswere asked to share their main concerns or priority topics for (a) seismic resilience of Arcticand sub-Arctic built infrastructure and (b) seismic resilience of the Arctic and sub-Arcticsocial systems and whether those are significantly impacted by climate change. Theworkshop identified priority concerns in the seismic resilience of built infrastructure andsocial systems and how climate change will affect these concerns. Participants drafted sixconvergent research ideas to address the highest priority concerns and motivate futureresearch initiatives. More data is available on the workshop website athttps://sites.google.com/view/1st-arctic-seismic-resiliency/home. This workshop broughttogether about 50 participants from different sectors including researchers, policy makers,first responders and disaster recovery planners, industry partners, local and Indigenous community representatives, and other related stakeholders. The participants expertisecovered a wide range of disciplines ranging from earthquake engineers, seismologists,permafrost experts, geo-hydrologists, climate scientists, disaster managers and urbandevelopers, social scientists, risk and uncertainty experts, economists and communitydevelopment professionals. Although most of the attendees were from the United States,researchers from Greenland (Denmark), Iceland, and Japan also participated.- Interaction between local communities and natural and built environments is certainly thekey to the success of convergence research. To address the communitys apprehensionsconcerning climate change and the resilience of infrastructure in Alaska, a communityoutreach initiative was undertaken in Copper River Valley, Alaska, on June 1, 2023. Duringthis gathering, participants engaged in various group activities aimed at deliberating theirconcerns and perspectives. The primary focus was on understanding their most critical needsduring emergency (i.e., earthquake) scenarios. Participants were prompted to think about fourkey questions including climate stressors in their locality, seismic events, damages, andworks to be done.- The findings from the workshop and other activities were integrated to identify influentialvariables for seismic infrastructure resilience in the Arctic, considering both engineering andcoupled human-environment perspectives. This knowledge and data were leveraged todevelop a preliminary system dynamics model to simulate seismic resilience processes.- Three PhD students and three undergraduate researchers were involved in this project. Theyreceived mentoring and training, gained knowledge, and engaged in experiences on seismicresiliency and earthquake impacts on civil infrastructure and social systems. The graduatestudents were also involved in publications and dissemination of the research outcome.     Last Modified: 03/05/2024       Submitted by: AlexanderKholodov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
