<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building Entrepreneurship and Economic Development at EPSCoR's Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99512.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99512</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>andjohns@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925164</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This workshop grant by Alabama Agricultural &amp; Mechanical University and its Center for Entrepreneurship, Innovation and Economic Development is aimed at providing strategies and best practices to enhance research competitiveness and economic development at Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) by strengthening STEM innovation capacity and capability. While HBCUs play an important role in training black professionals, few are research-focused and thus, few are engaged in innovation and entrepreneurial development. To address this low level of entrepreneurship and innovation at HBCUs, the project aims to engage 44 HBCUs across eight EPSCoR jurisdictions, along with the broader academic and industry community working on STEM innovation entrepreneurship. The project anticipates that employing HBCUs as a source of diverse entrepreneurial innovators will provide a wider network of valuable resources, thereby enhancing scientific and technological knowledge and increasing the national pipeline of enabled, well-trained technology entrepreneurs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of this workshop is to engage the current 44 HBCUs in eight EPSCOR jurisdictions working on STEM innovation and entrepreneurship as well as the broader academic and industry-related STEM community, to provide a platform for discussion of best approaches, activities, and implementation strategies to develop these campuses into high-performing resources of STEM innovation and entrepreneurship. The focus of the workshop is to (1) create a platform for building approaches for broadening participation, grounded in learning and social science research, to develop and advance participation of HBCUs in the nation's science and engineering innovation enterprise; (2) inform and engage various stakeholders, including HBCUs, government, and industry, in building diverse STEM communities of innovation and lead to promising strategies, models, and technologies for broadening participation of HBCUs in the current innovation and entrepreneurship space; and (3) deliver sustainable learning activities designed to expand the development of entrepreneurship and social entrepreneurship programs and courses at HBCUs that encourage innovation and complement current EPSCoR investments and interest in broadening participation. The intent of the workshop is to demonstrate novel and effective strategic approaches for inclusiveness in science and engineering innovation that can be adapted and replicated nationally by HBCUs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022768</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Orok</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teresa M Orok</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[teresa.orok@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000499271</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alabama A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>NORMAL</CityName>
<ZipCode>357627500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2563728186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4900 MERIDIAN STREET NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JDVGS67MSLH7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALABAMA A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alabama A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>Normal</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>357620411</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4900 Meridian Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>916800</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Outreach and Workshops</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9168</Code>
<Text>EPSCOR OUTREACH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99512</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes Report: National Science Foundation EPSCoR Program Funding</strong></p> <p><strong>Project Title:</strong> Building Entrepreneurship and Economic Development at EPSCoR&rsquo;s Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs)<br /><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Dr. Teresa Merriweather Orok, Alabama A&amp;M University</p> <p>The "Building Entrepreneurship and Economic Development at EPSCoR&rsquo;s Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs)" project made a significant impact, adding to the body of knowledge on HBCUs and the strategies required to drive forward progress in innovation and economic development. Despite challenges posed by the COVID-19 pandemic, the project achieved several key objectives through participation in major events and initiatives aimed at fostering entrepreneurship and economic prosperity at HBCUs. Below are two significant national programs and my role in each.</p> <h3>Key Achievements:</h3> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Establishment of a National Leadership Council</strong> One of the most notable outcomes of this project was the formation of a National Leadership Council focused on addressing the challenges HBCUs face in institutionalizing innovation and entrepreneurship programs. The council, composed of diverse professionals from innovation, entrepreneurship, higher education (including EPSCoR leaders from various states), and venture capital (e.g., VentureWell), played a critical role in advancing this dialogue. Additionally, key partners such as the United Negro College Fund (UNCF) and the Association of Public and Land-grant Universities (APLU) contributed to this effort. The council organized and facilitated three webinars that provided strategies for advancing innovation and entrepreneurship at HBCUs.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Partnerships with National Programs</strong> Although the pandemic prevented the convening of all 50 EPSCoR HBCUs as originally planned, the project successfully partnered with key national programs such as NASA&rsquo;s HBCU Capacity Building Programs, the U.S. Department of Commerce Minority Business Development Agency, and the University-Industry Demonstration Partnership (UIDP). These collaborations led to participation in multiple hybrid summits focused on capacity building within HBCU ecosystems. In my role as a member of the UIDP, I was invited to serve on panels for HBCU-focused events, where I shared insights on the innovative capacity of HBCUs.</p> </li> </ol> <h3>Leadership in HBCU Engagement and Strategic Planning</h3> <p>In my capacity as Vice President (and now President-elect) of the University Economic Development Association (UEDA), my efforts have focused on increasing HBCU participation in national economic development initiatives. Recent UEDA briefings by institutions such as Southern University, Virginia State University, and Florida A&amp;M University highlighted key efforts in accelerating awareness and developing playbooks for HBCUs as they work to reimagine curriculum and community engagement.</p> <p>Additionally, my collaboration with the UNCF, particularly through the "UNCF Meeting of the Minds" event, allowed me to contribute as a major presenter and thought leader. This gathering of 60-75 HBCUs cemented many strategies developed over the course of the NSF HBCU Leadership Team&rsquo;s three-year effort, resulting in a clear call to action for HBCUs to reimagine their curriculum and community engagement strategies. Dr. Chad Womack of UNCF played a pivotal role in this collaboration and contributed to the strategic framework developed by the NSF AAMU EPSCoR project.</p> <h3>Future Directions: Critical Research Questions</h3> <p>As we look toward the future of HBCU innovation and entrepreneurship, several key research questions have emerged, shaping the agenda for future research and programming. These questions will guide our efforts to elevate the HBCU narrative and build a sustainable HBCU 2.0 model for entrepreneurship and innovation:</p> <ul> <li>What data and evidence are needed to construct a new framework for the HBCU 2.0 model?</li> <li>How can we enhance academic and economic competitiveness through R&amp;D commercialization and entrepreneurship?</li> <li>What are the capital requirements necessary to sustain an HBCU 2.0 R&amp;D model?</li> <li>What resources are essential to building R&amp;D infrastructure and capacity at HBCUs?</li> <li>How will federal agencies play a role in expanding HBCU R&amp;D, and how will the HBCU 2.0 model engage with these agencies differently from past models?</li> <li>How can private philanthropy accelerate the development and implementation of the HBCU 2.0 model?</li> <li>What cultural shifts are necessary to foster a sustainable culture of innovation and entrepreneurship at HBCUs?</li> <li>How can HBCUs contribute to building robust African American K-12 STEM pipelines that prepare students for post-secondary education?</li> </ul> <p>These questions will continue to drive my research, and with additional support from NSF, I plan to host major convenings and develop actionable strategies for HBCUs in the future.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion:</strong></p> <p>The NSF EPSCoR-funded project has laid a strong foundation for advancing entrepreneurship and economic development at HBCUs. Despite challenges, the collaborations and strategic initiatives undertaken have established a clear pathway forward, and I look forward to further research and continued efforts to support HBCUs in realizing their full potential in innovation and economic growth.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/09/2024<br> Modified by: Teresa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Orok</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Outcomes Report: National Science Foundation EPSCoR Program Funding   Project Title: Building Entrepreneurship and Economic Development at EPSCoRs Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) Principal Investigator: Dr. Teresa Merriweather Orok, Alabama A&M University   The "Building Entrepreneurship and Economic Development at EPSCoRs Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs)" project made a significant impact, adding to the body of knowledge on HBCUs and the strategies required to drive forward progress in innovation and economic development. Despite challenges posed by the COVID-19 pandemic, the project achieved several key objectives through participation in major events and initiatives aimed at fostering entrepreneurship and economic prosperity at HBCUs. Below are two significant national programs and my role in each. Key Achievements:     Establishment of a National Leadership Council One of the most notable outcomes of this project was the formation of a National Leadership Council focused on addressing the challenges HBCUs face in institutionalizing innovation and entrepreneurship programs. The council, composed of diverse professionals from innovation, entrepreneurship, higher education (including EPSCoR leaders from various states), and venture capital (e.g., VentureWell), played a critical role in advancing this dialogue. Additionally, key partners such as the United Negro College Fund (UNCF) and the Association of Public and Land-grant Universities (APLU) contributed to this effort. The council organized and facilitated three webinars that provided strategies for advancing innovation and entrepreneurship at HBCUs.     Partnerships with National Programs Although the pandemic prevented the convening of all 50 EPSCoR HBCUs as originally planned, the project successfully partnered with key national programs such as NASAs HBCU Capacity Building Programs, the U.S. Department of Commerce Minority Business Development Agency, and the University-Industry Demonstration Partnership (UIDP). These collaborations led to participation in multiple hybrid summits focused on capacity building within HBCU ecosystems. In my role as a member of the UIDP, I was invited to serve on panels for HBCU-focused events, where I shared insights on the innovative capacity of HBCUs.   Leadership in HBCU Engagement and Strategic Planning   In my capacity as Vice President (and now President-elect) of the University Economic Development Association (UEDA), my efforts have focused on increasing HBCU participation in national economic development initiatives. Recent UEDA briefings by institutions such as Southern University, Virginia State University, and Florida A&M University highlighted key efforts in accelerating awareness and developing playbooks for HBCUs as they work to reimagine curriculum and community engagement.   Additionally, my collaboration with the UNCF, particularly through the "UNCF Meeting of the Minds" event, allowed me to contribute as a major presenter and thought leader. This gathering of 60-75 HBCUs cemented many strategies developed over the course of the NSF HBCU Leadership Teams three-year effort, resulting in a clear call to action for HBCUs to reimagine their curriculum and community engagement strategies. Dr. Chad Womack of UNCF played a pivotal role in this collaboration and contributed to the strategic framework developed by the NSF AAMU EPSCoR project. Future Directions: Critical Research Questions   As we look toward the future of HBCU innovation and entrepreneurship, several key research questions have emerged, shaping the agenda for future research and programming. These questions will guide our efforts to elevate the HBCU narrative and build a sustainable HBCU 2.0 model for entrepreneurship and innovation:  What data and evidence are needed to construct a new framework for the HBCU 2.0 model? How can we enhance academic and economic competitiveness through R&D commercialization and entrepreneurship? What are the capital requirements necessary to sustain an HBCU 2.0 R&D model? What resources are essential to building R&D infrastructure and capacity at HBCUs? How will federal agencies play a role in expanding HBCU R&D, and how will the HBCU 2.0 model engage with these agencies differently from past models? How can private philanthropy accelerate the development and implementation of the HBCU 2.0 model? What cultural shifts are necessary to foster a sustainable culture of innovation and entrepreneurship at HBCUs? How can HBCUs contribute to building robust African American K-12 STEM pipelines that prepare students for post-secondary education?    These questions will continue to drive my research, and with additional support from NSF, I plan to host major convenings and develop actionable strategies for HBCUs in the future.   Conclusion:   The NSF EPSCoR-funded project has laid a strong foundation for advancing entrepreneurship and economic development at HBCUs. Despite challenges, the collaborations and strategic initiatives undertaken have established a clear pathway forward, and I look forward to further research and continued efforts to support HBCUs in realizing their full potential in innovation and economic growth.        Last Modified: 09/09/2024       Submitted by: TeresaMOrok]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
