<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[GP:IN Geoscience Teaching Outdoors in NC (GET OUT in NC)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>318896.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>318896</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Institute for the Environment at the University of North Carolina (NC) at Chapel Hill, together with the NC Museum of Natural Sciences, will implement Geoscience Teaching Outdoors in NC (GET OUT in NC). The goal of this project is to support a diverse future workforce and STEM-literate public, by implementing educational programming on community resilience to climate change for secondary science teachers and youth. Over three years, GET OUT in NC will engage 40 secondary teachers from eastern NC in learning experiences in state parks, building their capability to incorporate current research on climate change impacts into their teaching. The project also will directly engage 50-60 high school aged youth in programming at the Greenville, NC location of the NC Museum of Natural Sciences, introducing diverse youth to education and careers in geosciences. NC State Parks and Martin County Schools also are collaborating on this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of Geoscience Teaching Outdoors in NC (GET OUT in NC) is to support a diverse future workforce and STEM-literate public, specifically by engaging diverse youth in eastern North Carolina in geoscience research, education, and career pathways. The project has three primary objectives: (1) enhance secondary science teachers’ geoscience knowledge and pedagogy to enable them to engage their students in active geoscience learning; (2) increase knowledge of and interest in geosciences research and careers among high school aged youth through informal learning about local/regional climate change impacts and solutions; and (3) cultivate a geoscience learning ecosystem by supporting collaboration among educators, researchers, and natural resource professionals from local science centers and state parks, local school districts, and university geoscience departments. By interweaving two critical issues facing our society, namely the need for community resilience to climate change impacts and lack of diversity in geosciences, this project lays a foundation for diversifying the workforce while developing local solutions that can replicated broadly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023173</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Piehler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael F Piehler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mpiehler@email.unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000207218</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Gray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathleen M Gray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kmgray@email.unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000249680</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275995023</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>D3LHU66KBLD5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D3LHU66KBLD5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~318896</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>From 2020-2024, the Center for Public Engagement with Science (CPES) implemented <strong><em>Geoscience Teaching Outdoors in North Carolina</em></strong> (<strong><em>GET OUT in NC</em></strong>), in partnership with the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences (NCMNS). CPES is based in the UNC Institute for the Environment at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and NCMNS is headquartered in Raleigh, NC with several satellite locations in the eastern part of the state. North Carolina State Parks also was a key partner and hosted <em><strong>GET OUT in NC </strong></em>programming at multiple parks in eastern NC.</p>  <p>This&#8239;informal science learning program had an overarching goal of supporting a diverse future workforce and STEM-literate public, which was achieved through three objectives: (1) building the capacity of secondary science teachers to engage students in active geoscience learning; (2) increasing knowledge and interest in geosciences research and careers among high school youth; and&nbsp;(3) cultivating a geoscience-focused community of practice by facilitating collaboration among formal and informal educators, natural resource professionals, and university-based geoscience researchers.&nbsp;</p>  <p>Major outcomes of <em><strong>GET OUT in NC</strong></em> included the following:</p>  <p>Thirty-two teachers were introduced to outdoor science learning approaches, with most reporting enhanced knowledge, development of skills to support outdoor science teaching, and increased self-efficacy for outdoor science teaching; some of these changes were statistically significant. As a result of the program, participating teachers were better prepared to integrate outdoor learning approaches into instruction and highlight climate impacts in NC, providing their students with authentic and relevant geoscience learning opportunities. These teachers also were introduced to strategies for creating inclusive science learning environments, and several secured additional resources to support outdoor learning (such as a grant to support construction of an outdoor observation deck and purchase of backpacks, stools, binoculars, and field guides).</p>  <p>Twelve university-based geoscientists, including early career investigators and trainees, modeled field research techniques and shared emerging science with teachers. Simultaneously, the university researchers developed and practiced their science communication skills. One trainee co-authored a lesson on the nitrogen cycle with project-affiliated formal and informal educators. An additional 30 informal educators participated in programming over the funding period, including: five NCMNS educators, 12 rangers and interpretation / education staff from NC State Parks, 13 informal educators from eastern NC environmental education centers, and several staff associated with a participating school district.</p>  <p>Thirty-eight youth in eastern NC experienced hands-on geoscience programming, increasing their knowledge of related topics and skills and their interest in geoscience career pathways. Most of these participants reported statistically significant increases in their ability to use community science approaches and technology to explore Earth systems, use nature journaling to build scientific observation skills, and to document and share their findings. A majority also reported statistically significant increases in career awareness and interest in environmental or geoscience career pathways.</p>  <p><strong><em>GET OUT in NC </em></strong>programming fostered a community of practice among participating teachers, expanding their professional networks to include informal educators, science centers, and other natural resource organizations in eastern NC. As a result, new science enrichment programs were launched, including a week-long summer science enrichment program implemented jointly by an eastern NC school district and one of the satellite locations of the NCMNS. This team secured a follow-on small grant to continue programming after NSF support ends.</p>  <p>Existing programs also expanded their foci and scope with support from <strong><em>GET OUT in NC</em></strong>. Specifically, CPES educators shared project-created instructional materials and led programming for another youth science enrichment program in the region, the GeoHealth Interns program in Robeson County, NC, one of NC&rsquo;s most diverse counties. In another example, interactions during <strong><em>GET OUT in NC</em></strong> led to a long-term collaboration between a university-based geoscientist (and regular contributor to <strong><em>GET OUT IN NC</em></strong>) and NC State Parks, enabling expansion of a citizen science monitoring network across eight state parks. Additionally, project leadership supported NC State Parks as it expanded staffing to include a group of informal educators, assisting with onboarding and training these new educators, and contributed to other teacher professional development programs within CPES, including an energy-science program.</p>  <p>Following unprecedented flooding in western NC associated with Hurricane Helene (in fall 2024), the&nbsp;<strong><em>GET OUT in NC&nbsp;</em></strong>team, including collaborators in North Carolina State Parks, provided a day of hands-on science programming for students in an elementary school that was displaced by flooding. The team of educators rotated all students in grades K-5&nbsp;through multiple science stations and replaced some of the science instructional materials and reference books that were lost in the flood.</p>  <p>Lastly, project outcomes and insights were shared nationally through presentations at the annual meetings of the American Geophysical Union, the North American Association for Environmental Education, and the National Science Teachers Association.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/19/2024<br> Modified by: Kathleen&nbsp;M&nbsp;Gray</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2023173/2023173_10704128_1734623257591_Taylor_GEOPATHS_retreat_2021--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2023173/2023173_10704128_1734623257591_Taylor_GEOPATHS_retreat_2021--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ghost forest research"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2023173/2023173_10704128_1734623257591_Taylor_GEOPATHS_retreat_2021--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ghost forest research"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GET OUT in NC teachers, project leaders Dr. Kathleen Gray and Sarah Yelton, and NCMNS Educator Taylor Prichard participate in ghost forest research with Dr. Marcelo Ardon</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kathleen Gray</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kathleen&nbsp;M&nbsp;Gray <div class="imageTitle">ghost forest research</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  From 2020-2024, the Center for Public Engagement with Science (CPES) implemented Geoscience Teaching Outdoors in North Carolina (GET OUT in NC), in partnership with the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences (NCMNS). CPES is based in the UNC Institute for the Environment at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and NCMNS is headquartered in Raleigh, NC with several satellite locations in the eastern part of the state. North Carolina State Parks also was a key partner and hosted GET OUT in NC programming at multiple parks in eastern NC.    This&#8239;informal science learning program had an overarching goal of supporting a diverse future workforce and STEM-literate public, which was achieved through three objectives: (1) building the capacity of secondary science teachers to engage students in active geoscience learning; (2) increasing knowledge and interest in geosciences research and careers among high school youth; and(3) cultivating a geoscience-focused community of practice by facilitating collaboration among formal and informal educators, natural resource professionals, and university-based geoscience researchers.    Major outcomes of GET OUT in NC included the following:    Thirty-two teachers were introduced to outdoor science learning approaches, with most reporting enhanced knowledge, development of skills to support outdoor science teaching, and increased self-efficacy for outdoor science teaching; some of these changes were statistically significant. As a result of the program, participating teachers were better prepared to integrate outdoor learning approaches into instruction and highlight climate impacts in NC, providing their students with authentic and relevant geoscience learning opportunities. These teachers also were introduced to strategies for creating inclusive science learning environments, and several secured additional resources to support outdoor learning (such as a grant to support construction of an outdoor observation deck and purchase of backpacks, stools, binoculars, and field guides).    Twelve university-based geoscientists, including early career investigators and trainees, modeled field research techniques and shared emerging science with teachers. Simultaneously, the university researchers developed and practiced their science communication skills. One trainee co-authored a lesson on the nitrogen cycle with project-affiliated formal and informal educators. An additional 30 informal educators participated in programming over the funding period, including: five NCMNS educators, 12 rangers and interpretation / education staff from NC State Parks, 13 informal educators from eastern NC environmental education centers, and several staff associated with a participating school district.    Thirty-eight youth in eastern NC experienced hands-on geoscience programming, increasing their knowledge of related topics and skills and their interest in geoscience career pathways. Most of these participants reported statistically significant increases in their ability to use community science approaches and technology to explore Earth systems, use nature journaling to build scientific observation skills, and to document and share their findings. A majority also reported statistically significant increases in career awareness and interest in environmental or geoscience career pathways.    GET OUT in NC programming fostered a community of practice among participating teachers, expanding their professional networks to include informal educators, science centers, and other natural resource organizations in eastern NC. As a result, new science enrichment programs were launched, including a week-long summer science enrichment program implemented jointly by an eastern NC school district and one of the satellite locations of the NCMNS. This team secured a follow-on small grant to continue programming after NSF support ends.    Existing programs also expanded their foci and scope with support from GET OUT in NC. Specifically, CPES educators shared project-created instructional materials and led programming for another youth science enrichment program in the region, the GeoHealth Interns program in Robeson County, NC, one of NCs most diverse counties. In another example, interactions during GET OUT in NC led to a long-term collaboration between a university-based geoscientist (and regular contributor to GET OUT IN NC) and NC State Parks, enabling expansion of a citizen science monitoring network across eight state parks. Additionally, project leadership supported NC State Parks as it expanded staffing to include a group of informal educators, assisting with onboarding and training these new educators, and contributed to other teacher professional development programs within CPES, including an energy-science program.    Following unprecedented flooding in western NC associated with Hurricane Helene (in fall 2024), theGET OUT in NCteam, including collaborators in North Carolina State Parks, provided a day of hands-on science programming for students in an elementary school that was displaced by flooding. The team of educators rotated all students in grades K-5through multiple science stations and replaced some of the science instructional materials and reference books that were lost in the flood.    Lastly, project outcomes and insights were shared nationally through presentations at the annual meetings of the American Geophysical Union, the North American Association for Environmental Education, and the National Science Teachers Association.         Last Modified: 12/19/2024       Submitted by: KathleenMGray]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
