<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Belmont Forum Collaborative Research: Risk mapping and targeted snail control to support schistosomiasis elimination in Brazil and Cote d'Ivoire under future environmental change]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Uhle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>muhle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support to U.S. researchers participating in a project competitively selected by a 55-country initiative on global change research through the Belmont Forum.  The Belmont Forum is a consortium of research funding organizations focused on support for transdisciplinary approaches to global environmental change challenges and opportunities.  It aims to accelerate delivery of the international research most urgently needed to remove critical barriers to sustainability by aligning and mobilizing international resources. Each partner country provides funding for their researchers within a consortium to alleviate the need for funds to cross international borders. This approach facilitates effective leveraging of national resources to support excellent research on topics of global relevance best tackled through a multinational approach, recognizing that global challenges need global solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Working together in this Collaborative Research Action, the partner agencies have provided support to foster global transdisciplinary research teams of natural (including climate), health and social scientists and stakeholders from across the globe to improve understanding of climate, environment and health pathways to protect and promote health. The projects will provide crucial new understanding into the health implications arising from the impacts of climate change and variability on; 1) the quality/quantity of food, 2) chronic exposure to increases/changes in heat and humidity and 3) changes in the distribution and incidence of a range of infectious diseases and emergence of novel pathogens. This award provides support for the U.S. researchers to cooperate in consortia that consist of partners from at least three of the participating countries to increase our knowledge of the complex linkages and pathways between the climate, environment and health to help solve complex challenges that face societies.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project seeks to investigate the combined effect of environmental and land use change, such as the development of water management infrastructures, on the distribution of snail-borne schistosomiasis, a debilitating parasitic disease of poverty, affecting more than 200 million people worldwide. The study will focus on Brazil and Ivory Coast as these countries are countries particularly vulnerable to this parasitic disease as a consequence of projected climate change combined with growing human population, deforestation, expansion of agriculture and of marginal urban settings and the development of dams and irrigation canals. The project will couple different model types to understand how species are distributed in response to relevant socio-economic and environmental drivers of schistosomiasis to produce maps of present and future risk for schistosomiasis under projected environmental conditions. The project will provide a major step forward in the development of novel ways to profile schistosomiasis risk by integrating models of schistosomiasis transmission with remote sensing and GIS spatial representation of other ecological, environmental and socioeconomic drivers of schistosomaisis risk.  The project will combine field data at different scales with theory to investigate the linked human and natural drivers of parasite transmission to improve understanding of the expected future distribution of schistosomiasis risk.  The project will provide a reference framework to investigate the environmental determinants of a wide family of snail-borne and soil-transmitted infections affecting over 1.5 billion of the world’s poorest people.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kamazima</FirstName>
<LastName>Lwiza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kamazima M Lwiza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kamazima.lwiza@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000184917</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ping</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ping Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ping.liu@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000529642</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117945000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>731300</Code>
<Text>Intl Global Change Res &amp; Coord</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1679</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7313</Code>
<Text>REGIONAL INST FOR GLOBAL CHANG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~41465</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~28457</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~28078</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>The group goals of the collaborative project:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;FIRST: To examine the impact of climate change on schistosomiasis transmission risk by integrating a mechanistic, process-based, thermal-sensitive model of schistosomiasis dynamics with GIS-based risk mapping of present and future temperature, precipitation, and the presence of water as well as other important ecological, environmental and socio-economic determinants of schistosomiasis transmission.&nbsp;</p> <p>SECOND: Conduct initial feasibility and nutritional studies and market analyses of aquaculture of freshwater prawns native to Brazil and Cote d'Ivoire with the goal of using prawns as biological control agents of schistosome's snail host while, at the same time, promoting the development of small-scale prawn aquaculture businesses for poverty alleviation.&nbsp;</p> <p>THIRD: Examining future changes in the distribution and abundance of the snail hosts by developing machine learning algorithms with computer vision as an "environmental diagnosis" tool for the quick and accurate identification of potential schistosome-host snails and parasites from field-acquired cellphone images.</p> <p><strong>The goals of this specific project:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>There were two specific goals for our project component: (1) to download historical and projected climatic variables from several different databases and interpolate them to a 1-km grid for Brazil and C&ocirc;te D&rsquo;Ivoire, and compute bioclimatic variables relevant to schistosomiasis epidemiology; (2) to install weather sensors in Brazil and C&ocirc;te D&rsquo;Ivoire for ground truthing the data from the databases.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Products:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Our group, specializing in climate dynamics worked hand in hand with all groups on the team, fostering a sense of inclusivity and shared purpose. This collective effort led to the production of the following:</p> <p>1. A paper on the temperature-based model of schistosomiasis based on patterns of present and future temperature, precipitation, presence of water, and other critical environmental variables was published, and another manuscript is in progress.</p> <p>2. A paper was published based on a machine learning approach examining the change in schistosomiasis hotspot sites in Brazil for future climate.</p> <p>3. We created a repository of BIO19 = Precipitation of Coldest Quarter for Brazil and C&ocirc;te D'Ivoire at 1-km resolution based on CHELSA and&nbsp; WorldClim databases for the periods 1981&ndash;2010, 2011&ndash;2040, 2041&ndash;2070, and 2071&ndash;2100. We also included a FORTRAN code that produced it. It is being shared through this link:<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13963743"> https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13963743</a></p> <p>4. We are currently preparing several manuscripts that will delve deeper into our findings and their implications for schistosomiasis research and control strategies. These manuscripts will cover a range of topics, from the impact of climate change on snail distribution to the potential use of prawns as biological control agents.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Significant findings:</strong></p> <ol> <li>Our results indicate that climate change has caused broad shifts in the geographical range of snails. In contrast, urban sprawl and expansion of peri-urban areas have influenced the local expansion of habitat suitability. Or findings also show that analysis of change in Biomphalaria distribution, which includes the nonlinear relationships that are difficult to detect from regional case studies may help inform schistosomiasis control strategies</li> <li>Our research revealed that the thermal optima for the transmission of <em>S</em>. <em>mansoni</em> and <em>S</em>. <em>haematobium fall within the</em> range of 23.1&ndash;27.3&deg;C and 23.6&ndash;27.9&deg;C (95% CI), respectively. This means that as the temperature increases, the risk of schistosomiasis transmission also rises. The refined nonlinear thermal-response model developed here suggests a more suitable current climate and a greater risk of increased transmission with future warming for more than half of the schistosomiasis-suitable regions with mean annual temperature below the thermal optimum.</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 11/11/2024<br> Modified by: Kamazima&nbsp;M&nbsp;Lwiza</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The group goals of the collaborative project:   FIRST: To examine the impact of climate change on schistosomiasis transmission risk by integrating a mechanistic, process-based, thermal-sensitive model of schistosomiasis dynamics with GIS-based risk mapping of present and future temperature, precipitation, and the presence of water as well as other important ecological, environmental and socio-economic determinants of schistosomiasis transmission.   SECOND: Conduct initial feasibility and nutritional studies and market analyses of aquaculture of freshwater prawns native to Brazil and Cote d'Ivoire with the goal of using prawns as biological control agents of schistosome's snail host while, at the same time, promoting the development of small-scale prawn aquaculture businesses for poverty alleviation.   THIRD: Examining future changes in the distribution and abundance of the snail hosts by developing machine learning algorithms with computer vision as an "environmental diagnosis" tool for the quick and accurate identification of potential schistosome-host snails and parasites from field-acquired cellphone images.   The goals of this specific project:   There were two specific goals for our project component: (1) to download historical and projected climatic variables from several different databases and interpolate them to a 1-km grid for Brazil and Cte DIvoire, and compute bioclimatic variables relevant to schistosomiasis epidemiology; (2) to install weather sensors in Brazil and Cte DIvoire for ground truthing the data from the databases.      Products:   Our group, specializing in climate dynamics worked hand in hand with all groups on the team, fostering a sense of inclusivity and shared purpose. This collective effort led to the production of the following:   1. A paper on the temperature-based model of schistosomiasis based on patterns of present and future temperature, precipitation, presence of water, and other critical environmental variables was published, and another manuscript is in progress.   2. A paper was published based on a machine learning approach examining the change in schistosomiasis hotspot sites in Brazil for future climate.   3. We created a repository of BIO19 = Precipitation of Coldest Quarter for Brazil and Cte D'Ivoire at 1-km resolution based on CHELSA and WorldClim databases for the periods 19812010, 20112040, 20412070, and 20712100. We also included a FORTRAN code that produced it. It is being shared through this link: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13963743   4. We are currently preparing several manuscripts that will delve deeper into our findings and their implications for schistosomiasis research and control strategies. These manuscripts will cover a range of topics, from the impact of climate change on snail distribution to the potential use of prawns as biological control agents.   Significant findings:  Our results indicate that climate change has caused broad shifts in the geographical range of snails. In contrast, urban sprawl and expansion of peri-urban areas have influenced the local expansion of habitat suitability. Or findings also show that analysis of change in Biomphalaria distribution, which includes the nonlinear relationships that are difficult to detect from regional case studies may help inform schistosomiasis control strategies Our research revealed that the thermal optima for the transmission of S. mansoni and S. haematobium fall within the range of 23.127.3C and 23.627.9C (95% CI), respectively. This means that as the temperature increases, the risk of schistosomiasis transmission also rises. The refined nonlinear thermal-response model developed here suggests a more suitable current climate and a greater risk of increased transmission with future warming for more than half of the schistosomiasis-suitable regions with mean annual temperature below the thermal optimum.         Last Modified: 11/11/2024       Submitted by: KamazimaMLwiza]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
