<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Determination of the cross-over frequency of SARS-CoV-2 for rapid identification concentration]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>193230.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>193230</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric Lyons</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>erlyons@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee received an award to investigate an electrical trapping technique to rapidly concentrate SARS-CoV-2 virus to produce highly pure samples for the development of vaccines and therapeutics. Currently, purification through multiple in-series applications of filtration and centrifugation require up to two days to prepare virus samples.  Unfortunately, the purity and viability of the separated viruses are still low after being collected by conventional methods. In this research, a correlation between the virus, nanoparticle size, and electrical dielectrophoretic trapping conditions is investigated to determine the best operating conditions to concentrate 80 – 160 nm size SARS-CoV-2. The developed method will enable the rapid concentration of pure viruses from cell culture and patient samples. The concentrated samples will enhance the development of vaccines, cures, and rapid diagnostic methods for infectious diseases by rapidly supplying highly concentrated pure virus samples. Thus, the research will contribute to improve the public safety related to infectious diseases and economy in the diagnostics and therapeutics area. The developed method is also applicable to the concentration of biomolecules, including DNA, protein, cell lysed fragments and particles, in addition to viruses. Thus, this research will give a substantial improvement on the rapid characterization and applications of molecules in various disciplines, such as virology, genomics, proteomics, diagnosis, forensic science, in addition to vaccine and therapeutics development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The novel dielectrophoretic nanoparticle manipulating method developed in this research can rapidly concentrate viruses into highly pure samples from virus-infected cell media and samples from patients. A charge polarization happens to a dielectric particle when the particle is exposed to an unevenly distributed electric field. The particle will move to either a dense or sparse electric field area depending on the given condition, such as electrical potential, frequency, and permittivities of the particle and medium. The direction of particle movement is inverted depending on the frequency; this is called cross-over frequency. The cross-over frequency varies depending on the characteristics of the particles, such as components, structure, charge, etc. In this research, the cross-over frequency of different bio-nano-particles, ranged from 60 to 500 nm size, will be investigated using heat-treated SARS-CoV-2 and nanoparticles. Initially, the cross-over frequency of different size nano-particles will be determined using dielectrophoretic traps, by modifying the applied potential, frequency, and particle size. Then, the same operating condition screening strategy will be applied to heat-treated SARS-CoV-2. Purity and efficiency of the isolated nano-particles and SARS-CoV-2 will be determined using the developed conditions. The developed method will circumvent the drawbacks that exist with the current serial treatment method used to separate virus, which are: time-intensive, laborious, complicated, and less effective. Consequently, this research will significantly enhance the understandings of the structures and characteristics of bio-nano-particles, such as live viruses, by supplying higher purity samples rapidly. Obtained results will be rapidly applied to other viruses and particles for further characterization and detection, as well as development of applications.  This RAPID award to the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee is made by the Division of Biological Infrastructure using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031741</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Woo Jin</FirstName>
<LastName>Chang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Woo Jin Chang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wjchang@uwm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000599914</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee]]></Name>
<CityName>MILWAUKEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>532113153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142294853</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3203 N DOWNER AVE # 273]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JBQ9M3PLFDP5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee]]></Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532113029</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3200 N Crammer St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y00</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~193230</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aimed to explore the use of dielectrophoresis (DEP) for the manipulation, separation, and analysis of viruses, particularly focusing on coronaviruses, including SARS-CoV-2, Human coronavirus 229E, and Betacoronavirus 1 as model viruses. The intellectual merit lies in the innovative application of DEP to viruses, while the broader impacts encompass significant advancements in virus detection and isolation techniques, contributing to virology, cell biology, public health and bioengineering.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project's intellectual merit is demonstrated through its innovative approach to using DEP for virus manipulation. DEP relies on the interaction between the electric field and the dielectric properties of particles to control their movement. This technique was applied to determine the crossover frequency (COF) of various viruses, a critical parameter for effective virus manipulation. The project successfully identified the COF for HI-SARS-CoV-2 and Human coronavirus 229E, enabling their separation based on their distinct dielectric properties.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of this work are substantial, particularly in the context of virology and public health. The ability to selectively isolate and manipulate viruses using DEP can lead to more efficient diagnostic tools and methods for handling viral pathogens. This technology has the potential to enhance identification of unknown virus, contributing to faster and more accurate responses to viral outbreaks. Moreover, the project's outcomes can inform future research and development in microfluidics and biosensors, promoting advancements in point-of-care diagnostics and environmental monitoring.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Project Outcomes:</p> <p>1. DEP Trap Device Fabrication and Setup:</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp; A microfluidic DEP trap device was fabricated, featuring a circular array of traps designed to capture viruses. This device was critical for conducting DEP experiments and analyzing virus behavior under varying electric fields in single particle level.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>2. Determination of Crossover Frequency (COF):</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp; The COF for HI-SARS-CoV-2 and Human coronavirus 229E was identified at different frequencies, indicating the points where the DEP force changes direction. This discovery is crucial for separating these viruses based on their unique dielectric properties. However, Betacoronavirus 1 did not exhibit a COF under the tested conditions, suggesting a virus type-specific behavior under the same DEP condition.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>3. Continuous Virus Separation:</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp; The project demonstrated the possibility of continuous separation of viruses using DEP under flow conditions. By selecting appropriate flow rates and frequencies, HI-SARS-CoV-2 and Human coronavirus 229E were successfully separated, highlighting the potential of DEP for real-time virus isolation and concentration.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has achieved significant milestones in the application of DEP for virus manipulation. By identifying COFs and optimizing DEP conditions, it has paved the way for advanced techniques in virus separation and analysis. These outcomes not only contribute to the field of biology but also hold promise for improving public health responses to viral infections through better diagnostic and isolation methods. The findings from this research have the potential to influence future developments in biosensor technology and microfluidic devices, driving innovation in various biological and biomedical applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The advancements made in this project show the importance of interdisciplinary approaches in tackling complex biological challenges, ultimately contributing to the broader scientific and healthcare communities.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 08/14/2024<br> Modified by: Woo Jin&nbsp;Chang</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project aimed to explore the use of dielectrophoresis (DEP) for the manipulation, separation, and analysis of viruses, particularly focusing on coronaviruses, including SARS-CoV-2, Human coronavirus 229E, and Betacoronavirus 1 as model viruses. The intellectual merit lies in the innovative application of DEP to viruses, while the broader impacts encompass significant advancements in virus detection and isolation techniques, contributing to virology, cell biology, public health and bioengineering.      The project's intellectual merit is demonstrated through its innovative approach to using DEP for virus manipulation. DEP relies on the interaction between the electric field and the dielectric properties of particles to control their movement. This technique was applied to determine the crossover frequency (COF) of various viruses, a critical parameter for effective virus manipulation. The project successfully identified the COF for HI-SARS-CoV-2 and Human coronavirus 229E, enabling their separation based on their distinct dielectric properties.      The broader impacts of this work are substantial, particularly in the context of virology and public health. The ability to selectively isolate and manipulate viruses using DEP can lead to more efficient diagnostic tools and methods for handling viral pathogens. This technology has the potential to enhance identification of unknown virus, contributing to faster and more accurate responses to viral outbreaks. Moreover, the project's outcomes can inform future research and development in microfluidics and biosensors, promoting advancements in point-of-care diagnostics and environmental monitoring.      Project Outcomes:   1. DEP Trap Device Fabrication and Setup:    A microfluidic DEP trap device was fabricated, featuring a circular array of traps designed to capture viruses. This device was critical for conducting DEP experiments and analyzing virus behavior under varying electric fields in single particle level.      2. Determination of Crossover Frequency (COF):    The COF for HI-SARS-CoV-2 and Human coronavirus 229E was identified at different frequencies, indicating the points where the DEP force changes direction. This discovery is crucial for separating these viruses based on their unique dielectric properties. However, Betacoronavirus 1 did not exhibit a COF under the tested conditions, suggesting a virus type-specific behavior under the same DEP condition.      3. Continuous Virus Separation:    The project demonstrated the possibility of continuous separation of viruses using DEP under flow conditions. By selecting appropriate flow rates and frequencies, HI-SARS-CoV-2 and Human coronavirus 229E were successfully separated, highlighting the potential of DEP for real-time virus isolation and concentration.      The project has achieved significant milestones in the application of DEP for virus manipulation. By identifying COFs and optimizing DEP conditions, it has paved the way for advanced techniques in virus separation and analysis. These outcomes not only contribute to the field of biology but also hold promise for improving public health responses to viral infections through better diagnostic and isolation methods. The findings from this research have the potential to influence future developments in biosensor technology and microfluidic devices, driving innovation in various biological and biomedical applications.      The advancements made in this project show the importance of interdisciplinary approaches in tackling complex biological challenges, ultimately contributing to the broader scientific and healthcare communities.     Last Modified: 08/14/2024       Submitted by: Woo JinChang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
