<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Matching Experienced and Novice Teachers for Ongoing Rigorous Support in Computer Science (MENTORS in CS)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299724.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299724</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Forbes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jforbes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925301</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Computer Science Teachers Association (CSTA), in collaboration with the CSTA Chapter in Wisconsin and WestEd, will develop Matching Experienced and Novice Teachers for Ongoing Rigorous Support in Computer Science (MENTORS in CS), a Research Practitioner Partnership to develop and iteratively improve a high school computer science (CS) teacher mentorship program to provide ongoing, rigorous, and job-embedded support to teachers who are new to CS. While novice teachers often require more intensive support to be effective, there are relatively few opportunities for ongoing professional development and support in CS. In this project, experienced CS teachers will guide novice CS teachers in setting, monitoring progress toward, and meeting individualized growth goals to strengthen their teaching practices and their ability to effectively serve students traditionally underrepresented in CS, particularly African American and Hispanic students and students from economically disadvantaged backgrounds. This project will reach 60 CS teachers in two years, impacting approximately 7,200 high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;MENTORS in CS Key project activities involve developing the mentorship structures, mentor training, and teacher matching process; holding frequent mentorship meetings and mentor community of practice meetings; and using research and evaluation data to iteratively improve the program and outcomes. The MENTORS IN CS partners expect the following project outcomes: (1) Increased confidence in teaching CS, as measured by surveys and interviews; (2) Increased pedagogical content knowledge, as measured through surveys, interviews, and mentor evaluations; (3) Increased use of equitable and inclusive teaching practices, as measured by surveys, interviews, and mentor evaluations; and (4) Growth towards mastery of indicators within the CSTA Standards for CS Teachers as measured by pre-, mid-, and post-self-reflections. The partners aim to develop and refine mentorship structures and protocols first at one chapter (CSTA Wisconsin Dairyland), with an explicit strategy to scale the mentorship program across CSTA’s growing chapter network in subsequent years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031314</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aleata</FirstName>
<LastName>Hubbard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aleata K Hubbard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ahubbar@wested.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000642999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Twarek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryan Twarek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bryan.twarek@csteachers.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000778769</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[COMPUTER SCIENCE TEACHERS ASSOCIATION, LLC.]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100197434</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7736273300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1601 BROADWAY FL 10]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YXNGL9KDXMM1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COMPUTER SCIENCE TEACHERS ASSOCIATION, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[COMPUTER SCIENCE TEACHERS ASSOCIATION, LLC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606016436</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 East Randolph Street, Suite 200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>055Y00</Code>
<Text>CISE Education and Workforce</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~299724</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-d466aa53-7fff-07e0-3ccc-c4d3447f853b"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>OBJECTIVE 1: REACH 60 CS TEACHERS, IMPACT 7,200 STUDENTS</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>MENTORS in CS offered a peer mentoring program to teachers in Wisconsin across three school years (2021-22, 2022-23, and 2023-24). We initially aimed to reach 60 teachers, but several participants chose to return to the program for a second or third year. Our project reached 44 schools, 49 unique teachers, and approximately 7,317 students.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>OBJECTIVE 2: DEVELOP MENTORING PROGRAM, TRAINING &amp; MATCHING PROCESS</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We developed several resources to support a structured mentoring program: a self-reflection, partnership agreements and relationship-building activities, goal setting templates and example goals, and meeting logs that guide each mentoring session. These resources are publicly available at </span><a href="https://csteachers.org/mentors/#toolkit"><span>https://csteachers.org/mentors/#toolkit</span></a><span>.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We held a two-day training at the start of each year for mentors. The training focused on: (a) the phases of mentoring, (b) effective mentoring practices, (c) equitable and inclusive pedagogy, (d) building a supportive community of mentors, (e) the social, political and historical context of computer science education, and (f) program resources.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We developed a participant recruitment and selection process that supported our broadening participation goals. As a result, approximately 75% of mentees taught at Title I schools, 57% taught at schools with large populations of Black and/or Latinx students, and 68% taught in rural or urban communities (27% and 41%, respectively).</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We strategically matched mentors with mentees based on the courses they teach, school, and community context (e.g., rural/urban setting, student population), mentees' goals and mentors' strengths, and the teachers' preferences. Virtual meetings allowed us to match mentors and mentees who did not live or work in the same region.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>OBJECTIVE 3: HOLD MENTORSHIP MEETINGS &amp; COMMUNITY OF PRACTICE MEETINGS</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Mentor/mentee partners met at least twice per month at mutually agreeable times. In three, 2.5-month mentoring cycles, partners worked to reflect and then set and achieve one specific professional learning goal aligned to a focal teacher standard. We estimate that mentees participated in about 20 hours of personalized professional learning in a year.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Ongoing mentor professional development consisted of a monthly, 1.5-hour, community of practice meeting with three parts: </span></p> <ol> <li><span>Mentors connected and built relationships with one another, while working to troubleshoot issues and showcase best practices.</span></li> <li><span>Mentors developed or practiced specific, timely skills, such as refining example goals, identifying strategies and resources that will help mentees meet their goals, providing feedback, and guiding mentees' self-reflection.</span></li> <li><span>Mentors engaged in equity-centered professional learning.</span></li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>OBJECTIVE 4: IMPROVE THE PROGRAM AND OUTCOMES WITH RESEARCH</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We gathered data from mentors, mentees, and facilitators each year to address the following research questions:</span></p> <p><em>(1) What support and structures facilitate quality and effective relationships between mentors and mentees?&nbsp;</em></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Based on year 1 findings, we modified our supports and structures to include more meetings where all mentors and mentees came together. We also redesigned our mentoring resources so they were easier to navigate and helped participants focus on their goals. At the end of the project, participants mostly expressed positive sentiments about the resources and found them supportive of their mentoring experiences.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><em>(2) How does MENTORS in CS support mentees' confidence, job satisfaction and commitment to teaching CS, pedagogical content knowledge, and use of equitable and inclusive teaching practices?</em></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Mentees (a) felt an increase in their proficiency of the CSTA Standards for CS Teachers, (b) had a medium to moderate level of confidence in their equitable and inclusive teaching practices, and (c) had a medium to moderate level of confidence in their computer science teaching knowledge. The program had little impact on job satisfaction but many mentees still wanted to teach CS for many more years.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><em>(3) How does MENTORS in CS support mentors' job satisfaction and commitment to teaching CS, confidence in teaching CS, and mentoring ability?&nbsp;</em></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Mentors (a) had high confidence in their mentoring skills overall, (b) increased confidence in their computer science teaching knowledge, and (c) had a medium level of confidence in using equitable and inclusive teaching practices. The program had little impact on job satisfaction but many mentees still wanted to teach CS for many more years.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>DEVELOP A HEALTHY RESEARCH/PRACTICE PARTNERSHIP (RPP)</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We sought to develop an effective RPP team across CSTA, WestEd, and CSTA Wisconsin Dairyland. Biannual pulse surveys, recurring team discussions, and reports from our external advisory board indicate a healthy partnership that strengthened across the three years of our collaboration.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In late 2023, our team secured funding for a mid-sized NSF CSforAll RPP grant (Award #2318232) that will enable us to expand to two additional communities: CSTA New Jersey and CSTA's Black Affinity Group. We will </span><span>welcome four new practitioner partners into our RPP while working to </span><span>support 76 mentoring partnerships across three years, reaching approximately 10,000 students total.</span></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 02/26/2024<br> Modified by: Bryan&nbsp;Twarek</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718274180_MENTORS_in_CS_Logo__purple_--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718274180_MENTORS_in_CS_Logo__purple_--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MENTORS in CS Logo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718274180_MENTORS_in_CS_Logo__purple_--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MENTORS in CS Logo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">MENTORS in CS Logo, represented by a plant created from circuit lines (indicating growth of CS teaching knowledge)</div> <div class="imageCredit">CSTA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bryan&nbsp;Twarek <div class="imageTitle">MENTORS in CS Logo</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718414687_MENTORS_in_CS_Annotated--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718414687_MENTORS_in_CS_Annotated--rgov-800width.png" title="MENTORS in CS Annotated"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718414687_MENTORS_in_CS_Annotated--rgov-66x44.png" alt="MENTORS in CS Annotated"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">MENTORS in CS = Matching Experienced and Novice Teachers for Ongoing Rigorous Support in Computer Science</div> <div class="imageCredit">CSTA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bryan&nbsp;Twarek <div class="imageTitle">MENTORS in CS Annotated</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718933480_Example_Goal_Setting___Mentoring_Log--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718933480_Example_Goal_Setting___Mentoring_Log--rgov-800width.png" title="Example Goal & Mentoring Log"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718933480_Example_Goal_Setting___Mentoring_Log--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Example Goal & Mentoring Log"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example professional learning goal aligned to CS Teacher Standard 2. Equity & Inclusion around increasing diverse representation in curriculum, plus the start of a mentoring log summarizing the sessions across a mentoring cycle.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CSTA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bryan&nbsp;Twarek <div class="imageTitle">Example Goal & Mentoring Log</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718639987_Theory_of_Action__Simple_--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718639987_Theory_of_Action__Simple_--rgov-800width.png" title="Theory of Action"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718639987_Theory_of_Action__Simple_--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Theory of Action"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Primary activities are: teacher recruitment and matching, 1:1 mentoring, resources, and mentor training + CoP. Outcomes are: teachers' growth in CS teaching knowledge, confidence, mentoring skills, use of equitable and inclusive teaching practices, and commitment to CS teaching.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CSTA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bryan&nbsp;Twarek <div class="imageTitle">Theory of Action</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718764951_Map_of_Mentors___Mentees_2--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718764951_Map_of_Mentors___Mentees_2--rgov-800width.png" title="Map of Teacher Participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708718764951_Map_of_Mentors___Mentees_2--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Map of Teacher Participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of Wisconsin indicating the school location of teacher participants (both mentors and mentees)</div> <div class="imageCredit">CSTA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bryan&nbsp;Twarek <div class="imageTitle">Map of Teacher Participants</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708719883634_017_CSTAdailyHighlights--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708719883634_017_CSTAdailyHighlights--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dissemination"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2031314/2031314_10712456_1708719883634_017_CSTAdailyHighlights--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dissemination"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Amy and Linnea, two RPP members who were also mentor participants in the program, present the MENTORS in CS program at the 2022 CSTA Annual Conference and Chapter Leadership Summit in Chicago, IL</div> <div class="imageCredit">CSTA / Caught in the Moment</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bryan&nbsp;Twarek <div class="imageTitle">Dissemination</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      OBJECTIVE 1: REACH 60 CS TEACHERS, IMPACT 7,200 STUDENTS   MENTORS in CS offered a peer mentoring program to teachers in Wisconsin across three school years (2021-22, 2022-23, and 2023-24). We initially aimed to reach 60 teachers, but several participants chose to return to the program for a second or third year. Our project reached 44 schools, 49 unique teachers, and approximately 7,317 students.      OBJECTIVE 2: DEVELOP MENTORING PROGRAM, TRAINING & MATCHING PROCESS   We developed several resources to support a structured mentoring program: a self-reflection, partnership agreements and relationship-building activities, goal setting templates and example goals, and meeting logs that guide each mentoring session. These resources are publicly available at https://csteachers.org/mentors/#toolkit.   We held a two-day training at the start of each year for mentors. The training focused on: (a) the phases of mentoring, (b) effective mentoring practices, (c) equitable and inclusive pedagogy, (d) building a supportive community of mentors, (e) the social, political and historical context of computer science education, and (f) program resources.   We developed a participant recruitment and selection process that supported our broadening participation goals. As a result, approximately 75% of mentees taught at Title I schools, 57% taught at schools with large populations of Black and/or Latinx students, and 68% taught in rural or urban communities (27% and 41%, respectively).   We strategically matched mentors with mentees based on the courses they teach, school, and community context (e.g., rural/urban setting, student population), mentees' goals and mentors' strengths, and the teachers' preferences. Virtual meetings allowed us to match mentors and mentees who did not live or work in the same region.      OBJECTIVE 3: HOLD MENTORSHIP MEETINGS & COMMUNITY OF PRACTICE MEETINGS   Mentor/mentee partners met at least twice per month at mutually agreeable times. In three, 2.5-month mentoring cycles, partners worked to reflect and then set and achieve one specific professional learning goal aligned to a focal teacher standard. We estimate that mentees participated in about 20 hours of personalized professional learning in a year.   Ongoing mentor professional development consisted of a monthly, 1.5-hour, community of practice meeting with three parts:   Mentors connected and built relationships with one another, while working to troubleshoot issues and showcase best practices. Mentors developed or practiced specific, timely skills, such as refining example goals, identifying strategies and resources that will help mentees meet their goals, providing feedback, and guiding mentees' self-reflection. Mentors engaged in equity-centered professional learning.       OBJECTIVE 4: IMPROVE THE PROGRAM AND OUTCOMES WITH RESEARCH   We gathered data from mentors, mentees, and facilitators each year to address the following research questions:   (1) What support and structures facilitate quality and effective relationships between mentors and mentees?   Based on year 1 findings, we modified our supports and structures to include more meetings where all mentors and mentees came together. We also redesigned our mentoring resources so they were easier to navigate and helped participants focus on their goals. At the end of the project, participants mostly expressed positive sentiments about the resources and found them supportive of their mentoring experiences.   (2) How does MENTORS in CS support mentees' confidence, job satisfaction and commitment to teaching CS, pedagogical content knowledge, and use of equitable and inclusive teaching practices?   Mentees (a) felt an increase in their proficiency of the CSTA Standards for CS Teachers, (b) had a medium to moderate level of confidence in their equitable and inclusive teaching practices, and (c) had a medium to moderate level of confidence in their computer science teaching knowledge. The program had little impact on job satisfaction but many mentees still wanted to teach CS for many more years.   (3) How does MENTORS in CS support mentors' job satisfaction and commitment to teaching CS, confidence in teaching CS, and mentoring ability?   Mentors (a) had high confidence in their mentoring skills overall, (b) increased confidence in their computer science teaching knowledge, and (c) had a medium level of confidence in using equitable and inclusive teaching practices. The program had little impact on job satisfaction but many mentees still wanted to teach CS for many more years.      DEVELOP A HEALTHY RESEARCH/PRACTICE PARTNERSHIP (RPP)   We sought to develop an effective RPP team across CSTA, WestEd, and CSTA Wisconsin Dairyland. Biannual pulse surveys, recurring team discussions, and reports from our external advisory board indicate a healthy partnership that strengthened across the three years of our collaboration.   In late 2023, our team secured funding for a mid-sized NSF CSforAll RPP grant (Award #2318232) that will enable us to expand to two additional communities: CSTA New Jersey and CSTA's Black Affinity Group. We will welcome four new practitioner partners into our RPP while working to support 76 mentoring partnerships across three years, reaching approximately 10,000 students total.     Last Modified: 02/26/2024       Submitted by: BryanTwarek]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
