<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Implications of Solar Radiation Management for Strategic Behavior and Climate Governance]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>396274.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>396274</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With recent scientific reports warning of serious global impacts if greenhouse gas emissions are not quickly curtailed, some nations or other entities may be inclined to pursue a technological climate management strategy that does not require international cooperation. Solar radiation management (SRM) is emerging as the leading candidate from among a variety of potential “geoengineering” technologies. SRM seeks to increase the amount of sunlight reflected back into space to offset the heat-trapping effects of GHG emissions. One approach, which involves widespread release of reflective particles in the stratosphere, is expected to be especially cheap and fast‐acting. This means that a single nation that is especially vulnerable to climate change may decide to deploy SRM, even if it is potentially detrimental to other nations. This research project is designed to investigate how the potential availability and implementation of geoengineering is likely to impact future climate action and impacts. The research team also explores the ways in which alternative international governance frameworks might promote strategies that lead to the greatest global benefit. The project advances existing theory and models of climate action by considering the potential evolution of decision making as climate change becomes more urgent and nations struggle to reach a cooperative solution. This theoretical advancement is reinforced by behavioral laboratory experiments as well as computer model simulations. By providing insight into the wider ramifications of geoengineering, The research is timely and socially relevant. Specifically, the researchers broaden the impact of the work via three main mechanisms: (i) Direct engagement of domestic and international climate policymakers, to improve mutual understanding of the implications of SRM; (ii) Translation and dissemination of our modeling and experimental tools and results for application to other problems in science and technology policy; (iii) Provision of socially relevant experiences for diverse students that develop their capacity to communicate with decision makers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Climate change is a typical public goods problem, requiring collective action to successfully co-manage. Global collective action on climate change is a challenge, however, as each potential actor has an incentive to “free‐ride” on the actions of others. This leads to insufficient overall action – the so‐called “tragedy of the commons.” This situation may be transformed, however, by the potential of solar radiation management (SRM) as a non‐cooperative climate change management strategy. In particular, the injection of reflective particles into the stratosphere may be a sufficiently cheap and easy means of cooling the earth to be feasibly implemented by a single nation. However, SRM is an imperfect solution as it is short‐lived and has its own risks and governance challenges. In this project, we seek to understand the potential impacts of SRM on future climate management strategy, the prospects of cooperative action, and the role of international governance. Key research questions include: Under what conditions will SRM encourage free‐riding, free‐driving, or cooperation? Will nations reserve SRM as a last resort, or implement it before it is necessary? What role can SRM play in a climate management portfolio that includes mitigation and adaptation? How will heterogeneity among nations in their preference for SRM impact the potential for cooperation? How can international institutions rein in any free‐driver impetus created by SRM while incentivizing cooperation? This project addresses these and other research questions by connecting theory, model simulation, and experiment in pursuit of three specific aims: 1. Develop and analyze a game theoretic model of the dynamics of international climate cooperation when some nations have the ability to implement SRM. 2. Design and implement experimental games that represent the key features of SRM to test the theoretic model against actual behavior and to inform development of an agent‐based simulation. 3. Simulate and field test alternative&lt;br/&gt;frameworks for international governance and institutional design that promote climate strategies with the greatest social benefit. While our project is motivated by the prospect of SRM as a non‐cooperative, short‐term solution to climate change, insights from our project are potentially applicable to any situation in which a risky technology is being presented as a quick fix for problems traditionally addressed through collective action. Finally, the project team addresses opportunities for transferring the theory, modelling, and experimental rameworks to other settings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033855</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
<LastName>Cherry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Todd L Cherry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tcherry@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000249810</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 E UNIVERSITY AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y00</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>132100</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~126430</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~126061</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~143783</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In 2020, the University of Wyoming received a collaborative research award with Duke University entitled &ldquo;Collaborative Research: Implications of Solar Radiation Management for Strategic Behavior and Climate Governance.&rdquo; The project investigated the ramifications of the emergence of solar radiation management (SRM), which is a collection of large-scale interventions to cool the planet by managing the amount of solar radiation that reaches the Earth. As global emissions of greenhouse gases (GHG) continue to increase, experts increasingly believe SRM may be a necessary option to offset excessive warming and avoid the most damaging impacts of climate change. SRM has the potential to reduce global temperatures quickly with existing technology and at a relatively low cost. However, SRM complicates the politics of climate change because, while mitigation calls for collective action, the low cost of SGE allows a single country to unilaterally decide the level of SGE deployed. Thus, a single country or a small group of countries could potentially determine the global average temperature, which likely differs from what other countries prefer. Such unconstrained unilateral action may provoke international conflict. Thus, it is important to understand the challenges of governing SRM and the implications of failing to govern SAI.</p> <p>Given SRM technologies have not been intentionally deployed, the opportunities for researchers to study the impacts are limited. The project therefore employed a multi-method approach to create a diverse combination of theoretical and empirical evidence, including game-theoretic modeling, survey experiments, incentivized laboratory experiments, agent base modeling, and surveys of international climate policy experts. The findings can be organized into the following three topics. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>SGE and Mitigation. </strong>&nbsp;A leading concern is that the emergence of SGE will lessen efforts to reduce GHG emissions. However, some experts suggest that SGE may serve as a clarion call that will increase efforts to mitigate emissions. The project produced several studies to understand the behavioral underpinnings of this potential response and related outcomes. First, while game-theoretic models predict the introduction of SGE will lessen efforts to mitigate GHG emissions, the empirical evidence from a series of incentivized behavioral experiments indicate the opposite outcome. This finding suggests that the threat of SGE reduces the need for SGE. However, findings also highlight the complexity of this issue by showing that, as SGE becomes more effective and less risky, the improvements in the technologies will begin to reduce investment in mitigation. Another complexity identified by the research is that the response to SGE will differ for individual actors/countries based on how SGE helps or harms them. Thus, the aggregate impact of SGE on mitigation will depend on the relative size or distribution of these different countries.</p> <p><strong>Free-Driver and Anti-Driver.</strong>&nbsp; Another prominent concern with the emergence of SGE technologies is that the country that prefers the greatest SGE intervention will unilaterally deploy SGE at levels higher than the global optimum. The so-called &ldquo;free driver&rdquo; can set the level of SGE and level of cooling for the planet. The project&rsquo;s research provides theoretical and empirical evidence that free-driving behavior does lead to excessive SGE but not at the extremes predicted by theory. One study from the project finds that countries may take action to counter SGE deployment, which results in costly conflicts with little change in the final outcome. A significant contribution from this research is the concept of the &ldquo;anti-driver&rdquo;&mdash;countries that increase mitigation efforts to reduce the free driver&rsquo;s preferred level of SGE; thereby protecting themselves from the free driver&rsquo;s unilateral actions. The strategic interplay between the free-driver and anti-drivers is an important contribution to our understanding of the potential impact of SGE, in part, because it indicates that SGE technologies provide leverage that may shift the geopolitical landscape of climate negotiations.</p> <p><strong>Global Governance.</strong>&nbsp; There is widespread recognition that international governance of SGE technologies is a daunting challenge. Considering governance requires an understanding of the underlying behavior, which is why the project examined both strategic behavior and governance. SGE complicates climate policy because, while reducing GHG emissions requires advancing collective action, SGE deployment requires preventing unilateral action. The fundamental goal of SGE governance is to restrain unilateral action to meet a collective target. The project&rsquo;s research provides new evidence on how the emergence of SGE affects international climate agreements. For instance, compared to a world without SGE technologies, SGE technologies may lead to more effective international climate agreements when the technologies impose greater harm to some members. Also, the project collected and synthesized assessments of international climate policy experts and found them to be quite pessimistic about the likelihood for the global community to develop effective governance for SGE. Experts also anticipate international responses to unilateral development and deployment of SGE.</p> <p><strong>Summary:</strong> Research from this project created new knowledge about several potential implications of SRM technologies. The findings inform future research efforts on SRM and ongoing deliberations of international climate policy.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/29/2024<br> Modified by: Todd&nbsp;L&nbsp;Cherry</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  In 2020, the University of Wyoming received a collaborative research award with Duke University entitled Collaborative Research: Implications of Solar Radiation Management for Strategic Behavior and Climate Governance. The project investigated the ramifications of the emergence of solar radiation management (SRM), which is a collection of large-scale interventions to cool the planet by managing the amount of solar radiation that reaches the Earth. As global emissions of greenhouse gases (GHG) continue to increase, experts increasingly believe SRM may be a necessary option to offset excessive warming and avoid the most damaging impacts of climate change. SRM has the potential to reduce global temperatures quickly with existing technology and at a relatively low cost. However, SRM complicates the politics of climate change because, while mitigation calls for collective action, the low cost of SGE allows a single country to unilaterally decide the level of SGE deployed. Thus, a single country or a small group of countries could potentially determine the global average temperature, which likely differs from what other countries prefer. Such unconstrained unilateral action may provoke international conflict. Thus, it is important to understand the challenges of governing SRM and the implications of failing to govern SAI.   Given SRM technologies have not been intentionally deployed, the opportunities for researchers to study the impacts are limited. The project therefore employed a multi-method approach to create a diverse combination of theoretical and empirical evidence, including game-theoretic modeling, survey experiments, incentivized laboratory experiments, agent base modeling, and surveys of international climate policy experts. The findings can be organized into the following three topics.    SGE and Mitigation. A leading concern is that the emergence of SGE will lessen efforts to reduce GHG emissions. However, some experts suggest that SGE may serve as a clarion call that will increase efforts to mitigate emissions. The project produced several studies to understand the behavioral underpinnings of this potential response and related outcomes. First, while game-theoretic models predict the introduction of SGE will lessen efforts to mitigate GHG emissions, the empirical evidence from a series of incentivized behavioral experiments indicate the opposite outcome. This finding suggests that the threat of SGE reduces the need for SGE. However, findings also highlight the complexity of this issue by showing that, as SGE becomes more effective and less risky, the improvements in the technologies will begin to reduce investment in mitigation. Another complexity identified by the research is that the response to SGE will differ for individual actors/countries based on how SGE helps or harms them. Thus, the aggregate impact of SGE on mitigation will depend on the relative size or distribution of these different countries.   Free-Driver and Anti-Driver. Another prominent concern with the emergence of SGE technologies is that the country that prefers the greatest SGE intervention will unilaterally deploy SGE at levels higher than the global optimum. The so-called free driver can set the level of SGE and level of cooling for the planet. The projects research provides theoretical and empirical evidence that free-driving behavior does lead to excessive SGE but not at the extremes predicted by theory. One study from the project finds that countries may take action to counter SGE deployment, which results in costly conflicts with little change in the final outcome. A significant contribution from this research is the concept of the anti-drivercountries that increase mitigation efforts to reduce the free drivers preferred level of SGE; thereby protecting themselves from the free drivers unilateral actions. The strategic interplay between the free-driver and anti-drivers is an important contribution to our understanding of the potential impact of SGE, in part, because it indicates that SGE technologies provide leverage that may shift the geopolitical landscape of climate negotiations.   Global Governance. There is widespread recognition that international governance of SGE technologies is a daunting challenge. Considering governance requires an understanding of the underlying behavior, which is why the project examined both strategic behavior and governance. SGE complicates climate policy because, while reducing GHG emissions requires advancing collective action, SGE deployment requires preventing unilateral action. The fundamental goal of SGE governance is to restrain unilateral action to meet a collective target. The projects research provides new evidence on how the emergence of SGE affects international climate agreements. For instance, compared to a world without SGE technologies, SGE technologies may lead to more effective international climate agreements when the technologies impose greater harm to some members. Also, the project collected and synthesized assessments of international climate policy experts and found them to be quite pessimistic about the likelihood for the global community to develop effective governance for SGE. Experts also anticipate international responses to unilateral development and deployment of SGE.   Summary: Research from this project created new knowledge about several potential implications of SRM technologies. The findings inform future research efforts on SRM and ongoing deliberations of international climate policy.     Last Modified: 07/29/2024       Submitted by: ToddLCherry]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
