<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Self-Centering Pendulum Shear Walls in Buildings via Nonlinear Elastic Kinematics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>339690.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>339690</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A grand challenge in structural engineering is to develop building systems that can resist loads from extreme natural hazards, such as hurricanes or earthquakes, with minimum or no damage. Such building systems could enable immediate occupancy and minimum economic losses after an extreme event, contributing to continued national prosperity and welfare. Progress has been made towards addressing this challenge with the development of unbonded, post-tensioned, shear walls (UPSWs) in buildings; yet limiting issues for designing such shear walls remain. This research will explore an innovative concept for structural shear walls to resist lateral loads in buildings and perform damage free during an extreme event. The concept consists of coupled, unbonded, post-tensioned, reinforced concrete walls that interact with the foundation via a curved surface. Lateral deformations will be accommodated through a pendulum-type motion as the wall slides along the bottom curved surface. Lateral resistance will be provided by friction along the curved surface and the vertical unbonded post-tensioned cables. The post-tensioned cables also will help restore the wall to its initial configuration. Energy dissipation of these coupled pendulum walls will be provided by incorporating connecting devices that use elastic buckling and release accumulated elastic energy during the walls' deformations. The system response thus will leverage the resulting deformations rather than trying to constrain them, as in traditional systems. The result will be new technology related to the design of damage-free structural building systems, and a new way of thinking about leveraging system geometry and deformations for enhanced resilient and sustainable buildings. Parallel to the research effort will be complementary educational and outreach components, including the training of two Ph.D. students, research experiences for undergraduate students, a project website with tutorials and research findings for undergraduate and graduate students and practitioners, and outreach activities for middle and high school students.  The tutorials, as well as data from this project, also will be made publicly available in the NSF-supported Natural Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure Data Depot (https://www.designsafe-ci.org). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The core idea of this research is that of a new design philosophy envisioned to be unrestricted by traditional material failure limit states. This philosophy will be verified through a new concept for coupled UPSWs. The material response limitations of rocking UPSWs will be addressed by harnessing the nonlinear kinematic behavior resulting from coupled system deformations. Thus, the project objective is to develop the enabling theory and technology for a new concept of UPSWs that can perform damage free and unrestricted by material failure limit states. This objective will be achieved through two unique and complementary features: (1) individual walls gliding along a circular path with no separation at the footing interface, and (2) continuous energy dissipation via devices with controllable elastic instabilities along vertical wall joints. This concept will be designated as a pendulum UPSW system, as it rotates about a fixed point on the wall. The approach to be followed will be to characterize the in-plane response of pendulum UPSWs as viable lateral load resisting elements, develop and characterize the use of elastic meta-materials and meta-structures for dissipating energy via elastic instabilities, and characterize the response of pendulum UPSWs coupled with elastic multi-stable structures as connectors. A combination of analytical, numerical (finite element), and experimental methods will be used. This research will lead to the fundamental integration of system geometry and deformations for the design of lateral load resisting structures that are resilient and sustainable. The study will promote new design concepts that harness deformations for optimal performance rather than performance objectives set to target material limit states. The research also will contribute to the use of nonlinear elastic instabilities in large-scale structural systems. Theory and methods related to damage-free structural systems, friction models, and elastic energy dissipation devices will also be advanced.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035690</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rigoberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Burgueno</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rigoberto Burgueno</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rigoberto.burgueno@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000488055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>014Y00</Code>
<Text>Engineering for Natural Hazard</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7231</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~339690</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A new concept for unbonded post-tensioned shear walls was investigated with the objective of obtaining a system that performs damage-free and is self-centering under lateral loads from extreme events. The concept uses the complementary features of two systems: (1) a wall geometry with a circular profile at the footing interface, and (2) energy dissipation devices based elastic instabilities for use in coupled walls. This system is designated as a pendulum unbonded post-tensioned shear wall (UPSW) since the wall element rotates about a fixed point as it glides along the circular wall-base interface. The pendulum motion ensures that full contact is maintained between the wall and its base, resulting in negligible stress concentrations and energy dissipation through friction at the interface. For coupled pendulum UPSWs, supplemental energy dissipation and self-centering capabilities is provided by novel connectors that behave elastically yet provide hysteretic energy dissipation. Pendulum UPSWs address the limitations of traditional UPSWs with a flat interface, namely: concrete crushing at the wall toes, yielding of tendons, wall walking, and the need for supplemental energy dissipation.</p> <p>Elastic energy dissipation is possible by controlling the sequential snap-through elastic instabilities of periodically arranged slender elastic elements (units). The individual units exhibit a tailorable elastic limit-point response (snap-through instability) with a negative stiffness region. Their strategic arrangement and connection allows the generation of consecutive elastic snap-through buckling events that results in a hysteretic response with self-centering capability. Two novel elastic energy dissipating systems were developed through analytical, numerical and experimental studies. First, an energy-dissipative material that uses inclined beams in the microstructure of the material architecture, was shown to manage the strain energy generated due to cyclic shear deformations and dissipate it through sequential snap-through instabilities. The second system consists of an arrangement in series of shallow cosine-curved domes, or multiple-cosine-curved-domes (MCCD) that results in an elastic flag-type hysteretic response with self-centering capabilities. The devices&rsquo; stiffness, strength, deformation capacity and energy absorption can be optimized through the design of the individual units and their geometrical arrangement. Both systems display repeatable response without damage and are insensitive to loading rate.</p> <p>Full-scale experimental evaluation of the proposed pendulum UPSW concept was conducted at George Washington University through the collaborative elements of this project. Two experimental phases were conducted: proof-of-concept testing of a single/isolated pendulum light-frame wood (LiF) UPSW unit, and testing on two isolated precast concrete (PC) UPSW units that varied in the radius of the wall-base circular profile. Since the walls remained undamaged, a series of tests were performed on the noted units for varying levels of post-tensioning (PT) force, surface preparation of the wall-base interface, and loading rates. Experimental results showed that the circular wall-base profile led to a predominant gliding motion of the wall element along the base interface without uplift. Testing also demonstrated that friction and loading rate are critical components to obtain the desired pendulum motion. Additionally, increasing the applied PT force leads to an increase in the lateral load capacity and the energy dissipation capacity of isolated pendulum UPSWs. Compared with rocking UPSWs, test results demonstrated that pendulum UPSWs offer the following promising outcomes: (1) a damage-free response to high drift levels, (2) insignificant wall base sliding, (3) reduced stress concentrations at the wall toes, (4) nearly constant post-tensioning forces at high drift levels, and (5) increased energy dissipation capacity from friction at the wall-base interface.</p> <p>Nonlinear finite element (FE) analyses were conducted to study the pseudo-static and dynamic behavior of isolated/single UPSWs and dual UPSWs coupled with MCCD energy dissipation devices. The FE models were also used for the characterization of the curved interface of UPSWs, namely the effect of radius, coefficient of friction, and effective post-tensioning force on the desired sliding motion at the wall-base interface and the resulting energy dissipation. Results indicate that the PT level, base radius, and coefficient of friction significantly influence the stiffness and energy dissipation capacity of the wall systems. The FE models also adequately captured the lateral response of the single pendulum UPSWs tested at GWU. Implementation of MCCD systems as connectors between pendulum UPSWs demonstrated their potential for enhancing the performance of coupled walls by increasing their lateral stiffness, energy dissipation, and self-centering capability; with better effectiveness under larger displacements. The analyses enhanced understanding on the performance of pendulum UPSWs and validated the functionality of elastic energy dissipation devices for coupled wall systems.</p> <p>Knowledge generated from the project was disseminated through archived journal publications, MS and Ph.D. theses, and technical presentations. The project allowed support and research training of four MS students and three Ph.D. students.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/25/2024<br> Modified by: Rigoberto&nbsp;Burgueno</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884803277_Fig_3_MCCD_Modeling_and_Characterization--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884803277_Fig_3_MCCD_Modeling_and_Characterization--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MCCD Modeling and Characterization"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884803277_Fig_3_MCCD_Modeling_and_Characterization--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MCCD Modeling and Characterization"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Multiple cosine curved dome (MCCD) energy dissipating device. (a,b) Characterization of single cosine curved dome (CCD). (c) Testing of MCCD system. (d) Analytical response and idealized response of MCCD. (e) Experimental and analytical response of MCCD system.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mansour Alturki, Rigoberto Burgueno</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rigoberto&nbsp;Burgueno <div class="imageTitle">MCCD Modeling and Characterization</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885442742_Fig_5_Experimental_Validation_of_UPSW_FEA_Model--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885442742_Fig_5_Experimental_Validation_of_UPSW_FEA_Model--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experimental Validation of Pendulum UPSW FEA Model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885442742_Fig_5_Experimental_Validation_of_UPSW_FEA_Model--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experimental Validation of Pendulum UPSW FEA Model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Experimental evaluation and finite element simulation of isolated reinforced concrete pendulum unbonded post-tensioned shear wall. (a,b) Test setup at George Washington University. (c) Loading protocol. (d,e) Force-deformation response for post-tensioning (PT) levels of 20 and 40 kips.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pedro F. Silva, Darla-Ena Boyer, Rigoberto Burgueno</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rigoberto&nbsp;Burgueno <div class="imageTitle">Experimental Validation of Pendulum UPSW FEA Model</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885160466_Fig_4_FEA_of_Single_UPSWs_and_Parametric_Study--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885160466_Fig_4_FEA_of_Single_UPSWs_and_Parametric_Study--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FEA of Single Pendulum UPSWs"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885160466_Fig_4_FEA_of_Single_UPSWs_and_Parametric_Study--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FEA of Single Pendulum UPSWs"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Finite element characterization of isolated pendulum UPSWs under pseudo-static cyclic loading. (a) FE model. (b,c) Wall-base contact interaction definition. (d) Force-deformation response. (e) Variation of PT force during loading. (f) Shear vs. normal force at wall-base interface.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Darla-Ena Boyer, Daniel Ruiz, Rigoberto Burgueno</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rigoberto&nbsp;Burgueno <div class="imageTitle">FEA of Single Pendulum UPSWs</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884480761_Fig_1_Pendulum_UPSW_Concept--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884480761_Fig_1_Pendulum_UPSW_Concept--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pendulum UPSW Concept"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884480761_Fig_1_Pendulum_UPSW_Concept--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pendulum UPSW Concept"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Concept of pendulum unbonded post-tensioned shear walls (UPSW) coupled with elastic energy dissipators. (a) Schematic of coupled UPSWs. (b) Schematic response and prototype of an elastic energy dissipator. (c) Results from finite element simulation showing how pendulum motion of the UPSWs walls.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pedro F. Silva, Rigoberto Burgueno</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rigoberto&nbsp;Burgueno <div class="imageTitle">Pendulum UPSW Concept</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884677375_Fig_2_Shear_Energy_Dissipation_Device--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884677375_Fig_2_Shear_Energy_Dissipation_Device--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Shear Energy Dissipation Device"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729884677375_Fig_2_Shear_Energy_Dissipation_Device--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Shear Energy Dissipation Device"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Shear energy dissipating device. (a) Schematic of unit element. (b) Initial and deformed configurations of single-beam unit. (c) Prototype for half-cycle loading and experimental response.  (d) Prototype for full-cycle loading and experimental response</div> <div class="imageCredit">Suihan Liu, Rigoberto Burgueno</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rigoberto&nbsp;Burgueno <div class="imageTitle">Shear Energy Dissipation Device</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885690606_Fig_6_FEA_of_Coupled_Pendulum_UPSWs--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885690606_Fig_6_FEA_of_Coupled_Pendulum_UPSWs--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FEA of Coupled Pendulum UPSWs"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2035690/2035690_10543950_1729885690606_Fig_6_FEA_of_Coupled_Pendulum_UPSWs--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FEA of Coupled Pendulum UPSWs"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Finite element evaluation of coupled pendulum unbonded post-tensioned shear walls (UPSW) under earthquake loading. (a) FE model of UPSWs coupled with MCCD energy dissipators. (b) Simulation results displaying pendulum motion. (c) Time-history response coupled UPSWs. (e) Response of MCCD connectors.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Daniel Ruiz, Pedro F. Silva, Rigoberto Burgueno</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rigoberto&nbsp;Burgueno <div class="imageTitle">FEA of Coupled Pendulum UPSWs</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  A new concept for unbonded post-tensioned shear walls was investigated with the objective of obtaining a system that performs damage-free and is self-centering under lateral loads from extreme events. The concept uses the complementary features of two systems: (1) a wall geometry with a circular profile at the footing interface, and (2) energy dissipation devices based elastic instabilities for use in coupled walls. This system is designated as a pendulum unbonded post-tensioned shear wall (UPSW) since the wall element rotates about a fixed point as it glides along the circular wall-base interface. The pendulum motion ensures that full contact is maintained between the wall and its base, resulting in negligible stress concentrations and energy dissipation through friction at the interface. For coupled pendulum UPSWs, supplemental energy dissipation and self-centering capabilities is provided by novel connectors that behave elastically yet provide hysteretic energy dissipation. Pendulum UPSWs address the limitations of traditional UPSWs with a flat interface, namely: concrete crushing at the wall toes, yielding of tendons, wall walking, and the need for supplemental energy dissipation.   Elastic energy dissipation is possible by controlling the sequential snap-through elastic instabilities of periodically arranged slender elastic elements (units). The individual units exhibit a tailorable elastic limit-point response (snap-through instability) with a negative stiffness region. Their strategic arrangement and connection allows the generation of consecutive elastic snap-through buckling events that results in a hysteretic response with self-centering capability. Two novel elastic energy dissipating systems were developed through analytical, numerical and experimental studies. First, an energy-dissipative material that uses inclined beams in the microstructure of the material architecture, was shown to manage the strain energy generated due to cyclic shear deformations and dissipate it through sequential snap-through instabilities. The second system consists of an arrangement in series of shallow cosine-curved domes, or multiple-cosine-curved-domes (MCCD) that results in an elastic flag-type hysteretic response with self-centering capabilities. The devices stiffness, strength, deformation capacity and energy absorption can be optimized through the design of the individual units and their geometrical arrangement. Both systems display repeatable response without damage and are insensitive to loading rate.   Full-scale experimental evaluation of the proposed pendulum UPSW concept was conducted at George Washington University through the collaborative elements of this project. Two experimental phases were conducted: proof-of-concept testing of a single/isolated pendulum light-frame wood (LiF) UPSW unit, and testing on two isolated precast concrete (PC) UPSW units that varied in the radius of the wall-base circular profile. Since the walls remained undamaged, a series of tests were performed on the noted units for varying levels of post-tensioning (PT) force, surface preparation of the wall-base interface, and loading rates. Experimental results showed that the circular wall-base profile led to a predominant gliding motion of the wall element along the base interface without uplift. Testing also demonstrated that friction and loading rate are critical components to obtain the desired pendulum motion. Additionally, increasing the applied PT force leads to an increase in the lateral load capacity and the energy dissipation capacity of isolated pendulum UPSWs. Compared with rocking UPSWs, test results demonstrated that pendulum UPSWs offer the following promising outcomes: (1) a damage-free response to high drift levels, (2) insignificant wall base sliding, (3) reduced stress concentrations at the wall toes, (4) nearly constant post-tensioning forces at high drift levels, and (5) increased energy dissipation capacity from friction at the wall-base interface.   Nonlinear finite element (FE) analyses were conducted to study the pseudo-static and dynamic behavior of isolated/single UPSWs and dual UPSWs coupled with MCCD energy dissipation devices. The FE models were also used for the characterization of the curved interface of UPSWs, namely the effect of radius, coefficient of friction, and effective post-tensioning force on the desired sliding motion at the wall-base interface and the resulting energy dissipation. Results indicate that the PT level, base radius, and coefficient of friction significantly influence the stiffness and energy dissipation capacity of the wall systems. The FE models also adequately captured the lateral response of the single pendulum UPSWs tested at GWU. Implementation of MCCD systems as connectors between pendulum UPSWs demonstrated their potential for enhancing the performance of coupled walls by increasing their lateral stiffness, energy dissipation, and self-centering capability; with better effectiveness under larger displacements. The analyses enhanced understanding on the performance of pendulum UPSWs and validated the functionality of elastic energy dissipation devices for coupled wall systems.   Knowledge generated from the project was disseminated through archived journal publications, MS and Ph.D. theses, and technical presentations. The project allowed support and research training of four MS students and three Ph.D. students.     Last Modified: 10/25/2024       Submitted by: RigobertoBurgueno]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
