<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSFGEO-NERC: Collaborative Research: Subpolar North Atlantic Processes - Dynamics and pRedictability of vAriability in Gyre and OverturNing (SNAP-DRAGON)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>127342.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>127342</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Baris Uz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmuz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is a project that is jointly funded by the National Science Foundation's Directorate of Geosciences (NSF/GEO) and the National Environment Research Council (NERC) of the United Kingdom (UK) via the NSF/GEO-NERC Lead Agency Agreement. This Agreement allows a single joint US/UK proposal to be submitted and peer-reviewed by the Agency whose investigator has the largest proportion of the budget. Upon successful joint determination of an award, each Agency funds the proportion of the budget and the investigators associated with their own country. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The subpolar North Atlantic Ocean, stretching between the UK, Greenland, and Canada, plays a crucial role in local and global climate. This is the critical region where much of the warm water flowing northward in the upper North Atlantic releases its heat to the atmosphere and is converted to cold, dense water, before flowing southward again at depth in what is known as the Atlantic overturning circulation. The large amount of heat this circulation carries northward and releases to the atmosphere impacts the track of storms and determines the weather over western Europe. The overturning circulation also has profound implications for African rainfall and hurricane development via its effect on sea surface temperature at lower latitudes. In addition, the sinking of water in the subpolar region ventilates the deep ocean, transferring heat and carbon away from the surface and moderating the impact of anthropogenic greenhouse gases on surface temperature. Any warm water which does not sink in the subpolar region recirculates or carries its heat further north towards the Arctic, influencing sea-ice conditions and polar marine ecosystems before it too sinks and flows south. This study aims to produce a step change in our understanding of the processes that link atmospheric changes to subpolar ocean variability, their implications for ocean and climate predictability in this region, and the degree to which we can trust their representation in climate models. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recently, the first ever observations of the overturning circulation in the subpolar North Atlantic have been made by the Overturning in the Subpolar North Atlantic Program (OSNAP, www.o-snap.org). These have revealed large amplitude variations in the overturning and raised questions about the locations and processes that give rise to this variability and its likely impact on surface ocean conditions and climate. Representing this region properly in climate models is essential for making useful climate predictions on seasonal, interannual, decadal and longer timescales. However, the current generation of models struggle to represent the processes known to be important here and disagree with the observations on the locations in which warm water is transformed into dense water. The disagreements limit our confidence in model predictions. The scientific community cannot assess model performance properly because there is limited understanding of all the links between atmospheric conditions and ocean circulation variability. This project will combine OSNAP and other observations with numerical models that can represent small-scale processes to reveal the cause of the variations in subpolar ocean circulation. Once it is clear which processes are most important and how they work, the team will be able to establish what climate models are getting wrong and suggest improvements. This will improve predictions of ocean and climate variability in the subpolar North Atlantic and beyond. The team will investigate how cold, dense waters find their way into the boundary currents that export them to the south. It will establish the role that winds play, which is likely more complicated than we have assumed in the past and it will determine the impact on overturning variability of changes in freshwater export from the Arctic and Greenland. To characterize and quantify these key processes, in addition to using ocean observations, the investigators will perform "What if?" experiments in ocean models, asking questions such as: what happens to the subpolar ocean circulation if the atmospheric jet stream over the Atlantic shifts or strengthens? They will use statistical methods more common in weather forecasting to figure out how subpolar ocean properties and overturning connect to potentially predictable larger-scale atmospheric circulation patterns. Innovative ways of combining models with observations will be used to determine a best estimate of the evolution of the subpolar North Atlantic over the OSNAP observation period.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2038449</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Chassignet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric P Chassignet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[echassignet@coaps.fsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000482395</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaobiao</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaobiao Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xxu3@fsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000641690</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323060001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[874 TRADITIONS WAY]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF2BLNN4PJC3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University, COAPS]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323062741</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2000 Levy Avenue, Research Build]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>161000</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~127342</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Large-scale ocean currents carry and redistribute heat and freshwater throughout different part of ocean basins, hence play an important role in the earth climate system. Numerical models that can truthfully represent these currents are a useful tool for our understanding of the mechanisms behind the change in these currents. The overall goal of the UK-US collaborative project &ldquo;Subpolar North Atlantic Processes&rdquo; is to use observations and numerical models to improve our understanding of the currents in the subpolar North Atlantic. Our research focused on numerical models of the North Atlantic Ocean, and we tackled basic questions like how important is vertical resolution (that is to resolve different water masses in the ocean) in representing these currents? Do small scale bathymetry details matter in the pathway and variability of the major current like the Gulf Stream? And what is nature of the variability that is in the subpolar North Atlantic? The main outcomes of the project include 3 scientific papers (2 led by the PIs) published in<em> Journal of Physical Oceanography </em>and<em> Ocean modelling</em>, and 1 manuscript to be submitted to&nbsp;<em>Journal of Geophysical Research-Oceans</em>. These studies help us understand the detail spatial structure of these currents as part of the basin scale ocean circulation that is fundamental to the earth climate system.</p> <p>The selected five figures in this outcome report highlight</p> <p>a)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; the impact of relatively small details in the bathymetry of the New England Seamount Chain on the path and variability of the Gulf Stream. The results are based on 1/50&deg; simulations and they show that including the fine-scale details of the New England Seamount Chain led to a more realistic path and variability pattern as observed (Figure 1).</p> <p>b)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; the impact of vertical resolution on the spatial structure of the Atlantic circulation. The results are based on 1/12&deg; simulations and they show that, as the vertical resolution increases, the vertical structure of the modeled AMOC streamfunction is improved toward a closer agreement with the observations (Figure 2). The difference from 24 to 96 layer, however, is relatively small, indicating that the modeled AMOC structure is robust when the vertical resolution is adequate for a reasonable representation of the key water masses in the North Atlantic. Similarly, these four models with vertical resolution ranging from 24 to 96 layers represent a similar the horizontal circulation pattern that agree with the observations (Figure 3).</p> <p>c)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; the AMOC variability in the subpolar North Atlantic. The results based on interannually forced nature run show that the model represent a significant part of the observed AMOC variability (Figure 4). The seasonal variability of the AMOC is contributed from the variability in the East Greenland Current, which is modulated by the up and down movements in density surfaces due to seasonal warming/cooling in the western Irminger Sea (Figure 5); the shorter, intraseasonal variability is primarily contributed directly from the wind variability over the full trans-Atlantic section through Ekman transport.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Xu, X., Chassignet, E. P., and A. J. Wallcraft, 2023, Impact of vertical resolution on representing baroclinic modes and water mass distribution in the North Atlantic,&nbsp;<em>Ocean Modelling</em>, doi: 10.1016/j.ocemod.2023.102261.</p> <p>Chassignet, E. P., X. Xu, A. Bozec, and T. Uchida, 2023, Impact of the New England seamount chain on Gulf Stream pathway and variability, Journal of Physical Oceanography, doi:10.1175/JPO-D-23-0008.1</p> <p>Lozier, M. S., A. S. Bower, H. H. Furey, K. L. Drouin, X. Xu, and S. Zou, 2022, Overflow water pathways in the North Atlantic,&nbsp;<em>Progress in Oceanography</em>, doi:10.1016/j.pocean.2022.102874</p> <p>Xu, X. and E. P. Chassignet, 2024, Subpolar North Atlantic in 2014-2020, what do we learn from comparing high-resolution numerical simulation and observations? manuscript to be submitted to&nbsp;<em>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</em></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/31/2024<br> Modified by: Xiaobiao&nbsp;Xu</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406313689_Outcome_Figure02--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406313689_Outcome_Figure02--rgov-800width.png" title="Impact of vertical resolution on representing the vertical structure of the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (AMOC)."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406313689_Outcome_Figure02--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Impact of vertical resolution on representing the vertical structure of the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (AMOC)."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The vertical structure of the AMOC streamfunction based on observations (black) and 5 simulations with different vertical resolution (16 to 96 layers), showing as the resolution improves the model AMOC agrees better with the observations.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xiaobiao</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaobiao&nbsp;Xu <div class="imageTitle">Impact of vertical resolution on representing the vertical structure of the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (AMOC).</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406541475_Outcome_Figure03--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406541475_Outcome_Figure03--rgov-800width.png" title="Impact of vertical resolution on horizontal structure of the Atlantic circulation."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406541475_Outcome_Figure03--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Impact of vertical resolution on horizontal structure of the Atlantic circulation."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">time averaged sea surface height (in cm) from a) observations and 5 models with vertical resolution ranging from 16 to 96 layers. Other than low resolution 16-layer case, 4 models represent the circulation pattern similar to the observations.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xiaobiao</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaobiao&nbsp;Xu <div class="imageTitle">Impact of vertical resolution on horizontal structure of the Atlantic circulation.</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406844679_Outcome_Figure04--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406844679_Outcome_Figure04--rgov-800width.png" title="AMOC variability in the Subpolar North Atlantic Ocean"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406844679_Outcome_Figure04--rgov-66x44.png" alt="AMOC variability in the Subpolar North Atlantic Ocean"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Variability of the AMOC transport (in Sv) across the OSNAP section in the subpolar North Atlantic: a) full, b) east, and c) west OSNAP sections. Black lines and gray shadings are the best estimates and uncertainties from observations, red lines are from a HYCOM nature simulation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xiaobiao</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaobiao&nbsp;Xu <div class="imageTitle">AMOC variability in the Subpolar North Atlantic Ocean</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406088596_Outcome_Figure01--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406088596_Outcome_Figure01--rgov-800width.png" title="impact of New England Seamount Chain on the Gulf Stream."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730406088596_Outcome_Figure01--rgov-66x44.png" alt="impact of New England Seamount Chain on the Gulf Stream."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Panel a-c) show bathymetry of New England Seamount Chain (NESC) in three 1/50 models: a) low res. NEATL, b) high-res. NEATL-HB, and c) same as NEATL-HB but with NESC removed. Panels e-g) show the SSH variability (in cm) from d) observations and three 1/50 models with different bathymetry (panel a-c)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xiaobiao Xu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaobiao&nbsp;Xu <div class="imageTitle">impact of New England Seamount Chain on the Gulf Stream.</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730407092777_Outcome_Figure05--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730407092777_Outcome_Figure05--rgov-800width.png" title="Seasonal variability of the AMOC variability in the subpolar North Atlantic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2038449/2038449_10691827_1730407092777_Outcome_Figure05--rgov-66x44.png" alt="Seasonal variability of the AMOC variability in the subpolar North Atlantic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">a) variability of the AMOC (black line) and the East Greenland Current (red, above 27.50 kg/m3), b) variability of the average depth of the isopycnal surface 27.50 kg/m3. Lines and connected dots are 30-day and 1-year averages, respectively.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xiaobiao</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaobiao&nbsp;Xu <div class="imageTitle">Seasonal variability of the AMOC variability in the subpolar North Atlantic</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Large-scale ocean currents carry and redistribute heat and freshwater throughout different part of ocean basins, hence play an important role in the earth climate system. Numerical models that can truthfully represent these currents are a useful tool for our understanding of the mechanisms behind the change in these currents. The overall goal of the UK-US collaborative project Subpolar North Atlantic Processes is to use observations and numerical models to improve our understanding of the currents in the subpolar North Atlantic. Our research focused on numerical models of the North Atlantic Ocean, and we tackled basic questions like how important is vertical resolution (that is to resolve different water masses in the ocean) in representing these currents? Do small scale bathymetry details matter in the pathway and variability of the major current like the Gulf Stream? And what is nature of the variability that is in the subpolar North Atlantic? The main outcomes of the project include 3 scientific papers (2 led by the PIs) published in Journal of Physical Oceanography and Ocean modelling, and 1 manuscript to be submitted toJournal of Geophysical Research-Oceans. These studies help us understand the detail spatial structure of these currents as part of the basin scale ocean circulation that is fundamental to the earth climate system.   The selected five figures in this outcome report highlight   a) the impact of relatively small details in the bathymetry of the New England Seamount Chain on the path and variability of the Gulf Stream. The results are based on 1/50 simulations and they show that including the fine-scale details of the New England Seamount Chain led to a more realistic path and variability pattern as observed (Figure 1).   b) the impact of vertical resolution on the spatial structure of the Atlantic circulation. The results are based on 1/12 simulations and they show that, as the vertical resolution increases, the vertical structure of the modeled AMOC streamfunction is improved toward a closer agreement with the observations (Figure 2). The difference from 24 to 96 layer, however, is relatively small, indicating that the modeled AMOC structure is robust when the vertical resolution is adequate for a reasonable representation of the key water masses in the North Atlantic. Similarly, these four models with vertical resolution ranging from 24 to 96 layers represent a similar the horizontal circulation pattern that agree with the observations (Figure 3).   c) the AMOC variability in the subpolar North Atlantic. The results based on interannually forced nature run show that the model represent a significant part of the observed AMOC variability (Figure 4). The seasonal variability of the AMOC is contributed from the variability in the East Greenland Current, which is modulated by the up and down movements in density surfaces due to seasonal warming/cooling in the western Irminger Sea (Figure 5); the shorter, intraseasonal variability is primarily contributed directly from the wind variability over the full trans-Atlantic section through Ekman transport.      Xu, X., Chassignet, E. P., and A. J. Wallcraft, 2023, Impact of vertical resolution on representing baroclinic modes and water mass distribution in the North Atlantic,Ocean Modelling, doi: 10.1016/j.ocemod.2023.102261.   Chassignet, E. P., X. Xu, A. Bozec, and T. Uchida, 2023, Impact of the New England seamount chain on Gulf Stream pathway and variability, Journal of Physical Oceanography, doi:10.1175/JPO-D-23-0008.1   Lozier, M. S., A. S. Bower, H. H. Furey, K. L. Drouin, X. Xu, and S. Zou, 2022, Overflow water pathways in the North Atlantic,Progress in Oceanography, doi:10.1016/j.pocean.2022.102874   Xu, X. and E. P. Chassignet, 2024, Subpolar North Atlantic in 2014-2020, what do we learn from comparing high-resolution numerical simulation and observations? manuscript to be submitted toJournal of Geophysical Research: Oceans     Last Modified: 10/31/2024       Submitted by: XiaobiaoXu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
