<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Code-switching in Three Groups of Bilinguals]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17588.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17588</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rachel M. Theodore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rtheodor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924770</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Language provides people with a unique means to conceptualize the world and interact with their fellow members in a society. How is this process affected when individuals speak more than one language? Although more people in the world are bilingual than are monolingual, bilingualism has only recently received attention from researchers, particularly in the U.S. Studies of language processing have shown that the interactions across the bilingual's two languages produce dynamics that are not evident in monolingual speakers, such as code-switching across the two languages in the middle of a sentence. In addition, the rich sociocultural contexts in which bilinguals use the two languages distinguish them from monolingual speakers. To better understand how bilingual language processing is influenced by the context in which languages are used, this dissertation project will examine the code-switching behavior in bilinguals who use both languages with a high level of proficiency but who live in locations in which the two languages are used differently. By demonstrating the diverse competencies of bilingual speakers, this study will investigate the cognitive benefits of bilingualism and contribute to the documentation of one of the largest minority language communities in the U.S. and around the world that has received little attention. The project will also support educational diversity by engaging a group of undergraduate research assistants who are drawn from the relevant bilingual community and who are often first-generation college students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An increasing number of studies show that there is variation among bilinguals who speak the same two languages. Adopting both psycholinguistic and sociolinguistic approaches, the planned research examines bilingual speakers' practice of code-switching in three groups of highly proficient bilinguals, with different contexts for the two languages they  speak : homeland bilinguals raised in a context in which one language is dominant while being educated in the other language; heritage bilinguals raised in a household that speaks one language within an environment where the other language is dominant; and immersed bilinguals raised in an environment in which one language is dominant but later moved for higher education to an environment in which the other language is dominant. By examining code-switched word perception and production, this study will address three questions: (1) How do variations across language acquisition and sociocultural context affect speakers' perception and production of words in the code-switching context? (2) What do code-switching practices reveal about the impact of linguistic structure? (3) What do differences in code-switching patterns across the three types of bilingual speakers reveal about the interaction between sociocultural context, cultural identity, cognition, and language processing broadly? Using code-switching as a tool to examine bilinguals' speech processing holds the promise of revealing fundamental principles of language, cognition, and social interaction that may require a revision of the traditional understanding of culture and context in language use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042479</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ariel</FirstName>
<LastName>Chan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ariel Chan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arielchan@ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818565</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Kroll</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith F Kroll</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[judith.kroll@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000187627</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shoichi</FirstName>
<LastName>Iwasaki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shoichi Iwasaki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[iwasaki@humnet.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000601433</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 Wilshire Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>837400</Code>
<Text>DDRI Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~17588</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span class="s1">While the majority of the world's population is bilingual, much of the existing bilingualism research tends to use monolingualism as the standard against which bilinguals are measured. However, an emerging body of research demonstrates that there is significant variation among bilingual individuals who speak the same two languages. Moreover, interactional contexts have been found to influence bilinguals' cognitive control and language processing.&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">This project aimed to understand the impact of language experience and cultural identity on bilingual cognitive and language processing and to develop an integrated psycholinguistic and sociolinguistic approach to study bilingualism. Using quantitative and qualitative methods, this project examined code-switching in three groups of highly proficient Cantonese-English bilinguals. These groups were differentiated by the contexts in which they use the two languages: homeland bilinguals, raised in a Cantonese-dominant environment while receiving education in English; heritage bilinguals, raised in a Cantonese-speaking household within an English-dominant environment; and immersed bilinguals, raised in a Cantonese-dominant environment but later moved to an English-dominant environment for higher education.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">One significant finding of this project is that language experience influences bilinguals' processing of code-switching words. Findings from three studies examining code-switching production and comprehension at both lexical and sentence levels indicate that language experience impacts processing time across the three groups of bilinguals to varying degrees. While heritage and homeland bilinguals consistently exhibit markedly distinct performance, immersed bilinguals' code-switching processing occasionally aligns with that of heritage bilinguals and other times with that of homeland bilinguals. This suggests that immersion experience in an environment where one language is dominant may characterize how bilinguals process their two languages.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">The second major finding of this project is the impact of cultural identity on bilinguals' code-switching processing. Regardless of their language experience, bilinguals with hybrid cultural identities demonstrate shorter processing times for code-switching words than bilinguals with alternating cultural identities. Furthermore, those with more hybrid cultural identities also exhibit greater flexibility in code-switching, evidenced by higher overall frequency, greater engagement in bi-directional code-switching between Cantonese and English, and using a broader range of grammatical categories in code-switching. This suggests that sociocultural factors, such as cultural identity, contribute to the variation in cognitive and language processing among bilinguals.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Together, these findings further support that bilingualism is not a monolithic concept predicting a uniform linguistic and cognitive outcome.</span><span class="s2">&nbsp;</span><span class="s1">Understanding the social context in which languages are used, along with considering the sociocultural environment in which bilinguals are situated, is critical for comprehending how language and the brain adapt to the environment.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">One implication of this project is that it highlights the significance of integrating sociocultural contexts into bilingualism research, contributing to developing a syncretic approach that integrates psycholinguistic and sociolinguistic perspectives. This approach may allow us to have a more unified understanding of bilingual language processing, cognitive control, social interaction, and cultural identity.</span></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 02/27/2024<br> Modified by: Ariel&nbsp;Chan</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  While the majority of the world's population is bilingual, much of the existing bilingualism research tends to use monolingualism as the standard against which bilinguals are measured. However, an emerging body of research demonstrates that there is significant variation among bilingual individuals who speak the same two languages. Moreover, interactional contexts have been found to influence bilinguals' cognitive control and language processing.   This project aimed to understand the impact of language experience and cultural identity on bilingual cognitive and language processing and to develop an integrated psycholinguistic and sociolinguistic approach to study bilingualism. Using quantitative and qualitative methods, this project examined code-switching in three groups of highly proficient Cantonese-English bilinguals. These groups were differentiated by the contexts in which they use the two languages: homeland bilinguals, raised in a Cantonese-dominant environment while receiving education in English; heritage bilinguals, raised in a Cantonese-speaking household within an English-dominant environment; and immersed bilinguals, raised in a Cantonese-dominant environment but later moved to an English-dominant environment for higher education.   One significant finding of this project is that language experience influences bilinguals' processing of code-switching words. Findings from three studies examining code-switching production and comprehension at both lexical and sentence levels indicate that language experience impacts processing time across the three groups of bilinguals to varying degrees. While heritage and homeland bilinguals consistently exhibit markedly distinct performance, immersed bilinguals' code-switching processing occasionally aligns with that of heritage bilinguals and other times with that of homeland bilinguals. This suggests that immersion experience in an environment where one language is dominant may characterize how bilinguals process their two languages.   The second major finding of this project is the impact of cultural identity on bilinguals' code-switching processing. Regardless of their language experience, bilinguals with hybrid cultural identities demonstrate shorter processing times for code-switching words than bilinguals with alternating cultural identities. Furthermore, those with more hybrid cultural identities also exhibit greater flexibility in code-switching, evidenced by higher overall frequency, greater engagement in bi-directional code-switching between Cantonese and English, and using a broader range of grammatical categories in code-switching. This suggests that sociocultural factors, such as cultural identity, contribute to the variation in cognitive and language processing among bilinguals.   Together, these findings further support that bilingualism is not a monolithic concept predicting a uniform linguistic and cognitive outcome.Understanding the social context in which languages are used, along with considering the sociocultural environment in which bilinguals are situated, is critical for comprehending how language and the brain adapt to the environment.   One implication of this project is that it highlights the significance of integrating sociocultural contexts into bilingualism research, contributing to developing a syncretic approach that integrates psycholinguistic and sociolinguistic perspectives. This approach may allow us to have a more unified understanding of bilingual language processing, cognitive control, social interaction, and cultural identity.     Last Modified: 02/27/2024       Submitted by: ArielChan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
