<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Scholars Award: Following the Residues of the Lead Industry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>94361.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>94361</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christine Leuenberger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cleuenbe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927563</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lead - a toxic heavy metal - is dispersed across yards, playgrounds, parks, and empty lots in cities around the world, the result of decades of leaded automobile emissions and centuries of mining and industrial pollution. Because lead does not break down over time, remediation of urban soils to some previously pure or safe baseline condition may be impossible. Given this challenge, how do scientists, decision-makers, and affected communities attempt to reduce the harms caused by soil lead? This project answers these questions by tracing soil lead residues in four regions with distinctive roles in the lead industry. The main goal is to understand how people in each area create knowledge about soil lead, develop and promote methods to reduce exposures, and change the social and economic circumstances in which lead exposures occur. By "following the chemical" across four areas, from lead mines to the soils of urban neighborhoods, this project has potential to affect environmental politics and policy, offering new ways to conceptualize the global problem of lead residues, while illuminating possible solutions that are emerging in particular locales. Other broader impacts include communicating with urban gardeners about the hazards associated with lead exposure, developing ties among academic and community-based soil researchers and advocates, and demonstrating how soil science and social science can mutually support and inform each other.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is the first sustained analysis of soil lead as a ubiquitous residue that continues to accrete around the globe. This project contributes to research conversations in science and technology studies about life in polluted environments, where toxic contamination and its consequences often evade scientific apprehension. Furthermore, it expands the work of historians and social scientists whose research on lead poisoning and the long struggle to regulate the lead industry has generally focused on single locations. In addition to multiple field sites, multiple methods are used in this study: 1) ethnographic fieldwork in historical and present-day lead mining and processing communities; 2) interviews of scientists and activists who conduct community-based soil testing research; 3) analysis of documents about lead mining, the lead-acid battery industry, and other historical and contemporary sources of lead residues in soils across the planet; and, 4) examination of the scientific literature and risk modeling about soil lead exposures. This study also deploys a novel research method called ethnographic soil testing. By interviewing urban gardeners while collaboratively testing their soil for traces of lead, insights are produced regarding how people think about their own exposures to lead, their relationships to the environmental histories of their communities, and living safely in contaminated environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Science and Technology Studies program in SBE and Environmental Engineering Program in ENG.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043301</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abby</FirstName>
<LastName>Kinchy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abby Kinchy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kincha@rpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000519356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>TROY</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803590</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U5WBFKEBLMX3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803590</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y00</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>144000</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~94361</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Lead (Pb) is dispersed across the soils of planet Earth, a durable record of decades of mining, smelting, and the use of myriad lead-based products, such as paint, gasoline, and pesticides. While soil may appear distant and inert, in fact, contaminated soils enter human bodies through numerous pathways. People eat garden vegetables without fully washing off every particle of soil. Children playing outdoors put dirty hands or toys in their mouths. People track dirt onto floors where toddlers play. Dry conditions create dust that is inhaled, or the dust coats surfaces inside the home where people cook, eat, and play. Yet is easy to overlook these everyday encounters with soil and its contaminants.</p> <p>This Scholars Award supported Abby Kinchy's sociological research for a book (in preparation) that calls attention to the importance of soil pollution and explains how soil pollution <em>socially disappears</em> even when the material itself (e.g. particles of lead) remain present underfoot. With a focus on lead, the purpose of the study was to understand the governance challenges that soil pollution poses and to probe how to overcome the social invisibility of soil pollution, across diverse communities. Research was conducted in several parts of the world with distinctive roles in the global lead industry (US, Chile, England, and Australia). Data was gathered about how people in each area have created knowledge about lead in soil--despite obstacles--and developed methods to reduce exposures.</p> <p>Kinchy used several research methods, "following the chemical" from lead mines to the soils of urban neighborhoods. First, she studied how community-engaged researchers in the United States, England, and Australia are challenging scientific ignorance about the bodily harms caused by soil lead. Data gathering involved conducting in-depth interviews with members of the eclectic and loosely organized network of scientists who are studying lead contamination in soil and its effects on health. Second, she led or co-led several small-scale community-based participatory studies of soil contamination, in locations including Troy, New York; Arica, Chile; Sydney and Broken Hill, Australia; and Newcastle and Durham, England. These "citizen science" interventions served several research purposes: 1) To allow local participants to answer their own questions about soil contamination in places that mattered to them, 2) To test and reflect on the virtues and limitations of citizen science as a strategy for reducing lead exposures, and 3) To ethnographically explore how not-knowing about lead in the soil arises from a confluence of social forces, which vary across countries and regions. Third, Kinchy consulted archives, conducted interviews with environmentalists and public health workers, and visited historical sites connected to the lead industry. This mix of sources enabled her to analyze how the legacy of the lead industry and anti-lead activism have shaped policy responses to contaminated soil in diverse settings.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: This study expands on existing histories of lead mining and manufacturing, histories of public health science and lead regulation, and social studies of political conflicts and social movements confronting lead poisoning. While previous scholars have not ignored soil lead, the unique properties of soil, and its challenges, have not been fully addressed. The research also responds to changing cultural perceptions of soil. Cultural analysts have noted some important movements in public understandings of soil, seen in scientific, artistic, and soil care practices that emphasize biological wonder, ecological interdependence, and regeneration. These ideas challenge the still-dominant views of soil as an inert resource for agricultural production or merely dirt to be removed or covered over. Building on these new cultural orientations to soil, this study illuminates the many ways that people are reducing lead exposures by caring for plants, soils, and communities. While focusing on the social disappearance and misapprehension of lead residues in soil, this research has also led to insights about what it might mean to remediate, abate, or otherwise live with contaminated soils. &nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts: With the support of this Scholars Award, Kinchy made interventions that expanded access to knowledge about soil lead and encouraged the use of low-cost and ecologically sound efforts to improve soil health. For example, the participation of urban gardeners in the citizen science portion of this project served to communicate the hazards associated with lead exposure, supported efforts to use gardening as a means of environmental remediation, and brought university researchers and the public together to create social and scientific knowledge. Additionally, the research has implications for environmental politics and policy, offering new ways to conceptualize the problem of contaminated soils and the possibilities for remediation.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 04/26/2024<br> Modified by: Abby&nbsp;Kinchy</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Lead (Pb) is dispersed across the soils of planet Earth, a durable record of decades of mining, smelting, and the use of myriad lead-based products, such as paint, gasoline, and pesticides. While soil may appear distant and inert, in fact, contaminated soils enter human bodies through numerous pathways. People eat garden vegetables without fully washing off every particle of soil. Children playing outdoors put dirty hands or toys in their mouths. People track dirt onto floors where toddlers play. Dry conditions create dust that is inhaled, or the dust coats surfaces inside the home where people cook, eat, and play. Yet is easy to overlook these everyday encounters with soil and its contaminants.   This Scholars Award supported Abby Kinchy's sociological research for a book (in preparation) that calls attention to the importance of soil pollution and explains how soil pollution socially disappears even when the material itself (e.g. particles of lead) remain present underfoot. With a focus on lead, the purpose of the study was to understand the governance challenges that soil pollution poses and to probe how to overcome the social invisibility of soil pollution, across diverse communities. Research was conducted in several parts of the world with distinctive roles in the global lead industry (US, Chile, England, and Australia). Data was gathered about how people in each area have created knowledge about lead in soil--despite obstacles--and developed methods to reduce exposures.   Kinchy used several research methods, "following the chemical" from lead mines to the soils of urban neighborhoods. First, she studied how community-engaged researchers in the United States, England, and Australia are challenging scientific ignorance about the bodily harms caused by soil lead. Data gathering involved conducting in-depth interviews with members of the eclectic and loosely organized network of scientists who are studying lead contamination in soil and its effects on health. Second, she led or co-led several small-scale community-based participatory studies of soil contamination, in locations including Troy, New York; Arica, Chile; Sydney and Broken Hill, Australia; and Newcastle and Durham, England. These "citizen science" interventions served several research purposes: 1) To allow local participants to answer their own questions about soil contamination in places that mattered to them, 2) To test and reflect on the virtues and limitations of citizen science as a strategy for reducing lead exposures, and 3) To ethnographically explore how not-knowing about lead in the soil arises from a confluence of social forces, which vary across countries and regions. Third, Kinchy consulted archives, conducted interviews with environmentalists and public health workers, and visited historical sites connected to the lead industry. This mix of sources enabled her to analyze how the legacy of the lead industry and anti-lead activism have shaped policy responses to contaminated soil in diverse settings.   Intellectual Merit: This study expands on existing histories of lead mining and manufacturing, histories of public health science and lead regulation, and social studies of political conflicts and social movements confronting lead poisoning. While previous scholars have not ignored soil lead, the unique properties of soil, and its challenges, have not been fully addressed. The research also responds to changing cultural perceptions of soil. Cultural analysts have noted some important movements in public understandings of soil, seen in scientific, artistic, and soil care practices that emphasize biological wonder, ecological interdependence, and regeneration. These ideas challenge the still-dominant views of soil as an inert resource for agricultural production or merely dirt to be removed or covered over. Building on these new cultural orientations to soil, this study illuminates the many ways that people are reducing lead exposures by caring for plants, soils, and communities. While focusing on the social disappearance and misapprehension of lead residues in soil, this research has also led to insights about what it might mean to remediate, abate, or otherwise live with contaminated soils.    Broader Impacts: With the support of this Scholars Award, Kinchy made interventions that expanded access to knowledge about soil lead and encouraged the use of low-cost and ecologically sound efforts to improve soil health. For example, the participation of urban gardeners in the citizen science portion of this project served to communicate the hazards associated with lead exposure, supported efforts to use gardening as a means of environmental remediation, and brought university researchers and the public together to create social and scientific knowledge. Additionally, the research has implications for environmental politics and policy, offering new ways to conceptualize the problem of contaminated soils and the possibilities for remediation.     Last Modified: 04/26/2024       Submitted by: AbbyKinchy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
