<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Improving the Conceptual Mastery of Engineering Students in High Enrollment Engineering Courses through Oral Exams]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>298659.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>298659</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kcrosby@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922124</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest by improving the conceptual understanding of students in the lower division engineering courses that build the foundation for future success. Mastery of basic concepts is essential for student success and perseverance in engineering programs. To gain this mastery and prepare for life-long learning as engineers, students need to develop effective learning strategies. Since assessments drive students’ learning strategies, this project will implement and evaluate oral exams in high enrollment introductory engineering courses.  The oral exams will be used to assess students’ understanding of fundamental concepts, which is difficult to measure using traditional exams and quizzes. A new training program will be created to prepare faculty and teaching assistants to administer oral exams. The project will also provide guidelines to help engineering educators implement oral exams in other courses. It is expected that the oral exams will guide students to use learning strategies that enhance conceptual mastery and critical thinking. By strengthening students’ verbal communication skills, oral exams can also help prepare them for the engineering workforce. This project will add to research on oral exams by contributing new knowledge about the effectiveness of oral exams in undergraduate engineering core courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to improve undergraduate students’ conceptual mastery and critical thinking skills in engineering. Critical thinking has been identified as an essential skill for engineering graduates and conceptual mastery is a prerequisite. It has been shown that students adopt learning strategies based on how they will be assessed. For example, if an exam is procedural in nature, students will pursue procedural knowledge over deep conceptual understanding. Thus, assessment plays an important role in measuring the level of students' conceptual understanding and in guiding students' selection of learning strategies toward achieving greater concept mastery and critical thinking skills. The adaptive dialogic nature of oral exams holds promise for improving both assessment of conceptual mastery and students’ learning strategies. However, the issues of the reliability, validity, and scalability to high enrollment courses of oral exams have not been fully addressed. This project will create a framework to integrate oral exams in core undergraduate engineering courses, complementing existing assessment strategies. Key elements of the project are the involvement of the entire instructional team (instructors and teaching assistants) and the emphasis on training that includes considerations of issues such as bias and students with disabilities. The project will implement an iterative design strategy using an evidence-based approach of evaluation. The effectiveness of the oral exams will be evaluated by tracking student improvements on conceptual questions across consecutive oral exams in a single course, as well as across other courses. The training program will be made freely available online to faculty at other institutions who are interested in using oral exams for assessment. The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044472</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Curt</FirstName>
<LastName>Schurgers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Curt Schurgers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cschurgers@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000489172</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Delson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan J Delson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nate@egrove.education]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000656344</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Sandoval</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carolyn L Sandoval</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[c2sandoval@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000705314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huihui</FirstName>
<LastName>Qi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huihui Qi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[huqi@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833713</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marko</FirstName>
<LastName>Lubarda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marko Lubarda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mlubarda@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 GILMAN DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930411</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, MC 0411]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~298659</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-7e9f5b84-7fff-b691-06f9-c5c3ed08894c" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Critical thinking has been identified as one of the key skills of STEM graduates. As such, undergraduate STEM education should strive to provide conceptual mastery to its learning. This is especially true for the core courses students take early on, due to their role as both the foundations of the discipline and creating the appropriate mindset with which to approach the remainder of their curriculum and careers.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Assessment not only plays an important role in measuring the level of students' conceptual understanding, but also, importantly, in guiding students' learning strategies to be aligned with this learning outcome. Exams that effectively, validly and reliably gauges conceptual mastery is thus key. Written exams, a pervasive assessment format in STEM undergraduate education, often leans towards testing procedural knowledge (&ldquo;know-how&rdquo;) rather than true &ldquo;know-why&rdquo;. Oral exams, on the other hand, can provide the power of assessing conceptual mastery in depth due to their adaptive dialogic nature. While the benefits of oral exams have been studied in principle, the implementation of oral exams in core STEM undergraduate courses is still underdeveloped in the US context. Scalability issues (due to high enrollment) are often cited, in addition to challenges of validity and reliability (bias).</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The goal of this project was to advance the knowledge of how to design and implement oral exams in engineering classes to positively impact students&rsquo; learning and scale it up for high-enrollment classes, and generate transferable materials to allow more other engineering educators to implement oral exams for their classes. We achieved this goal through four project components: 1) We designed and implemented oral exams in 10 unique engineering courses at the project home institution - University of California San Diego (UCSD) for 46 classes. 2) We developed and implemented Instructional Training to prepare them to be effective oral exams assessors. The materials include 5 videos and training reference guide. 3) We conduct scholarly inquiry about the impact of oral exams and effectiveness of the IA training, and use the results to inform our oral exams and training redesign. 4) We actively disseminated our project findings and results through various venues to a broad group of educators.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The intellectual merit of this project includes: This project created a framework and practical approach and materials to integrate oral exams effectively in core undergraduate STEM courses to enhance students&rsquo; learning and learning experience. Key elements are the integration of the entire instructional team (instructors and Instructional Assistants), as well as an emphasis on training and considerations regarding issues such as bias.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">This project has had broad impacts by guiding students' learning strategies towards a desire to pursue concept mastery, preparing engineering students with the skills and attitudes necessary for the rapid pace of technological change through oral exams. The dialogic nature of oral assessments has been shown to strengthen students&rsquo; verbal communication skills, and to have positive impacts on persistence and retention in STEM, which are particularly important for underserved, underrepresented students. Oral exams have also fostered diversity and inclusion, and be useful tools in the pursuit of maintaining academic integrity standards. The oral exam design and implementation process developed in this project also advanced STEM educators&rsquo; evidence-based knowledge on the adoption of oral exams. During this project, faculty and Instructional Assistants increased their STEM education competency, with dedicated training on effective assessor and assessed communication and a focus on diversity, impacts of bias and importance of interpersonal communication cues. While benefiting faculty, there has been a particular salient impact on Instructional Assistants in preparing them with extensive training and practice in professional engineering skills as future leaders and educators. In the 3 project years, We actively disseminated our project findings and results through various venues to a broad group of educators, including numerous informal consultation meetings with colleagues, presentations in department meetings, 2 campus educational conferences and 2 workshops at UCSD, 3 presentations at other institutions, 16 papers and 1 workshop nationwide and international engineering education conferences, 1 essay published in educational community. Our work has also been highlighted in medium press (Wall Street Journal, EdSurge, and UCSD Today).&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 05/01/2024<br> Modified by: Huihui&nbsp;Qi</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Critical thinking has been identified as one of the key skills of STEM graduates. As such, undergraduate STEM education should strive to provide conceptual mastery to its learning. This is especially true for the core courses students take early on, due to their role as both the foundations of the discipline and creating the appropriate mindset with which to approach the remainder of their curriculum and careers.      Assessment not only plays an important role in measuring the level of students' conceptual understanding, but also, importantly, in guiding students' learning strategies to be aligned with this learning outcome. Exams that effectively, validly and reliably gauges conceptual mastery is thus key. Written exams, a pervasive assessment format in STEM undergraduate education, often leans towards testing procedural knowledge (know-how) rather than true know-why. Oral exams, on the other hand, can provide the power of assessing conceptual mastery in depth due to their adaptive dialogic nature. While the benefits of oral exams have been studied in principle, the implementation of oral exams in core STEM undergraduate courses is still underdeveloped in the US context. Scalability issues (due to high enrollment) are often cited, in addition to challenges of validity and reliability (bias).      The goal of this project was to advance the knowledge of how to design and implement oral exams in engineering classes to positively impact students learning and scale it up for high-enrollment classes, and generate transferable materials to allow more other engineering educators to implement oral exams for their classes. We achieved this goal through four project components: 1) We designed and implemented oral exams in 10 unique engineering courses at the project home institution - University of California San Diego (UCSD) for 46 classes. 2) We developed and implemented Instructional Training to prepare them to be effective oral exams assessors. The materials include 5 videos and training reference guide. 3) We conduct scholarly inquiry about the impact of oral exams and effectiveness of the IA training, and use the results to inform our oral exams and training redesign. 4) We actively disseminated our project findings and results through various venues to a broad group of educators.      The intellectual merit of this project includes: This project created a framework and practical approach and materials to integrate oral exams effectively in core undergraduate STEM courses to enhance students learning and learning experience. Key elements are the integration of the entire instructional team (instructors and Instructional Assistants), as well as an emphasis on training and considerations regarding issues such as bias.      This project has had broad impacts by guiding students' learning strategies towards a desire to pursue concept mastery, preparing engineering students with the skills and attitudes necessary for the rapid pace of technological change through oral exams. The dialogic nature of oral assessments has been shown to strengthen students verbal communication skills, and to have positive impacts on persistence and retention in STEM, which are particularly important for underserved, underrepresented students. Oral exams have also fostered diversity and inclusion, and be useful tools in the pursuit of maintaining academic integrity standards. The oral exam design and implementation process developed in this project also advanced STEM educators evidence-based knowledge on the adoption of oral exams. During this project, faculty and Instructional Assistants increased their STEM education competency, with dedicated training on effective assessor and assessed communication and a focus on diversity, impacts of bias and importance of interpersonal communication cues. While benefiting faculty, there has been a particular salient impact on Instructional Assistants in preparing them with extensive training and practice in professional engineering skills as future leaders and educators. In the 3 project years, We actively disseminated our project findings and results through various venues to a broad group of educators, including numerous informal consultation meetings with colleagues, presentations in department meetings, 2 campus educational conferences and 2 workshops at UCSD, 3 presentations at other institutions, 16 papers and 1 workshop nationwide and international engineering education conferences, 1 essay published in educational community. Our work has also been highlighted in medium press (Wall Street Journal, EdSurge, and UCSD Today).     Last Modified: 05/01/2024       Submitted by: HuihuiQi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
