<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Feedback between training and practice in conceptualizations of phenotypic variation among medical trainees]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>How humans make sense of the world around them depends on a combination of experience and instruction. Medical education often relies on typologies and thresholds to inform medical practice. What happens when experiences of more graded variation in human phenotypes contradicts typological medical instruction? How do trainees’ experiences in care delivery feedback on instruction centered on typologies? How do emergent technologies shape understandings of phenotypic variation and the effects of such understandings on practice? This project merges theory from medical anthropology, science and technology studies, and the anthropology of education to inform an understanding of how characterization of human variation takes shape in reaction to education and experience. Project findings will be broadly disseminated to academic and non-academic audiences and the project will train a graduate student in anthropology in the methods of empirical, scientific data collection, and analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This doctoral dissertation project will leverage 15 months of ethnographic research among medical trainees, including participant observation, semi-structured interviews, oral history interviews, and textual analysis of pedagogical materials, to: 1) capture how trainees are taught to understand human variation, 2) investigate how scientific technologies and instruments reflect and affect understanding of human variation in care delivery, and 3) clarify how personal experience interacting with and providing care for varied subjects feeds back on concepts and typologies of human variation. By paying explicit attention to the dynamics of how concepts of variability are shaped and reshaped in reaction to education, experience, and technology, this project will advance a synthetic understanding of how humans mobilize concepts of variation in everyday practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044020</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Ballestero</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Ballestero</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aballes@usc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000332150</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yesmar</FirstName>
<LastName>Oyarzun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yesmar S Oyarzun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yesmar@rice.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834742</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>K51LECU1G8N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 Main St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>760500</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~25200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Yesmar Oyarzun has completed research for the National Science Foundation-funded project entitled &ldquo;Feedback between training and practice in conceptualizations of phenotypic variation among medical trainees.&rdquo; This project was funded by the NSF&rsquo;s Dissertation Improvement Grant mechanism under the Cultural Anthropology Program (Award # 2044020). Oyarzun conducted ethnographic research in order to understand how dermatologists and dermatology trainees learn to perceive skin disease in the context of human diversity in skin tone. As a cultural anthropologist of science and medical anthropologist, Oyarzun sought to understand the relationship and interplay between cultural beliefs about human difference and medical/scientific perception and categorization of disease and disease states.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To understand how dermatologists develop skill and expertise in diagnosis and management of skin disease across patients with a diverse range of skin tones, Oyarzun completed 13.5 months of digital observations and 7.5 months of in-person observation (6.5 months concurrent) among dermatologists and dermatology residents across four research sites. Oyarzun also supplemented these observations with participant observation at dermatology conferences, analysis of popular dermatology textbooks, and semi-structured interviews with 32 dermatologists, trainees, and close colleagues. Over the course of the research, Oyarzun found that dermatologists engage in a process of disease perception, detection, and diagnosis, which focuses primarily on the aesthetic features of skin lesions identified using precise and profession-specific terminology. They learn this process through real-world practice in clinics which provide a localized social milieu through which to learn, and they supplement this with game-like practices that use images to train learners to associate specific visual patterns with specific lesion categories, which are then associated with specific disease categories. As dermatologists learn to see in profession-specific ways, dark skin is repeatedly posed as abnormal, generally subtly, through mechanisms such as the absence of dark skin in depictions of normal skin biology or the overrepresentation of people with dark skin in the depiction of culturally stigmatized diseases, such as infectious diseases of the skin and genitals. This indicates that the pictorial content of medical educational materials is crucial to what and how medical trainees learn, rather than only the written material. In addition, throughout their training and in their everyday practices dermatologists and trainees encounter and use technological instruments and devices that were developed without sufficient attention to or applicability for people with darker skin tones, which can lead to the tools' under- or misutilization when applied to people within this group.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Oyarzun also engaged in historical research methodologies to situate current practices within specialized fields of dermatology, particularly those related to &ldquo;skin of color&rdquo; and &ldquo;ethnic skin&rdquo; dermatology. Oyarzun compiled and analyzed archival materials, including 20<sup>th</sup> century textbooks and articles, extant oral histories, and biographical files of dermatologists who focused on pigmentation research. The research showed that dermatologists who have focused on dark skin or skin pigmentation over the course of their careers have attempted to introduce new ways of looking at dark skin in efforts to&nbsp; improve the healthcare quality of patients with dark skin. This has included increased representation of normal and abnormal skin biology as it appears on people with dark skin, as well as engaging in projects to increase the presence and visibility of patients of color in learning and research settings.</p> <p>The development of perceptual skills requires that trainees practice perceptual skills using a wide range and variety of cases, of persons with different backgrounds and physical characteristics, and of scenarios in order for trainees to develop the expertise needed to work in a diverse society. Overall, this study highlights the need for diversity in medicine, and particularly in contexts that have been underexplored in the extant literature. This includes a need for expanded diversity in both photographic and illustrated textbook images, in studies introducing or confirming the validity of clinical and educational tools (including scales, indices, and technological instruments), in clinical trials for drugs, and in the dermatology workforce and educational pipeline.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 08/29/2024<br> Modified by: Yesmar&nbsp;S&nbsp;Oyarzun</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Yesmar Oyarzun has completed research for the National Science Foundation-funded project entitled Feedback between training and practice in conceptualizations of phenotypic variation among medical trainees. This project was funded by the NSFs Dissertation Improvement Grant mechanism under the Cultural Anthropology Program (Award # 2044020). Oyarzun conducted ethnographic research in order to understand how dermatologists and dermatology trainees learn to perceive skin disease in the context of human diversity in skin tone. As a cultural anthropologist of science and medical anthropologist, Oyarzun sought to understand the relationship and interplay between cultural beliefs about human difference and medical/scientific perception and categorization of disease and disease states.      To understand how dermatologists develop skill and expertise in diagnosis and management of skin disease across patients with a diverse range of skin tones, Oyarzun completed 13.5 months of digital observations and 7.5 months of in-person observation (6.5 months concurrent) among dermatologists and dermatology residents across four research sites. Oyarzun also supplemented these observations with participant observation at dermatology conferences, analysis of popular dermatology textbooks, and semi-structured interviews with 32 dermatologists, trainees, and close colleagues. Over the course of the research, Oyarzun found that dermatologists engage in a process of disease perception, detection, and diagnosis, which focuses primarily on the aesthetic features of skin lesions identified using precise and profession-specific terminology. They learn this process through real-world practice in clinics which provide a localized social milieu through which to learn, and they supplement this with game-like practices that use images to train learners to associate specific visual patterns with specific lesion categories, which are then associated with specific disease categories. As dermatologists learn to see in profession-specific ways, dark skin is repeatedly posed as abnormal, generally subtly, through mechanisms such as the absence of dark skin in depictions of normal skin biology or the overrepresentation of people with dark skin in the depiction of culturally stigmatized diseases, such as infectious diseases of the skin and genitals. This indicates that the pictorial content of medical educational materials is crucial to what and how medical trainees learn, rather than only the written material. In addition, throughout their training and in their everyday practices dermatologists and trainees encounter and use technological instruments and devices that were developed without sufficient attention to or applicability for people with darker skin tones, which can lead to the tools' under- or misutilization when applied to people within this group.      Oyarzun also engaged in historical research methodologies to situate current practices within specialized fields of dermatology, particularly those related to skin of color and ethnic skin dermatology. Oyarzun compiled and analyzed archival materials, including 20th century textbooks and articles, extant oral histories, and biographical files of dermatologists who focused on pigmentation research. The research showed that dermatologists who have focused on dark skin or skin pigmentation over the course of their careers have attempted to introduce new ways of looking at dark skin in efforts to improve the healthcare quality of patients with dark skin. This has included increased representation of normal and abnormal skin biology as it appears on people with dark skin, as well as engaging in projects to increase the presence and visibility of patients of color in learning and research settings.   The development of perceptual skills requires that trainees practice perceptual skills using a wide range and variety of cases, of persons with different backgrounds and physical characteristics, and of scenarios in order for trainees to develop the expertise needed to work in a diverse society. Overall, this study highlights the need for diversity in medicine, and particularly in contexts that have been underexplored in the extant literature. This includes a need for expanded diversity in both photographic and illustrated textbook images, in studies introducing or confirming the validity of clinical and educational tools (including scales, indices, and technological instruments), in clinical trials for drugs, and in the dermatology workforce and educational pipeline.     Last Modified: 08/29/2024       Submitted by: YesmarSOyarzun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
