<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Improving Undergraduate Student Persistence, Performance, and Perspectives in Online STEM Courses via a Community of Inquiry and Decreasing Students' Cognitive Load]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>237298.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>237298</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert M. Talbot III</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rtalbot@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to serve the national interest in high-quality undergraduate STEM education by designing and studying a pilot program to improve online discussion forums in STEM courses.  The overall goal of the project is to improve students’ performance and persistence in online STEM courses, while simultaneously improving their attitudes toward STEM itself. To achieve this goal, the project focuses on introducing practices that reduce extraneous cognitive load, while also improving educators’ instructional and social presence, and students’ social and cognitive presence.  The project will study a specific practice: a faculty-student learning community that uses discussion forums and other online components to minimize non-relevant technical complexity.  The project intends to produce guidelines for creating a productive online learning community that does not require additional effort that is unrelated to the intended learning.  The project will provide professional development to support instructors’ implementation of the guidelines.  It is anticipated that the guidelines may be transferable to other online STEM courses.  The projects’ data about student retention, persistence, and attitudes toward STEM will provide a base for additional research on online STEM learning.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to positively impact student persistence, performance, and perspectives in asynchronous online STEM courses.  It expects to do to by supporting learning communities in ways that mitigate the impacts of extraneous cognitive load. To this end, the project will design and test a pilot program for infusing the components of the Community of Inquiry framework into asynchronous course discussions, including a best practices redesign of the discussion prompts, rubrics, and instructions by subject matter experts and instructional designers.  The pilot program will use existing institutional structures to support the redesign and to provide faculty with the related professional development. In a mixed-methods research study, information will be collected about students’ academic success (course grades, discussion transcript analysis), persistence (withdrawal rate), and perspectives (surveys on STEM attitudes, cognitive load, and community of inquiry).  These data will be complemented by results from focus group interviews.  The project intends to generate a Community of Inquiry – Cognitive Load framework for asynchronous online STEM courses that supports student outcomes by promoting social, teaching, and cognitive presences via the Community of Inquiry, while mitigating cognitive load that is disconnected from disciplinary learning. The framework may be transferrable and scalable to other asynchronous online STEM courses. By identifying reasons for persistence and retention in online STEM courses, the project expects to lay the foundation for further research on interventions that improve student outcomes in online STEM courses.  The NSF IUSE:EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044302</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Faulconer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily K Faulconer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[faulcone@erau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000800147</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Chamberlain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darryl J Chamberlain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Darryl.Chamberlain@erau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beverly</FirstName>
<LastName>Wood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beverly L Wood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[woodb14@erau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University]]></Name>
<CityName>DAYTONA BEACH</CityName>
<ZipCode>321143910</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3862267695</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 AEROSPACE BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U5MMBAC9XAM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMBRY-RIDDLE AERONAUTICAL UNIVERSITY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University]]></Name>
<CityName>Daytona Beach</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>321143966</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Aerospace Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>199800</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~237298</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h1><span style="color: #000000; font-size: 12px; font-weight: normal;">This project was implemented at Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University&rsquo;s Worldwide Campus from June 2021 to May 2024. The goal of this project was to target key course persistence factors through building community in online undergraduate STEM classrooms by promoting Community of Inquiry (CoI) in asynchronous online discussions while mitigating extraneous cognitive load (CL). The efficacy of the CoI-CL Framework was evaluated by measuring cognitive load and CoI presences before and after the intervention. The goal of the Framework was to 1) increase online STEM course persistence, 2) increase performance in online STEM courses, and 3) positively influence STEM attitudes.</span></h1> <p><strong>Efficacy of CoI-CL Framework</strong></p> <p>The CoI-CL Framework was evaluated using multiple criteria, demonstrating its potential to have positive impacts on student outcomes. Key findings from the evaluation (and a summary of all outputs and outcomes related to this project) can be found in our Research Summary Document (<a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.7951445),">https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.7951445),</a> publicly available and utilized for strategic outreach efforts.</p> <ul> <li>Increase in cognitive presence coupled with increased CL in reading and replying to posts suggests increase in germane cognitive load</li> <li>Decrease in frustration for understanding expectations, crafting an initial post, and integrating instructor feedback suggests reduction in extraneous cognitive load</li> <li>Increased effort in replying to posts and less effort in replying to instructor, suggesting increased student-to-student engagement</li> <li>Improved course persistence (decreased withdrawal rate)</li> <li>Improvement in STEM attitudes (normative beliefs, control beliefs, and intention in STEM)</li> <li>No impact on pass rate. Impact on grade distribution requires further analysis to understand nuances.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p><strong><em>Transferability. </em></strong>Our evaluation of the CoI-CL framework validates it as a tool for improving asynchronous online learning with potential for adoption and adaptation to other disciplines within and beyond STEM. Our Transferability Plan is publicly available (<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11203344">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11203344</a>).</p> <p><strong><em>Educational Research. </em></strong>Our research established the influence of CoI and CL on persistence, performance, and STEM attitudes through robust SEM modeling and empirical evidence. This knowledge has been (and will continue to be) disseminated through peer-reviewed publications, with manuscripts under review and in progress, with key findings for each output detailed in our Research Summary Document.</p> <p><strong><em>Administrative. </em></strong>Experiences with targeted course development and faculty professional development can inform policy decisions related to online faculty. Voluntary opt-in professional development may not recruit an appropriate pool; impacts of professional development erode over time and strategies to ensure continued impact are needed. The data collection challenges related to withdrawal reasons from online STEM courses are documented in our white paper (<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11094757">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11094757</a>). The challenges and potential solutions explored may enable other institutions to evaluate their own data collection and curation processes and make necessary changes to enable more impactful, insightful research.</p> <p><strong><em>Data Science Research Practices. </em></strong>Our systematic progress on developing 100% accuracy methods for extracting student and instructor discussion posts has led to open-source Python scripts that can be used by other educational researchers to conduct their own qualitative and quantitative analysis.</p> <h2><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2> <p>This project established an adaptable framework for improving learner outcomes in asynchronous online STEM courses by promoting Community of Inquiry and mitigating extraneous cognitive load. The research behind evaluating the Framework led to notable contributions to educational research, including validated survey instruments and Python scripts for data cleaning. Importantly, learners benefitted from the CoI-CL framework through improvements to persistence and perspectives.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/16/2024<br> Modified by: Darryl&nbsp;J&nbsp;Chamberlain</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project was implemented at Embry-Riddle Aeronautical Universitys Worldwide Campus from June 2021 to May 2024. The goal of this project was to target key course persistence factors through building community in online undergraduate STEM classrooms by promoting Community of Inquiry (CoI) in asynchronous online discussions while mitigating extraneous cognitive load (CL). The efficacy of the CoI-CL Framework was evaluated by measuring cognitive load and CoI presences before and after the intervention. The goal of the Framework was to 1) increase online STEM course persistence, 2) increase performance in online STEM courses, and 3) positively influence STEM attitudes.   Efficacy of CoI-CL Framework   The CoI-CL Framework was evaluated using multiple criteria, demonstrating its potential to have positive impacts on student outcomes. Key findings from the evaluation (and a summary of all outputs and outcomes related to this project) can be found in our Research Summary Document (https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.7951445), publicly available and utilized for strategic outreach efforts.  Increase in cognitive presence coupled with increased CL in reading and replying to posts suggests increase in germane cognitive load Decrease in frustration for understanding expectations, crafting an initial post, and integrating instructor feedback suggests reduction in extraneous cognitive load Increased effort in replying to posts and less effort in replying to instructor, suggesting increased student-to-student engagement Improved course persistence (decreased withdrawal rate) Improvement in STEM attitudes (normative beliefs, control beliefs, and intention in STEM) No impact on pass rate. Impact on grade distribution requires further analysis to understand nuances.    Broader Impacts   Transferability. Our evaluation of the CoI-CL framework validates it as a tool for improving asynchronous online learning with potential for adoption and adaptation to other disciplines within and beyond STEM. Our Transferability Plan is publicly available (https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11203344).   Educational Research. Our research established the influence of CoI and CL on persistence, performance, and STEM attitudes through robust SEM modeling and empirical evidence. This knowledge has been (and will continue to be) disseminated through peer-reviewed publications, with manuscripts under review and in progress, with key findings for each output detailed in our Research Summary Document.   Administrative. Experiences with targeted course development and faculty professional development can inform policy decisions related to online faculty. Voluntary opt-in professional development may not recruit an appropriate pool; impacts of professional development erode over time and strategies to ensure continued impact are needed. The data collection challenges related to withdrawal reasons from online STEM courses are documented in our white paper (https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11094757). The challenges and potential solutions explored may enable other institutions to evaluate their own data collection and curation processes and make necessary changes to enable more impactful, insightful research.   Data Science Research Practices. Our systematic progress on developing 100% accuracy methods for extracting student and instructor discussion posts has led to open-source Python scripts that can be used by other educational researchers to conduct their own qualitative and quantitative analysis. Conclusion   This project established an adaptable framework for improving learner outcomes in asynchronous online STEM courses by promoting Community of Inquiry and mitigating extraneous cognitive load. The research behind evaluating the Framework led to notable contributions to educational research, including validated survey instruments and Python scripts for data cleaning. Importantly, learners benefitted from the CoI-CL framework through improvements to persistence and perspectives.     Last Modified: 07/16/2024       Submitted by: DarrylJChamberlain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
