<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Seismic and aseismic slip in faults with rock gouge using a 3D laboratory earthquake setup: the effect of fluid injection rate]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>452600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>452600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Panero</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wpanero@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925058</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fluids play a key role in earthquake source processes. A large body of observations has shown the close connection between fluids and faulting. This is observed in natural events and in earthquakes induced by human activities, such as carbon sequestration, geothermal energy extraction, and wastewater disposal associated with oil and gas extraction. Here the researchers investigate the relation between fluid injection and the resulting seismic response.  This response ranges from slow aseismic slip (no earthquake) to unstable seismic slip (earthquake).  They use a highly instrumented laboratory setup comprising fault analogs which allow 3-D visualization of fault responses.  Time sequences of unstable slips are captured by a high-speed camera.  Fluid injection rate and pressures are recorded at the fault interface. The state-of-the-art bench top experiments contribute to the fundamental understanding of the role of fluids in faulting. They provide critical experimental measurements for the validation of 3-D numerical codes modeling fluid induced seismicity.  The project provides support for an early-career scientist, graduate and undergraduate students, and fosters outreach toward high-school and middle-school students and their teachers. Its outcomes improve earthquake hazard assessment, notably related to human activities. The project is co-funded by both the Geophysics program and the Tectonics program.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Here, the laboratory experiments produce frictional ruptures triggered by highly controlled fluid injection in 3-D specimens. The simulated fault can host a range of rupture behavior, ranging from slow slip all the way to fully dynamic response. Dynamic ruptures spontaneously propagate along a frictional interface with slip rates of the order of 0.1-10 m/s; this range is highly relevant to natural earthquakes. 3-D specimens and setup allow testing the hypothesis that low vs. fast injection rate can result in stable vs. unstable slip behavior. The experiments feature rock gouge interfaces embedded in specimens made of a polymeric material, poly-methyl-methacrylate (PMMA).  This material is readily available in bulk form and makes possible the production of 3-D samples. Using polymers as analog materials yields several advantages, including their small nucleation sizes for unstable slip, and transparency, which are here essential. The ability to closely monitor the fault behavior at a high level of detail enable the team to explore and quantify the connection between slow slip and dynamic rupture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2045285</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ares</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosakis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ares J Rosakis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arosakis@caltech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000468556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E CALIFORNIA BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U2JMKHNS5TG4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>157200</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>157400</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~452600</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fluids play a key role in earthquake source processes. A large body of observations has shown the close connection between fluids and faulting, both in natural events and in earthquakes induced by human activities, such as carbon sequestration, geothermal energy extraction, and wastewater disposal associated with oil and gas extraction. &nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, we have investigated the relation between fluid injection and the resulting seismic response, using a highly instrumented laboratory setup. Using previous NSF support, we have developed a setup able to modulate and monitor fluid effects on a simulated interface. In this setup, fluids can be injected on the interface with various injection rates, varying from slow (megapascals per hour) to fast (megapascals per second). In this project, we have studied the slip behavior of analogue and fault gouge interfaces from seismic to aseismic slip rates.</p> <p>During the course of this study, we have investigated rupture behavior along interfaces with rock gouge. We have developed a hybrid configuration featuring a gouge interface embedded in a Homalite specimen. This configuration exploits the small nucleation scales associated with the bulk Homalite properties and at the same time allows us to investigate the frictional properties of gouge interfaces during spontaneous dynamic ruptures. We have studied dynamic ruptures propagating through gouge interfaces positioned both in bulk of the specimen and close to the free boundaries, where sudden reduction of normal stress take place. In both cases, ruptures navigate the gouge fault regions through a complex, intermittent slip process, featuring marked friction changes.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have investigated slow (aseismic) slip, by developing a novel experimental procedure capable of local (on-fault) slip rate measurements along interfaces with analog materials as well as fault gouge. We find that the frictional interfaces are indeed sliding with decaying slip rate imperceivable to the eye, reaching 10<sup>-12</sup>&nbsp;m/s after 18 hours. This behavior contradicts classical models of friction, such as those incorporating the concept of static friction, but confirms the prediction of rate-and-state models. The diminishing slip rates of nominally stationary interfaces reflect interface healing, which would manifest itself in higher peak friction in subsequent slip events, such as earthquakes and landslides, significantly modifying their nucleation and propagation and hence their hazard.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The outcomes of this project contribute to our fundamental understanding of the role played by fluids in generating earthquakes and of dynamic friction evolution in rock gouge interfaces, which are key aspects to understand earthquake physics. Our studies have highlighted the complex interaction between fluids and faulting and have helped to strengthen friction formulations for earthquake-producing faults,&#8232;a key ingredient in dynamic rupture simulations and physics-based assessment of seismic hazard. Several students and postdoctoral fellows have had valuable research experience participating in the interdisciplinary activities of this project.&nbsp;&nbsp;The results have been disseminated through publications in leading professional journals and at professional meetings. We have used the results of our study to graphically illustrate earthquakes and to teach the associated science questions to high-school and middle-school students and their teachers, since the conducted experiments and simulations provide a unique insight into earthquake physics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 10/29/2024<br> Modified by: Ares&nbsp;J&nbsp;Rosakis</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Fluids play a key role in earthquake source processes. A large body of observations has shown the close connection between fluids and faulting, both in natural events and in earthquakes induced by human activities, such as carbon sequestration, geothermal energy extraction, and wastewater disposal associated with oil and gas extraction.    In this project, we have investigated the relation between fluid injection and the resulting seismic response, using a highly instrumented laboratory setup. Using previous NSF support, we have developed a setup able to modulate and monitor fluid effects on a simulated interface. In this setup, fluids can be injected on the interface with various injection rates, varying from slow (megapascals per hour) to fast (megapascals per second). In this project, we have studied the slip behavior of analogue and fault gouge interfaces from seismic to aseismic slip rates.   During the course of this study, we have investigated rupture behavior along interfaces with rock gouge. We have developed a hybrid configuration featuring a gouge interface embedded in a Homalite specimen. This configuration exploits the small nucleation scales associated with the bulk Homalite properties and at the same time allows us to investigate the frictional properties of gouge interfaces during spontaneous dynamic ruptures. We have studied dynamic ruptures propagating through gouge interfaces positioned both in bulk of the specimen and close to the free boundaries, where sudden reduction of normal stress take place. In both cases, ruptures navigate the gouge fault regions through a complex, intermittent slip process, featuring marked friction changes.   We have investigated slow (aseismic) slip, by developing a novel experimental procedure capable of local (on-fault) slip rate measurements along interfaces with analog materials as well as fault gouge. We find that the frictional interfaces are indeed sliding with decaying slip rate imperceivable to the eye, reaching 10-12m/s after 18 hours. This behavior contradicts classical models of friction, such as those incorporating the concept of static friction, but confirms the prediction of rate-and-state models. The diminishing slip rates of nominally stationary interfaces reflect interface healing, which would manifest itself in higher peak friction in subsequent slip events, such as earthquakes and landslides, significantly modifying their nucleation and propagation and hence their hazard.   The outcomes of this project contribute to our fundamental understanding of the role played by fluids in generating earthquakes and of dynamic friction evolution in rock gouge interfaces, which are key aspects to understand earthquake physics. Our studies have highlighted the complex interaction between fluids and faulting and have helped to strengthen friction formulations for earthquake-producing faults,&#8232;a key ingredient in dynamic rupture simulations and physics-based assessment of seismic hazard. Several students and postdoctoral fellows have had valuable research experience participating in the interdisciplinary activities of this project.The results have been disseminated through publications in leading professional journals and at professional meetings. We have used the results of our study to graphically illustrate earthquakes and to teach the associated science questions to high-school and middle-school students and their teachers, since the conducted experiments and simulations provide a unique insight into earthquake physics.        Last Modified: 10/29/2024       Submitted by: AresJRosakis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
