<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[A Quantitative Meta-Analysis and Qualitative Synthesis on the Impacts of Informal STEM and ICT Programs on Cognitive and Socio-emotional Outcomes of Youth Participants]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299056.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299056</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julie Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjohnson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As the pace of innovation accelerates, the need for technology-rich experiences and pathways to science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) and information and communications technology (ICT) careers has become increasingly essential. Thus, a critical challenge faced by educators is to develop strategies that provide youth access to high quality STEM and ICT programs, and that motivate them to persist in STEM trajectories. Alarmingly, data suggest that positive STEM attitudes, especially among females and members of historically underrepresented racial and ethnic groups, tend to decline as youth transition from elementary to middle school and again from middle school to high school. Promisingly, informal STEM learning programs are thought to be important vehicles for addressing issues of underrepresentation, declining interest, and for facilitating sustained participation in STEM and ICT trajectories. However, it is largely unknown how and to what extent informal learning programs impact participants’ awareness, interest, and engagement in STEM and ICT majors and careers. To address this knowledge gap, this synthesis project will investigate the impact of informal STEM and ICT programs on the cognitive and social emotional outcomes of youth participants. Importantly, this synthesis study differs from many other quantitative analyses and qualitative syntheses because one of the major goals of this project is to extract program design principles, technology-based innovations, theoretical underpinnings, and best practices from studies that exhibit exemplary evidence of rigorous research design and impact. This project is funded by the Innovative Technology Experiences for Students and Teachers (ITEST) program, which supports projects that build understandings of practices, program elements, contexts and processes contributing to increasing students' knowledge and interest in STEM and ICT careers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this synthesis study is to perform a quantitative meta-analysis and qualitative synthesis of research on youth participants of informal STEM and ICT programs. The project addresses two major research questions: (1) How and to what extent do informal, out-of-school time STEM and ICT learning experiences impact participants’ awareness, interest and engagement in STEM majors and careers? (2) What are the program design principles, technology-based innovations, theoretical underpinnings, and best practices of rigorously designed informal, out-of-school time STEM and ICT programs that exhibit exemplary evidence of impact that can be adopted by STEM practitioners to maximize impact and broaden participation of underrepresented groups? To address the two main research questions, first, the project team will perform a systematic literature review and a quantitative meta-analysis to assess how and to what extent informal STEM and ICT learning experiences impact participants’ awareness, interest, and engagement in STEM majors and careers. Second, the project team will use two validated rubrics to identify studies that exhibit exemplary evidence of research design quality and impact. From these studies, the team will conduct qualitative analyses to identify program design principles, technology-based innovations, theoretical underpinnings, and best practices for adoption by STEM practitioners to maximize impact and broaden participation of underrepresented groups. By focusing on programs with exemplary evidence of impact that specifically target females, underserved populations, and members of historically marginalized racial and ethnic groups, the findings can be used by practitioners to inform program design and practice, and to maximize the impact of underrepresented students. The deliverables of this project will include peer-reviewed publications, webinars, and conference presentations to ensure that the results of this study are disseminated to the science education community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2048544</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mande</FirstName>
<LastName>Holford</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mande Holford</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mholford@hunter.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000188945</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Hunter College]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100655024</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2127724020</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[695 PARK AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EK93EZLLBSC4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Hunter College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100655024</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>722700</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>1300XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[H-1B FUND, EDU, NSF]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>045176</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~299056</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Engagement in STEM career pathways can result in positive outcomes, including earning higher incomes and making meaningful contributions to society. However, a significant challenge encountered by educators is to identify strategies that motivate youth to consider a STEM career pathway. While several informal STEM institutions have developed programming specifically designed to foster STEM major and STEM career awareness, gauging the effectiveness of these initiatives remains elusive.&nbsp; This study conducts a meta-synthesis of research on informal STEM programs and outlines barriers and opportunities involved in Promoting STEM Major and STEM Career Awareness to youth participants. Specifically we address three questions: (1) How and to what extent do informal STEM learning experiences impact K-12 participants&rsquo; knowledge and understanding of STEM career pathways and careers (STEM major awareness and STEM career awareness)? (2) What are program design principles, target audiences, effective practices, and technological innovations of rigorously designed studies of programs that exhibit strong or exemplary evidence of impact? (3) What are program design principles, effective practices, and technological innovations proven to work effectively in underserved and underrepresented populations?</p> <p>We used a mixed methods approach, incorporating meta-analyses and qualitative syntheses, to evaluate how and to what extent informal STEM learning experiences impact knowledge and understanding of STEM career pathways. We found a significant positive association between participation in informal STEM programs and increased STEM career awareness. Our meta-syntheses revealed that informal STEM programs that targeted high school students, girls, or members of historically underrepresented groups, and also focused on career exploration and experiential learning, were most effective at fostering STEM career awareness. Our findings identified program design principles, effective practices, and technological innovations that can be adopted by STEM practitioners, and suggests that informal STEM institutions play an underappreciated role in ensuring that youth are introduced to potential future STEM careers.</p> <p>To disseminate our findings to researchers and the public, our database was submitted to Dryad, an open data publishing platform that makes research data publicly available: DOI (10.5061/dryad.0rxwdbs7v). Our database, is based on 678 studies that met the inclusion criteria of our meta-analyses, includes the following information: (1) citation information; (2) general description of each study; (3) overview of the curriculum; (4) theoretical framework; (5) demographic characteristics of participants (e.g. grade; gender; ethnic/racial background); (6) description of data (qualitative; quantitative; mixed method)/methods applied; (7) what was measured (STEM major or STEM career awareness, interest, or engagement); (8) sample size; (9) summary of results; (10) location of program (e.g. museum, non-profit organizations, university, zoo, etc.); (11) program time frame (e.g. summer, afterschool, longitudinal); and (12) type of paper (research, evaluation, conference, white paper).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/29/2024<br> Modified by: Mande&nbsp;Holford</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Engagement in STEM career pathways can result in positive outcomes, including earning higher incomes and making meaningful contributions to society. However, a significant challenge encountered by educators is to identify strategies that motivate youth to consider a STEM career pathway. While several informal STEM institutions have developed programming specifically designed to foster STEM major and STEM career awareness, gauging the effectiveness of these initiatives remains elusive. This study conducts a meta-synthesis of research on informal STEM programs and outlines barriers and opportunities involved in Promoting STEM Major and STEM Career Awareness to youth participants. Specifically we address three questions: (1) How and to what extent do informal STEM learning experiences impact K-12 participants knowledge and understanding of STEM career pathways and careers (STEM major awareness and STEM career awareness)? (2) What are program design principles, target audiences, effective practices, and technological innovations of rigorously designed studies of programs that exhibit strong or exemplary evidence of impact? (3) What are program design principles, effective practices, and technological innovations proven to work effectively in underserved and underrepresented populations?   We used a mixed methods approach, incorporating meta-analyses and qualitative syntheses, to evaluate how and to what extent informal STEM learning experiences impact knowledge and understanding of STEM career pathways. We found a significant positive association between participation in informal STEM programs and increased STEM career awareness. Our meta-syntheses revealed that informal STEM programs that targeted high school students, girls, or members of historically underrepresented groups, and also focused on career exploration and experiential learning, were most effective at fostering STEM career awareness. Our findings identified program design principles, effective practices, and technological innovations that can be adopted by STEM practitioners, and suggests that informal STEM institutions play an underappreciated role in ensuring that youth are introduced to potential future STEM careers.   To disseminate our findings to researchers and the public, our database was submitted to Dryad, an open data publishing platform that makes research data publicly available: DOI (10.5061/dryad.0rxwdbs7v). Our database, is based on 678 studies that met the inclusion criteria of our meta-analyses, includes the following information: (1) citation information; (2) general description of each study; (3) overview of the curriculum; (4) theoretical framework; (5) demographic characteristics of participants (e.g. grade; gender; ethnic/racial background); (6) description of data (qualitative; quantitative; mixed method)/methods applied; (7) what was measured (STEM major or STEM career awareness, interest, or engagement); (8) sample size; (9) summary of results; (10) location of program (e.g. museum, non-profit organizations, university, zoo, etc.); (11) program time frame (e.g. summer, afterschool, longitudinal); and (12) type of paper (research, evaluation, conference, white paper).        Last Modified: 09/29/2024       Submitted by: MandeHolford]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
