<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Crop-Climate Feedback Cycle and its Implications for Global Food Production]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeremy Koster</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkoster@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922664</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Crop growth often creates conditions more favorable for crop production, this is known as the crop-climate feedback cycle. Research has demonstrated that in some of the world's most productive agricultural regions, crop growth may cool the local climate, reducing the impact of crop-damaging hot temperatures, thereby boosting crop yields. This project's geographical analysis demonstrates the strength and spatial variability of the crop-climate feedback, as well as the physical mechanisms driving it. By better understanding how crops interact with local climate, this project informs efforts to anticipate environmental changes that could impact future agricultural potential as well as adapting strategies to limit crop yield losses. The project's findings will be made available to the public via media outlets and presentations and will be of interest to various agricultural stakeholders and those who analyze food security. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project integrates spatial analysis, climate science, and statistical crop yield modeling to assess the extent to which crop growth affects local climate, and how this, in turn, impacts crop production. This research is guided by four questions: (1) what are the physical mechanisms driving the crop-climate feedback? (2) how does the strength and importance of the feedback vary across geographic space and across differing levels of economic development and patterns of vulnerability to natural disasters? (3) how might the crop-climate feedback affect crop yield trends in the coming decades? and (4) could the crop-climate feedback enable an adaptive strategy of agricultural consolidation to reduce crop yield losses in a warming climate? The project's findings inform researchers about the interaction between crops and the climate, which is critical for assessing the future risk of climate-driven food insecurity, the potential for economic losses in agricultural regions, and for developing adaptation strategies to increase the climate resilience of food production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049262</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Mankin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin S Mankin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mankin@dartmouth.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779746</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
<LastName>Coffel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ethan D Coffel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[edcoffel@maxwell.syr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>13244</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 S CROUSE AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C4BXLBC11LC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>141Y00</Code>
<Text>Human-Envi &amp; Geographical Scis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>105Z</Code>
<Text>HEGS: Human-Envirnmnt and Geogrphcl Sci</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project explored how agricultural intensification influences local climate conditions and how these crop-driven changes in climate affect food production. This grant has supported several research projects, resulting in 4 peer-reviewed publications and one other paper currently in review.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual merit</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our research showed that agricultural intensification &ndash; meaning increasing yields through technological improvements &ndash; can cool hot days over croplands. In the central US, this crop-driven cooling masks some of the CO2-driven warming since 1980. This cooling effect, driven by increased moisture in the atmosphere from crop evapotranspiration, reduces the intensity of heat waves in agricultural areas and thus reduces the harmful effects of heat on crop yields. However, we also showed that current climate models do not fully capture this crop-driven cooling, leading to an overestimation of temperature over croplands.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The grant also supported two associated projects. The first showed that agricultural workers face growing risks from extreme heat. In some regions, irrigation or crop ET could actually worsen this heat exposure by increasing wet bulb temperatures. This poses challenges for worker safety and productivity, potentially affecting agricultural output in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The second measured the effect of hot and humid vs hot and dry days on crop yields. We show that hot and humid days are not harmful to crops, while hot and dry days are, even when dry-bulb temperatures are the same. This result supports the mechanism behind the crop-climate feedback: moistening the atmosphere through ET can reduce heat-related crop damage.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our research findings have already been incorporated into several research-oriented undergraduate courses at Syracuse University. The grant also supported a postdoctoral researcher for two years, providing valuable experience and mentorship in interdisciplinary research. The postdoctoral researcher was able to attend two conferences and has a paper currently in review. Additionally, the project supported collaborative research between Syracuse University and Dartmouth College, enhancing the reach and impact of our research across institutions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 09/13/2024<br> Modified by: Ethan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Coffel</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project explored how agricultural intensification influences local climate conditions and how these crop-driven changes in climate affect food production. This grant has supported several research projects, resulting in 4 peer-reviewed publications and one other paper currently in review.      Intellectual merit      Our research showed that agricultural intensification  meaning increasing yields through technological improvements  can cool hot days over croplands. In the central US, this crop-driven cooling masks some of the CO2-driven warming since 1980. This cooling effect, driven by increased moisture in the atmosphere from crop evapotranspiration, reduces the intensity of heat waves in agricultural areas and thus reduces the harmful effects of heat on crop yields. However, we also showed that current climate models do not fully capture this crop-driven cooling, leading to an overestimation of temperature over croplands.      The grant also supported two associated projects. The first showed that agricultural workers face growing risks from extreme heat. In some regions, irrigation or crop ET could actually worsen this heat exposure by increasing wet bulb temperatures. This poses challenges for worker safety and productivity, potentially affecting agricultural output in the future.      The second measured the effect of hot and humid vs hot and dry days on crop yields. We show that hot and humid days are not harmful to crops, while hot and dry days are, even when dry-bulb temperatures are the same. This result supports the mechanism behind the crop-climate feedback: moistening the atmosphere through ET can reduce heat-related crop damage.      Broader impacts      Our research findings have already been incorporated into several research-oriented undergraduate courses at Syracuse University. The grant also supported a postdoctoral researcher for two years, providing valuable experience and mentorship in interdisciplinary research. The postdoctoral researcher was able to attend two conferences and has a paper currently in review. Additionally, the project supported collaborative research between Syracuse University and Dartmouth College, enhancing the reach and impact of our research across institutions.              Last Modified: 09/13/2024       Submitted by: EthanDCoffel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
