<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[REU Site: Undergraduate Research Experiences in Computer Systems at University of Louisville]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405051.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405051</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Louisville will  establishes a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site to host a diverse cohort of undergraduate students across the nation in 10-week summer sessions to conduct research with faculty mentors on topics related to computer systems, including operating systems, parallel and distributed systems, embedded systems, mobile systems, and computer architecture. In addition to the significant broader social impacts of the proposed research projects, this REU site will impact undergraduate students from schools with limited research opportunities by helping them gain theoretical and practical knowledge in computer systems, training them in conducting cutting-edge computer systems research and inspiring them to pursue postgraduate education in computer science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The end of Moore's Law is an exciting time to explore new computer system designs for the future. This REU Site includes a broad range of computer systems research topics, ranging from processor architecture to storage systems and from small-scale systems such as mobile and edge devices to large-scale systems including exascale data centers. Research projects will advance the state-of-the-art in computer systems by exploring new architectures for emerging applications on mobile and edge devices, energy-efficient storage stack designs for operating systems, energy-efficient embedded systems and microcontrollers, new software tools for data-intensive and high-performance computing, new graph analytics algorithms, holistic security solutions for IoT applications, novel distributed and explainable machine learning algorithms, new quantum acceleration techniques, and novel GPU enabled parallel document inversion algorithms for bioinformatics applications. A multi-level mentoring model will be followed through weekly meetings with the PIs, daily meetings with the mentors, and continuous interaction with graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050925</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wei.zhang@louisville.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000227345</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nihat</FirstName>
<LastName>Altiparmak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nihat Altiparmak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nihat.altiparmak@louisville.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662271</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>LOUISVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>402081838</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5028523788</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2301 S 3RD ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E1KJM4T54MK6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF LOUISVILLE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>402021959</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>113900</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~405051</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The REU Site, "Undergraduate Research Experiences in Computer Systems at the University of Louisville," has attracted 30 diverse undergraduate students from across the nation over the past three years, including many from institutions with limited research opportunities. Participants have engaged in research spanning various computer systems projects, such as memory, storage, and file systems; mobile and extensible distributed systems; cloud and data-intensive processing systems; as well as embedded and multicore systems and accelerators. Given the foundational importance of computer science, fostering a robust and diverse pipeline of students equipped with substantial research experience in computer systems is essential for cultivating the next generation of researchers in this field.</p> <p>The first two summers of this project occurred during the COVID-19 pandemic, prompting us to conduct the REU site virtually, ensuring students could still benefit from full-time research experience in computer systems within a safe and healthy environment. However, the third summer of the REU took place in person at the University of Louisville, providing participants greater opportunities for face-to-face interactions with mentors and peers.</p> <p>Over the course of these three years, our REU site has consistently attracted a significant number of applicants and participants from Kentucky, aligning with our project's objective of expanding research opportunities for students in Kentucky, an EPSCoR state. Simultaneously, we have successfully recruited nationwide, enrolling a total of 12 students from 8 different states. Particularly noteworthy is our project's engagement of 16 students from institutions with limited research prospects, fulfilling our aim of broadening research opportunities for students who might otherwise lack access to computer systems research opportunities.</p> <p>Evaluation results from an independent evaluator have indicated that REU participants at our site were highly satisfied with their experience, noting significant increases in their knowledge of computer systems and research skills. These include proficiency in employing the scientific method to solve problems, designing experiments, creating graphs from data, and composing technical reports. Additionally, students reported enhancements in their coding skills, Linux proficiency, problem-solving abilities, and resilience in navigating long-term challenges with numerous obstacles. Moreover, 70% of surveyed students expressed an interest in pursuing graduate studies in computer science or computer engineering. Notably, the previous REU project yielded 5 peer-reviewed conference or workshop papers, 10 technical reports, and 30 research posters.</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 05/12/2024<br> Modified by: Wei&nbsp;Zhang</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The REU Site, "Undergraduate Research Experiences in Computer Systems at the University of Louisville," has attracted 30 diverse undergraduate students from across the nation over the past three years, including many from institutions with limited research opportunities. Participants have engaged in research spanning various computer systems projects, such as memory, storage, and file systems; mobile and extensible distributed systems; cloud and data-intensive processing systems; as well as embedded and multicore systems and accelerators. Given the foundational importance of computer science, fostering a robust and diverse pipeline of students equipped with substantial research experience in computer systems is essential for cultivating the next generation of researchers in this field.   The first two summers of this project occurred during the COVID-19 pandemic, prompting us to conduct the REU site virtually, ensuring students could still benefit from full-time research experience in computer systems within a safe and healthy environment. However, the third summer of the REU took place in person at the University of Louisville, providing participants greater opportunities for face-to-face interactions with mentors and peers.   Over the course of these three years, our REU site has consistently attracted a significant number of applicants and participants from Kentucky, aligning with our project's objective of expanding research opportunities for students in Kentucky, an EPSCoR state. Simultaneously, we have successfully recruited nationwide, enrolling a total of 12 students from 8 different states. Particularly noteworthy is our project's engagement of 16 students from institutions with limited research prospects, fulfilling our aim of broadening research opportunities for students who might otherwise lack access to computer systems research opportunities.   Evaluation results from an independent evaluator have indicated that REU participants at our site were highly satisfied with their experience, noting significant increases in their knowledge of computer systems and research skills. These include proficiency in employing the scientific method to solve problems, designing experiments, creating graphs from data, and composing technical reports. Additionally, students reported enhancements in their coding skills, Linux proficiency, problem-solving abilities, and resilience in navigating long-term challenges with numerous obstacles. Moreover, 70% of surveyed students expressed an interest in pursuing graduate studies in computer science or computer engineering. Notably, the previous REU project yielded 5 peer-reviewed conference or workshop papers, 10 technical reports, and 30 research posters.     Last Modified: 05/12/2024       Submitted by: WeiZhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
