<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAR-PF: Impact of flooding intensity on levee development and dynamics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aisha Morris</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>armorris@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927081</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is funded in whole or in part under the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (Public Law 117-2).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Eric Barefoot has been granted an NSF EAR Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out research and education plans at Indiana University.  Dr. Barefoot will study flooding, a significant natural hazard that threatens critical infrastructure and communities in the US and across the world. Artificial embankments (or dikes) along river corridors are often constructed to reduce flooding hazards and these engineering projects often take advantage of natural levees on the floodplain. Levees form next to a river channel when the river floods and sediment spreads out away from the river. Because levee formation correlates poorly with river attributes, it remains challenging to predict where and when levees will form. This project seeks to test a new hypothesis: that the intensity of floods is a key control on levee formation. By combining analysis of floodplains across the State of Indiana with monitoring on the Lower Mississippi River, this project will determine the importance of flood intensity for levee formation. Dr. Barefoot will also identify processes by which sediment is transported on river floodplains during floods. These research outcomes will be coupled with an educational outreach plan that focuses on engaging public-school educators to produce new curriculum focused on flood hazards and sustainability in Indiana. Additionally, this project will bolster STEM engagement for LGBTQ+ undergraduate students through local field-based research opportunities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Natural levees form and develop during overbank flow, when sediment-laden water decants from the river, and deposits adjacent to the channel. The pattern of sediment deposition is controlled by water surface gradients across the inundated floodplain. The orientation and mag- nitude of water surface gradients are hypothesized to depend on flooding intensity; operationally defined here as the coefficient of variation of discharge (CVQ). However, the impact of flooding intensity on floodplain deposition is poorly constrained because direct observations of co-evolving floodplain topography and inundation hydraulics are scarce. This project will quantify the impact of flooding intensity on floodplain inundation patterns and analyze how resulting water surface gradients influence levee formation and development. This research will combine repeat lidar datasets with field surveys and sedimentological observations on floodplains in Indiana, USA, to compare levee morphology and composition spanning a range of historical flooding intensities. To link flooding intensity and sediment dispersal in a mechanistic framework, a complementary case study will be conducted in an end-member locality typified by low flooding intensity. In-situ measurements of water surface elevation and velocity during annual overbank conditions in an engineered section of the Mississippi River will be paired with repeat lidar topography surveys to couple inundation hydraulics with topographic evolution. New insights from this project will fill a critical research need because intensified flooding due to contemporary climate change threatens sustainability of river corridors. The scientific outcomes will inform land management strategies while also driving fundamental advances in sedimentology and geomorphology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052844</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Barefoot</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric A Barefoot</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000837356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Barefoot, Eric A]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University Bloomington]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474057000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>722200</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~174000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a870fdcf-7fff-19b2-0c51-fd386b44aa7b"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Rivers naturally form levees at their margins when water spills out during floods and inundates the floodplain. Levees (both natural and engineered) serve an important flood-control function. People live on levees, build their cities around levees, and depend on levees during floods to protect their property from damage. And yet, because levees are subtle landforms which form during rare events, we know surprisingly little about how, when, or where they form. This project explored a new way for understanding levee formation. The researchers worked at two different levels.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>First, the researchers worked at the scale of the entire continental USA, collecting publicly-funded and freely-available topographic data. They manually examined a random sample of rivers, and determined which segments of rivers possessed levees and which did not. They found that about the majority of rivers possess levees on some portion of their banks. They found that on average, rivers have levees more often in wet climates, when they are close to the shoreline, and when the river flows through a low-sloping landscape.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Second, the researchers established an intensive field monitoring campaign for a small floodplain, to examine how overbank flow produces levees. The researchers installed equipment like water level loggers, water velocity sensors, and cameras to monitor spring floods in an environment that reliably floods every year. This ongoing monitoring campaign has revealed that sediment accumulation and transport on the river floodplain depends very strongly on the pathways floodwater takes from the river.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>These results will form the foundation for a new understanding of river levee formation. By taking both a detailed view, the researchers observed that the mechanics of how levees form may depend on the local hydrology and geomorphology. But by taking a broad view, the researchers discovered that there are consistent factors that make levee formation more likely. Both of these observations can improve our understanding of the life-cycle of a river levee, and reveal more about this ubiquitous, but enigmatic, natural landform.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition, the researchers engaged the broader community in this science. The researchers hosted high school students for a summer research immersion program. The researchers have involved community citizen scientists in data collection efforts. The researchers have also presented their work and gotten feedback from local conservation groups interested in the floodplain monitoring project.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 07/02/2024<br> Modified by: Eric&nbsp;A&nbsp;Barefoot</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Rivers naturally form levees at their margins when water spills out during floods and inundates the floodplain. Levees (both natural and engineered) serve an important flood-control function. People live on levees, build their cities around levees, and depend on levees during floods to protect their property from damage. And yet, because levees are subtle landforms which form during rare events, we know surprisingly little about how, when, or where they form. This project explored a new way for understanding levee formation. The researchers worked at two different levels.   First, the researchers worked at the scale of the entire continental USA, collecting publicly-funded and freely-available topographic data. They manually examined a random sample of rivers, and determined which segments of rivers possessed levees and which did not. They found that about the majority of rivers possess levees on some portion of their banks. They found that on average, rivers have levees more often in wet climates, when they are close to the shoreline, and when the river flows through a low-sloping landscape.   Second, the researchers established an intensive field monitoring campaign for a small floodplain, to examine how overbank flow produces levees. The researchers installed equipment like water level loggers, water velocity sensors, and cameras to monitor spring floods in an environment that reliably floods every year. This ongoing monitoring campaign has revealed that sediment accumulation and transport on the river floodplain depends very strongly on the pathways floodwater takes from the river.   These results will form the foundation for a new understanding of river levee formation. By taking both a detailed view, the researchers observed that the mechanics of how levees form may depend on the local hydrology and geomorphology. But by taking a broad view, the researchers discovered that there are consistent factors that make levee formation more likely. Both of these observations can improve our understanding of the life-cycle of a river levee, and reveal more about this ubiquitous, but enigmatic, natural landform.   In addition, the researchers engaged the broader community in this science. The researchers hosted high school students for a summer research immersion program. The researchers have involved community citizen scientists in data collection efforts. The researchers have also presented their work and gotten feedback from local conservation groups interested in the floodplain monitoring project.        Last Modified: 07/02/2024       Submitted by: EricABarefoot]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
