<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: AI-Driven Multi-Scale Design of Materials under Processing Constraints]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>272440.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>272440</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jitesh H. Panchal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpanchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this project is to improve the knowledge of materials design by developing a multi-scale methodology that combines physics-based models of thermo-mechanical processing and materials with artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML). The underlying hypothesis is that the metallic components can be designed to achieve targeted macro-scale properties and performance by optimizing the underlying microstructural features and processing parameters. The project will build design methodology that enables: (i) investigation of the effects of microstructures and processing parameters on macro-scale properties; and (ii) identification of multiple optimum material designs that provide desired macro-scale performance. The ability to optimize macro-scale properties by designing microstructures and processes will improve the performance of current and future engineering systems. Additionally, with the consideration of manufacturing constraints, this multi-scale design framework will not merely identify mathematical solutions, but the designs that will be manufacturable. The researched methods and results will be tested against the experimental data of a Titanium-Aluminum alloy. The societal impacts of the project will be on the economy, with performance improvement in metallic components and minimization of the time and costs associated with manufacturing. The gained knowledge will be disseminated to academia and industry with technical activities and open-access software tools. Additional deliverables of the project include curriculum development at both undergraduate and graduate levels, research and education experiences for students, and other outreach activities involving students and educators with a special focus on individuals from underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of this project is to advance knowledge in the design of metallic materials by developing a multi-scale optimization strategy that will be driven by the physics-based models of thermo-mechanical processing and microstructures, and AI/ML-based predictive modeling and knowledge discovery approaches. The research will address the inverse design problem that aims to optimize the thermo-mechanical processing parameters (i.e., strain rate, temperature, duration) to achieve desired microstructural features (i.e., crystallographic texture, grain morphology) and macro-scale properties by investigating the coupled, multi-scale, and high-dimensional interactions within the processing-(micro)structure-property chain. To achieve this goal, the project will develop physics-based models that enable explicit quantification of microstructural orientations and morphology (grain sizes and shapes), and an ML-guided feedback-aware identification strategy for key processing/(micro)-structure parameters, which will be subsequently explored by targeted sampling. The research will improve the understanding of inverse materials design by also integrating manufacturing constraints into the design framework and exploring multiple optimum material solutions that provide desired macro-scale properties. The physics-based and AI/ML-driven models, as well as the optimum results obtained by the multi-scale design framework, will be validated using the experimental processing, microstructure, and property data of a Titanium-Aluminum alloy. The education and outreach objectives of the project focus on training students and the future workforce to create new knowledge on computational and ML-driven design of materials, which will be supported with curriculum development and an extensive dissemination and outreach plan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2053840</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pinar</FirstName>
<LastName>Acar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pinar Acar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pacar@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000768812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 TURNER ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QDE5UHE5XD16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE &amp; STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X6KEFGLHSJX7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[635 Price's Fork Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>072Y00</Code>
<Text>EDSE-Engineering Design and Sy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068E</Code>
<Text>DESIGN THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>075Z</Code>
<Text>Artificial Intelligence (AI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>077E</Code>
<Text>SIMULATION MODELS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~272440</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has aimed to advance knowledge in materials design by developing a unique multi-scale optimization method that is driven by artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML). Component-level material properties of metals are strictly dependent on microstructural features, which in turn are dependent on the processing of the materials. Consequently, the material design requires multi-scale information transfer between processing, microstructure, and properties. Addressing the effects of processing on microstructures and the effects of microstructures on homogenized properties is a key challenge of materials design due to the high dimensionality and challenging nature of processing-structure-property linkages. To address these challenges, this project has built a design methodology combining physics-based processing and microstructure models with AI/ML algorithms to understand the evolution of microstructures under processing and to compute mechanical properties as a function of microstructural features.</p>  <p>The proposed methodology has consisted of two phases: random data generation for unoptimized but valid solutions satisfying given constraints, followed by an ML-guided feedback-aware identification of key processing/structure parameters which would be subsequently explored by targeted sampling. By leveraging our team&rsquo;s vast expertise in materials informatics, we have demonstrated a proof-of-concept of the proposed approach for structure-property optimization with a specific and limited structure representation. Furthermore, our team has built on this approach by incorporating more generic and complete structure representations, and extending it to process design, thereby discovering processing routes for microstructural evolution and thus enabling true data-driven multi-scale materials design with process-structure-property linkages. In particular, physics-based models of process-microstructure and microstructure-property interactions have been developed and used to create data to train AI/ML algorithms. Next, a multi-scale design framework has been developed by integrating data-driven AI/ML models into the physics-based models.</p>  <p>The intellectual merit of the project is addressing<strong> </strong>the knowledge gap in the multi-scale design of metals by considering the effects of materials processing on microstructures and properties. Following the developed ML-driven strategy linking process-structure-property, the location-specific properties of components can be optimized through the inverse design of the underlying microstructure and processing parameters. The developed design framework has been applied to different polycrystalline metals such as Copper, Galfenol, and Titanium-Aluminum alloys while our design methodology is applicable to all polycrystalline metals with the necessary adjustments related to the changing crystalline structures. The ability gained within this project to optimize the homogenized mechanical response of materials by designing microstructures and processes will be instrumental in improving the performance of current and future engineering systems. The developed methodology in this project can also be applied to the inverse design of 3-D printed metals in the future.</p>  <p>The broader impacts of the project are related to the performance improvements that can be achieved in metallic components through the design of microstructures. Additionally, the developed data-driven multi-scale design framework can be utilized to minimize the time and costs associated with the manufacturing of many different materials. The knowledge gained on materials design and AI/ML throughout the project has also been shared with graduate, undergraduate, and K-12 students through various events involving student training, research and independent study opportunities, and educational activities. Such activities also included curriculum development. The PI has developed a new graduate class for the engineering students at Virginia Tech, &ldquo;Data-Driven Modeling and Materials Design&rdquo;, which will leverage expertise and data from this project.</p>  <p>The findings of the project have been reported in journal articles, peer-reviewed conference proceedings, conference presentations, and invited talks. Some of the project findings are also discussed by our Virginia Tech Team in our recent invited review article (Billah et al, Advanced Engineering Materials (2024)) and highlighted by the Aerospace America Magazine (<a href="https://aerospaceamerica.aiaa.org/year-in-review/innovations-in-design-and-test-for-the-new-space-frontier/" target="_blank">https://aerospaceamerica.aiaa.org/year-in-review/innovations-in-design-and-test-for-the-new-space-frontier/</a>). The project data are disseminated through our group&rsquo;s GitHub webpage and VTechData repository of Virginia Tech.</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/06/2024<br> Modified by: Pinar&nbsp;Acar</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2053840/2053840_10751252_1733505933539_General_Overview--rgov-214x142.png" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2053840/2053840_10751252_1733505933539_General_Overview--rgov-800width.png" title="General Overview of the Materials Design Problem"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2053840/2053840_10751252_1733505933539_General_Overview--rgov-66x44.png" alt="General Overview of the Materials Design Problem"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The developed AI/ML-driven methodology investigated the forward and inverse engineering design for processing and microstructure parameters to achieve targeted property distributions throughout the components by utilizing forward physics-based material models.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pinar Acar and Ankit Agrawal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pinar&nbsp;Acar <div class="imageTitle">General Overview of the Materials Design Problem</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project has aimed to advance knowledge in materials design by developing a unique multi-scale optimization method that is driven by artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML). Component-level material properties of metals are strictly dependent on microstructural features, which in turn are dependent on the processing of the materials. Consequently, the material design requires multi-scale information transfer between processing, microstructure, and properties. Addressing the effects of processing on microstructures and the effects of microstructures on homogenized properties is a key challenge of materials design due to the high dimensionality and challenging nature of processing-structure-property linkages. To address these challenges, this project has built a design methodology combining physics-based processing and microstructure models with AI/ML algorithms to understand the evolution of microstructures under processing and to compute mechanical properties as a function of microstructural features.    The proposed methodology has consisted of two phases: random data generation for unoptimized but valid solutions satisfying given constraints, followed by an ML-guided feedback-aware identification of key processing/structure parameters which would be subsequently explored by targeted sampling. By leveraging our teams vast expertise in materials informatics, we have demonstrated a proof-of-concept of the proposed approach for structure-property optimization with a specific and limited structure representation. Furthermore, our team has built on this approach by incorporating more generic and complete structure representations, and extending it to process design, thereby discovering processing routes for microstructural evolution and thus enabling true data-driven multi-scale materials design with process-structure-property linkages. In particular, physics-based models of process-microstructure and microstructure-property interactions have been developed and used to create data to train AI/ML algorithms. Next, a multi-scale design framework has been developed by integrating data-driven AI/ML models into the physics-based models.    The intellectual merit of the project is addressing the knowledge gap in the multi-scale design of metals by considering the effects of materials processing on microstructures and properties. Following the developed ML-driven strategy linking process-structure-property, the location-specific properties of components can be optimized through the inverse design of the underlying microstructure and processing parameters. The developed design framework has been applied to different polycrystalline metals such as Copper, Galfenol, and Titanium-Aluminum alloys while our design methodology is applicable to all polycrystalline metals with the necessary adjustments related to the changing crystalline structures. The ability gained within this project to optimize the homogenized mechanical response of materials by designing microstructures and processes will be instrumental in improving the performance of current and future engineering systems. The developed methodology in this project can also be applied to the inverse design of 3-D printed metals in the future.    The broader impacts of the project are related to the performance improvements that can be achieved in metallic components through the design of microstructures. Additionally, the developed data-driven multi-scale design framework can be utilized to minimize the time and costs associated with the manufacturing of many different materials. The knowledge gained on materials design and AI/ML throughout the project has also been shared with graduate, undergraduate, and K-12 students through various events involving student training, research and independent study opportunities, and educational activities. Such activities also included curriculum development. The PI has developed a new graduate class for the engineering students at Virginia Tech, Data-Driven Modeling and Materials Design, which will leverage expertise and data from this project.    The findings of the project have been reported in journal articles, peer-reviewed conference proceedings, conference presentations, and invited talks. Some of the project findings are also discussed by our Virginia Tech Team in our recent invited review article (Billah et al, Advanced Engineering Materials (2024)) and highlighted by the Aerospace America Magazine (https://aerospaceamerica.aiaa.org/year-in-review/innovations-in-design-and-test-for-the-new-space-frontier/). The project data are disseminated through our groups GitHub webpage and VTechData repository of Virginia Tech.         Last Modified: 12/06/2024       Submitted by: PinarAcar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
