<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Path to Information Technology (IT) Practice: Increasing Credential Completions in IT within the Southern Tier of Virginia]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>495026.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>495026</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Tymann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ptymann@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922832</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is well documented that the Information Technology (IT) workforce is chronically understaffed, and predictions show that the shortage of IT workers will reach alarming levels in a few years. The goal of this project is to increase the number of students from Southside Virginia Community College, especially those from populations currently underrepresented in the IT professions, who are ready to enter the regional IT workforce. The project will target high school students in dual enrollment programs, as well as adult learners, employing a culturally responsive model that will increase enrollments and retention. Project goals will be attained by the deployment of a program infrastructure that incorporates a comprehensive recruitment strategy, with a specific focus on students from groups traditionally underrepresented in IT careers, coupled with academic support strategies and identity-building and self-efficacy activities to ensure student success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project team will study methods to increase recruitment and attainment of success in community college IT programs, especially among students traditionally underrepresented in IT careers. Increased educational attainment is positively correlated with higher standards of living, increased wages, and overall prosperity and welfare. This project has the potential to improve the understanding and implementation of culturally responsive advising for all students, but especially for those traditionally underrepresented in IT professions. Results from this work will inform the Governor's G3 Initiative ("Get a Skill. Get a Job. Get Ahead") in Virginia, which is focused on getting credentialed students back to school to upskill for emerging technical careers. Providing opportunities for students, specifically those who are marginalized, will help address the gap in the IT industry by increasing the number of women and underrepresented minorities obtaining credentials. This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2055631</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
<LastName>Patton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chad Patton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chad.patton@southside.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833730</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/22/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
<LastName>Patton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chad Patton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chad.patton@southside.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833730</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/14/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
<LastName>Patton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chad Patton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chad.patton@southside.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833730</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Crystal</FirstName>
<LastName>Pendergrass</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Crystal J Pendergrass</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[crystal.pendergrass@southside.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834059</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/22/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vondrenna</FirstName>
<LastName>Smithers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vondrenna N Smithers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vondrenna.smithers@southside.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000839268</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/14/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meredith</FirstName>
<LastName>Dawson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meredith V Dawson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[meredith.dawson@southside.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000936836</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joan</FirstName>
<LastName>Tuck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joan B Tuck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[joan.tuck@southside.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000936858</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southside Virginia Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>ALBERTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>238212930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349491000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[109 CAMPUS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KR1MNR2VXMD5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTHSIDE VIRGINIA COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>P19GJUAZJN83</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southside Virginia Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Alberta</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>238212930</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[109 Campus Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>741200</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~495026</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-7805d1db-7fff-4988-bf14-e9f118bf46e2"> </span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Overview</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>In 2021, Southside Virginia Community College received a $495,026 National Science Foundation (NSF) award entitled, "Path to Information Technology (IT) Practice (PIP)".&nbsp; PIP was a three-year award focusing on increasing the number of students in underrepresented populations in the IT field who achieve stackable and/or stacked industry credentials.&nbsp; This award was deployed within the Center for Information Technology Excellence (CITE) program at the college.</span></p>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Core Objectives</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>PIP had three core objectives:</span></p>  <ul>  <li>Increase total enrollment by 35% (30 students) and enrollment of underrepresented students by 45% (28 students),</li>  <li>Increase total credential attainment by 45% (10 students) and of underrepresented students by 50% (6 students), and</li>  <li>Institutionalize a sustainable model to continue the PIP program activities.</li>  </ul>  <ol> </ol>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Specific Activities</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>To meet these core objectives, deliverables centered around four specific activities:</span></p>  <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-7805d1db-7fff-4988-bf14-e9f118bf46e2"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Program Infrastructure</span><br /><br /></span>The CITE program is offered to both dual enrollment high school students and adult learners.&nbsp; A new Career Studies Certificate, Information Technology Help Desk, was created specifically for the dual enrollment students to 1) promote credential attainment, 2) offer a path to success for those with limited prior knowledge in IT, and 3) comprehend the course learning outcomes for Information Technology courses.&nbsp; Dual enrollment students in this program have an opportunity to earn two CompTIA industry certifications.<br /><br />The CITE program for adult learners leads to a Career Studies Certificate in Cybersecurity and Networking Foundations.&nbsp; Students in this program have the opportunity to earn five CompTIA industry certifications.&nbsp; During the award period, program infrastructure improvements centered around the sequence of courses taken as well as the availability of resources to assist students in preparing for certification exams. A key factor in meeting the enrollment goals for this award was a comprehensive and consistent offering of the seven classes required for the college certificate.&nbsp; This resulted in the hiring of additional adjuncts.</p>  <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Comprehensive Recruitment Strategies</span><br /><br />Recruitment strategies were intentional with a focused lens on underrepresented students in Information Technology.&nbsp; A CITE Resource Wizard webpage was created on the college website with information regarding the IT field, program description, program courses, industry certifications, and contact information. <br /><br />Since the CITE program includes both dual enrollment high school students and adult learners, recruitment activities were varied and expanded.&nbsp; Dual enrollment recruiting included presentations on campus for "College for a Day" events for K12 students, visitations to K12 schools by CITE staff for career days, and tours of the CITE location provided to K12 groups.&nbsp; An additional activity hosted by the college was a one-week "Girls in IT" summer camp for high school students.<br /><br />For adult students, recruitment strategies focused on social media campaigns, flyers (digital and print), email marketing campaigns, telephone campaigns, and one-on-one advising.&nbsp; Individual development plans were created for CITE students to assist with advising.</p>  <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Academic Support Strategies</span><br /><br />Key strategies implemented related to academic support included an orientation to the CITE program presented to every class during the first two weeks of the semester, and availability of tools and resources designed to help prepare students for industry certification exams, specifically CompTIA exams.</p>  <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Identity-Building and Self-Efficacy Strategies</span><br /><br />During the award period, a required class, Preparation for Employment, was updated to ensure that resume writing, LinkedIn account creation, and interviewing skills were aligned with employer needs.&nbsp; Soft skills training was included.&nbsp; The promotion of internships in the IT field was also a focus during this period.</p>  <ol> </ol> <ol> </ol>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Results</strong></p>  <ul>  <li> Total enrollment increased by 40% throughout the grant period, exceeding the project's&nbsp;target of a 35% increase. The total enrollment among underrepresented groups, including Black students, Hispanic students, and female students, increased by 62.2% throughout the grant period.</li>  <li>Since the summer of 2022, 52 CITE students passed a CompTIA certification exam, including 18 Black students and 16 female students.&nbsp; This exceeded the project's target.</li>  <li>During the grant period, the project team hired three adjunct faculty members who represented underrepresented populations and were employed in the IT field.&nbsp; This ensured that all courses required for the college certificate could be offered each semester by skilled and credentialed faculty.&nbsp; In addition, a full-time CITE Program Head was hired to sustain the PIP program activities that demonstrated strategies for growth and success.</li>  </ul>  <ol> </ol>  <p dir="ltr"><strong>Summary</strong></p>  <p dir="ltr"><span>This award led to successful increased enrollment in IT programs, diversification of its IT student body, a strengthened IT curriculum, industry certification testing preparation, hiring of additional faculty and a CITE Program Head, the launch of intentional recruitment activities, and implementation of academic support strategies.</span></p>  <div><span><br /></span></div>  <p>&nbsp;</p>  <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 12/20/2024<br> Modified by: Joan&nbsp;B&nbsp;Tuck</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       Overview    In 2021, Southside Virginia Community College received a $495,026 National Science Foundation (NSF) award entitled, "Path to Information Technology (IT) Practice (PIP)". PIP was a three-year award focusing on increasing the number of students in underrepresented populations in the IT field who achieve stackable and/or stacked industry credentials. This award was deployed within the Center for Information Technology Excellence (CITE) program at the college.    Core Objectives    PIP had three core objectives:    Increase total enrollment by 35% (30 students) and enrollment of underrepresented students by 45% (28 students),  Increase total credential attainment by 45% (10 students) and of underrepresented students by 50% (6 students), and  Institutionalize a sustainable model to continue the PIP program activities.         Specific Activities    To meet these core objectives, deliverables centered around four specific activities:    Program Infrastructure  The CITE program is offered to both dual enrollment high school students and adult learners. A new Career Studies Certificate, Information Technology Help Desk, was created specifically for the dual enrollment students to 1) promote credential attainment, 2) offer a path to success for those with limited prior knowledge in IT, and 3) comprehend the course learning outcomes for Information Technology courses. Dual enrollment students in this program have an opportunity to earn two CompTIA industry certifications.  The CITE program for adult learners leads to a Career Studies Certificate in Cybersecurity and Networking Foundations. Students in this program have the opportunity to earn five CompTIA industry certifications. During the award period, program infrastructure improvements centered around the sequence of courses taken as well as the availability of resources to assist students in preparing for certification exams. A key factor in meeting the enrollment goals for this award was a comprehensive and consistent offering of the seven classes required for the college certificate. This resulted in the hiring of additional adjuncts.    Comprehensive Recruitment Strategies  Recruitment strategies were intentional with a focused lens on underrepresented students in Information Technology. A CITE Resource Wizard webpage was created on the college website with information regarding the IT field, program description, program courses, industry certifications, and contact information.   Since the CITE program includes both dual enrollment high school students and adult learners, recruitment activities were varied and expanded. Dual enrollment recruiting included presentations on campus for "College for a Day" events for K12 students, visitations to K12 schools by CITE staff for career days, and tours of the CITE location provided to K12 groups. An additional activity hosted by the college was a one-week "Girls in IT" summer camp for high school students.  For adult students, recruitment strategies focused on social media campaigns, flyers (digital and print), email marketing campaigns, telephone campaigns, and one-on-one advising. Individual development plans were created for CITE students to assist with advising.    Academic Support Strategies  Key strategies implemented related to academic support included an orientation to the CITE program presented to every class during the first two weeks of the semester, and availability of tools and resources designed to help prepare students for industry certification exams, specifically CompTIA exams.    Identity-Building and Self-Efficacy Strategies  During the award period, a required class, Preparation for Employment, was updated to ensure that resume writing, LinkedIn account creation, and interviewing skills were aligned with employer needs. Soft skills training was included. The promotion of internships in the IT field was also a focus during this period.         Results     Total enrollment increased by 40% throughout the grant period, exceeding the project'starget of a 35% increase. The total enrollment among underrepresented groups, including Black students, Hispanic students, and female students, increased by 62.2% throughout the grant period.  Since the summer of 2022, 52 CITE students passed a CompTIA certification exam, including 18 Black students and 16 female students. This exceeded the project's target.  During the grant period, the project team hired three adjunct faculty members who represented underrepresented populations and were employed in the IT field. This ensured that all courses required for the college certificate could be offered each semester by skilled and credentialed faculty. In addition, a full-time CITE Program Head was hired to sustain the PIP program activities that demonstrated strategies for growth and success.         Summary    This award led to successful increased enrollment in IT programs, diversification of its IT student body, a strengthened IT curriculum, industry certification testing preparation, hiring of additional faculty and a CITE Program Head, the launch of intentional recruitment activities, and implementation of academic support strategies.                Last Modified: 12/20/2024       Submitted by: JoanBTuck]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
