<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Establishing Veteran Career Training for Advanced Manufacturing Careers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Davis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdavis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Elizabethtown-Fort Knox, Kentucky region has a robust advanced manufacturing industry that is increasingly using automation and robotics.  This industry now has more than 400 annual openings for Manufacturing Engineers, and it takes an average of 40 days to fill these positions with a qualified candidate. This project intends to increase the pool of qualified candidates for these and related positions.  To do so, Elizabethtown Community and Technical College will partner with the U.S. Army Garrison - Fort Knox to provide educational opportunities in Advanced Manufacturing to soldiers transitioning to civilian life.  These opportunities will include the high-demand areas of Automation, Robotics, Industrial Maintenance, and Electrical Technology.  The college will use flexible course options to meet the needs of transitioning soldiers so that they can use their post-service time to obtain industry-recognized, stackable credentials, including academic certificates and associate degrees.  The result is expected to be a new career pathway that will expand advanced manufacturing education to more students.  In addition, by redesigning their Advanced Manufacturing courses to closely align with the skills needed in high-demand industries in the region, the project can benefit soldiers reentering civilian life.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project at Elizabethtown Community and Technical College will focus on serving transitioning military personnel and will gain a better understanding of veteran culture and the necessary services needed to promote student success.  Student services will be combined with portable, relevant, affordable education in high-demand areas in Advanced Manufacturing.  The college intends to shorten the time to a credential through flexible course options that include online, hybrid, and face to face instruction, combined with increased acceptance of experiential credit from military transcripts.  The goal of the project is that at least 90% of the students in each cohort will be placed in industry or retained for graduation with an Associate degree.  The academic and service model developed by the project will be shared among the 16 colleges in the Kentucky Community and Technical College System.  The program will also disseminate their model and findings nationally, to assist other colleges that want to serve growing veteran populations that would benefit from similar academic and career support.  This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2055582</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Cordova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy M Cordova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[timothym.cordova@kctcs.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nolan</FirstName>
<LastName>Massaroni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nolan Massaroni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nmassaroni0001@kctcs.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832090</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heidi</FirstName>
<LastName>Hasty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heidi S Hasty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hhasty0002@kctcs.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832002</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brent</FirstName>
<LastName>DOTY</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brent M DOTY</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bdoty0002@kctcs.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000831982</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kentucky Community & Technical College System]]></Name>
<CityName>VERSAILLES</CityName>
<ZipCode>403831245</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8592563397</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 N MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GWSXAJZALU69</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KENTUCKY COMMUNITY &amp; TECHNICAL COLLEGE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GWSXAJZALU69</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Elizabethtown Community & Technical College/KCTCS]]></Name>
<CityName>Elizabethtown</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>427011001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 College Street Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>741200</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes: Establishing Veteran Career Training for Advanced Manufacturing Careers</strong></p> <p>Over the past three years, the Establishing Veteran Career Training for Advanced Manufacturing Careers grant, in collaboration with the military's Career Skills Program (CSP) and the Operation Next program, has achieved significant success. This initiative has effectively supported transitioning military members and addressed critical workforce needs in the local advanced manufacturing industry.</p> <p><strong>Year 1: Laying the Foundation</strong></p> <p>In the first year, the program faced initial challenges, including the resignation of the original ACTIVE Program Coordinator. A quick hire of a replacement with military experience helped streamline recruitment and onboarding. Additionally, dependence on soldiers' commanders and military obligations caused delays and difficulties in maintaining a cohesive cohort model. To address these issues, the program implemented flexible curriculums and modular course structures, accommodating varying participant timelines.</p> <p>Despite these challenges, the program achieved key objectives, such as developing marketing materials, creating new curriculum, and hiring an ACTIVE Coordinator with a military background. These foundational elements set the stage for continued growth and impact.</p> <p><strong>Year 2: Continued Growth and Adaptation</strong></p> <p>In the second year, the partnership continued to navigate challenges related to soldiers' military commitments, impacting enrollment and completion timelines. However, faculty flexibility and modular courses helped mitigate these issues. Although the program did not reach a 100% completion rate, it achieved a remarkable 90% success rate, with graduates either employed in related fields or continuing their education.</p> <p>During this period, the CSP expanded its certificate offerings to include Electrical Construction, Industrial Automation and Robotics, Welding, and Machine Tool. This expansion provided a broader range of tuition-free, career-focused training options for exiting soldiers, helping them develop skills in high-demand industries.</p> <p><strong>Year 3: Overcoming Operational Hurdles</strong></p> <p>The third year brought challenges such as high demand depleting scholarship funds and regulatory changes reducing training time for participants. Turnover in the Career Skills Administrator role also created operational hurdles. Despite these challenges, the program maintained a 90% employment or continued education rate among graduates, addressing critical workforce gaps in the region's advanced manufacturing sector.</p> <p><strong>Operation Next Partnership</strong></p> <p>Operation Next, a DOD-funded and SkillBridge-approved program, provided free advanced manufacturing training to military personnel and their spouses. It offered tuition-free certificates in key areas like Exploratory Machining 1 and Gas Metal Arc Welding, joining the project primarily in Year 3.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Conclusion: Lasting Impact and Future Implications</strong></p> <p>As the partnership concludes, it reflects on three years of significant impact. The Operation Next and CSP partnership equipped transitioning service members with valuable industry-recognized credentials and skills in high-demand areas like Industrial Automation, Robotics, Welding, and Machine Tool operation. The program's success is attributed to strategic planning, operational agility, and a commitment to supporting military members.</p> <p>The achievements and lessons learned from this program will inform future initiatives aimed at empowering transitioning service members and strengthening regional workforce development. The partnership has produced highly skilled technicians and addressed critical workforce needs in the advanced manufacturing sector, leaving a lasting positive impact on both participants and the broader community.</p> <p>Through strategic planning, operational agility, and a deep commitment to supporting military members, the Operation Next and CSP partnership has delivered exceptional outcomes for both its participants and the broader community. As this program concludes, its successes and lessons learned will undoubtedly inform future initiatives aimed at empowering transitioning service members and strengthening regional workforce development.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 06/03/2024<br> Modified by: Heidi&nbsp;S&nbsp;Hasty</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ><div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)          </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439587875_M._McWhorter--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439587875_M._McWhorter--rgov-800width.jpg" title="M. McWhorter"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439587875_M._McWhorter--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="M. McWhorter"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mr. McWhorter one of our CSP completers.</div> <div class="imageCredit">ECTC/Ft. Knox Marketing</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Heidi&nbsp;S&nbsp;Hasty <div class="imageTitle">M. McWhorter</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439478222_CSP_group--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439478222_CSP_group--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CSP Group"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439478222_CSP_group--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CSP Group"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A group of CSP participants.</div> <div class="imageCredit">ECTC/Ft. Knox Marketing</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Heidi&nbsp;S&nbsp;Hasty <div class="imageTitle">CSP Group</div> </div> </li><li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439411043_CSP_group_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439411043_CSP_group_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Group at ECTC"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2024/2055582/2055582_10722926_1717439411043_CSP_group_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Group at ECTC"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CSP students on Campus at ECTC</div> <div class="imageCredit">ECTC Marketing</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Heidi&nbsp;S&nbsp;Hasty <div class="imageTitle">Group at ECTC</div> </div> </li></ul> </div> </div></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Project Outcomes: Establishing Veteran Career Training for Advanced Manufacturing Careers   Over the past three years, the Establishing Veteran Career Training for Advanced Manufacturing Careers grant, in collaboration with the military's Career Skills Program (CSP) and the Operation Next program, has achieved significant success. This initiative has effectively supported transitioning military members and addressed critical workforce needs in the local advanced manufacturing industry.   Year 1: Laying the Foundation   In the first year, the program faced initial challenges, including the resignation of the original ACTIVE Program Coordinator. A quick hire of a replacement with military experience helped streamline recruitment and onboarding. Additionally, dependence on soldiers' commanders and military obligations caused delays and difficulties in maintaining a cohesive cohort model. To address these issues, the program implemented flexible curriculums and modular course structures, accommodating varying participant timelines.   Despite these challenges, the program achieved key objectives, such as developing marketing materials, creating new curriculum, and hiring an ACTIVE Coordinator with a military background. These foundational elements set the stage for continued growth and impact.   Year 2: Continued Growth and Adaptation   In the second year, the partnership continued to navigate challenges related to soldiers' military commitments, impacting enrollment and completion timelines. However, faculty flexibility and modular courses helped mitigate these issues. Although the program did not reach a 100% completion rate, it achieved a remarkable 90% success rate, with graduates either employed in related fields or continuing their education.   During this period, the CSP expanded its certificate offerings to include Electrical Construction, Industrial Automation and Robotics, Welding, and Machine Tool. This expansion provided a broader range of tuition-free, career-focused training options for exiting soldiers, helping them develop skills in high-demand industries.   Year 3: Overcoming Operational Hurdles   The third year brought challenges such as high demand depleting scholarship funds and regulatory changes reducing training time for participants. Turnover in the Career Skills Administrator role also created operational hurdles. Despite these challenges, the program maintained a 90% employment or continued education rate among graduates, addressing critical workforce gaps in the region's advanced manufacturing sector.   Operation Next Partnership   Operation Next, a DOD-funded and SkillBridge-approved program, provided free advanced manufacturing training to military personnel and their spouses. It offered tuition-free certificates in key areas like Exploratory Machining 1 and Gas Metal Arc Welding, joining the project primarily in Year 3.      Conclusion: Lasting Impact and Future Implications   As the partnership concludes, it reflects on three years of significant impact. The Operation Next and CSP partnership equipped transitioning service members with valuable industry-recognized credentials and skills in high-demand areas like Industrial Automation, Robotics, Welding, and Machine Tool operation. The program's success is attributed to strategic planning, operational agility, and a commitment to supporting military members.   The achievements and lessons learned from this program will inform future initiatives aimed at empowering transitioning service members and strengthening regional workforce development. The partnership has produced highly skilled technicians and addressed critical workforce needs in the advanced manufacturing sector, leaving a lasting positive impact on both participants and the broader community.   Through strategic planning, operational agility, and a deep commitment to supporting military members, the Operation Next and CSP partnership has delivered exceptional outcomes for both its participants and the broader community. As this program concludes, its successes and lessons learned will undoubtedly inform future initiatives aimed at empowering transitioning service members and strengthening regional workforce development.           Last Modified: 06/03/2024       Submitted by: HeidiSHasty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
